<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.sfdeb.18590825">
    <teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
	    <titleStmt>
		<title level="m" type="main">Revolution of Affairs in Mormondom</title>
		<author></author>
		<principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
		</titleStmt>
		<editionStmt>
		    <edition>
		 	<date>2010</date>
		     </edition>
		</editionStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
		    <idno>mmm.news.sfdeb.18590825</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

	    <notesStmt>
		<note type="summary"></note>
	    </notesStmt>

	    <sourceDesc>
		<bibl>
		    <title level="j">San Fransisco Daily Evening Bulletin</title>
		    <title level="a" type="main">Revolution of Affairs in Mormondom.</title>
		    <title level="a" type="sub">The Mountain Meadow Massacre and Mormon Agency.</title>
		    <author></author>
		    <publisher></publisher>
	  	    <pubPlace>San Francisco, CA</pubPlace>
		    <date when="1859-08-25">August 25, 1859</date>
		</bibl>
	   </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
	<textClass>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
	        <term>newspaper</term>
	    </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
	   	<term></term>
	    </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="action">
		<term></term>
	    </keywords>
	</textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
	<change when="2011-08-11"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enhancement</change>
	<change when="2011-04-20"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept Highlighting</change>
	<change when="2010-03-29"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Validation</change>
	<change when="2008-08-14"><name>Katie M. Heupel</name> Initial Encoding</change>
	<change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
	<change when="2008-08-14"><name>Katie Heupel</name> Original transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>


<body>

<div1 type="newspaper">

    <pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.sfdeb.18590825.001"/>

<head type="main">Revolution of Affairs in Mormondom.</head>

<head type="sub">The Mountain Meadow Massacre and Mormon Agency.</head>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Lynch">Mr. <persName key="Lynch, James">James Lynch</persName>, lately Wagon-master in the service of the U.S. Government in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah Territory</placeName>&#8212;from whom we derived mush interesting information as to the latest state of affairs there</seg>, <seg type="Source" subtype="Reprinted">published in our issue of yesterday</seg>&#8212;has laid before us a statement by himself as to certain circumstances connected with the never-to-be-forgotten Mountain Meadow massacre, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">the part which Mormon agency played in that terrible deed, and subsequently thereto.</seg>  Mr. <persName key="Lynch, James">Lynch</persName> made oath to the truth of this statement in <placeName type="county" key="Cedar County, UT">Cedar county</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">U. T.</placeName>, on 27th July last, before Judge <persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">Eckels</persName>, Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.  Two persons named in the statement, <persName key="Dunn, Thomas">Thomas Dunn</persName> and <persName key="Lofink, John">John Lofink</persName>, likewise made oath at the same time, before Judge <persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">Eckels</persName>, to the facts narrated by <persName key="Lynch, James">Lynch</persName>, so far as they were personally aware of them.  The sworn statement of these parties had been forwarded to President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>.  It reads as follows:.</p>

<floatingText><body>
<p><placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">UTAH TERRITORY</placeName>, Cedar <placeName type="county" key="Cedar County, UT">County</placeName></p>

<p><persName key="Lynch, James">James Lynch</persName>, of lawful age, being first duly sworn, states on oath:  That he was one of the party who accompanied Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName>, Superintendent of Indian Affairs, in an expedition to the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadow">Mountain Meadow</geogName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Santa Clara, CA">Santa Clara</placeName>, etc., in the months of March and April last, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">when we recovered seventeen children, sole survivors of the wholesale massacre</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">perpetrated at the former place</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in the month of September, 1857</seg>.  <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The children, when we first saw them, were in a most wretched and deplorable condition&#8212;with little or no clothing, covered with filth and dirt.  They presented a sight heart-rending and miserable in the extreme.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">The scene of the fearful murder still bears evidence of the atrocious crime</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">charged by the Mormons and their friends to have been perpetrated by Indians</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSZealots"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSBloodAtonement"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution">but really by Mormons disguised as Indians, who, in their headlong zeal, bigotry and fanaticism, deemed this a favorable opportunity of at once wreaking their vengeance on the hated people of <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, and of making another of those iniquitious "Blood Offerings" to God, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">so often recommended by <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and their other leaders</seg></seg></seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">For more than two square miles, the ground is strewn with the skulls, bones and other remains of the victims. In places the water had washed many of these remains together, forming little mounds&#8212;raising monuments, as it were, to the cruelty of man to his fellow-man.  Here and there may be found the remains of an innocent infant beside those of some fond, devoted mother, ruthlessly slain by men worse than demons; their bones le bleaching in the noon-day sun, a mute, but eloquent appeal to a just but offended God for vengeance.  I have witnessed many harrowing sights on the field of battle, but never did my heart thrill with such horrible emotions as when standing on that silent plain contemplating the remains of the innocent victims of <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSZealots">Mormon avarice, fanaticism and cruelty</seg>.  Many of these remains are now in possession of Mr. <persName key="Rogers">Rogers</persName>, a gentleman who accompanied us on the expedition.  Why were not these remains interred, if not in a Christian-like and proper manner, at least covered from sight?  But no! the hatred of their murderers extended to them after death.  There they lay, a prey to the famished wolves that run howling over the desolate plains to the unlooked-for feast&#8212;good for the croaking ravens that through the tainted air with swift wing wended their way to revel in their banquet of blood.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">I inquired of <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>, who is a high Church dignitary, why these remains were not buried some time subsequent to the murder?  He said the bodies were so much decomposed that it was impossible to inter them.</seg>  No longer let us boast of our citizenship, freedom or civilization.  <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">Here were <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one hundred and forty poor, harmless emigrants</seg> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg> butchered in cold blood</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS">by white men, too, with attending circumstances far exceeding anything in cruelty that we have ever heard or read of being perpetrated by savages</seg>.  <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Extra-legalViolence">It is now high time that the actors and perpetrators of this dreadful crime should be brought to condign punishment.  For years these Mormons have possessed an immunity from punishment, or a sort of privilege for committing crimes of this nature; but soon, it is to be hoped, a new state of things must dawn&#8212;a retribution must come, vengeance must be had&#8212;civilization, humanity and Christianity call for it, and the American people must have it.  Blood may be shed and difficulties may be encountered, but just as sure as there is a sun at noon-day, retribution will yet overtake the guilty wretches, their aiders and abettors, whether open or <hi rend="italic">hidden under disguise of Government employment</hi>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils"><persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, a Mormon President, has knowledge of the whereabouts of much of the property taken from these ill-fated emigrants, and, if I am not misinformed, in possession of a large quantity of it.  Why not make him disgorge this ill-gotten plunder, and disclose the amount escheated to, and sold out by the Mormon Church, as its share of the blood of helpless victims?  When he enters into a league with hell and covenant with death, he should not be allowed to make feasts and entertain Government officials at his table, as he did Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName>, Superintendent of Indian Affairs, while the rest of his party refused in his hearing, and that of Lee, to share the hospitalities of hits notorious murderer, this scourge of the desert.</seg>  <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">This man <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> does not deny, but admits, that he was present at the massacre, but pretends he was there to prevent bloodshed.  But positive evidence implicates him as the leader of the murderers, too deeply for denial.  The children point him out as one of them that did the bloody work.  He and other white men had these children, and they never were in the hands of the Indians, but in those that murdered them; and <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hemblin</persName> and <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName> know it.</seg>  <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The children pointed out to us the dresses and jewelry of their mothers and sisters, that now grace the forms of these murderers' women and children.</seg>  Verily, it would seem that men and women alike combined in this wholesale slaughter.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">This ill-fated train consisted of 18 wagons, 280 head of cattle, household goods to a large amount, besides money estimated at $50,000 or $90,000, the greater part of which, it is believed, new makes rich the harems of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>.</seg>  <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hatch">Of this train, a man whose name is unknown fortunately escaped at the time of the massacre to <placeName type="settlement" key="Las Vegas, NV">Vegas</placeName>, 100 miles distant from the scene of blood, on the California road.  Here he was followed by five Mormons, who, through promises of safety &amp;c., prevailed upon him to begin his return to <placeName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</placeName>, and, contrary to their promises, and his just expectations, they inhumanely butchered him&#8212;laughing at, and disregarding his loud and repeated cries for mercy</seg>, as witnesses ant told by <persName key="Harch, Ira">Ira Hatch</persName>, one of the five.</seg>  <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The object in killing his man, was to leave no witness competent to give testimony in a court of justice</seg>; but God, whose ways are inscrutable, has thought proper, through the instrumentality of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">the "babes and sucklings" recovered by us</seg>, to bring to light this most horrible tragedy, and make known its barbarous and inhuman perpetrators.  Already a step has been taken by Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> in the right direction, of which we see the evidence in the flight of presidents, bishops and elders to the mountains, to escape the just penalty of the law for their crimes.  If the vengeance of the Lord is slow, it is equally sure.  <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Mormons have reported that the principals, and in fact all the actors in this fearful massacre, were Indian savages</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS">but subsequent events have thrown sufficient light upon this mystery to fix the foul blot indellibly on the Mormon escutcheon.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">Many of the leaders are well known.  <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was the Commander-in-Chief; President <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Height</persName> and Bishop <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Smith</persName> in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and, besides these, one hundred actors and accomplices, are known to Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> and Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>.</seg>  <seg type="Blame" subtype="USGovernment">Some of those implicated are and have been in the confidence and under the employment of the Superintendent of Indian Affairs&#8212;Bishop <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>, for instance, who is employed by Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> among the Indians down South, who knows all the facts, but refuses to disclose them.</seg>  <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> falsely reported to Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> that the children we brought away were recovered by him from persons who had bought them from Indians, and who knew what he reported was false, and it was so done to cheat the Government out of money to again reward the guilty wretches for their inhuman butcheries.</seg>  It is pretended that this man is friendly towards the United States Government, yet it is a well known fact that he screened some of these murderers about his house from justice, among whom are an Indian named <persName key="George">George</persName> and a white man named <persName key="Fillis">Fillis</persName>, recognized by <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">one of these children&#8212;a little girl eight years old, who has been sent off to the States by Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>&#8212;as the man who killed her mother.</seg>  <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> cannot be a Mormon Bishop and a friend of the United States, at least where Mormons or Mormonism is concerned.  His creed and oaths forbid it, and he could not if he would, with safety to himself, do it.  They why not out with him?  Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> can find another and more trustworthy agent than he.  Why, then, keep and patronize the abettor of crime?</p>

<p>Before I close, my duty to my country calls upon me to state to the public the course of Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> to engender in the minds of the Mormons feelings of antipathy and opposition to the Judiciary, and the many obligations which he violated, and promises which he disregarded, during this trip.</p>

<p>I left <orgName type="military" key="Camp Floyd">Camp Floyd</orgName> in March last, in charge of 39 men emigrating to Arizona.  About the 27th of that month, we came up with Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver City</placeName>, who there informed me that he was <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">to the scene of the Mountain Meadow massacre</seg> and <placeName type="settlement" key="Santa Clara, CA">Santa Clara</placeName>, to procure evidence in relation thereto, and to secure <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">the surviving children.</seg>  He informed me that all his men had left him, being Mormons, and who, before leaving, had informed him (<persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>) that if he went down south, the people down there would make a eunuch of him; and he asked us for aid and assistance.  I cheerfully placed the whole party at his command, telling him that he had started upon an errand of mercy, and it was strange that he should have employed Mormons&#8212;the very confederates of these monsters who had so wantonly murdered unoffending emigrants&#8212;to ferret out the guilty parties.  He was left without a man, and we found him guarding his mules and wagons.  He requested two of the men of my party (<persName key="Dunn, Thomas">Thomas Dunn</persName> and <persName key="Lofink, John">John Lofink</persName>) to return to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake city</placeName> with him, promising to give them employment during the following summer and the winter.  They consented to abandon their trip to <placeName type="state" key="Arizona">Arizona</placeName> upon these terms, and returned with the Doctor; and, I am sorry to say, he violated his plighted faith and his solemn contract on reaching the city, by immediately discharging them without cause and hiring Mormons to take their place, as I am informed has been his custom since he came into the Valley.</p> 

<p>I was with Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> from the time I joined him until he returned to the city of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, having voluntarily abandoned my expedition to Arizona to aid his humane enterprise, and during the trip I repeatedly heard him tell the Mormons "that they need not fear Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> (whose disclosures and energy had created some alarm;) that he (<persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>) would have him removed from office; that the Mormons (murderers and all) were all included in the President's proclamation and pardon, and would not be tried or punished for any offence whatever committed prior to the issuing of the pardon; that Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> was not a fit man for office"&#8212;in fact, abusing and slandering the Judge in unmeasured terms&#8212;no language being too low for filthy to apply to him.  I could arrive at no other conclusion, from his conduct, than that the Doctor desired to influence the minds of the Mormons against the Judiciary, and that he cared more to create a prejudice against Judge Cradlebaugh's course in attempting to bring these murders to light, than he did to elicit the truth relative to the murders; and that he was only following out his instructions from the general Government in going after the children, while he was availing himself of this journey to make a pilgrimage to the south settlements to abuse and traduce Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, and arouse a feeling of resistance to his authority among the guilty murderers.</p>

<p>It is to be regretted that the Doctor has manifested so hostile a feeling to his associate Federal officers, and that he course of the Judges, especially that of Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, has to be criticized by such a man as <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName>&#8212;a more veritable old granny than whom, in my opinion, never held an official position in this country; and in this opinion I am home out by the concurrent opinions of nearly all the Gentile population in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> who know him, as well as by many of the Mormon people.</p>

<p>I now reside in<placeName type="county" key="Cedar County, UT"> Cedar county</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">U. T.</placeName> 
<persName key="Lynch, James">JAMES LYNCH</persName></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Lynch"><persName key="Lynch, James">James Lynch</persName>, being duly sworn, states on oath that all the material fact stated by him the foregoing affidavit, so far as he states the same of his own knowledge are true, and so far as he states the same as from information derived from others; as, also the conclusions drawn from the same he believes to be true, and further saith not.</seg></p>

<closer><signed><persName key="Lynch, James">JAMES LYNCH</persName><lb/>
	Sworn and subscribed to July 27th, 1859.</signed></closer>
</body></floatingText>

<closer><persName key="Eckels, D. H.">D. H. ECKELS</persName>,<lb/>
Chief Justice Supreme Court.<lb/>
The undersigned state on oath that the foregoing affidavit has been carefully read to them: that they are the identical person named in it as having been employed by Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName> to return with him to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>; that they went from <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver City</placeName> with said <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> south and back again; and that we fully concur in the statements made by <persName key="Lynch, James">James Lynch</persName> in the foregoing affidavit, as to what we saw and heard on the trip, and the conduct of Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>, Superintendent of Indian Affairs, and further say not.
<signed><persName key="Dunn, Thomas">THOMAS DUNN</persName><lb/>
<persName key="Lofink, John">JOHN LOFINK</persName><lb/>
Subscribed and sworn to before me July 27th, 1859,<lb/>
<persName key="Eckels, D. R.">D. R. ECKELS</persName>,<lb/>
Chief Justice of Supreme Court.</signed>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>