<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.dn.18590629">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Affairs in Utah</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"/>
                <author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.news.dn.18590629</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary"> </note>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">Affairs in Utah</title>
                    <title level="j">Deseret News</title>
                    <author>Editor</author>
                    <publisher>Deseret News</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Salt Lake City, UT</pubPlace>
                    <date when="1859-06-29">1859-06-29</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>newspaper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
                    <term> </term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="sympathy">
                    <term>LDS</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
	<change when="2011-06-16"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept Highlighting Enhancement</change>
        <change when="2007-04-27"><name>Douglas Seefeldt</name> Initial Encoding</change>
        <change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
        <change when="2004-01-01"><name>Will Bagley</name> Original transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

    <text>


        <body>
            <div1 type="newspaper">
                
                <pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.dn.18590629.001"/>

<head type="main">AFFAIRS IN UTAH!!</head>
<head type="sub">THE PRESIDENT'S INSTRUCTIONS TO THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY OF THE TERRITORY.</head>

<p>The following letter from the United States Attorney General to the District Attorney for Utah is published in the <orgName type="Newspaper"
    key="Washington Constitution">Washington <hi rend="italic">Constitution</hi></orgName></p>

<p>ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE, May 17, 1859</p>

<p><persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Sir</persName>:&#8212;<seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">Your letters of March 24 and April 6 addressed to <persName
key="Black, Jeremiah Sullivan">me</persName> have been received. The grave
import of the facts contained in them, and in other communications from Utah by
the same mail, required that the whole correspondence of the several departments
with the officers of the Territory should be laid before the <persName
key="Buchanan, James">President</persName>.&#8212;He has carefully considered the
subject, and his opinion will be found in a letter to the two Associate Justices
of the Territory&#8212;a copy of which I send you.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">You are clothed with the authority of a public accuser for the <placeName
type="state" key="Utah Territory">Territory</placeName>. It is your duty to
commence and carry on all public prosecutions with such aid and assistance as
you see proper to call in. On proper occasions, in a proper, respectful manner
you must oppose every effort which any judge may make to usurp your
functions.&#8212;Do not allow your rights to remain unasserted.&#8212;If the judges will confine themselves to the simple and plain duty imposed upon them by law of hearing and deciding cases that are brought before them, I am sure that the business of the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Territory
</placeName>will get along very well. This must be impressed upon their minds,
if possible, for, if they will insist upon doing the duties of Prosecuting
Attorney, and Marshal, as well as their own, every thing will be thrown into
confusion, and the peace of the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory"
>Territory </placeName>may be destroyed at any moment.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">But your duty must be performed with energy and impartiality. Every crime that is committed, no matter by whom, should be exposed and punished. I need not say
that you are to make no distinction between Gentile and <orgName
type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints"
>Mormon</orgName>, or between <orgName type="native" key="Indian">Indian
</orgName>and white man. You will prosecute the rich and the poor, the
influential and the humble with equal vigor, and thus entitle yourself to the
confidence of all.</seg></p>

<p>It is only by these general remarks that I can express the wishes of the
<persName key="Buchanan, James">President </persName>with reference to your
office; for at this distance it is impossible to give you detailed instructions.
But there is one subject to which I would call your special attention. It
appears that a company of emigrants <seg type="Emigrants"
subtype="Route">from <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">Arkansas </seg>to California </seg>was <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"
>attacked </seg>at <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">Mountain
Meadows, three hundred miles south of Salt Lake</seg>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one
hundred and nineteen</seg> cruelly murdered, none being spared except <seg
type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">a few children, all of whom were
under seven years of age.</seg> This crime, by whomever committed, was one of the most atrocious that has ever blackened the character of the human race. <seg
type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Mormons blame it upon the
Indians, and the accusation receives some color from the fact that
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">all the children who survived the
massacre were found in the possession of Indians</seg></seg>; others, among them a
<persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">judge of the territory</persName>,
declared their unhesitating belief that <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS">the
Mormons themselves committed this foul murder</seg>. All the circumstances
seem, from the correspondence, to be enveloped in mystery. In your letter the
manner of the murder is described&#8212;showing that <seg type="Massacre"
subtype="Surrender">the emigrants agreed to surrender their arms upon the
promise that their lives should be spared, and after doing so were all of
them treacherously butchered.</seg> <seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">Why does the information stop there? If
that much be known how is it that we know no more? Who were the parties that
received this surrender and how is it proved? Cannot the <persName
key="Young, Brigham">Superintendent of Indian Affairs</persName>, or someone
connected with that department of the public service <seg type="Massacre"
subtype="Survivors">trace back the children from the Indians in whose
possession they were found to <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">the
corral, where their parents were slain</seg></seg>. <seg type="Massacre"
subtype="Spoils">It is said that some of the Mormon inhabitants of Utah have
property of the emigrants in their possession.</seg> If this be true, will
it not furnish a thread which, properly followed, would lead back to the scene
of the crime?</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">These are mere suggestions, which are intended to show the interest of the government on the subject, rather than instruct you in the performance of your duty. It is, however, confidently expected of you that you will intermit no watch, nor let any opportunity escape you of learning all that can be known upon this subject. If you shall be under the necessity of employing agents, such reasonable expenses as you may be put to on that account will be paid.</seg></p>

<p>Your conduct at Provo seems, from all accounts of it, to have been perfectly
proper, and is totally approved by the <persName key="Buchanan, James"
>President</persName>. Your refusal on a former occasion to violate the
promise of pardon contained in the President's proclamation, was equally
praiseworthy and correct.</p>

<closer><salute>I am, very respectfully, Yours &amp;c.,</salute>
<signed>J. S. BLACK</signed>. <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">ALEX. WILSON, Esq.,<lb/>
<lb/> U.S. District Attorney,<lb/> Utah Territory</persName></closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>