<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Wild Life in the Rocky Mountains</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                    <author><forename>D.</forename> <forename type="middle">K.</forename> <surname>Thomas</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.wa.thomas.1917</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">This record contains Chapter 16 pgs 118-128. </note>
            </notesStmt>            
            <sourceDesc>                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m" type="main">Wild Life in the Rocky Mountains: Or The Lost Million Dollar Gold Mine</title>
                    <author><forename>D.</forename> <forename type="middle">K.</forename> <surname>Thomas</surname></author>
                    <publisher>C.E. Thomas Pub. Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>N. p.</pubPlace>
                    <extent>118-128</extent>
                    <date when="1917">1917</date>
		    <note type="source">D. K. Thomas. <hi rend="italic">Wild Life in the Rocky Mountains, or, The Lost Million Dollar Gold Mine</hi>. N. p.: C. E. Thomas Pub. Co., 1917. 118-28.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>            
        </fileDesc>        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>western_americana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-02-16"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enrichment</change>
            <change when="2010-07-15"><name>Stephen Pipkin</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="118" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.123"/> 
  
<head>CHAPTER XVI
<hi rend="smallcaps">THE MOUNTAIN MEADOW MASSACRE &#8212; AN ENTIRE
WAGON TRAIN WIPED OUT</hi></head>

<p><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> seemed to lose his power and
influence in the Church after the Mountain Meadows
massacre. This happened previously to the disruption
in the Church and was, indeed, one of the main
causes of the trouble. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership"><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> was supposed
to be one of the main instigators of that awful crime.</seg>
The following is the report of the massacre taken from
the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> Magazine:</p>

<!-- The Text in this quotation is also in Clampitt - Echos from the Rocky Mountains Chapter XXV --> 
 
<q><p>"<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">In the summer of 1857</seg> a train of emigrants <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">from
<placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">on their way to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, entered <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
Lake City</placeName></seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">It was perhaps the wealthiest and most
populous train that ever entered the valley, bound
for <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>. It numbered nearly one hundred
fifty persons, men, women and children; four hundred
head of cattle and seventy&#8212;five horses. It was a rich
train and carried money, jewelry, household goods,
pianos, books, and fireside penates, with which to add
comfort and beauty to their new homes on the Pacific.</seg></p>

<p>"<seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">They were told that snows on the Sierras would
prevent their passage by the northern route. They,
therefore, resolved to pass down through the southern
settlements of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and enter <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> by the
southern route.</seg> It was not only a wealthy train but   

<pb n="119" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.124"/>
	
a highly respectable, peaceable, and Christian people,
who frequently held religious services.</p>

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">"Hitherto, <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
Lake City</placeName> had been the great
recruiting station on the barren road to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>. 
Jaded and weary trains of men and animals found
rest and recuperation in this oasis of the desert high
way. To their great surprise, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">this <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> train</seg>
found, on reaching <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
Lake City</placeName>, that nothing could
be procured from the Mormons for love nor money.
Their gold and silver, their cattle, nor aught that they
possessed, could purchase sufficient food to keep them
from starvation. Not only were they denied food but
rest. They were peremptorily ordered to break camp
on the Jordan and depart from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
Lake City</placeName>. Wearily they passed down through the villages that
blossomed at the foot of the Wasatch, each proving as
inhospitable as the other.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">"The corn had ripened, the grain had all been
harvested, every granary was filled to repletion, for
the year had been exceptionally proline; yet money
had lost its purchasing power, for everywhere food
was denied. At <placeName type="settlement" key="American Fork, UT">American Fork</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Battle Creek, UT">Battle Creek</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>,
<placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Spanish Fork, UT">Spanish Fork</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Payson, UT">Payson</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Nephi, UT">Nephi</placeName>, and <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore City</placeName> they received the same harsh treatment.
And, not until their arrival in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> in a famished condition were they able to obtain a pound of
grain for man or beast. The command of authority
had preceded them. The second in command of the
church, <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, the Prophet’s first counselor,
had preached to the Mormons in every settlement,

<pb n="120" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.125"/>

and, under pain of excommunication, had
forbidden them to sell food or grain to the starving
emigrants. At <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, however, they managed
to obtain sixty bushels of corn, which they had
ground into meal at the mill. They then pushed on
to <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg> to recruit their stock before crossing the desert.</seg></p>

<p>"<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">While encamped upon the grassy knolls at Cane
Springs</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">they were suddenly attacked by what they
presumed to be a large body of Indians</seg>, who <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">killed
ten of their number</seg> and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">ran off their grazing stock</seg>.
But, forming a cordon of their wagons, behind which
they fought desperately, each emigrant being well
armed, they kept the enemy at bay for five days.
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Every attempt to obtain water was met by slaughter.
Two little girls, dressed in pure white, were sent
down to the spring. Hand in hand they proceeded on
their way, the way of death, for their tender innocence 
did not protect them; their little bodies were
riddled with bullets. A woman that attempted to
milk a cow that had approached their inclosure was
instantly shot to death.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">"Unable to succeed by assault, these pseudo Indians
now determined upon wicked strategy. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">The affidavit
of the apostate Mormon Bishop, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingen
Smith</persName>, relates that a regular military council was
held in the town of Parowan, at which were present
President <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, commanding
the Mormon Military Regiment, which had been
called out to do the bloody work; Bishop <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D.</persName>
  
<pb n="121" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.126"/>

<persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, its Major; Bishop <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Rigbee</persName> and <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>.
<persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was also Indian agent for southern <placeName type="settlement" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>
and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">he invited bands of Pahutes and Pahvents to
accompany him in the cruel butchery to take place.</seg> 
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">It was planned that a flag of truce should be borne
by white men, to offer to negotiate terms with the
Indians and thus gain the confidence of the besieged.</seg></seg>
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">Accordingly a wagon containing white men with a
white flag made its appearance before the lines of the
besieged, who, beholding the faces of white men,
hailed it with joy. This wagon contained <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">J. B.
Haight</persName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, Bishop <persName key="Higbee, Isaac M.">Rigbee</persName> and other
Mormon dignitaries. They stated that they had come
to offer aid to the emigrants and intercede in their
behalf with the Indians, if they so desired. This offer
was gladly accepted and the Mormons departed.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">"They returned soon after with the ultimatum of
the Indians, that the emigrants should surrender all
of their arms and property and return to the settlements 
the way they came</seg>. In case they accepted
these hard conditions the Mormons promised to conduct
them safely to the settlements. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">Placing implicit
reliance in the good will and intentions of the Mormons,
who were known to be at peace with the Indian
tribes, cruel as were the terms</seg>, they were accepted
by the famished emigrants; and, surrendering their
arms and other property, they started on their march
to the grave!</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">"The arms, the wounded, and the children were
placed in two wagons driven by Mormons. Behind

<pb n="122" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.127"/>

them came the women marching in single file; a little
back of them, the starved and worn out men; and,
immediately in their rear, a guard of sixty Mormon
militia. A mile from the Spring the road ran through
a thicket of scrub oak and many rocks intercepted
their way. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">Here, by previous agreement, lay a band
of Indians in ambush.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">At this moment, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, who
marched between the wagons, discharged his gun,
killing, it is said, a woman.</seg> It was the signal for the
massacre. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The Indians sprang suddenly from behind
the rocks and bushes, and, together with the Mormon
guard, began the work of horrible massacre.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Old
men and young, pitiable women with babes in their
arms, youths and maidens, all were alike butchered
by the remorseless <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">red and white demons</seg>. Hell hath
no record upon its avenging pages that can compare
with this unpitying crime. The prayers of men, the
tears and wails of women fell upon unheeding ears.
Sick mothers, too ill to leave the wagons, were
dragged therefrom and their throats cut from ear to
ear. Little girls were slaughtered like sheep in the
shambles, and venerable gray&#8212;haired clergymen while,
kneeling in prayer. The fury of perdition seemed to
seize upon the slayers. One young man, <persName key="Pierce, James">James Pierce</persName>,
was shot by his own father for protecting a young,
beseeching girl who lay crouched at his feet. A
beautiful young girl threw herself into the arms of
the son of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, who attempted to shield
her with his own body. His inhuman father bent his
head aside and plunged his dripping dagger into her
young heart. All of the little children were killed

<pb n="123" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.128"/>

save <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">those too young to remember</seg>.</seg> Such was the
order. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Fifteen alone survived, the eldest but two
and a half years old.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">"In an incredibly short space of time <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one hundred
twenty&#8212;eight men, women and children, unarmed
and defenseless, weak, weary, worn and famished,
were butchered</seg> by those inhuman monsters who,
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">under the guise of friendship and human sympathy,
had decoyed them into this terrible slaughter pen.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">"Eight days after the massacre people who visited
the field of death saw the bodies of the slain strewn
upon the ground and heaped in piles. Some were
stabbed, many shot, while others, principally women,
had their throats cut. The wolves and ravens had
lacerated the bodies of all save one, that of a beautiful, 
well&#8212;formed woman with long flowing locks of
hair. For some unexplained reason her body had
escaped the print of wolves’ teeth. A single bullet
had pierced her side. There was no clothing left on
any of the bodies, save one torn stocking which clung
to the ankle of one of the men; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">their bloody clothing
having been torn from their mutilated bodies and
sold at auction <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">by the order of the church authorities
at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</seg></seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">"Most of the bodies had been thrown into three
piles, distant two and a half rods from each other.
The most signiicant fact connected with the dead
was that not a scalp was taken. Those acquainted
with Indian character know full well their savage
instincts. After <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">a continuous battle of five days</seg>,
resulting finally in the capture and slaughter of their

<pb n="124" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.129"/>

foe, does it hold to reason that not a scalp should be
taken! The inference follows swift and sure. Had
revenge been their object, scalps would have been
taken. As it was, not a trace of the scalping knife
could be discovered."</seg></seg></seg></p></q>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">For the whole year following, this revolting crime
was kept secret, locked up within the mountain walls
of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. When finally their bodies were
discovered and the ghastly deed made known, it
sent a thrill of horror throughout the world. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">When
secrecy was no longer available the Mormons 
declared it to be the work of savages. <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>,
as superintendent of Indian affairs in the Territory,
sent a report to the Department at <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName>
alleging it to be the work of hostile Indians.</seg>
<seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution">It was declared to be the organized work of 
Mormon authorities, who sought to revenge themselves
upon the people of <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> for the killing of <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley
B. Pratt</persName> by <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName>, whose wife <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> had succeeded
in proselyting and who afterwards became one of
his wives at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
Lake City</placeName>.</seg> Pining for her children,
she induced <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> to accompany her back to
<placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> in the hope of obtaining them from her 
husband; but who, incensed at the robbery of his
wife and the attempted abduction of his children, fell
upon <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> and killed him while he was trying to
escape.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The little children whose lives had been spared
were, two years after, by the order of the United
States authorities, gathered from the Mormon families
in which they had been placed and sent to their

<pb n="125" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.130"/> 

friends at home.</seg> Two years after the Mountain
Meadow massacre the United States goverment
established a military camp north of the city on a
high bench overlooking the city, which was named
Camp Douglass, at which camp a regiment of soldiers
was stationed under the command of General <persName key="Connor, Patrick">Connors</persName>.
<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">After this fewer murders were committed in
<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Seldom, if ever, was an emigrant
train attacked and robbed, which the Mormons had
always claimed was done by the Indians.</seg> <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham
Young</persName>’s <q>"Destroying Angels"</q> seemed to go out
of business.</seg></p>

<p>The Mormon General Conference, which convenes
twice a year, was in session the week that <persName key="Thomas, D. K.">Thomas</persName> and
party were in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
Lake City</placeName>. Large numbers of
Mormons were in attendance from all parts of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the
Territory</placeName>. Much information was, therefore, gained
by them in regard to Mormonism and of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham
Young</persName> and his numerous wives.</p>

<p><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, the Prophet and President of the
Mormon Church, also the Governor of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory
of Utah</placeName>, was a large, broad-shouldered man five feet
eight or ten inches in height. He had a large head
and wore a full beard. He looked to be a man of
strong will, not easily excited or discouraged. When
seen on the street he looked different from most of
the Mormon officials, especially in his dress. He wore
a tall silk hat and black cloth clothes. He wore a
gold watch and chain, and walked with a large 

<pb n="126" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.131"/>

gold-headed cane. When he stopped to talk with anyone
on the street he seemed to rest on his cane.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">It was reported that he had over thirty wives;
eighteen of them were his lawful and wedded wives.
They were young women in years, ranging from sixteen
to thirty. The rest of his wives were older
women, who were sealed to him. Most of them were
widows of Mormon officials. He was said to have a
wife in nearly every town in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. While
traveling and attending to church and official duties,
therefore, he could be at home with one of his wives
every night. It was said that he had over one hundred
children in his different homes.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">In traveling through the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Territory of Utah</placeName>, we
found that there were not as many polygamous 
marriages as had been reported. The number that were
reported were among the wealthy class and the high
officials of the church. They were required to pay a
certain amount of tithing each year. Those who were
not able to pay that amount were not considered able
to support more than one family. There seemed to be
much dissatisfaction and jealousy in most polygamous
families. The first wife seemed to have control of 
everything belonging to the family. The other wives
could not buy or sell without her consent.</seg></p>

<p><persName key="Thomas, D. K.">Thomas</persName> and <persName key="Woodbury">Woodbury</persName> attended the Mormon Conference and <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>’s Theatre. The
Tabernacle being too small to hold the large number
of saints who attended the meetings, a place was
prepared for out&#8212;of&#8212;door meetings along and east of

<pb n="127" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.132"/>

the Tabernacle. Seats for several thousand people
were prepared. A covering for shade was constructed
out of forks, poles and pine branches. At the north
end of the ground, a stand was erected large enough
to seat all of the officials and the twelve apostles of
the church.</p>

<p><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> being indisposed, <persName key="Kimble, Heber C.">Heber C. Kimble</persName>,
the vice&#8212;president, presided and made the first talk.
He did not announce any text, and his talk was
mainly abusing the Gentiles and lauding the saints.
It was more like a political meeting than a religious
gathering. When he became tired of abusing the 
Gentiles and commenced praising the saints, his talk was
frequently interrupted by <q>"amens"</q> from the entire
congregation. One old lady, apparently about four
score and ten years of age, in order to make it more
emphatic, arose to her feet to say <q>"amen,"</q> which she
repeated several times.</p>

<p>All of those who do not belong to the Mormon
Church are Gentiles. All of the speakers who 
followed <persName key="Kimble, Heber C.">Kimble</persName> spoke along the same lines. The
speakers frequently asked those present to sanction
what they said by saying <q>"amen,"</q> which they
heartily did.</p>

<p>The people at the Theatre were much more quiet
during the play and the order much better than at
the Conference, owing, perhaps, to the strict rules
posted on the outside as well as on the inside of the
building. Police, moreover, were stationed in all
parts of the building. Tickets for seats in all parts

<pb n="128" xml:id="mmm.wa.thomas.1917.133"/>

of the building were sold at the uniform price of one
dollar. The play, given by a <placeName type="state" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> company, was
considered a good one.</p>

<p><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> occupied his box on the right side
of the stage, and was accompanied by eight or ten
young women, who were supposed to be some of his
wives. <persName key="Kimble, Heber C.">Heber C. Kimble</persName>, the vice president, occupied
a box on the left side of the stage, with a number of
young women.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>