<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Two Americas</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename>Rose</forename> <forename type="middle">Lambart</forename> <surname>Price</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.wa.price.1877</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m" type="main">The Two Americas</title>
		            <title level="m" type="sub">An Account of Sport and Travel. With Notes on Men and Manners in North and South America.</title>
                    <author><forename>Rose</forename> <forename type="middle">Lambart</forename> <surname>Price</surname></author>
                    <publisher>Sampson Low, Marston, Searle, and Rivington</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>London, ENG</pubPlace>
                    <extent></extent>
                    <date when="1877">1877</date>
		    <note type="source">Rose Lambart Price.  <hi rend="italic">The Two Americas.</hi> London, ENG: Sampson Low, Marston, Searle and Rivington, 1877. 228-270.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>western_americana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2010-07-15"><name>Rosie Hanneke</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2011-02-16"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enrichment</change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>

<text>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="228" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.257"/>
  
<head>CHAPTER X.</head>

<p><hi rend="center">Lathrop&#8212;Merced&#8212;American Politicians&#8212;Tuolumne Grove&#8212;The Yo-Semite Valley&#8212;Garrote&#8212;Mammoth Grove of "Big Trees," Calaveras County&#8212;South Park Grove of "Big Trees"&#8212;Lake Tahoe&#8212;Fishing on Tahoe&#8212;Carson&#8212;Night ride on a "cow-catcher"&#8212;Visit to a silver mine&#8212;Gold&#8212;Earthquakes&#8212;Virginia City&#8212;Land of Mormon&#8212;Funeral of George A. Smith&#8212;The Tabernacle&#8212;A Mormon sermon&#8212;Sulphur Springs&#8212;The trowel-bayonet&#8212;The Great Salt Lake&#8212;Jackass rabbits.</hi></p>

<!-- Following Section Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows Massacre:

<p>A<hi rend="smallcaps">t</hi> Lathrop we halted for dinner, and here I parted
with my friends, Mr. and Mrs. G., who continued
their journey to San Francisco. The next passenger-
train for Merced did not go for five hours, and I was,
after they left, somewhat disconsolately contemplating
a large grizzly bear confined on the platform in a
cage, and anatomically considering the best place for
driving in a bullet if ever I got a shot at one,&#8212;a
favourite habit of mine when examining captive wild
beasts,&#8212;when I heard the whistle of a goods train,
and finding that I could go by it at once if I liked,
and save a long delay, I jumped on board and
started.</p>

<p>Our track lay through a perfectly flat stubble-
covered plain, and though it was interesting to know
that much of the land we were passing over, though
a common prairie and covered with shaparall and
scrub not six years ago, was now yielding from fifty

<pb n="229" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.258"/>

to a hundred bushels of grain an acre, the monotony
became unbearable, and I was heartily glad when the
journey ended. These great plains are horribly 
irksome. In England a man can amuse himself for
hours&#8212;at any rate, I can&#8212;by selecting the places in
a fence we are coming at, that, out hunting, I should
ride for, and looking as the train passes to see
whether my judgment was sound, or if I should have
got a "cropper." Here the land was flat as a 
pancake, not a fence or tree to be seen, or even a bird,
to break the never-ending stagnation of sameness.</p>

<p>Merced is a town of but little over two years’
growth. It has a first-class hotel, "El Capitan,"
which is four stories high, and can accommodate two
hundred visitors; and a handsome Court House,
which would be an ornament to a town ten times its 
size and importance. From Merced the tourist starts
by coach for Yo-Semite.</p>

<p>The rivalry that exists between the different
companies renders a decision as to the route to be
taken somewhat baffling, each tout swearing that the
other’s road is uninteresting or wrong, and that the
unavailing regret of a lifetime will follow its 
selection. Being hard up for amusement to kill time,
I made no choice until the different stages were
actually about to start, and was considerably 
entertained by the skirmishes which continually took
place at intervals during the day, between the rival
agents to secure my dollars.</p>

<p>In the evening I was fortunate enough to hear a
couple of republican members of Congress, who
were what is usually termed "stumping the

<pb n="230" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.259"/>

country," give vent to their pent-up patriotism by a
violent attack on another body of political opponents
termed "independents." The speeches took place
opposite the hotel, and though the audience chiefly
consisted of people belonging to the Democrat 
persuasion, they listened to the address of their 
antagonists with attention and forbearance, and gave
them a far more liberal hearing, than a Radical
audience at home would ever dream of giving 
Conservatives similarly situated.</p>

<p>A gentleman, called Bidwell, candidate for the
post of Governor, was the chief object of their 
vituperation; and the fact of his owning a farm of some
fifty thousand acres, which was all highly cultivated,
and had been made so entirely by his own energy
and capital, seemed their principal grievance and
cause of complaint against him.</p>

<p>In the course of the speeches, one of the 
honourable gentlemen described how, from the summit of a
neighbouring hill, he had beheld the vast plain
covered with standing crops, amid which was situated
this gentleman's country-house, and how his blood
boiled at such an act of monopoly. "Am I," he
cried, "in England or America? Is this the castle of
some feudal baron&#8212;or the house of an American
citizen? Am I under the Cross of St. George&#8212;or
the glorious ‘Stars and Stripes’ of liberty and
freedom? Citizens, this land should have belonged
to you. Each hundred and sixty acres should have
supported a happy family," &amp;c., &amp;c. As the property
in question was by no means an unusually large one
for California, and as there are any amount of millions

<pb n="231" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.260"/>

of acres of equally valuable land in the States, still
lying idle and uninhabited, I thought it a little
rough on Mr. Bidwell, that, after taking so much
trouble, an outsider should quietly distribute his 
property into one-hundred-and-sixty-acre lots; though
goodness knows such political reasoning is not 
uncommon, as one of our own shining lights attempted
a line of policy not very dissimilar with regard to
other people’s estates in Ireland.</p>

<p>All staging in America commences abominably
early, and six o’clock one morning saw me start with
a four-horse team for the Yo-Semite <hi rend="italic">via</hi> Coulterville.
I was fortunate in having pleasant companions for 
the trip, and during my stay in the valley we
generally did our sight-seeing together. Coulterville
is an almost deserted mining-town. In its immediate
vicinity the surface of the land is burrowed and
turned over in every direction, lasting monuments to
all ages of the race for gold, which rendered California
once so famous; but not till we reached Dudley’s, a
comfortable little crib where we spent the night, did
the aspect of the country become a bit inviting, or
show the slightest approach to pretty scenery. Next
day the drive became more interesting. For miles
we passed through the Foot Hills, covered with 
endless acres of forest; and gradually getting into the
Sierra Nevadas, beheld the magnificent timber for
which this part of the world is so justly celebrated.</p>

<p>All the trees were large, but occasionally we met
some veritable giants among the sugar-pines, which
ran frequently up to two hundred feet in height, often
having a diameter of as much as nine feet at their

<pb n="232" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.261"/>

base. Great, however, as these trees undoubtedly
were, the Tuolumne grove of "big trees" (<hi rend="italic">Sequoia
gigantea</hi>), which we drove through in the afternoon,
quite surpassed them. The stump of one, partly
burned out, was over twenty feet in diameter, and
many of the others were but little inferior to it in
size. Most of them ran to a height of from two
hundred to two hundred and fifty feet, and their huge
stature and bulk certainly produced an effect on all of
us of more astonishment and wonder than any trees
had ever done before. One of our party, an American
colonel, who had lost an arm during their late civil
war, was justly indignant at the manner in which
many of the trees were disfigured by idiots hacking
their names on the bark. All through the Yo-Semite
I afterwards found this to be the prevailing custom,
and though I thought our own people were the
greatest snobs in existence for cutting, hacking, and
disfiguring trees, churches, and buildings of all sorts,
I am glad to be able to add as a rider, to gratify my
national conceit, that in this most unpleasant family
failing our Yankee cousins lick us hollow.</p>

<p>We passed through some exquisite morsels of
scenery, and at last reached the crowning point of all
that is enchanting&#8212;the great valley of the Yo-Semite
itself. Words are quite inadequate to do it justice,
or convey to the reader anything of an idea of this
marvellously beautiful spot. I not only never saw,
but cannot even conceive anything more soul-
inspiring or grand. What so many skilled writers
have failed in attempting to describe, I shall not
venture on; for I never read an account yet that

<pb n="233" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.262"/>

brought the picture to my mind’s eye that I now saw
before me.</p>

<p>The road into the valley was just sufficiently wide
to allow our leaders room to move along, but nothing
could have passed us on the way. In some places the
grade was exceedingly steep; the corners were 
invariably as sharp as they could possibly be made with
the slightest regard to safety, and, the whole way
down, the smallest move off the road would have
entailed certain destruction for all of us. I occupied
the box-seat, and was delighted with the manner our
driver (the "Buffalo" he was called, and I do not
know his real name) handled his team of five horses,
the three leaders being harnessed abreast. With the
brake hard on, we went at first a fair trot all the way.
Over such ground a man should have a nerve of iron,
a hand of steel, and the eye of a hawk, and my friend
"the Buffalo" seemed to possess all of them. As I
have observed before, there are no "whips" in the
world that can touch the Californians&#8212;I do not mean
to say that there are not a few "muffs" among them;
but the general lot are marvels, and if you sit by the
side of a good man on visiting the Yo-Semite for the
first time, I do not think ages will ever efface your
enjoyment of the drive.</p>

<p>There is little to choose in the matter of hotels.
They are not bad, but, considering the length of 
time the valley has been declared a "national park,"
none of them are as good as they ought to be. Smith’s
Cosmopolitan Saloon and Bath-house is the only
establishment among them that shows any of the 
enterprise and improvement that the Americans as a

<pb n="234" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.263"/>

rule are famous for. If, immediately after your hot
and dusty drive, Mr. Smith makes <hi rend="italic">himself</hi> for the
thirsty traveller one of his celebrated iced claret
punches, a very happy termination to the day’s 
journey will have been satisfactorily arrived at, as he
is certainly one of the most clever manipulators of
liquor in the States. <hi rend="italic">Apropos</hi> of drinks, much as the
Californians praise their wine to strangers, I observed
they studiously refrained from drinking it 
themselves; and though San Franciscan bars are 
invariably crowded, I never heard any of the <hi rend="italic">habitués</hi> ever
call for the beverage they so frequently vaunt as
equalling the wines of France or Spain.</p>

<p>Next morning we rode to the Nevada falls, 700
feet high and called by the Indians, Yo-wi—e; had
luncheon at Snow’s hotel, and after a swim in a 
deliciously cool little pond just above them, sent our
ponies round, and walked to the Vernal, or Pi-wa-
ack, which signifies a cataract of diamonds, and has
about 350 feet of clear descent.</p>

<p>Our next expedition was to Mirror Lake, on whose
surface during a clear still morning, the reflection of
the "South Dome," 4737 feet above the Merced river,
and the perpendicular face of smoothly cut granite on
the side towards Tenaza Ca&#241;on, are as distinctly
visible as one’s own countenance when looking at a
glass. The "Bridal Veil" fall, Po-ho-no, or Spirit of
the Evil Wind, 940 feet, was also done. This was
a very easy day’s work, as, with the exception of a 
slight scramble of a few hundred yards over rocks to
get to the immediate base of the Bridal Veil, both
places were visited by carriage.</p>

<pb n="235" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.264"/>

<p>Glacier Point and South Dome formed the next
trip. This, in my opinion, is the cream of the whole
lot of points of observation to which trails have been
cut, and strangers recommended to visit. By a 
winding zigzag path an altitude of over 4000 feet is
gradually attained. As each grade in the road is
ascended, fresh beauties in the valley are brought to
view; cattle and horses become mere specks; until
at last the grand old El Capitan&#8212;Tu-tock-a-mu-la&#8212;
lies almost beneath us, and on looking over a rock at
the summit, an apparently perpendicular wall shows
a sheer descent to the bottom, and startles the gazer 
by its terrible abruptness and fearful depth. From
this point one not only gets an entire view of the
valley, absolutely looking down on the Yo-Semite
falls, themselves 2634 feet, but gains also an 
extended range of the Sierra Nevada Mountains, which
rise in serried peaks, pine-clad or snow-capped, far, far
away in the distance. Nothing can be more beautiful
or grander; and if time should be an object, and only
one day be devoted by the hurried traveller to see the
valley, he cannot do better than select Glacier Point
as the one thing to be visited.</p>

<p>In the Yo-Semite are several very beautiful trees
for cabinet purposes, and a German residing here
has manufactured many pieces of inlaid work formed
entirely from the woods found in the valley. The
Manzaneta (<hi rend="italic">Arctostaphylos glauca</hi>), the Buck-eye
(<hi rend="italic">&#1236;sculus Paira</hi>), and the Laurel (<hi rend="italic">Tetranthera 
Californica</hi>), all take a beautiful polish, and are much
sought after for veneering.</p>

<p>I killed a few dozen small trout with fly in the

<pb n="236" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.265"/>

Merced river. The fish run small, and the water is very
clear and much hacked in the immediate vicinity of
the hotel; but by riding about eight miles down the
river, tolerably fair sport can be obtained, and any
one possessed of ordinary skill will easily capture
from three to six dozen.</p>

<p>My friend Mr. G., who is, however, a first-class
fisherman, constantly made much larger bags; but
ordinary anglers will easily manage the numbers I
have given them, though the hotel-keepers invariably
talk of their extraordinary shyness, and pretend that
the Indians alone are able to kill trout on the Merced.</p>

<p>Having exhausted the principal views of the Yo-
Semite, though still wishing to linger, we tore 
ourselves away, and at the usual disagreeably early hour
started one morning for the Mammoth and South
Park Grove of Sequoias in Calaveras County, a
three days' drive by stage from the valley. Our
intention was to have halted for the night at Chinese
Camp, which, with any regard to equalising the
distance and comfort of next day's drive, would
undoubtedly have been our wisest plan; but at
Garrote we were seized upon by a predatory and
plausible inn-keeper, who by the bribe of a butterfly
to one man, and a swim to another, prevailed on the
whole party to halt there, and I was perforce obliged
to follow their example, though much against my
will. The butterfly was described as being rare and
beautiful; the bathing as refreshing as divine. The
road, like all Californian ones, was dusty in the
extreme, and cleanliness being next to godliness,
only a good deal easier of attainment, I became

<pb n="237" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.266"/>

somewhat reconciled to my fate, and cross-questioned
our plausible friend as to the locality of the stream
he had been describing. How far off was it ? Oh,
quite close&#8212;not a quarter of a mile,&#8212;and he
would show us the way. Was it deep? Not
very, but we could wade in nicely. Away started
the Colonel and myself in the direction pointed out,
and at last, after a hot and tiresome walk, of at least
a mile and a half, came on the long-looked-for water.
It was a dirty little mud ditch, not four feet wide,
used for conveying water to some neighbouring
hydraulic and placer mines. Not two inches of
water ran over its slimy-looking bottom, and the
wading <hi rend="italic">in</hi> could only be accomplished by wading
<hi rend="italic">through</hi> two feet of soft mud. The butterfly, I am
happy to say, was as great a sell as the bath; but I
will do the fellow justice by saying that his feeding
was good, his charges reasonable, and his house
scrupulously clean.</p>

<p>Our next day’s drive lay through a country
burrowed and excavated in every possible direction
by the seekers after gold. Round Senora parties
were still busily engaged at this captivating species
of toil, and several mines were pointed out by our
driver which were yielding very heavy receipts
above their working expenditure. Parts of the
country were pretty, and particularly so near where
we crossed the Tuolumne river by a ferry kept by
an old Yorkshire man, who gave us several bunches
of fine grapes. At Murpheystown, a small village
entirely supported by a mining population, we
halted for the night, and a good plunge in the clear

<pb n="238" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.267"/>

blue water of an old worked-out and deserted mine
over a hundred feet deep, reconciled us to our
disappointment on the previous day.</p>

<p>The elections were still being busily pushed, and 
noisy politicians loudly proclaimed their individual
opinions, until gradually in the small hours of the
morning I went to sleep with the sounds of 
Republican, Independent, Democrat, and Dolly Varden,
rapidly chasing one another through my bewildered
brain, till Morpheus reigned triumphant, and 
temporary oblivion at last conquered all things. Next
morning we again started, but this day only sixteen
miles had to be accomplished, and a four hours’ drive
&#8212;the horses were bad and the roads hilly&#8212;landed us
at the Mammoth Grove. In one of the narrowest
and worst parts of the road we suddenly came on a
waggon load of "campers." To pass abreast was
impossible, and I soon had an opportunity of judging
of one of the many resources of Californian travel.
The driver of the waggon, unhitching his team,
fastened them behind, and we, all getting out of our
coach, clapped on to the pole and quietly dragged
the obstructive conveyance over the almost 
precipitous bank, locked the wheels to prevent its
sliding, and passed above in safety.</p>

<p>The hotel kept by Messrs. De Briges and Sperry
at the "big trees" is comfortable and clean, and the
<hi rend="italic">cuisine</hi> far superior to anything we met with in the
Yo-Semite. The approach to it passes between the
Two Sentinels, each over three hundred feet high;
the largest is twenty-three feet in diameter, and on the
right-hand side lies the celebrated Mammoth Grove.</p>

<pb n="239" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.268"/>

<p>Description almost fails to give a person an 
adequate idea of the vastness and grandeur of these huge
vegetable monsters, and even after viewing them, one
is obliged to measure, to get inside, to walk round
or crawl on the fallen ones, to gradually comprehend
their enormous structure. One of these trees which
has fallen is called the "Father of the Forest," and
must have been four hundred and fifty feet high,
and forty feet in diameter before it fell. Through a
hundred feet of the trunk, which is hollow, I rode
a moderate-sized horse without stooping my head.
In 1853 one of the largest trees, ninety-two feet in
circumference, and over three hundred feet high,
was cut down. Five men worked twenty-five days
in felling it, and as many as thirty-two dancers have
figured together on its stump.</p>

<p>Near the stump lies a section of the trunk, twenty-
five feet in diameter. And beyond lies the immense
trunk as it fell, measuring three hundred and two
feet from end to end. Upon this was constructed a 
bar-room and a bowling alley, which stretching along
its upper surface for a distance of eighty-one feet,
afforded ample space for two alley-beds side by side.
I believe there are ninety-three of these sequoias in
the grove, not including those under twenty years’
growth, but out of the number there are ten, each
thirty feet in diameter; and over seventy, between
fifteen and thirty feet for the same measurement.
All the largest have names nailed upon them, and
"Starr King," three hundred and sixty-six feet high,
is, I believe, the biggest standing in the group.</p>

<p>Having dawdled for a couple of days among these

<pb n="240" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.269"/>

monsters, and varied the amusement by catching a
few trout in a small stream ("creek," they always
call them here) running within a couple of miles of
the house, we determined on visiting the South Park 
Grove, six miles distant from our hotel.</p>

<p>Horses, guides, and luncheon being forthcoming,
we started off, and after an exceedingly pleasant ride
arrived at a likely-looking stream about a mile from
the grove, where, having my trout-rod with me and
a cast of flies, I soon managed to kill sufficient fish to
form an acceptable addition to our mid-day meal.
The South Park Grove is far away the finest of all
the groups of <hi rend="italic">Sequoia gigantea</hi> yet discovered. It
contains one thousand three hundred and eighty of
these trees, many of them of immense size. Into a
hollowed portion five of us rode our horses, which
had plenty of room to turn without the slightest
inconvenience, and the guide declared he had seen
fifteen mounted people inside at the same time. A
tall, wiry-looking man has located himself in this
grove, and pre-empted the usual allowance of land
about it. He took us to his house, which is formed
in the hollow of a nobly-grown sequoia. It made
a first—rate chamber, affording plenty of space for
bed, table, and chair, and even allowed him room to
offer, during very severe weather, stabling and 
protection to his trusty steed. In this singular abode,
for eleven years, he had resided alone and happy.
No rent to pay, taxes to afflict, or wife to torment
him. He ate when hungry, and slept when tired;
fished during the summer, and hunted bear and
deer and did his trapping during winter, and was,

<pb n="241" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.270"/>

according to his own account, perfectly contented
with his lot. One of the chief charms of this grove at
present, independent of its vast size, is that everything
is in a perfect state of nature. The trees are 
undoubtedly much larger and better grown than any
of those at the Mammoth Grove, and are not spoiled
by having a lot of names, like so many signboards,
stuck upon them. They are less visited, and are 
consequently less disfigured by Tom, Dick, and Harry 
hacking their uninteresting designations all over the 
bark; and, as no, hotel or bar-room is in the 
immediate vicinity, silence and nature reign supreme. On
the embers of an oak-bark fire I cooked our trout,
and a delightful afternoon was passed in wandering
quietly about this wonderful grove. The sugar-pines
(<hi rend="italic">Pinus sabininai</hi>) seem to attain more astonishing
proportions in the immediate vicinity of these "big
trees" than in any other locality. Some of them
attain a height of two hundred and seventy feet, and
not unfrequently a diameter of from nine to eleven
and a half and twelve feet. Their proportions are,
to my mind, far more symmetrical than the sequoia;
and, notwithstanding the latter’s enormous growth,
I was often puzzled to tell, while looking at them
together, which tree I admired most.</p>

<p>After leaving Calaveras our party broke up. Some
went east, and others west; and, tumbling across
another wandering baronet, we directed our steps
towards Virginia City, the great centre of all silver
mining; the modern Potosi in fact of North America.
Mr. G. had given me a letter of introduction to Messrs.
Mackay and Fair, the managers and part proprietors

<pb n="242" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.271"/>

of the California and Virginia Consolidated Mines, at
the present moment the most wealthy and best paying
in the world, and H., thinking the opportunity of
seeing them under their auspices too good to be lost,
came with me, though he was in a red-hot hurry to
get to Denver for the shooting.</p>

<p>The scenery from the train in the neighbourhood
of Cape Horn was undoubtedly grand, and as the
guide-books have it: "Timid ladies draw back with
a shudder, one look into the awful chasm being 
sufficient to unsettle their nerves, and deprive them of
the wish to linger near the grandest scene on the
whole line of the trans-continental railroad." Had I
not so very recently seen Yo-Semite, I might have
admired it more, but under the circumstances I was
rather glad when at 10 <hi rend="smallcaps">P.M.</hi> our train arrived at a
station called Truckee, where, at a second or third rate
kind of inn attached to the railway station, we were
obliged to pass the night.</p>

<p>Our drive next morning from Truckee to Lake
Tahoe, along the banks of the River Truckee, was one
to be remembered. A well-kept road followed the
river’s bank through forest and meadow, forming a
kind of ca&#241;on. On each side rose steep 
mountains, in some places showing extraordinary rock
formations, whose fantastic outlines and queer 
conformation added considerably to the general effect of all
around us. The river was clear as crystal and formed
a very beautiful piece of water, spoiled, however, for
trout fishing by the numberless saw-mills and mill-
dams that are established along its banks; this part
of Nevada being the great lumber region of the

<pb n="243" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.272"/>

state, and Truckee City (almost every town of half-
a-dozen streets, or even houses, in America is called
a city) the principal dep&#244;t and chief market.</p>

<p>On our road we were pointed out the scene of a
recent coach disaster, in which a couple of people
were killed, and a few more badly injured. It seems
that in going down a steep incline with a high bank
on one side and a precipice on the other, the brake 
had carried away. The horses became unruly, and
finally the stage was pitched about sixty or eighty
feet down an almost precipitous declivity, killing and
wounding the people mentioned. The horses were, I
believe, all killed, and on examining the place, my
only surprise was that the whole party had not 
suffered the same fate.</p>

<p>Our intention had been to cross Lake Tahoe at
once and go on to Virginia City, but while waiting
for the steam-boat which was to convey us across the
lake, H. became so enamoured of a beautiful dish of
trout, some of them running about five pounds, that
he determined on staying to try his luck, a local
fisherman promising to provide the necessary 
equipment, and I was only too glad of the delay. Lake
Tahoe is really very beautiful. The water is 
singularly clear. Even on coral banks in the Indian
Ocean, atolls rising from an almost unfathomable
depth nearly perpendicularly, and celebrated for
the extraordinary translucency of the blue water
that surrounds them, have I never seen to greater
depths. On a calm, clear, bright day, when the
surface of the lake is unruffled, a white plate can
easily be discerned a hundred feet beneath its tranquil

<pb n="244" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.273"/>

waters. The counties of Eldorado and Placer in
California, and Washoe, Ormsby, and Douglas in
Nevada, share it between them. Its greatest depth
is 1700 feet, its length twenty-two miles, and width
about ten miles.</p>

<p>After a swim we repaired to the boat, where our
fisherman awaited us, and judge of our surprise when
the means of capture met our astonished gaze. A
huge cod-line, armed with a hook large enough to
kill a shark, was the rude and unsportsmanlike 
implement used for killing the speckled beauties, whose
good looks we had both so much admired. No play
and no sport could possibly be obtained, as neck and
crop by main force the wretched fish is bundled into
the boat. Of course fishing under such circumstances
was a "dead sell," and not having our own gear with
us, nothing could be done. The Tahoe hotel was
exceedingly comfortable, and I can hardly recommend
a pleasanter or more charming spot for any one
willing to linger a week amid delightful scenery,
with the certain knowledge of returning each day
after his wanderings to a good dinner; but should he
be an angler, let him remember to bring his own rod.</p>

<p>Our next day was somewhat eventful. It was
polling day for California, and instead of being 
conveyed directly across the lake to meet the coach for
Carson, we were trotted round to accommodate the
different voters whose patriotism demanded their
presence at the poll. The cruise was certainly
pleasant enough, and one could hardly fail to admire
the beauty of all around, but the delay nearly 
necessitated our spending the night in Carson, an event,

<pb n="245" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.274"/>

under the peculiar circumstances of our being pressed
for time, devoutly to be dreaded. On arriving at the
pier, we were, as I expected, several hours late for the
train; and not even the driving of Hank Monk,
Mark Twain’s "b&#234;te noir," served to do us any good.</p>

<p>Carson, the capital town of Nevada, seemed a
bustling thriving spot. The shops appeared good
and the streets crowded, but there was nothing of any
particular interest to be seen or done, and we wanted
to get on. All the passenger trains for that day had
departed, and our only chance being that the manager
of the line would give us permission to travel up on
one of the freight trains during the night, we sent in
our cards and requested an interview. This 
gentleman was no exception to the rest of his countrymen 
with whom I have had the pleasure of being brought
into contact; and being as kind and obliging as all
the educated Americans I have ever come across
invariably are to Englishmen who require a favour
and ask for it civilly, he readily gave the necessary
order, which enabled us to reach Virginia City 
without stopping; At 10 <hi rend="smallcaps">P.M.</hi> our train started. The
waggons were all quite full; the standing room on
the engine (already pretty well crowded by the
driver, stoker, and conductor) was hot and dirty; so
a good-natured clerk belonging to the company, who
came down to see us off, recommended our sitting just
over the cow-catcher in front of the engine.</p>

<p>I remember once seeing in ‘Punch’ a cartoon which
represented a director somewhat similarly placed, with
the exception, that I think he had a glass of grog and
an arm-chair. I did not envy his position even then,

<pb n="246" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.275"/>

but little thought that circumstances over which I
had no control would have ever led me to be situated
infinitely worse off. Up we both scrambled, the
whistle screamed, and holding on tightly by a
stanchion, we dashed forward into darkness. Our
billet had certainly the sensation of novelty to 
recommend it, and after confidence became restored by
getting over the first half-dozen miles in safety, we
lighted our pipes, and began somewhat to relish our
queer ride. As well as we could make out, the line
seemed occasionally to run over ground somewhat
similar in places to Cape Horn on the Union Pacific.
Lights and fires at times glimmered in the valleys
many feet beneath us, and an occasional streak like
silver told us that we passed a stream. Going through
the tunnels produced an odd sensation. However, on
the whole we both enjoyed the trip, and in a few hours
our journey ended by the engine suddenly detaching
itself from its burden, and halting at a "Round house"
about a mile from the city.</p>

<p>The conductor I imagine went with his freight, as
he did not take our fare and we never saw him again;
the stoker disappeared likewise, and the driver was
of an uncommunicative and slightly morose 
disposition, not given to answer questions. "Where are we
to go?" asked H. "The engine stays here," was his
laconic reply; and almost intimating by his silence
that we might go to the d&#8212;l if it pleased us, he also
vanished from our view.</p>

<p>Our position was so ludicrous and absurd that we
both fairly screamed with laughter. Alone on an
engine, in the dark, hampered with a lot of luggage,

<pb n="247" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.276"/>

and not knowing where on earth we were, for a few
minutes we could only look at each other and roar.
There seemed every prospect of our spending the
night by the wayside, when fortunately we discovered
a couple of men smoking in the engine-house, who
were of a more friendly and amiable disposition than 
the driver. They allowed us to leave our baggage
in a place of safety, and telling us the town was about
a mile off, pointed out the way, and H. shouldering a
light portmanteau, we again started in the dark.
Tripping over railway sleepers, barking our shins
against unseen obstacles, at last we reached the
town, a couple of as disreputable looking objects as
well could be imagined. The road between Lake
Tahoe and Carson is far and away the dirtiest in
the West, which is saying a very great deal; and
the blacks gathered on the engine, lying over the
coating of dust picked up during our drive with
Hank Monk, rendered us simply filthy. H. also
carried his portmanteau himself, a thing very few
free-born Americans ever dream of doing, and the
remarks that greeted us on passing through a 
somewhat disreputable portion of the town were, if not
complimentary, at least good-natured and amusing.
"Where are you poor beggars going to?" "Pretty
well played out I guess?” and "Have a drink?"
were the various comments of the sympathising
"innocents," who evidently took us for discharged
miners or workmen on the tramp. At last we 
succeeded in getting comfortably settled in an hotel,
and were glad enough to turn in after our 
adventurous but somewhat fatiguing journey.</p>

<pb n="248" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.277"/>

<p>Next day I presented my introduction to Messrs.
Mackay and Fair, who were exceedingly kind, and
sent one of their foremen to show and explain the
workings of their mine.</p>

<p>Our first visit was to the robing-room, where, after
divesting ourselves of every stitch of clothing, we
were soon equipped in full miner’s costume, of shirt,
trowsers, thick stockings, boots, and an old hat. Thus
apparelled we were conducted to the mouth of the
shaft, and holding tightly to an iron bar running
across the cage which held us, we rapidly descended
into the bowels of the earth. Fifteen hundred feet
were soon run down, and stepping out of the cage
we were introduced to Mr. Lamb, the leading foreman
of the gang of hands at present working, who giving
us each a lantern, conducted us round the various
workings, passages, and shafts; pointing out what he
deemed interesting, and explaining everything we
saw. The heat in places was intense, but 
ventilation effected by engines worked by compressed air
rendered it perfectly healthy. No noxious gases are
ever developed, and naked lights are carried freely
and without danger. In each shaft was placed a
barrel of iced water, from which the tired miners
drank copiously, as, stripped to their trowsers and
pouring with sweat, they from time to time repaired
to them for this grateful refreshment.</p>

<p>The quality of ore obtained in the various 
workings varied considerably, but some was of immense
value, and so thoroughly impregnated with gold
that even by the dull light of the miner’s candle
we could see the yellow flecks that betokened the

<pb n="249" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.278"/>

presence of the precious metal. In these places we
were literally surrounded by silver. The ground we 
trod on was silver, almost pure, and the sides of the
shaft and the roof were formed of the same substance.
A square, formed by cuttings some 200 feet long,
was almost entirely composed of this extraordinarily
valuable deposit, and according to the most reliable
authority the estimated value of what we ourselves
beheld was £74,000,000 sterling. The work on the 
men is severe, but as none receive less than sixteen
shillings a day, and a foreman gets £750 a year,
there is little difficulty in providing as many hands as
are required. As the ore is excavated from the mine
the vacant space is carefully shored up with timber,
and eventually a solid mass of wood replaces the
abstracted metal. It was singular to observe the
commencement of the "find" in the shafts. As
regular as possible were the marks which betokened
the presence of the metal, which was preceded by dirt,
clay, and porphyry. The end of a worked-out shaft
always finished by showing silver, porphyry, clay, and
dirt, in as regular a succession as the strata through 
which we entered. I was surprised at the extreme
dryness of the workings; hardly a drop of water was
to be found in any of them except what was used for
drinking purposes, and occasionally water had 
absolutely to be pumped on the timbers to prevent dry rot.</p>

<p>Such enormous excavations as are here perpetually
being carried on necessarily take proportionately
enormous masses of timber to replace them.
Hundreds of thousands of square feet of ore have to
be replaced by an equally great quantity of wood,

<pb n="250" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.279"/>

and whole forests are soon buried deep in the inmost
recesses of the earth, peradventure after the lapse of
many years to undergo a strange reconstitution, and
bother some scientific discoverer as to how on earth
such enormous masses of&#8212;whatever it may be&#8212;got
together. The mere conveyance of these forests,
doomed to such premature burial, was in itself a
herculean labour, until the managers of the mine, at
the cost of about a quarter of a million of dollars,
built a water flume fifteen miles in length, which,
from the heavily-wooded summits of the Sierras
west and north-west from Huffaker, belonging to
the company, conveys at little expense and with
extraordinary rapidity all the timber they can
possibly require. The flume is constructed of planks
two inches thick, and built in the shape of the letter
V. To gain a uniform grade it was found necessary
to build it on trestle work and stringers from one end 
to the other, and this framework, which in some places
is forty-eight feet high, is substantial enough to support
a narrow-gauge railway, it being thoroughly braced
longitudinally and across. All the main supports,
which are five feet apart, are firmly set in mud sills;
the boxes rest in brackets placed four feet apart, and
these again rest upon substantial stringers. Mr.
Fair described a trip he took by nailing a piece of
board at the end of one of the V-shaped boxes, and
being floated down by the workmen.</p>

<p>A strip of wood nailed across furnished a seat,
and being once started, away he flew at the rate of
twenty miles an hour for a commencement. The
average grade is sixteen inches to sixteen feet, but

<pb n="251" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.280"/>

the sharpest fall is three in six, which is, however,
only for two hundred feet, and over this he flew at 
such a pace that he could hardly gain breath. H.
and myself were both extremely anxious for a sail on
such queer waters, and begged hard for a ride. Mr.
Fair, however, declared the risk too great, that he
had only gone down as a matter of duty, and that
nothing would ever induce him to do so again. As the
workmen go down it almost every day, this was all
rubbish; however, he would not give us a mount, and
we were both a good deal disappointed at his raising
our curiosity without gratifying it.</p>

<p>At one of the richest deposits our guide begged
we would take a sample of the ore, and seizing a
pick, I set to work at the part being cleared out. It
was astonishing with what surprising ease the pick
detached large masses of metal, and selecting a small
piece strongly marked with gold, I took it away in
remembrance of our visit. I never saw anything
more interesting than these extraordinary mines, and
we both felt quite bewildered at the enormous
amount of wealth we beheld all round us.</p>

<p>In connection with these mines, Mr. G. related a
singular fact which I fancy is not generally known,
but which must I imagine upset many a cherished
theory on the subject of earthquakes.</p>

<p>While he was a resident in Virginia City, an
earthquake of unusual severity one day terrified all
its inhabitants. Houses shook, roofs fell in, and
frightened women and children rushed into the
streets thinking their last hour surely had arrived.
After a few terrible shocks, the commotion subsided

<pb n="252" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.281"/>

and tranquillity again reigned in the shaken town.
Immediate apprehension for their own safety having
ceased, the cry instantly became, "The miners!" Away
rushed mothers and children to the mouths of the
various shafts that honeycombed the mountain.
Again terror, more intense than that caused by the
fear of personal safety, seized the mother and the
wife, and half dead with excitement, they reached the
pit’s mouth. The miners, astonished, looked at them,
and could not make out what was the matter. The
earthquake! "Guess they had felt no earthquake.
What the thunder was up?" So indeed it was; and
fifteen hundred feet under ground not the slightest
movement of a shock, so severe on the surface as to
cause the most intense alarm even among a 
population comparatively inured to such visitations, was
even felt.</p>

<p>Having been through all the workings, a task that
took nearly three hours in an atmosphere somewhat
resembling the hot room in a Turkish bath, we bid
adieu to our good-natured conductor, regretting that
our unscientific education had not enabled us better 
to follow and comprehend the many descriptions he
so kindly tried to make us understand; and once
more getting on the cage we ascended to earth.</p>

<p>On our arrival we found a warm bath in readiness,
and a glass of excellent whisky-and-water soon made
us fit to examine the next process in the working of
the metal.</p>

<p>Mr. John Mackay now kindly became our pilot,
and showed the first process, where the large lumps
of ore, having been brought up from the mine, are

<pb n="253" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.282"/>

crushed by what, not knowing its correct name in
machinery, I shall call a "mouth of iron." These
iron jaws having broken in pieces the larger lumps,
they are passed under stampers, ponderous iron rods 
shod with steel, which, rising and falling heavily with
unceasing regularity, soon pulverise the already
broken ore lying beneath their massive hammers.
Water passing through this latter machinery turns
the crushed metal into a kind of thick paste, which
then passes into large circular pans; where water,
quicksilver, and certain chemicals being added, the
whole is kept constantly in motion by iron rakes 
radiating from the centre of the vat and revolving
rapidly round it. The quicksilver seizes on the gold
and silver, and finally settles in large flannel bags 
placed in boxes separate from but near the bottom of
the vats, and this amalgam is fit for the furnace.
Water carries off the superfluous dirt, but as this is
often charged with precious metal, it is subjected to
a still further examination by being caused to pass
over coarse blankets laid on a small wavy kind of bed,
which being charged with more quicksilver soon
grasps the minute particles which have escaped
seizure in the former process, and forming more
amalgam likewise becomes fit for smelting. The
amalgam being now all collected is placed in iron
retorts and subjected to the action of fire. The gold
and silver mass soon becomes liquid, the quicksilver
passing away in a vapour, which being caused to
pass through water, again consolidates itself and
becomes available for further use. The molten
metal is then cast into bricks which contain a certain

<pb n="254" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.283"/>

amount of silver and a certain quantity of gold. To
determine the accurate value of each is the next
process. A corner of each brick is chipped off and
sent to the assayer, who, determining the exact value
of each metal in the brick it belongs to, registers the
same and has the correct value stamped on the huge
ingot, which is then fit for the market, and, I need
hardly observe, finds a ready sale. The whole
process, even to a tyro like myself, was exceedingly
curious; but to a man versed in machinery, who
could understand the beauty of the powerful engines,
etc., he saw in play all around him, I can imagine it
to be still more interesting and instructive.</p>

<p>Virginia City is well worth a visit on its own
account, even without a trip to the mines. Few
towns in the world are so lively, and a very few
years back the lively nature of its inhabitants
exhibited itself in constant shootings when they
imagined things were getting slow. I was told by
an old resident before I went there that it was a
somewhat rapid place. "If you are in luck," he
said, "you ought to get a man for breakfast;" which
expression, I afterwards learned, meant that an
account of a murder should be served up in the
morning paper with my matutinal meal. Every
other shop in the principal streets seemed to be a
drinking saloon, and in most of them were established
"hells" for the carrying on of the popular game of
"faro." Drinking, gambling, and other 
unmentionable vices seem the chief occupation of the above-
ground population. Underground I had seen them
hard at work, and now I could witness their ideas of

<pb n="255" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.284"/>

enjoyment. The two principal streets run parallel
to each other and are about half a mile long. One 
consists of shops, stores, gambling-houses, and 
drinking-bars, the latter greatly predominating; and the 
other entirely of houses kept by Phrynes of various
and manifold nationalities. Wages being high, 
everything was proportionately extravagant, and the
ordinary charge of the common street shoe-black
was a quarter-dollar (a shilling) for cleaning one°s
boots.</p>

<p>I had expected to have seen people wearing the
proverbial red flannel that is supposed to designate
the son of toil in this particular industry, but it 
was quite the reverse; "biled shirts,” the western
American name of white ones, were the rage, and
H. and myself suffered severely by our contrast to
these wonderfully got-up gentry. Mr. F. had put
our names down as hon. members of the Washoe
Club, but never dreaming that there was more than
one club in such a place, we omitted to inquire its
name, thinking "the club" would be sufficient. On
going there we missed our way, and H., addressing
a gentleman with flashy diamond studs in a very 
much "biled shirt," asked him to be kind enough to
tell us the way to the club. "The club!" he replied.
"What club?" H. was nonplussed, but managed,
Englishman-like, to stammer, "Oh&#8212;ah&#8212;why&#8212;don’t
you know? <hi rend="italic">the</hi> club." Our friend looked at us
both from top to toe with a perplexed expression of
countenance, evidently taking stock of our probable
social position. Neither of us had diamond studs or
a black coat. I wore a rather seedy hat. I think the

<pb n="256" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.285"/>

hat decided him, for with a spit of relief he answered,
"Guess you want the Miner’s Club: straight down
two blocks and turn to your right." H. looked
bewildered, but it was somewhat more than delicious
to see a member of "White’s," the "Marlborough,"
and goodness knows how many of the best clubs in
London, quietly pooh-poohed for not wearing a
"biled shirt," and when the possessor of the diamond
studs was out of hearing, we both laughed till our
sides ached. Eventually we did arrive at the club,
and found it an exceedingly nice and comfortable one,
and every member in it quite willing to be kind and
obliging.</p>

<p>Before 1861 the State of Nevada, now the richest
mining country in the world, formed part of Utah;
and prior to that, in 1848, being a part of Alta
California, it belonged to Mexico. The whole
country is more or less covered with mines, good,
bad, or indifferent, and their names on the "Share
List" are legion. The Comstock lode is pretty well
known throughout the world; for the others, those
who care about such things know well enough where
to get detailed accounts, and those who do not would
not care to see them enumerated here. With regard
to its wealth, I may state without exaggeration that
the streets of Virginia City are paved with silver.
A curious statement, but nevertheless a true one, as
the metal used in laying down the roads has been
found on analysis to be composed of dirt which if
worked would return a very fair profit per ton.</p>

<p>At about two o’clock one morning I was awakened
by bugles, horns, whistles, and all kinds of music.

<pb n="257" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.286"/>

Wondering what new and peculiar phase of life in
America I was about to witness, I jumped out of bed,
and on throwing open my window needed no 
interpreter to explain the cause. The whole town seemed
in a blaze. Fire-engines shrieked, men shouted, and
women in scanty apparel rushed wildly about the
passages of the hotel. I proceeded to rouse out my
companion, and after a couple of bad shots at his
door, of which I forgot the number, discovered him
sleeping tranquilly through all the turmoil. On
getting into the street we found that a livery stable
about a block off had been entirely destroyed, and
that the Odd-fellows’ Hall, a handsome brick edifice,
was now battling with the flames. At one time 
there was every prospect of Virginia City emulating
Chicago in its holocaust. The houses are nearly all
built of wood, and on their shingle roofs a perfect
hailstorm of fire was being rained down. Many
people packed up all their effects, and piling them
in the streets, quietly sat on them, waiting to see
how things would turn out; while others repaired to
the saloons, considerately opened for so festive an
occasion, and nerved themselves by a morning 
cocktail for the coming struggle. The fire brigade,
a volunteer one, did its duty well, and after a hard
fight the flames were got under and the excitement
subsided.</p>

<p>Having exhausted the chief wonders, and visited
the commencement of a shalt Messrs. Mackay and
Fair intend running 4000 feet deep, we took our
departure, and after a tiresome delay at Reno, an 
unimportant little town, twenty-one miles from Virginia

<pb n="258" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.287"/>

City, we once more found ourselves in a Palace
sleeping-car, and <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to the East.</p>

<p>We had breakfast at Humbolt, a small station with
a scanty garden, in which was a pond and a couple
of Mandarin ducks. The country all around is barren
and arid. Alkali incrustations render white the
surface of the ground, and sage-brush seems the only
vegetable produce. On the platform lay a huge mass
of sulphur in a solid lump; it was a desolate place,
and we were glad to get on.</p>

<p>The Humbolt ca&#241;on is curious; the river running
through it rather slimy and green. We dined at
Battle Mountain; elevation 4508 feet. Slight 
improvement in the aspect of the country. More
grazing land, and a few cattle were to be seen from
the train. A lot of children were in the car who
raced about from end to end, knocking over books
and incessantly disturbing one's papers. Occasionally
they varied the amusement by howling loudly, while
their mothers looked complacently on without 
endeavouring to stop them, evidently well pleased with
the healthy condition of the disagreeable little animals'
lungs. I certainly did pine for the ease and quiet
of an English first-class carriage, in which, thank
Heaven, such bores can be avoided. We fed again at
Elko; elevation 5065 feet. Badly divided time, only
a few hours having elapsed since the previous meal.
We passed the one thousand mile tree west from
Omaha, and at last arrived at the Mormon town of
Ogden, in the territory of Utah. Here we had
breakfast and parted company&#8212;H. going to Denver,
to shoot in the North and South Parks; while I

-->

<pb n="259" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.288"/>

<!--

continued my journey towards Salt Lake City, to
study Mormonism in its own headquarters.</p>

End of Section Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows Massacre -->

<p>I arrived there on Sunday September 5th, in time
to witness the funeral solemnities of one of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham
Young</persName>’s shining lights&#8212;Mr. <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>; his First Councillor, Church historian, and President of
the Twelve Apostles. This Apostle became identified
with the Mormon Church in its very infancy, and
participated in its travels and trials from <placeName type="state" key="New York">New York</placeName> to <placeName type="state" key="Ohio">Ohio</placeName>, to <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName>, to <placeName type="state" key="Illinois">Illinois</placeName>, and finally to <placeName type="state" key="Utah">Utah</placeName>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">Most people in <placeName type="state" key="Utah">Utah</placeName> suspected him of having been
the willing instrument that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> used in compassing the massacre of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the emigrants at <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadow">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg></seg>; and had Mr. <persName key="Smith, George A.">Smith</persName> lived another year, he would in all probability have been indicted and tried for that fearful crime.</seg> The Tabernacle&#8212;a huge building, looking at a distance more like an enormous
inverted boat on a pedestal than anything else I can
think of&#8212;was crowded to suffocation. Over ten
thousand people were congregated within its walls,
and it would have been impossible to have had a
better opportunity for inspecting these strange beings.</p>

<!-- Section: Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows:

<p>I was chiefly struck by the extreme ugliness of the
greater portion of their women, and by the shocking
manner in which they were dressed. I never saw
such a lot of frights, and can quite understand their
jumping at polygamy, as a last chance of becoming
entitled to even the fractional part of a husband,
after failing to secure an entire one in the various
parts of the world they may have come from. The
plainest women find no difficulty in getting married.
Becoming servants immediately after the ceremony,

<pb n="260" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.289"/>

in a country where domestic labour is almost 
impossible to be procured, unprepossessing as they
generally are, they represent a certain amount of
value to their owners; and as they are systematically
worked, they soon a good deal more than pay for
their keep. The men looked thick and brutish, and
in no part of the world have I seen so unprepossessing
a set of whites, or such a vast quantity of ugly men
and women congregated together, as were assembled
here to assist in burying their departed Apostle&#8212;
Mr. Smith.</p>

<p>While Brigham Young and some of the Apostles
were eulogising the departed saint, whom they 
endowed with every earthly virtue, I had time to
examine the interior of the building. It was 
tastefully decorated with flowers, and round the gallery
were various inscriptions, such as, "Brigham, our
leader and friend"; "We thank Thee, O God, for a
Prophet"; "Utah’s best crop&#8212;children.” In the
afternoon I again attended service in the Tabernacle,
and this time heard a sermon on secular matters.
The service was tedious and dragged out and
lengthened to a considerable extent by the 
administration to the entire congregation of the sacrament.
Several loaves of bread having been broken in small
fragments were handed round to the people, who
never left their pews; and shortly after large mugs
of water followed. The organ was a fine one, and
the music and singing fairly good. One of the
"Twelve Apostles" addressed the saints (they all
call themselves saints in Utah) and took them to
task roundly on their various short-comings. He

<pb n="261" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.290"/>

complained that they were paying too much attention
to the laying up of wealth, while at the same time
they begrudged the Church her accustomed share;
that they were adopting the vices and bad habits of the
Gentiles who had thrust themselves in among them,
and that while walking in the streets he had 
absolutely seen saints smoking pipes and cigars, without
even having the grace to seem ashamed of such a
thing. He believed some of them drank; but at any 
rate they would never prosper if they smoked or
took snuff. The women caught it next. They were
going to the bad also. Many of them used tea and
coffee, and perhaps sugar. They were departing
from the simplicity of that mode of life laid down as
best by their teachers, and he could hardly tell to
what depravities such behaviour might not lead.
He gave tongue for about half an hour, and talked
more bosh during that space of time than any man I
ever heard before or since.</p>

End of Section Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows -->

<p>I put up at a Mormon hotel, "The Townsend
House," and can strongly recommend it. The
proprietor, a Mormon, was extremely obliging, and
does all in his power to make his guests comfortable.
He took me to call on <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, and drove me about the city, showing and explaining the
various objects of interest. Just about this time the
excitement caused by the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> for his participation in the Mountain Meadow massacre was still
going on; and many of the atrocities perpetrated by
the Mormons were constantly being published in the
daily papers. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">There is not the slightest doubt but that the leaders of the Mormon Church encouraged

<pb n="262" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.291"/>

assassination in the most methodical and wholesale
manner; the confessions of some of their own
disciples who were actually engaged in these 
outrages showed that such atrocities actually did occur</seg>;
<seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">and to me it seems strange that the Government of the country did not, and do not, take some active
steps in avenging the victims.</seg></p>

<!-- Section Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows Massacre:

<p>Putting aside the wickedness and absurdity of the
religion, and the unscrupulous villainy of the 
sacerdotal power, which in Mormonism is omnipotent, there
is much to be admired in the industrious, frugal, and
simple customs of the people. Finding a desert,
they converted it into a garden, and Salt Lake City
is laid out with the strictest regard to both health
and convenience. Every street is about eighty yards
wide, and has broad side walks well sheltered by
locust or other ornamental trees; streams of clear
running water border each side, and every house is
surrounded by a garden laden with fruit-trees. The
town is built on a gentle slope, behind it are the lofty
ranges of the Wahsatch Mountains, and I doubt if it
be possible to find any town in the States better
planned for either comfort or scenic effect.</p>

<p>Gradually handsome buildings are beginning to
be constructed. The Temple, when finished, will
certainly be an attractive and ornamental structure,
its very unusual style of architecture perhaps 
constituting its principal charm. The Prophet's
favourite wife, Amelia, has had a handsome house
just finished for her particular benefit; and wealthy
Mormons in various parts of the town are building
residences that would be considered fine anywhere.

<pb n="263" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.292"/>

Fresh discoveries of mineral wealth are almost daily
taking place; and when confidence, so entirely
destroyed by that gigantic swindle the "Emma
Mine," again returns, and once more Gentile capital
becomes invested in the country, I expect to see not
only Salt Lake become a wealthy and prosperous
town, but the Mormon faith rapidly become shaken,
and the power of their Prophet and his apostles
sensibly decline.</p>

<p>Not far from the town are two sulphur springs,
over one of which has been built a bath-house. The
water is kept at a temperature of 90°, and besides
hip-baths they have constructed a very fair plunge
one. A mile farther another stream of strongly-
impregnated sulphur water, with about l30° of heat,
rushes from beneath a solid rock. The odour, which
is extremely unpleasant, can be detected at least
half a mile off, and the stones and herbage growing
near its banks are both tinted with a brilliant
emerald green.</p>

<p>A small garrison of United States troops are
quartered at Camp Douglas, which is built 
commanding the town and about two miles from it.
Mr. A., the brother of an old schoolfellow, living at
the hotel I was staying at, drove me over, and I met
with every kindness and attention from the officers.
I saw here, for the first time, the new American
bayonet, "Rice’s trowel bayonet with the 
Chillingworth attachment,"* and cannot speak too highly of
its admirable qualities. It is simply a sharp-pointed
strongly-built trowel, of eleven inches in length,
<note type="footnote">*See Appendix B.</note>

-->

<pb n="264" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.293"/>

<!--

exclusive of handle, and three and a half inches
broad&#8212;quite sufficiently formidable as a weapon of
offence; while for throwing up cover rapidly for
infantry troops exposed to an enemy’s fire it is
simply, as a tool, unparalleled. With it a man
can chop wood, build a wall, bake a cake, and
stab or cut down his enemy. I see no reason why,
without impairing its efficiency, one side should not
be partially filed into a saw. An officer, who had
seen troops drilled to its use, informed me that in
less than ten minutes he saw a company 
completely shelter themselves (on rather hard ground
into the bargain) from musketry. Our "shelter-
trench drill," with its necessary accompaniment of
picks and shovels, is as childish and grotesque in
comparison to the handy implement used by the
Americans, as the Indian bow in modern warfare
would be to the Henry &#8212; Martini breechloader.
Another exceedingly useful invention employed by
them is the stacking "swivel," <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> a small hook-
swivel placed on the upper band of the rifle, which
weighs almost nothing, and enables the men to stack
their arms regardless of any inequality of ground.
Were it the slightest use to urge our War 
Department to adopt any improvement not emanating from
themselves, I could not advocate too strongly the
adoption of both these plans in our own service.</p>

End of Section Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows -->

<p>Clintons station and hotel on the Great Salt Lake
is about a three hours’ ride from the town. The
country on each side of the line leading to it is flat,
and in some parts marshy. A few wet splashes,
which we passed through just before first coasting

<pb n="265" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.294"/>

the lake, were covered with wild duck; I also saw a 
few snipe, and should fancy the shooting there in
winter would be pretty good. The mosquitos on
this part of the line were fierce and bloodthirsty as
tigers, and quite took possession of the cars, driving
most of us who were not extra thick-skinned to take
refuge on the platform, where the current of air
prevented them effecting a lodgment. After passing
Black Rock we stopped at Clintons, nicely situated on
the Lake, and looking directly on Church and 
Antelope islands. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">On the former <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> is accused of
having stowed away the plunder so fearfully obtained
by the massacre at Mountain Meadows.</seg> A small
steamboat for the use of excursionists lay at a pier
near the hotel, and a few bathing boxes were erected
for the use of visitors.</p>

<!-- Section Not Relevant to the Mountain Meadows Massacre:

<p>I was somewhat curious to test the buoyancy of
these waters, and shortly after arriving was floating
about on their surface. The sensation of such
extreme buoyancy is certainly curious, and for an
indifferent swimmer I daresay pleasant. I could
stand upright without motion. Lying on my back
I could keep both feet entirely out of the water, with
my arms also at the same time extended upwards
to their full stretch. In breast swimming I could
keep both legs above water from the knee joints,
merely paddling with my hands; in fact, in any
position it was difficult to sink. Swimming a distance
was, however, difficult and tedious, as when on my
breast the extraordinary buoyancy of the water had
a tendency to throw the feet and legs right up in the
air, which naturally forced the head forward and

<pb n="266" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.295"/>

kept an unpleasant strain on the neck to secure its
elevation. Diving was next to impossible, and the
slightest drop of water getting into one’s eyes caused
extreme pain. The day was fine and the lake as
smooth as glass, and I pottered about very pleasantly
for over an hour, floating and paddling on its
surface experimentalising with its peculiarly buoyant
properties, when in one of my efforts I got and
swallowed a mouthful of water. Great goodness!
what a mouthful it was. The most nauseous medicine
I ever tasted was nectar to it, added to which, it
possessed a burning acrid power that almost took the
skin off my mouth. I tried no more tricks, and feel
convinced that the strongest swimmer in the world,
even the famed Captain Webb, would be unable to
live beyond thirty minutes in rough weather on Salt
Lake. Three such mouthfuls as I swallowed would
kill a water-buffalo "let alone" a man.</p>

<p>Round the lake, and extending for many miles on
each side of the long flat valley in which it is situated,
rims a curious but distinctly marked water line on the
hills, a hundred feet or so above the water's present
level; and at some distant and long past period, Salt
Lake must have covered an extent of ground at least
double its present area.</p>

<p>Among the sage-brush growing on the large
alkali plains in the vicinity of Salt Lake, there are
at certain seasons innumerable hares, or as people 
persist in calling them here, "jackass rabbits." They I
really are the true prairie hare (<hi rend="italic">Lepus Campestris</hi>, 
<hi rend="italic">Bachman</hi>), and not the jackass rabbit (<hi rend="italic">Lepus callotis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wagler</hi>), who is not to be found in either Utah or 

<pb n="267" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.296"/>

California; but as every description of hare or rabbit,
with the exception of the "cotton tail," is called
"jackass," I suppose we must let it pass and adopt the
national cognomen. A couple of Mormon 
gentlemen, hearing I was anxious to get a day at them, very
kindly drove me out some ten miles across the plains,
and passing the River Jordan, a muddy sluggish
stream that runs into Salt Lake, we shortly 
afterwards commenced operations. Although not the
best season of the year, immense numbers of them
were scattered through the sage-brush, the only plant
growing on these alkali bottoms. We found them
rather wild, still they afforded good sport, and as the
cover was in places somewhat thick, it required
tolerably quick shooting to knock them over.</p>

<p>Judge H., to whom I had an introduction, and
who had been residing for some years among the
Mormons, explained many of their eccentricities, and
told me many stories about these extraordinary
people; and though tempted to give some of the
benefits of his experience along with my own 
impressions, and "let out" on them, I will be merciful to
my readers and spare them a dissertation on such a
well-worn subject as Mormonism, contenting myself
with an adoption of Bret Harte's remarks 
concerning the "long-tailed gentry," to whom in some things
they are very similar, viz. "ways that are dark and
tricks that are vain."</p>

<p>Salt Lake City could hardly be visited at a more
favourable time of the year for witnessing it under
its brightest garb than during the month of 
September. The fruit-trees were laden with peaches, apples,

<pb n="268" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.297"/>

plums, and pears. The gardens were brilliant with
flowers of many colours. Trees with their 
spreading branches threw a cool and grateful shade on
all the side walks. Sparkling water rippled by
their sides. A delicious fragrance perfumed the air,
and whatever one may think of-the Mormons, it
is impossible to go away otherwise than charmed
with their capital town. Utah, like Nevada, 
California, and many of the Western States, abounds in
silver. For some inexplicable reason the wise people
of Salt Lake City got it into their heads that I was a
capitalist, and I was constantly beset with offers of
mines for a mere song, that only required some
of my superfluous wealth to develop into second
editions of the Comstock Lode.</p>

<p>It is quite impossible for any man with an ordinary
amount of brains to shut his eyes to the indisputable
fact, that from the immense quantities of silver being
poured into the market, a very serious and important
change must shortly take place in this great 
circulating medium, and one which, coming with such
extraordinary celerity as it really is doing, is certain
most seriously to affect the whole world.</p>

<p>Financiers and legislators cannot look to this
matter too soon; and accepting for a solution of the
difficulty the argument of short-sighted or wilfully
blind people, who assume that the adoption by
America and other countries of specie payments will
be sufficient to absorb the surplus, will only lead
them more and more astray.</p>

<p>Up to a very recent period, Mexico was the only
silver producing country of any importance in the

<pb n="269" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.298"/>

world, and the greater portion of the bullion even
sent from there came from but one mine&#8212;that of
Potosi. Since those days, silver has been discovered
in all directions, and were the country in a fit state
to warrant the introduction of foreign capital, most
of these mines could be made to pay.</p>

<p>The mines of Utah are many of them returning a
high dividend on the very small capital expended in
their primary working, and fresh deposits of ore are
being discovered daily by people without any capital
at all, and are consequently untouched. The Emma
Mine is strongly suspected by the knowing ones at
Salt Lake of having a rich "Bonanza" but a very
few hundred feet below the distance worked by its 
present shareholders.</p>

<p>On the mines in Nevada it is impossible to touch
without going into a matter of statistics and figures
too wearisome for a short gossiping book of travels,
but let it be borne in mind that, in only one mine
out of the several hundred that exist in a small
portion of Nevada, I saw myself ore which, still
unraised, represented seventy-four millions of pounds
sterling.</p>

<p>It has only been very recently that people have
systematically looked for silver at all. Up to this
the rage has merely been for gold. Experienced and
resolute men are now prospecting in all kinds of wild
and out of the way places for metals that a few
years ago were rarely searched for by men educated
to their task. Silver, more or less, exists in all
the Western States; even Alaska contains it; but
were not another mine to be discovered, those that

<pb n="270" xml:id="mmm.wa.price.1877.299"/>

exist at present are more than sufficient to halve
the present market value of silver, if they were only
properly worked.</p>

<p>In San Francisco the vulgar but successful 
speculator in mines has his dinner menu engraved on a
silver plate, which each guest puts in his pocket and
takes away; but if it even became the fashion to
pocket the spoons, the flow of silver is too incessant
and steady to feel the drain.</p>

<p>I have studied this subject at far greater length
than it is necessary to enter upon here, and feel
convinced that the depreciation of the metal, owing
to the immense quantities produced, will soon become
so decided that statesmen will be compelled to take
the matter very seriously up, and the sooner they
take their task in hand the better.</p>

-->

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>