<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">History of the Pacific States of North America, Volume XXVI, History of Utah, 1540-1886</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"/>
                <author><forename>Hubert</forename> <forename type="middle">Howe</forename> <surname>Bancroft</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.uh.bancroft.1889</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in
                    Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all
                        rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as
                        allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires
                        express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                        publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"/>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>

                <bibl>
                    <title level="m">History of the Pacific States of North America, vol. XXVI,
                        History of Utah, 1540-1886</title>
                    <author><forename>Hubert</forename> <forename type="middle">Howe</forename> <surname>Bancroft</surname></author>
                    <publisher>The History Company</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>San Francisco, CA</pubPlace>
                    <extent>543-571</extent>
                    <date when="1889">1889</date>
                    <note type="source">Hubert Howe Bancroft. <hi rend="italic">History of the Pacific States of North America, Vol. XXVI, History of Utah, 1540-1886.</hi> San Francisco, CA: The History Company, 1889. 543-571.
                    </note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>utah_history</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-06-28"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding</change>
            <change when="2009"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="543" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.543"/>

<head>CHAPTER XX</head>
<head>THE MOUNTAIN MEADOWS MASSACRE. 1867.</head>

<p><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="center">An Arkansas Emigrant Party Arrives at Salt Lake  City&#8212;Assassination Of Parley P. Pratt&#8212;Ill Feeling against the Emigrants&#8212; Alleged Outrages&#8212;Their Arrival at Mountain Meadows&#8212;They are Attacked by Indians&#8212;A Flag or Truce&#8212;Plan of the Massacre &#8212;surrender of the emigrants&#8212;the butchery&#8212;burial of the Slain&#8212;The Survivors&#8212;Judge Cradlebaugh's Investigation&#8212;The Aiken Massacre&#8212;John D. Lee on Trial&#8212; The Jury Disagree&#8212;The Second Trial&#8212;Lee Convicted and Sentenced&#8212;His Confession and Execution.</hi></hi></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> threat uttered by <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> during his interview with Captain "<persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName>, on the 9th of September, 1857, was speedily fulfilled&#8212;so speedily that, at first sight, its execution would appear to have been predetermined. "If," he declared, "the government dare to force the issue, I shall not hold the Indians by the wrist any longer." "If the issue comes, you may tell the government to stop all emigration across the continent, for the Indians will kill all who attempt it."</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Two days later</seg> occurred the Mountain Meadows massacre,<ref target="n0001">1</ref> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at a point about three hundred miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName></seg></seg>.</seg></p>

<note xml:id="n0001">1 In <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s Rept, in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc</hi>., 36th Cong. lst Sess., ii. no. 42, p. 79, and the <hi rend="italic">Hand-Book of Reference</hi>,
p. 75, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Sept. 9th is given as the date of the massacre</seg>. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>, as superintendent of Indian affairs, made a close investigation into the details of this tragedy, the result of which is given in his report ut supra, pp. 87-9, and elsewhere in this
document, which occupies 139 pages, and contains all the official information then
to be had on the subject. His reports are dated <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, 1859. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">He states that when the attack began on Monday, Sept. 5th, and lasted till Friday, Sept. 9th, when the massacre ocured; but Friday of that week fell on Sept. 11th.</seg> <persName key="Burton, Richard F.">Burton</persName>, <hi
rend="italic">City of the Saints</hi>, 411-12, note, also quotes an official
report, in which <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Sept. 4th or 5th is given as the date of the first attack.</seg> See also <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s confession in <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 218, 237, 239, where <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> states that the massacre occurred on Friday, and that the attack began on Tuesday.</seg> At <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s trial <persName key="Haslam, James Holt">James Haslem</persName> testified, as we shall see later, that he was sent from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, with a letter to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName>, on Monday, Sept. 7th, and that he reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">S.L. City</placeName> at 11 A. M. On Thursday. <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Sept. 20, 1876. The next day was the 11th. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Other accounts differ slightly as to date.</seg></note>

<pb n="544" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.544"/>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSZealots">The threat and the deed came so near together as to lead many to believe that one was the result of the other. But a moment's reflection will show that they were too nearly simultaneous for this to be the case; that in the absence of telegraph and
railroad, it would be impossible to execute such a deed three hundred miles away in
two days. <seg type="Blame" subtype="Lee">Indeed, it may as well be understood at the outset that this horrible
crime, so often and so persistently charged upon the Mormon church and its leaders,
was the crime of an individual, the crime of a fanatic of the worst stamp, one who
was a member of the Mormon church, but of whose intentions the church knew nothing,
and whose bloody acts the members of the church, high and low, regard with as much
abhorrence as any out of the church.</seg> Indeed, the blow fell upon the brotherhood
with three-fold force and damage. There was the cruelty of it, which wrung their
hearth; there was the odium attending its performance in their midst; and there was
the strength it lent their enemies further to malign and molest them. The Mormons
denounce the Mountain Meadows massacre, and every act connected therewith, as
earnestly and as honestly as any in the outside world. This is abundantly proved,
and may be accepted as a historical fact.</seg></p>

<p>I will now proceed to give the incidents as they occurred. In the spring of 1857 a
party of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one hundred and thirty-six</seg> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrants</seg>,<ref target="n0002">2</ref> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">among whom were a few Missourians</seg>,<ref target="n0003">3</ref> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">set forth for southern <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>. 

<note xml:id="n0002">2 U.S. Attorney <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Wilson</persName>, in his report in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc</hi>., 36th Cong. 1st Sec., ii. no. 42, p. 102, states that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">119 were killed</seg>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">it is certain that 17 children were rescued</seg>. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> and <persName key="Burton, Richard F.">Burton</persName> say that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">115 to 120 were massacred</seg>; <persName key="Waite, C. V. (Catherine Van Valkenburg Waite)">Waite</persName>, <hi rend="italic">The Mormon Prophet</hi>, 66, that the party consisted of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">150 men and women</seg>, besides<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"> a number of children</seg></seg>. <persName key="Stenhouse, Fanny">Stenhouse</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Tell It All</hi>, 324, mentions <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">120 to 130</seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Other reports vary from 120 to 150.</seg></note> <note xml:id="n0003">3 <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain"><persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhonse</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 424-8, says that the <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> and <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri"><placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> emigrants</seg></seg> formed two separate parties, the latter naming themselves <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> 'wild-cats,' and that the <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">Arkansas party</seg> was advised by a friend of his to keep clear of <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">the Missourians</seg> while paving through the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> settlements and the portion of that territory occupied by Indians. I find no confirmation of this in other authorities, though, according to Mrs <persName key="Stenhouse, Fanny">Stenhouse</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Tell It All</hi>, 323, her husband's friend, whose name was <persName key="Kelsey, Eli B.">Eli B. Kelsey</persName>, 'said that the train was divided into two parts, the first a rough-and-ready set of men&#8212;regular frontier pioneers; the other a picked community.' The truth appears to be, that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">there were a few Missourians</seg> in the <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> party</seg>, as stated in <hi rend="italic">Hutchings' Cal. Mag.,</hi>, iv. 345.</seg></note>

<pb n="545" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.545"/>

<seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">It included about thirty families, most of them related by marriage or kindred, and its members were of every age, from the grandsire to the babe in arms. They belonged to the class of settlers of whom <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> was in need. Most of them were farmers by occupation; they were orderly, sober, thrifty, and among them was no lack of skill and capital.</seg><ref target="n0004">4</ref> They travelled leisurely and in comfort, stopping at intervals to
recruit their cattle, and about the end of July arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>,<ref target="n0005">5</ref> where they hoped to replenish their stock of
provisions.</p>

<p>For several years after the gold discovery the arrival of an emigrant party was
usually followed, as we have seen, by friendly traffic between saint and gentile,
the former thus disposing, to good advantage; of his farm and garden produce. But
now all was changed.<seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"> The army of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> was advancing on Zion, and <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> families</seg> reached the valley at the very time when the Mormons first heard of its approach, perhaps while the latter were celebrating their tenth anniversary at Big Cottonwood Canon.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">Moreover, wayfarers from <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> were regarded with special disfavor; the former for reasons that have already appeared, the latter on account of the murder of a well-beloved apostle of the Mormon church.</seg></p>

<note xml:id="n0004">4 <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">They had about 600 head of cattle, 30 wagons, and 30 horses and mules. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'. Rept, ut supra, p. 75. <persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName> mentions that they had also several travelling-carriages. <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 424. At least $30,000 worth of plunder was collected after the massacre, besides what was appropriated by the Indians. <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> estimated the value of their property at $60,000 to $70,000.</seg></note>

<note xml:id="n0005">5 I find no mention of their arrival in the files of the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, although the names of passing emigrants were registered in that paper at a nominal charge; and when the party was a large one, its passage was usually noticed among the local items of news.</note>

<pb n="546" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.546"/>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">In May of 1857 <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley P. Pratt</persName> was arraigned before the supreme court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, on a charge of abducting the children of one <persName key="McLean, Hector">Hector McLean</persName>, a native of <placeName type="settlement" key="New Orleans, LA">New Orleans</placeName>, but then living in <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>. He was acquitted; but it is alleged by
anti-Mormon writers, and tacitly admitted by the saints, that he was sealed to
<persName key="McLean, Hector">Hector McLean</persName>'s <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">wife</persName>, who had been baptized into the faith years before, while living in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, and in 1855 was living in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>.<ref target="n0006">6</ref> <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> swore vengeance against the apostle, who was advised to make his escape, and set forth on horseback, unarmed, through a sparsely settled country, where, under the circumstances, escape was almost impossible. His
path was barred by two of <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName>'s friends until <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> himself with three others overtook the fugitive, when he fired six shots at him, the balls lodging in his saddle or passing through his clothes. <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> then stabbed him twice</seg> 

* * <note xml:id="n0006">6 <seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">The account given in the <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>, xix. 417-18, is that <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName>, after treating his wife in a brutal manner for several years, turned her into the streets of <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, and secretly conveyed the children on board a steamer for <placeName type="settlement" key="New Orleans, LA">New Orleans</placeName>, where the woman followed him; but finding that her parents were in the plot, set forth for <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. Returning to <placeName type="settlement" key="New Orleans, LA">New Orleans</placeName> in 1856, she rescued her children and fled to <placeName type="state" key="Texas">Texas</placeName>; but was followed by her husband, who had previously returned to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, and now regained possession of the children. <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley</persName>, who had already befriended <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">Mrs McLean</persName>, had written to inform her that her husband was in pursuit. Hence the prosecution. <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> and <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">his wife</persName> finally separated in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName> in 1855. See also <hi rend="italic">Autobiog. of Parly P. Pratt</hi>, app. <persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName> relates that <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">Mrs McLean</persName> was married or sealed to <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>,
that she met <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> in <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> on her way to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and that the apostle was acquitted on account of her assuming the responsibility for the abduction. He
admits, however, that the apostle did not abduct the children. <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 429. <persName key="Burton, Richard F.">Burton</persName> says that <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> converted <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">Mrs McLean</persName> and took her to wife, but on what authority he does not state. City of the Saints, 412. The fact, however, that <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">Mrs McLean</persName> arrived on the scene of the apostle's assassination just before his death, as mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>, xix. 478, wears a auspicious look. In the <hi rend="italic">S. F. Bulletin</hi> of March 24, 1877, it is stated that the apostle made the acquaintance of <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">Mrs McLean</persName> while engaged in missionary work in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>; that her <persName key="McLean, Hector">husband</persName>, who was a custom-house official and a respectable citizen, ordered him to discontinue his visits, and kicked him out
of the house for continuing them surreptitiously; and that the woman was so infatuated with the Mormon elder that she devoutly washed his feet whenever he visited her. On arriving at Fort Smith (near <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName>), <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> found letters from <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley Pratt</persName> addressed to <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">his wife</persName>, one of them signed ' Your own,&#8212;&#8212;.' The McLean residence in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, on the corner of Jones and Filbert streets, was in 1877 a dilapidated frame building, a story and a half in height. As to the apostle's assassination, the Bulletin merely states that he was overtaken by <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> and shot within eight miles of <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName>, and that he died of his wounds an hour afterward.</seg></note>

<pb n="547" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.547"/> 

<seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">with a bowie-knife under the left
arm, whereupon <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley</persName> dropped from his horse, and the assassin, after thrusting his knife deeper into the wounds, seized a derringer belonging to one of his accomplices, and shot him through the breast. The party then rode off, and <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> escaped unpunished.</seg><ref target="n0007">7</ref></p>

<p>Thus, when <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> families</seg> arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, they found the Mormons in no friendly mood and at once concluded to break camp and move on. They had been advised by Elder <persName key="Rich, Charles C.">Charles C. Rich</persName> to take the northern route along the Bear River, but decided to travel by way of southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Passing through <placeName type="state" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Payson, UT">Payson</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, and intervening settlements, they attempted everywhere to purchase food, but without success.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">Toward the end of August they arrived at Corn Creek,<ref target="n0008">8</ref> some fifteen miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, where they encamped for several days. In this neighborhood, on a farm set apart for their use by the Mormons, lived the Pah Vants, whom, as the saints allege, the emigrants attempted to poison by throwing arsenic into one of the springs and impregnating their own dead cattle with strychnine. It has been claimed that this charge was disproved; and what motive <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> party</seg> could have had for thus surrounding themselves with treacherous and blood-thirsty foes has never been explained. In the valleys throughout the southern portion of the territory grows a poisonous weed, and It is possible that the cattle died from eating of this</seg> 

<note xml:id="n0007">7 This account of <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley</persName>'s murder is based on the testimony of <persName key="Higginson, George">Geo. Higginson</persName> and <persName key="Crouch, George">Geo. Crouch</persName>, whose letter, dated <placeName type="settlement" key="Flint, AR">Flint</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, May 17, 1854 was first published in a <placeName type="state" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> paper. Copies of it will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>, iii. 478, and <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Burton, Richard F.">Burton</persName>'s City of the Saints</hi>, 412-13, note. They state that the tragedy occurred close to the
residence of a farmer named Win, and was witnessed by two men who were in the house at the time, and from whose evidence at the wroner's jury the above version is taken. <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> lived long enough to give instructions as to his burial and the disposition of his property. The account given by <persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 429-30, does not differ materially, except that he makes no mention of any accomplices.</note>

<note xml:id="n0008">8 In his deposition at the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> and others, <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, the prophet's cousin, states that he found them at Corn Creek on Aug. 25th. <hi rend="italic">Millenial Star</hi> xxxvii. 675; <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Mormonism Unvailed</hi>. 307.</note>

<pb n="548" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.548"/> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">weed.<ref target="n0009">9</ref> It has been intimated that those who accused the emigrants of poisoning the Pah Vants were not honest in their belief, and that the story of the poisoning was invented,
or at least grossly exaggerated, for the purpose of making them solely responsible
for the massacre.<ref target="n0010">10</ref> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The fact has never been so
established, notwithstanding the report of the superintendent of Indian affairs, who
states that none of this tribe were present at the massacre.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">Continuing their journey, the emigrants proceeded to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver City</placeName>, and thence to <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Grain was scarce this year, and the emigrants were unable to purchase all they desired for their stock, though for their own immediate necessities they obtained what they required at this place. Arriving at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, they succeeded in purchasing about fifty bushels of wheat, which was ground at a mill belonging to <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, formerly commander of the fort at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, but then Indian agent, and in charge of an Indian farm near <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p>It is alleged by the Mormons, and on good authority, that during their journey from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> 

<note xml:id="n0009">9 <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison"><hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc</hi>., 36 Cong. 1st
Sess., ii. no. 42, p. 76. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> mentions that an ox belonging to a Dr <persName key="Ray, John">Ray</persName> of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName> died from this cause while the emigrants were in that neighborhood, that his wife was taken ill while rendering the tallow, and that a boy who was assisting her died a few days afterward. One or two Indians who ate some of the meat were also poisoned.</seg></note>

<note xml:id="n0010">10 <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">'<persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, living 150 miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, informed me that about twenty Indians and some cattle died from drinking of the poisoned water, and Indians from eating the poisoned meat.' <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s Rept</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., p. 75. This report was dated <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">S. L. City</placeName>, Aug. 1859. In a letter to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName>, dated <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, Nov. 20, 1857, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> writes:' The company there [at Corn Creek] poisoned the meat of an ox, which they gave the Pah Vant Indians to eat, causing four of them to die immediately, besides poisoning a number more. The company also poisoned the water where they encamped, killing the cattle of the settlers. This letter was used in evidence at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s trial in 1876.' <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi> 254-5. At this trial was also laced in evidence a letter from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> to the commissioner of Indian affairs, dated Jan. 6, 1858, in which <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s 'statement is repeated almost verbatim. <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., 313-15.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">In his confession, made a few months after his trial, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> declares that President <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> told him of the poisoning and other atrocities committed by the emigrants, and gave him instructions as to the part he should take in the massacre.</seg></seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">After that event <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> states (still in his confession), 'I thought over the matter, and made up my mind to write the letter to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and lay it all to the Indians.'</seg> <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., 254.</seg></seg></note>

<pb n="549" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.549"/> 

City to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">the emigrants were guilty of further gross outrage. If we can believe a statement made in the confession of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, a few days before his death, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, president of the stake at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">accused them of abusing women</seg>, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">of poisoning wells and, streams at many points on their route</seg>, of destroying fences and growing crops, of violating the city ordinances at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and resisting the officers who attempted to arrest them. These and other charges, even more improbable,<ref target="n011">11</ref> have been urged in extenuation of the massacre; but little reliance can be placed on <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s confession, and most of them appear to be unfounded.<ref target="n012">12</ref> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">It must be admitted, however, that rather than see their women and children starve, they perhaps took by force such necessary provisions as they were not allowed to purchase</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">Near <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> the Spanish trail to Santa F&#233; branched off from what was then known as Fr&#233;mont's route. About thirty miles to the south-west of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and within fifteen of the line of the route, are <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain Meadows</geogName>, which form the divide between the waters of the great basin and those that flow into the Colorado. At the southern end of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the meadows</geogName>, which are four to five miles in length and one in width, but here run to a narrow point, is a large stream, the banks of which are about ten feet in height. Close to this stream <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">the emigrants were encamped on the 5th of September</seg>, almost midway between two</seg> 

<note xml:id="n0011">11 <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">'They proclaimed that they had the very pistol with which the prophet <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Joseph Smith</persName> was murdered, and had threatened to kill <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> and all of the apostles. That when in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> City they said they would have friends in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, who would hang <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> by the neck until he was dead, before snow fell again in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName>. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">They also said that <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> was coming with his army from the east, and they were going to return from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> with soldiers, as soon as possible, and would then desolate the land, and kill ever, damned Mormon man, woman, and child that they could find in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.'</seg> <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 218-19.</seg></seg></seg></note>

<note xml:id="n012">12 'Conflicting statements were made to me of the behavior of
this company,' says the superintendent of Indian affairs. 'I have accordingly
made it a matter of material importance to make a strict inquiry to ascertain
reliable information on this subject...The result of my inquiries enables me to
say that the company conducted themselves with propriety.' <hi rend="italic"
><persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s Rept</hi>, et supra, p. 88.</note>
<pb n="550" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.550"/> ranges of hills, some fifty feet
high and four hundred yards apart. On either side of their camp were ravines
connected with the bed of the stream.</p>

<figure xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.550.figure">
<p>MOUNTAIN MEADOWS.</p>
<figDesc>A hand drawn black and white map of Mountain Meadows.</figDesc>
</figure>

<p>It was Saturday evening when <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> families</seg> encamped at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. On the sabbath they rested, and at the usual hour one of them conducted divine service in a large tent, as had been their custom throughout the journey. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">At daybreak on the 7th</seg>, while the men were lighting their camp-fires, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">they were fired upon by Indians</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">or white men disguised as Indians</seg>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">more than twenty were killed or wounded</seg>,<ref target="n0012">13</ref> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">their cattle having been driven off meanwhile by the assailants</seg>, who had crept on them under cover of darkness. The survivors now ran for their wagons, and pushing them together so as to form a corral, dug out the earth deep enough to sink them almost to the top of the wheels; then in the centre of the inclosure they made a rifle-pit large enough to contain the entire company, strengthening their defences by night as best they could. Thereupon the attacking party, which numbered from three to four hundred, withdrew to the hills, on the crests of which they built parapets, whence they shot down all who showed themselves outside the intrenchment.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">The emigrants were now in a state of siege, and though they fought bravely, had little hope of escape. All the outlets of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">the valley</seg> were guarded; their </seg><choice> <orig>am- 

<note xml:id="n0012">13 <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Seven were killed and sixteen wounded.</seg> <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Confession</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 226-7; see also <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s Rept</hi>. in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 36th Cong. 1st Sess., ii. no. 42, p. 88.</note>

<pb n="551" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.551"/>

munition</orig><reg>ammunition</reg></choice><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"> was almost exhausted; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">of their number, which included a large proportion of women and children, many were wounded</seg>, and their sufferings from thirst had become intolerable. Down in the ravine, and within a few yards of the corral, was the stream of water; but only after sundown could a scanty supply be obtained, and then at great risk, for this point was covered by the muskets of the Indians, <ref target="n0014">14</ref> who lurked all night among the ravines waiting for their victims.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">Four days the siege lasted; on the morning of the fifth a wagon was seen approaching from the northern end of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the meadow</geogName></seg>, and with it <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">a company of the Nauvoo legion</seg>.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">When within a few hundred yards of the intrenchment, the company halted, and one of them, <persName key="Bateman, William Lehi">William Bateman</persName> by name, was sent forward with a flag of truce. In answer to this signal a little girl, dressed in white, appeared in an open space between the wagons. Half-way between the Mormons and the corral, <persName key="Bateman, William Lehi">Bateman</persName> was met by one of the emigrants named <persName key="Hamilton, ">Hamilton</persName>, to whom he promised protection for his party on condition that their arms were surrendered, assuring him that they would be con-ducted safely to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. After a brief parley, each one returned to his comrades.</seg></p>

<p>By whose order the massacre was committed, or for what reasons other than those already mentioned, has never yet been clearly ascertained; but as to the incidents and the plan of the conspirators, we have evidence that is in the main reliable. During the week of the massacre, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, with several other Mormons, was encamped at a spring within half a mile of the emigrants' camp; and, as was alleged, though not distinctly proven at his trial, induced the Indians by promise of booty to make the attack; but, finding the resistance stronger than he anticipated, had sent for <note xml:id="n0014">14 'Thursday morning I saw two men start from the corral with buckets, and ran to the spring and fill their buckets with water, and go back again. The bullets flew around them thick and fast, but they got into their corral in safety.' <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 230.</note>

<pb n="552" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.552"/> 

aid to the settlements of southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.<ref target="n015">15</ref> Thus far the evidence is somewhat contradictory. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution">There is sufficient proof, however, that, in accordance with a programme previously arranged at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, a company of militia, among whom were <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> and Major <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName>, and which was afterward joined by Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>, bishop of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>,<ref target="n0016">16</ref> arrived at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s camp on the evening before the massacre.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">It was then arranged that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> should conclude terms with the emigrants, and, as soon as they had delivered themselves into the power of the Mormons, should start for <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s rancho, on the eastern side of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the meadows</geogName>, with the wagons and arms, the young children, and the sick and wounded. The men and women, the latter in front, were to follow the wagons, all in single file, and on each side of them the militia were to be drawn up, two deep, and with twenty paces between their lines. Within two hundred yards of the camp the men were to be brought to a halt, until the women approached a copse of scrub-oak, about a mile distant, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">near to which Indians lay in ambush</seg>. The men were now to resume their march, the militia forming in single file, each one walking by the side of an emigrant, and carrying his musket on the left arm. As soon as the women were close to the ambuscade;</seg> <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>,<ref target="n0017">17</ref> who was in charge of the detachment, was to give the signal by saying to his command, "Do your duty;" whereupon the militia were to shoot down the men, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">the Indians were to</seg> 

<note xml:id="n0015">15 See the district attorney's opening address to the jury, in the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Sept. 2, 1877. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> states that his object in sending for aid was to protect the emigrants. <hi rend="italic">Confession, in Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 229.</note>

<note xml:id="n0016">16 A full list of the company is given in Id., 379-80, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">a list of all the Mormons who took part in the massacre</seg> in the <hi rend="italic">S. L. City Tribune</hi>, June 2 1877. See also the speech delivered by Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> in the house of representatives, Feb. 7, 1863. <hi rend="italic">Cong. Globe</hi>, 1862-3, app. 119. The speech was afterward published in pamphlet form, one copy of it being entitled <hi rend="italic" >Mormonism</hi>, and another <hi rend="italic">Utah and the Mormons</hi>.
The former was reprinted from the <hi rend="italic">S. L. Daily Tribune</hi>,
Apr. 8, 1877. The parts of it relating to the massacre will be found in <hi
rend="italic">Waite's The Mormon Prophet</hi>, 65, and <hi rend="italic"
><persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 447-50.</note>

<note xml:id="n0017">17 First councillor to <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>.</note>

<pb n="553" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.553"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">slaughter <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the women and children</seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">sparing only those of tender age</seg></seg>, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> with some of the wagoners was to butcher the sick and wounded.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Mounted troopers were to be in readiness to pursue and slay those who attempted to escape, so that, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">with the exception of infants</seg>, no living soul should be left to tell the tale of the massacre.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">Entering the corral, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> found <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the emigrants engaged in burying two of their party who had died of wounds</seg>. Men, women, and children thronged around him, some displaying gratitude for their rescue, some distrust and terror. The brother played his part well. Bidding the men pile their arms in the wagons, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">to avoid provoking the Indians</seg></seg>, he placed in them the women, the small children, and a little clothing. While thus engaged, one <persName key="McFarland, Daniel">Daniel McFarland</persName> rode up, with orders from Major <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> to hasten their departure, as <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Indians threatened to renew the attack</seg></seg>. The emigrants were then hurried away from the corral, the men, as they passed between the files of militia; cheering their supposed deliverers.</seg> Half an hour later, as the women drew near the ambuscade, the signal was given, and the butchery commenced. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Most of the men were shot down at the first fire. Three only escaped from the valley; of these two were quickly run down and slaughtered, and the third was slain at Muddy Creek, some fifty miles distant.</seg></seg><ref target="n0018">18</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The women and those of the children who were on foot ran forward some two or three hundred yards, when <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">they were overtaken by the Indians, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">among whom were Mormons in disguise</seg></seg>. The women fell on their knees, and with clasped hands sued in vain</seg> 

<note xml:id="n0018">18 <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s Rept</hi>, ut supra, 89; <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Bruton, Richard F.">Burton</persName>'s City of the Saints</hi>, 412, note. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> also says that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">three escaped, but were overtaken and killed before reaching the settlements in <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>. <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 244. <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> states that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">two escaped and were overtaken in the desert 150 miles distant</seg>. Mormonism, 12. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><persName key="Beadle, John Hanson">Beadle</persName> mentions three, one of whom starved to death in the desert, another was murdered by Indians, 90 miles south of the desert, and a third was killed on the Colorado River by persons unknown.</seg> <hi rend="italic">Life in Utah</hi>. 184.</note>

<pb n="554" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.554"/> 

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">for mercy; clutching the garments of their murderers, as they grasped them by the hair, children pleaded for life, meeting with the steady gaze of innocent childhood <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">the demoniac grin of the savages</seg>, who brandished over them uplifted knives and tomahawks. Their skulls were battered in, or their throats cut from ear to ear, and, while still alive, the scalp was torn from their heads. Some of the little ones met with a more merciful death, one, an infant in arms, being shot through the head by the same bullet that pierced its father's heart. Of the women none were spared</seg>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">of the children only those who were not more than seven years of age</seg>.<ref target="n0019">19</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">To two of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s wagoners, <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> and <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName>, was assigned the duty, as it was termed, of slaughtering the sick and wounded. Carrying out their instructions, they stopped the teams as soon as firing was heard, and with loaded rifles approached the wagons where lay their victims, <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> being in front. "O Lord, my God," he exclaimed, "receive their spirits, it is for thy kingdom that I do this." Then, raising his rifle to his shoulder, he shot through the brain a wounded man who was lying with his head on a sick comrade's breast. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The Mormons were aided in their work<ref target="n0020">20</ref> by Indians</seg>, who, grasping the helpless men by
the hair, raised up their heads and cut their throats. The last victim was a little girl who came running up to the wagons, covered with</seg></seg>

<note xml:id="n0019">19 <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="SexualViolence">In the official report quoted by <persName key="Burton, Richard F.">Burton</persName>, <hi rend="italic">City of the Saints</hi>, 412, it is stated that a girl 16 years of age knelt before one of the Mormons imploring mercy, but he led her away into a thicket, violated her, and then cut her throat. <persName key="Beadle, John Hanson">Beadle</persName> attributes this deed to President <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and says that after violating the girl he beat out her brains with a club. He also accuses <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> of selecting one of the young women for his harem, and relates that, when he made known his purpose, she attempted to stab him, whereupon he shot her through the head.</seg> <hi rend="italic">Life in Utah</hi>, 183-4.</seg></note>

<note xml:id="n0020">20 <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in his confession, denied having killed any of them, but admits that he intended to do his part. He says: 'I drew my pistol and
cocked it, but somehow it went off prematurely, and I shot <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> across the thigh, my pistol-ball cutting his buckskin pants. <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> turned to me and said: "Brother <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, keep cool; you are excited."' <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 242. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">As we shall see later, it was clearly proved at his trial that he killed several of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the wounded</seg>.</seg></note>

<pb n="555" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.555"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">blood, a few minutes after the disabled men had been murdered. She was shot dead within sixty yards of the spot where <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was standing.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">The massacre was now completed, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">after stripping the bodies of all articles of value</seg>,<ref target="n0021">21</ref> Brother <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and his associates went to breakfast,<ref target="n0022">22</ref> returning after a hearty meal to bury the dead.</seg></seg></p>

<note xml:id="n0021">21 <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> states that only a little money and a few watches were found on them. <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., 244. This is improbable, and other accounts show that the Mormons gathered considerable booty.</seg></seg></note>

<note xml:id="n0022">22 'After breakfast,' says <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">'we all went back in a body to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the meadows</geogName>, to bury the dead and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">take care of the property that was left there</seg>.'</seg> The above account of the Mountain Meadows massacre is taken mainly from <hi
rend="italic"><persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'a Rept</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 35th Cong. lst Sess., ii. no. 42, pp. 87-9; <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>'s Mormonism</hi>, 12; the affidavit of <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingon Smith (Klingensmith)</persName>, bishop of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, who was present at the massacre, made in 1871 before the clerk of
court of the seventh judicial district of <placeName type="state" key="Nevada">Nevada</placeName>, in <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 439-42; the confession of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unveiled</hi>, 244, and his trial in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., 302-76. In the S. P. Call, July 30, 1881, it is stated that Bishop <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> was murdered in Mexico. There is no important discrepancy in the several versions. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> and <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> officially investigated the matter in 1859. The statements of both are very brief, and why the investigation was not made sooner does not appear. News of the massacre was first received in <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName> in Feb. 1858. See letter of <persName key="Mix, C. E.">C. E. Mix</persName>, acting commissioner of Indian affairs, to Senator <persName key="Sebastian, W. K.">W. K. Sebastian</persName>, and of the secretary of war to Representative <persName key="Greenwood, A. B.">A. B. Greenwood</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">Sen.
Doc.</hi>, 35th Cong. 1st Sess., ii. 42, pp. 4, 42. On the 18th of this month
Senator <persName key="Gwin, William M.">Gwin</persName> of <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> moved that the secretary of war be called upon to report what steps had been taken to bring the offenders to justice. <hi rend="italic"
>Gwin's Memoirs</hi>, MS., 138 a, 138 e. No steps had been taken, and for
reasons that will presently appear, none were taken&#8212;or none that were
effectual&#8212;until nearly 20 years later. For other accounts of the massacre,
see <persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 435-9; <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Stenhouse, Fanny">Stenhouse</persName>'s Tell It All</hi>, 328-37; Beadle's <hi rend="italic">Life in Utah</hi>, 180-4; <hi rend="italic">Waite's The Mormon Prophet</hi>,
60-9; <hi rend="italic">Beadles' Western Wilds</hi>, 306-7, 496-501;<hi
rend="italic"> Young's Wife No. 19</hi>, 228 et seq.; <hi rend="italic">Bowie's
Our New West</hi>, 266-8; <hi rend="italic">Rusting, Across America</hi>,
188-90; <hi rend="italic">Hayes' Scraps, Los Angeles</hi>, viii. 228-31, xvii. 3-7;
<hi rend="italic">Hutching's Cal. Mag.</hi>, iv. 345-9; <hi rend="italic">Utah
Review</hi>, Feb. 1682, 243-6. The story of the massacre has, of course, been
related thousands of times in the magazines and newspapers of Europe and America.
Some of these accounts are substantially correct and some are absurd. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">One writer, for instance, attempts to throw new light on the subject by giving what is claimed
to be a copy off the original order for the massacre, signed '<persName key="Wells, Daniel G.">Daniel G. Wells</persName>,' and dated <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">S. L. City</placeName>, Apr. 9, 1858. The massacre occurred, as we have seen, on Sept.
11, 1857.</seg> For statements and comments of the press of the Pacific slope, see, among
others, the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Dec. 1, 1869; <hi rend="italic">8.
L. City Tribune</hi>, Jan. 3, Aug. 22, Oct. 3, Nov. 28, 1874; Aug. 14, 1875;
Sept. 9, 1876; Apr. 23, 1879;. <hi rend="italic">S. F. Bulletin</hi>, Oct. 12, 27,
Nov. 12, 1867; Apr. 13, May 14, Aug. 12, 1858; Apr. 23, Aug. 25, Oct. 28, 1859;
Sept. 23, 27, Nov. 27, 1872; Nov. 17, 1674; July 26, 1875; March 24, Apr. 12, 1877;
<hi rend="italic">S. F. Call</hi>, July 21, 1866; May 23, Sept. 23, 1872; Oct.
14, 1874; July 18, 22, 25, 1875; Feb. 16, March 9, 24, 25, May 29, 1877; S. F. Alta,
Oct. 12, 21, 1867; Aug. 13, 1858; Jan. 6, May 8, June 26, 1859; Feb. 9, 1873; July
28, Aug. 23, 1875; March 24, Apr. 7, 1877; <hi rend="italic">S. F. Chronicle</hi>,
March 22, 23, 31, Apr. 8, 1877; S. F. Post, March 22, 23, 1877; <hi rend="italic">S.
F. Herald</hi>, Oct. 12, 27, Nov. 2, 1857; <hi rend="italic">Mining and
Scientific Press</hi>, July 31, 1875, March 31, 1877; <hi rend="italic">Pacific
Rural Press</hi>, March 31, 1877; <hi rend="italic">Oakland Tribune</hi>, Apr.
9, 1877; <hi rend="italic">Sac. Daily Union</hi>, Oct. 13, Dec. 18, 1857; March 1,
Aug. 14, 1868; Apr. 14, 25, 1859; Jan. 29, 1867; Nov, 28, 1872; Nov. 24, 1874; <hi
rend="italic">Cal. Mercantile Journal</hi>, 1860, pp. 183-4; <hi rend="italic"
>Stockton Independent</hi>, June 11, 1879; <hi rend="italic">San Jose Weekly
Argus</hi>, Dec. 5, 1874; <hi rend="italic">Santa Cruz Sentinel</hi>, May 12,
1877; <hi rend="italic">San Buenaventura Signal</hi>, June 23, 1877; <hi
rend="italic">Winnemucca Silver State</hi>, July 19, 1875; <hi rend="italic"
>Antioch Ledger</hi>, Nov. 21, 1875; <hi rend="italic">Austin Reese River
Reveille</hi>, July 12, 1864; <hi rend="italic">Gold Hill News</hi>, Sept. 21,
1872; Feb. 1, 1875; Sept 12, 1876; <hi rend="italic">Carson State Register</hi>,
Sept. 26, 1872; <hi rend="italic">Prescott Miner</hi>, Dec. 12, 1874, Apr. 11, 1870;
<hi rend="italic">Idaho World</hi>, Oct. 1, 1875; <hi rend="italic">Portland
Weekly Standard</hi>, Apr. 6, 1877; <hi rend="italic">Or. Argue</hi>, Dec. 12,
1857, July 16, 1858; <hi rend="italic">Or. Statesman</hi>, Nov. 3, 1857. For cuts of
the massacre, see <hi rend="italic">Beadle's Western Wilds</hi>, 498; <hi
rend="italic">Beadle's Life in Utah</hi>, facing p. 183; <hi rend="italic"
><persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, facing p. 424; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s <hi rend="italic"
>Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, facing p. 210.</note>

<pb n="556" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.556"/>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">It was a ghastly sight that met them at this Wyoming of the west, amid the peaceful vales of Zion, and one that caused even the assassins to sicken and turn pale. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The corpses had been entirely stripped by the Indians, who had also carried off the clothing, provisions, wagon-covers, and even the bedding of the emigrants.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">In one group were the naked bodies of six or seven women, in another those of ten young children, some of them horribly mangled and most of them scalped.</seg> The dead were now
dragged to a ravine near by and piled in heaps; a little earth was scattered over
them, but so little that it was washed away by the first rains, leaving the remains
to be devoured by wolves and coyotes, the imprint of whose teeth was afterward found
on their bones. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">It was not until nearly two years later that they were decently interred by a detachment of troops, sent for that purpose from Camp Floyd.</seg> On
reaching <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, the men found skulls and bones scattered for the space of a mile around the ravine, whence they had been dragged by wild beasts. Nearly all the bodies had keen gnawed by wolves, so that few could be recognized, and their
dismembered skeletons were bleached by long exposure. Many of the skulls were
crushed in with the but-ends of muskets or cleft with tomahawks; others were
shattered by fire-arms, discharged close, to the head. A few remnants of apparel,
torn from the backs of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">women and children</seg> as they ran from the clutch of their pursuers, still fluttered among the bushes, and near by were masses of human hair,
matted and trodden in the mould.</seg><ref target="n0023">23</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n0023">23 Rept of Assistant Surgeon <persName key="Brewer, Charles">Brewer</persName>, dated <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, May 6,1859, in Sen. Doc., 36th Cong. 1st Seas., ii. no. 42, pp. 16-17; Captain <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Campbell</persName>'s rept., in <hi rend="italic">Mess. and Doc.</hi>, 1859-60, pt 2, p. 207; <hi rend="italic">Hutchings' Cal. Mag.</hi>, iv. 316-7. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">A correspondent of the <hi rend="italic">New York Herald</hi>, writing from S. L. City, Nov. 8, 1874, states that <persName key="Rogers, William H.">William H. Rogers</persName>, Indian agent, was ordered to proceed from Camp Floyd with a party of cavalry and bury the remains in the summer of 1858. I find no mention of this in the official documents, though the massacre was known to Sup. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> at least as early as June 22d of that year.</seg></seg> See his letter to <persName key="Mix, C. E.">C. E. Mix</persName>, in
<hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, ut supra, pp. 44-5.</note>

<pb n="557" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.557"/>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">Over the last resting-place of the victims was built a cone-shaped cairn, some twelve feet in height, and leaning against its northern base was placed a rough slab of
granite, with the following inscription: "Here <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">120 men, women, and children</seg> were massacred in cold blood, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">early in Sept. 1857</seg>. <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">They were from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>." The cairn was surmounted by a cross of cedar, on which were inscribed the words: "Vengeance is mine: I will repay, saith the Lord."</seg><ref target="n0024">24</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The survivors of the slaughter were seventeen children, from two months to seven years of age, who were carried, on the evening of the massacre, by <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, <persName key="Tullis, Daniel">Daniel Tullis</persName>, and others to the house of <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>,<ref target="n0025">25</ref> and afterward placed in charge of Mormon families at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, and elsewhere. All of them were recovered in the summer of 1858, with the exception of one who was rescued a few months later, and though thinly clad, they bore no marks of ill usage.<ref target="n0026">26</ref> In the following year they were </seg>

<note xml:id="n0024">24 <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">Cuts will be found in <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Stenhouse, Fanny">Stenhouse</persName>'s Tell It All</hi>, 335; <hi rend="italic">Hutchings' Cal. Mag.</hi>, iv. 347. The cairn, cross, and slab are said to have been destroyed by order of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName>. <hi rend="italic">Cradlebaugh's Mormonism</hi>, 14.</seg></note> 

<note xml:id="n0025">25 <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s, rept, in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 36th Cong. 1st Seas., ii. no. 42, pp. 79-80, where their names are given; see also p.
87; <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 243. Bishop <persName key="Smith, George A.">Smith</persName>'s statement, in <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 441-2. In giving the result of his investigation, <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> states (p. 76) that <persName key="Habmlin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> had left his home several weeks before the massacre, and did not return until several days after it occurred. This statement was confirmed, at the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in the deposition of <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, who alleged that <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> was encamped with him at Corn Creek on Aug. 25, 1857. <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>, xxxvii. 675. See also <hi rend="italic">Little's Jacob Hamblin</hi>, 45. Nevertheless <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> was accused of complicity. Affidavit of Capt. <persName key="Lynch, James">Jas Lynch</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 36th Cong. 1st Sess., ii. no. 42, p. 83.</note>

<note xml:id="n0026"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">26 'I succeeded in getting sixteen children, all, it is said, that remain of this butchering affair. I have the children with me; they seem contented and happy; poorly clad, however.' <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'. letter to General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, ut supra, p. 8. 'The seventeenth child was recovered last April.' (1859.) 'It is proper to remark that when I obtained the children they were in a better condition than children generally in the settlements in which they lived.' <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s Rept</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., pp. 87, 89. On the other hand, Captain <persName key="Lynch, James">James Lynch</persName>, who accompanied <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>'s party, states under oath that when he first saw them the children were 'with little or no clothing, covered with filth and dirt.' <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., p. 81. Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> says nothing about their being ill treated. It was at first supposed that the children had been left in the hands of Indians, but this is denied by all the officers and officials whose reports are given in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., passim. 'No one can depict the glee of these infants,' remarks <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, when they realized that they were in the custody of what they called "the Americans"&#8212;for such is the designation of those not Mormons. They say they never were in the custody of the Indians. I recollect one of them, <persName key="Sorrow, John Calvin">John Calvin Sorrow</persName>, after be found he was safe, and before he was brought away from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, although not yet nine years of age, sitting in a contemplative mood, no doubt thinking of the extermination his family, sayin : "Oh, I wish I was a man! I know what I would do: I would shoot <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>. I saw him shoot my mother." I shall never forget how he looked.' <hi rend="italic">Mormonism</hi>, 13.</seg></note>

<pb n="558" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.558"/> 

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">conveyed to <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, the sum of $10,000 having been appropriated by congress for their recovery and restoration.</seg><ref target="n0027">27</ref></p>

<p>To <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, as governor and superintendent of Indian affairs, belonged the duty of ordering an investigation into the circumstances of the massacre and of bringing
the guilty parties to justice. His reasons for evading this duty are best explained
in his own words. In his deposition at the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, when asked why he had not instituted proceedings, he thus made answer: "Because another governor had
been appointed by the president of the United States, and was then on the way here
to take my place, and I did not know how soon he might arrive; and because the
United States judges were not in the territory. Soon after Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> arrived I asked him to take Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, who belonged to the southern district, with him, and I would accompany them with sufficient aid to investigate the matter and bring the offenders to justice."<ref target="n0028">28</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n0027">27 <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">For further particulars as to the treatment and disposition of the children, see <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 36th Cong. 1st Sess., ii. no.
42, passim; <hi rend="italic">S. F. Alta</hi>, Feb. 23, March 12, May 29, July 10,
20, 1859; <hi rend="italic">S. F. Bulletin</hi>, May 30, 31, June 6, Aug. 13, 1859;
<hi rend="italic">Sac. Union</hi>, July 19, 1859. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils"><persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> says that on their way back they frequently pointed out carriages and stock that had belonged to the train, and stated whose property they were.</seg></seg> <hi rend="italic">Mormonism</hi>, 14.</note>

<note xml:id="n0028">28 <hi rend="italic">The Lee Trial</hi>, 37; <hi rend="italic"
><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 305-6; <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>, xxxvii. 675; <hi rend="italic">Tullidge's Hist. S. L. City</hi>, 243. In a
conversation with Governor Cumming, <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName> remarked: 'If the business had not been taken out of our hands by a change of officers in the territory, the
Mountain Meadows affair is one of the first things we should have attended to when a
U.S. court sat in southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. We should see whether or not white men were concerned in the affair with the Indians.' <hi rend="italic">Little's Jacob
Hamblin</hi>, 57. </note>

<pb n="559" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.559"/>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The Mormons concerned in the massacre had pledged themselves by the most solemn oaths to stand by each other, and always to insist that the deed was done entirely by
Indians. For several months it was believed by the federal authorities that this was
the case</seg>; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">when it became known, however, that some of the children had been spared, suspicion at once pointed elsewhere, for among all the murders committed by the
Utahs, there was no instance of their having shown any such compunction.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Moreover, it was soon ascertained that an armed party of Mormons had left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, had returned with spoil, and that the Indians complained of being unfairly treated in the division of the booty.</seg></seg> Notwithstanding their utmost efforts, some time elapsed before the United States officials procured evidence sufficient to bring home the
charge of murder to any of the parties implicated, and it was not until March 1859
that Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> held a session of court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>. At this date only six or eight persons had been committed for trial, and were now in the guard-house at Camp Floyd,<ref target="n0029">29</ref> some of them being accused of taking part in the massacre and some of other charges.</seg></p>

<p>Accompanied by a military guard, as there was no jail within his district and no
other means of securing the prisoners, the judge opened court on the 8th. <seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">In his address to the grand jury he specified a number of crimes that had been committed in southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, including the massacre.</seg> "To allow these things to pass over," he observed, "gives a color as if they were done by authority. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">The very fact of such a case as the Mountain Meadows shows that there was some person high in the estimation of the people, and it was done by that authority...You can know no law but the laws of the United States and the laws you have here. No person can commit crimes and say</seg>

<note xml:id="n0029">29 <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>'s letter in <hi rend="italic">Mess</hi>. and <hi rend="italic">Doc</hi>., 1859-60, pt ii. 140.</note>

<pb n="560" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.560"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">they are authorized by higher authorities, and if they have any such notions they will have to dispel them."</seg><ref target="n0030">30</ref> The grand jury refused to find bills against any of the accused, and, after remaining in session for a fortnight, were discharged by <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> as "a useless appendage to a court of justice," the judge remarking: "If this court cannot bring you to a proper sense of your duty, it can at least turn the savages held in custody loose upon you."<ref target="n0031">31</ref></p>

<p>Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> address was ill advised. The higher authority of which he spoke could mean only the authority of the church, or in other words, of the first presidency; and to contemn and threaten to impeach that authority before a Mormon grand jury was a gross judicial blunder. Though there may have been cause for suspicion, there was no fair color of testimony, and there is none yet, that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> or his colleagues were implicated in the massacre. Apart from the hearsay evidence of <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> and of an officer in the army of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>,<ref target="n0032">32</ref> together with the statements of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>,<ref target="n0033">33</ref> there is no basis on which to frame a charge of complicity against them. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">That the massacre occurred the day after martial law was proclaimed, and within two days of the threat uttered by <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> in the presence of <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName></seg>; <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName>, as superintendent of Indian affairs, failed to embody in his report any mention of the massacre</seg>; 

<note xml:id="n0030">30 A copy of the judge's charge will be found in <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Rocky Mountains Saints</hi>, 403-6.</note>

<note xml:id="n0031">31 <hi rend="italic">Cradlebaugh's Mormonism</hi>, 11; <hi
rend="italic">The Lee Trial</hi>, 6.</note>

<note xml:id="n0032">32 Major <persName key="Carelton, James Henry">Carleton</persName>, of the first dragoons. In a despatch to the assistant adjutant-general at <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, dated <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, May 25, 1859, he says: <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">'A Pah Ute chief of the Santa Clara band, named <persName key="Jackson">Jackson</persName>, who was one of the attacking party, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">had a brother slain by the emigrants</seg> from their corral by the spring, says that orders came down in a letter from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> that the emigrants were to be killed; and a chief of the Pah Utes, named <persName key="Toucher">Toucher</persName>, now living on the Virgin River, told me that a letter from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> to the same effect was brought down. to the Virgin River band by a man named <persName key="Huntingdon">Huntingdon</persName>.' A copy of the major's despatch will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Hand-book of Mormonism</hi>, 67-9. <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> says that after the attack had been made, one of the Indians declared that a white man came to their camp with written orders from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> to 'go and help to whip the emigrants.'</seg></seg> <hi rend="italic">Mormonism</hi>, 11.</note>

<note xml:id="n0033">33 <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s confession, in <hi rend="italic">Mormonism
Unvailed</hi>, passim.</note> 

<pb n="561" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.561"/> 

<seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">that for a long time afterward no allusion to it was made in the tabernacle or in the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>&#8212;the church organ of the saints&#8212;and then only <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">to deny that the Mormons had any share in it</seg>;<ref target="n0034">34</ref> and that no mention was made in the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi> of the arrival or
departure of the emigrants;&#8212;all this was, at best, but presumptive evidence, and did not excuse the slur that was now cast on the church and the church dignitaries. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">"I fear, and I regret to say it," remarks the superintendent of Indians affairs, in August 1859, "that with certain parties here there is a greater anxiety to connect <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and other church dignitaries with every criminal offence than diligent endeavor to' punish the actual perpetrators of crime."</seg></seg><ref target="n0035">35</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">The judge's remarks served no purpose, except to draw forth from the mayor of <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> a protest against the presence of the troops, as an infringement of the rights of American citizens. The judge replied that good American citizens need have no fear of American troops, whereupon the citizens of <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> petitioned Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> to order their removal. <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, who was then at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, was officially informed by the mayor that the civil authorities were prepared and ready to keep in safe custody all prisoners arrested for trial, and others whose presence might be necessary. He therefore requested General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> to withdraw the force which was then encamped at the court-house, stating that its presence was unnecessary. The general refused
to comply, being sustained in his </seg>

<note xml:id="n0034">34 The massacre is thus mentioned for the first time in the <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>,. xxxix. 785 (Dec. 3, 1877). 'The reader cannot fail to perceive that any overt act&#8212;much less the terrible butchery <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>&#8212;was farthest from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s policy at that time, to say nothing of humanitarian considerations. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">There can be but one just view of that melancholy event&#8212;that it was an act of retaliation by the Indians</seg>.' <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">The emigrants are then accused of the poisoning at Corn Creek</seg>, and <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">blamed for taking the southern route contrary to the advice of the Mormons</seg>.</seg> <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> states that the names of the guilty parties were published in the <hi rend="italic">Valley Tan. Sen. Doc.</hi>, 36th Cong. 1st Sess., ii. no. 42, p. 86.</note>

<note xml:id="n0035">35 Letter to the commissioner of Indian affairs, in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 36th Cong. 1st Sess., ii. no. 42, p. 74. Capt. <persName key="Lynch, James">Lynch</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., p. 84, calls <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> 'a veritable old granny,' but, with the exception of Gov. <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, he appears to be the only one who kept his head at this juncture.</note> 

<pb n="562" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.562"/> 

<seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">action by the judges;<ref target="n0036">36</ref> and on the 27th of March <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> issued a proclamation protesting against all movements of troops except such as accorded with his own instructions as chief executive magistrate.<ref target="n0037">37</ref> A few days later the detachment was withdrawn.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">Notwithstanding the contumacy of the grand jury, <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> continued the sessions of his court, still resolved to bring to justice the parties concerned in the Mountain Meadows massacre, and in crimes committed elsewhere in the territory. Bench-warrants, based on sworn information, were issued against a number of persons, and the United States marshal, aided by a military escort, succeeded in making a few arrests.</seg><ref  target="n0038">38</ref></p>

<p>Among other atrocities laid to the charge of the Mormons was one known as the Aiken massacre, which also occurred during the year 1857. Two brothers of that name, with four others, returning from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> to the eastern states, were arrested in southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> as spies, and, as was alleged, four of the party were escorted to <placeName type="settlement" key="Nephi, UT">Nephi</placeName>, where it was arranged that <persName key="Rockwell, Porter">Porter Rockwell</persName> and <persName key="Collett, Sylvanus">Sylvanus Collett</persName> should assassinate them. While encamped on the Sevier River they were attacked by night, two of them being killed 

<note xml:id="n0036">36 Copies of all the correspondence in this matter, which is somewhat voluminous, will be found in <hi rend="italic">Mess. and Doc.</hi> 1859-60, ii. 139 et seq. The action of <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> was afterward sustained by the secretary of war, in a letter addressed to <persName key="Johnston, Alfred Sidney">Johnston</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., p. 157. The judges also received a sharp rebuke at the bands of Attorney-general <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName>, who thus sums up the case: 'On the whole, the president is very decidedly of opinion: 1. That the governor of the
territory alone has power to issue a requisition upon the commanding general for the whole or part of the army; 2. That there was no apparent occasion for the presence of the troops at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>; 3. That if a rescue of the prisoners in custody had been attempted, it was the duty of the marshal, and not of the judge, to summon the force which might be necessary to prevent it; 4. That the troops ought not to have been sent to <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> without the concurrence of the governor, nor kept there against his remonstrance; 5. That the disregard of these principles and rules of action have been in many ways extremely unfortunate.'</note>

<note xml:id="n0037">37 For copy of protest see <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, March 30, 1859, where is also a protest from the grand jury against their dishonorable discharge.</note>

<note xml:id="n0038">38 <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration"><persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> relates that when these arrests were made a general stampede occurred among the Mormons, especially among the church dignitaries, who fled to the mountains. <hi rend="italic">Mormonism</hi>, 11.</seg></seg></note>

<pb n="563" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.563"/> 

and two wounded, the latter escaping to <placeName type="settlement" key="Nephi, UT">Nephi</placeName>, whence they started for <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, but were murdered on their way at Willow Springs. Although the guilty parties were well known, it was not until many years later that one of them, named <persName key="Collett, Sylvanus">Collett</persName>, was arrested, and in October 1878 was tried and acquitted at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>.<ref target="n0039">39</ref> All the efforts of Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> availed nothing,<ref target="n0040">40</ref> and soon afterward he discharged the prisoners and adjourned his court sine die, entering on his docket the following minute: "The whole community presents a united and organized opposition to the proper administration of justice."</p>

<milestone unit="section" rend="space"/>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">This antagonism between the federal and territorial authorities continued until 1874, at which date an act</seg> 

<note xml:id="n0039">39 <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Oct. 16, 23, 1878, where is a report of <persName key="Collett, Sylvanus">Collett</persName>'s trial. A sensational account of this affair is given in <hi rend="italic">Hickman's Destroying Angel</hi>, 205-9. It is there stated that the party had with them money and other property to the amount of $25,000. See also <hi rend="italic">Young's Wife No. 19</hi>, 270-6; <hi rend="italic">S. F. Bulletin</hi>, May 30, 1859; <hi rend="italic">S. F. Post</hi>, Oct. 11, 1878; <hi rend="italic">S. L. City Tribune</hi>, Oct. 12, 1878. In the report of the trial I find no mention of the murdered men's property.</note>

<note xml:id="n0040">40 <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">Among others, an attempt was made to investigate what were known as the <persName key="Potter, Duff">Potter</persName> and <persName key="Parrish, Beatson"><persName key="Parrish, William">Parrish</persName></persName> murders at <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>, an account of which is given in <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 462-7. The proceedings in these cases will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Apr. 6, 1859. In his address to the grand jury, <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> states that three persons were killed on this occasion, and that young Parrish, who was among the intended victims but made his escape, could certainly identify
the parties.</seg> The judge also mentions the cases of <persName key="Fobbs, Henry">Henry Fobbs</persName>, murdered near Fort Bridger while on his way from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, and of <persName key="Jones, Henry">Henry Jones</persName>, said to have been castrated at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">S. L. City</placeName>, and afterward shot at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salem, UT">Pond Town</placeName>, near <placeName type="settlement" key="Payson, UT">Payson</placeName>. <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Rocky Mountain Saints</hi>, 404-5. This writer relates that the marshal and his posse approached <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName> before daylight and surrounded that settlement, but on entering the houses, it was found that the culprits had already escaped, and after searching the canon some few miles farther on, the party returned, having accomplished nothing. See also <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Apr. 6, 1859. <seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">For reports of other murders committed about this period, some of them being attributed to Mormons, see <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 36th Cons. 1st Sess., xi. no. 42, passim; <hi rend="italic"><persName key="Burton, Richard F.">Burton</persName>'s City of the Saints</hi>, 274; <hi rend="italic" >Hickman's Destroying Angel</hi>, 122 et seq.; <hi rend="italic">Bowles' Our
New West</hi>, 266. At this date the newspapers of the Pacific coast were teeming with accounts of atrocities said to have been committed by Mormons, for which I refer the reader to the <hi rend="italic">S. F.  Bulletin</hi>, May 20, Nov. 26, Dec. 21, 1858; Jan. 4, 24, Apr. 25, May 9, 30, Aug. 8, 24, 25, 30,
1859; <hi rend="italic">S. F. Alta</hi>, May 15, Oct. 28, Nov. 1, 1857; Jan. 25, Nov. 4, 1858; Jan. 13, May 9, Aug. 30, 31, Sept. 14, Nov. 20, 1859; Sac. Union, May 15, 1857; Jan. 6, 18, May 11, 14, Sept. 8, 1859; Jan. 16, 1860. Most of the murders committed appear to have been those of desperadoes who defied the law. On May 17, 1860, for instance, two men of this stamp were shot in the streets of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. Commenting on this affair, the <hi rend="italic">Deseret
News</hi> of May 23d remarks: 'Murder after murder has been committed with impunity within the precincts of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, till such occurrences do not
seemingly attract much attention, particularly when the murdered have had the reputation of being thieves and murderers or of associating with such characters.</seg></note>

<pb n="564" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.564"/> 

<seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">was passed by congress "in relation to courts and judicial officers in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName> of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>," and commonly known as the Poland bill,<ref target="n0041">41</ref> whereby the summoning of grand and petit juries was regulated, and provision made for the better administration of justice. The first grand jury impanelled under this law was instructed by <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Jacob S. Boreman</persName>, then in charge of the second judicial district, to investigate the Mountain Meadows massacre and find bills of indictment against the parties implicated. A joint indictment for conspiracy and murder was found against <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName>, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>, and others.<ref target="n0042">42</ref> Warrants were issued for their arrest, and after a vigorous search <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> were captured, the former being found concealed in a hog-pen at a small settlement named <placeName type="settlement" key="Panguitch, UT">Panguitch</placeName>, on the Sevier River.</seg><ref target="n0043">43</ref></p>

<p>After some delay, caused by the difficulty in procuring evidence, the 12th of July, 1875, was appointed for the trial at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver City</placeName> in southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.<ref target="n0044">44</ref> At eleven o'clock on this day the court was opened, Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> presiding, but further delay was caused by the absence of witnesses, and the fact that <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had promised to make a full confession, and thus turn state's evidence. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">In his statement the prisoner detailed minutely the plan and circumstances of the</seg></seg> <note xml:id="n0041">41 Appproved June 23, 1874. See <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, July 8, 1874.</note> 

<note xml:id="n0042">42 <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> Trial, 6. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> states that Smith, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higby</persName>, Bishop <persName key="Davies, William R.">Davis</persName>, <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Ira Hatch</persName>, and <persName key="Tullis, David">David Tullis</persName> were the most guilty.</seg> Letter. to the commissioner of Indian affairs, in <hi rend="italic">Sen. Doc.</hi>, 30th Cong. 1st Sens., ii. no. 42, p. 86.</note>

<note xml:id="n0043">43 A detailed account of the arrest of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> by <persName key="Stokes, William">Wm Stokes</persName>, deputy U. S. marshal, is given in <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s <hi  rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 293-301. See also <persName key="Beadle, John H.">Beadle</persName>'s Western Wilds, 490-2, where is a cut showing the scene of this incident. The two versions differ somewhat, <persName key="Beadle, John H.">Beadle</persName> stating that the arrest was made by Marshal <persName key="Owens, Jacob G.">Owens</persName>.</note>

<note xml:id="n0044"> More than 100 subpoenas had been issued, but though many obeyed the summons, several material witnesses were not forthcoming&#8212;among them being <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>, <persName key="White, Joel">Joel White</persName>, and <persName key="Hawley, William">William Hawley</persName>, all of whom were present at the massacre. <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, who had promised to make a confession, arrived a day or two later, in custody of a deputy, and <persName key="White, Joel">Joel White</persName> was induced to trust himself to the notorious <persName key="Hickman, Bill">Bill Hickman</persName>, then acting as special deputy marshal. <hi  rend="italic">The <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> Trial</hi>, 8.</note>

<pb n="565" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.565"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">tragedy, from the day when the emigrants left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> until the butchery <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>.</seg> He avowed that<persName key="Higbee, John M."> Higbee</persName> and <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> played a prominent part in the massacre, which, he declared, was committed in obedience to military orders, but said nothing as to the complicity of the higher dignitaries of the church, by whom it was believed that these orders were issued</seg>.<ref target="n0045">45</ref> The last was the very point that the prosecution desired to establish, its object, compared with which the conviction of the accused was but a minor consideration, being to get at the inner facts of the case. The district attorney<ref target="n0046">46</ref> refused, therefore, to accept the confession, on the ground that it was not made in good faith. Finally the case was brought to trial on the 23d of July, and the result was that the jury, of whom eight were Mormons, failed to agree, after remaining out of court for three days.<ref target="n0047">47</ref> <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was then remanded for a second trial, which was held before the district court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver City</placeName> between the 13th and 20th of September, 1876, Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> again presiding.<ref target="n0048">48</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n0045">45 Portions of this first confession will be found in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., 8-0; B. F. Call, July 21, 1875; B. F. Bulletin, July 21, 1875.</note>

<note xml:id="n0046">46 <persName key="Carey, William C.">William C. Carey</persName>, who was assisted by <persName key="Baskin, Robert N.">R. N. Baskin</persName>. <persName key="Sutherland, Jabez">Sutherland</persName> and <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName>, Judge Hoge, <persName key="Spicer, Wells">Wells Spicer</persName>, <persName key="McFarlane, Johne">John McFarlane</persName>, and <persName key="Bishop, William W.">W. W. Bishop</persName> appeared for the prisoner. <persName key="Sutherland, Jabez">Sutherland</persName> and <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName> were the attorneys of the first presidency.</note>

<note xml:id="n0047">47 For names of jurors, see The Lee Trial, IL On p. 52, it is stated that the foreman, who was a gentile, sided with the Mormons, the three remaining gentiles being in favor of a conviction. In The <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> Trial, published in pamphlet form by the B. L. Daily Tribuse-Reporter (S. L. City, 1875) we have a fair account of the proceedings at the first trial, except that the publishers seem
unduly anxious to cast the onus of the charge on the first presidency. Other reports will be found in the files of the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, commencing July 28, 1875; <persName key="Beadle, John H.">Beadle</persName>'s Western Wilds, 504-13; Young's Wife No. 19, 256-60; the Elko Independent, Aug. 7, 1875; the Helena Independent, July 29, 1875.</note>

<note xml:id="n0048">48 For names of jurors, see <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Sept. 20, 1876. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had been cut off from the church in 1871, and among anti-Mormon writers it is stated that the church authorities now withdrew all assistance and sympathy, and determined to sacrifice him. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Mormonism Unvailled, 32; <persName key="Beadle, John H.">Beadle</persName>'s Western Wilds, 515. In his introduction to the <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, <persName key="Bishop, William W.">W. W. Bishop</persName> says that the attorneys for the defendant were furnished with a list of jurymen, and that the list was examined by a committee of Mormons, who marked with a dash those who would convict, with an asterisk those who would probably not convict, and with two asterisks those who would certainly not convict. The names of the Jurors accepted were, of course, marked with two asterisks, but they found <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> guilty, as directed by the church authorities.</note>

<pb n="566" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.566"/>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The court-room was crowded with spectators, who cared little for the accused, but listened with rapt attention to the evidence, which, as they supposed, would certainly implicate the dignitaries of the church. They listened in vain. In opening the case to the jury, the district attorney<ref target="n0049">49</ref> stated that he came there to try <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, and not <persName key="Young,  Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and the Mormon church.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="Lee">He proposed to prove that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had acted in direct opposition to the feelings and wishes of the officers of the Mormon church;</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">that by means of a flag of truce <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had induced the emigrants to give up their arms;</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">that with his own hands the prisoner had shot two women, and brained a third with the but-end of his rifle; that he had cut the throat of a wounded man, whom he dragged forth from one of the wagons;</seg> and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">that he had gathered up the property of the emigrants and used it or sold it for his own benefit</seg>.<ref target="n0050">50</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">These charges, and others relating to incidents that have already been mentioned, were in the main substantiated. The first evidence introduced was documentary, and included the depositions of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">a letter written by <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> to the former, wherein he attempted to throw the entire responsibility of the deed upon the Indians.</seg> <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> alleged that he heard nothing about the massacre until some time after it occurred, and then only by rumor; <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">that two or three months later <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> called at his office and gave an account of the slaughter, which he charged to Indians;</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">that he gave no directions as to the property of the emigrants, and knew nothing about its disposal;</seg> that about the 10th of September, 1857, he received a communication from <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, concerning <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> party</seg>, and in his answer <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">had given orders</seg></seg> 

<note xml:id="n0049">49 <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Sumner Howard</persName>, who was assisted by <persName key="Denny, Presley">Presley Denny</persName>. The prisoner's counsel were <persName key="Spicer, Wells">Wells Spicer</persName>, <persName key="Foster, J. C.">J. C. Foster</persName>, and <persName key="Bishop, William W.">W. W. Bishop</persName>. The trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John Lee</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 302.</note>

<note xml:id="n0050">50 A summary of <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName>'s opening address to the jury, which was forcible and well studied, will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Sept. 20, 1876.</note>

<pb n="567" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.567"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">to pacify the Indians as far as possible</seg>, and to allow this and all other companies of emigrants to pass through the territory unmolested. <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, who had been suspected of complicity, through attending a council at which <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and others had arranged their plans, denied that he was ever an accessary thereto. He also deposed that he had met the emigrants at Corn Creek, some eighty miles north of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, on the 25th of August, while on his way to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, and that when he first heard of the massacre he was in the neighborhood of Fort Bridger.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The first witness examined was <persName key="Well, Daniel H.">Daniel H. Wells</persName>, who merely stated that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was a man of influence among the Indians, and understood their language sufficiently to converse with them. <persName key="Haslem, James">James Haslem</persName> testified that between five and six o'clock on Monday, September 7, 1857, he was ordered by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> to start for <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> and with all speed deliver a letter or message to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>. He arrived at 11 A. M. on the following Thursday, and four hours later was on his way back with the answer. As he set forth, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> said to him: "Go with all speed, spare no horse-flesh. The emigrants must not be meddled with, if it takes all <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron county</placeName> to prevent it. They must go free and unmolested."</seg><ref target="n0051">51</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">Samuel McMurdy</persName> testified that he saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> shoot one of the women, and two or three of the sick and wounded who were in the wagons. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName> alleged that soon after the massacre he met <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> within a few miles of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, when the latter stated that two young girls,<ref target="n052">52</ref> who had been hiding in the underbrush <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>, were brought into his presence by a Utah chief. The Indian asked what should be done with them. "They must be shot," answered <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>; "they are too old to be spared."</seg></seg> 
    
<note xml:id="n0051">51 Ibid. <persName key="Haslem, James">Haslem</persName>'s testimony, together with other evidence tending to exculpate the dignitaries of the church, is omitted in the account of the trial given in <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>.</note>

<note xml:id="n0052">52 <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">From 13 to 15 years of age.</seg></note>

<pb n="568" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.568"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">"They are too pretty to be killed," answered the chief. "Such are my orders," rejoined <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>; <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">whereupon the Indian shot one of them</seg>, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> dragged the other to the ground and cut her throat.</seg><ref target="n0053">53</ref></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">On the testimony which we have now before us I will make but one comment. If <persName key="Haslbem, James Holt">Haslem</persName>'s statement was true, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> was clearly no accomplice;</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">if it was false, and his errand to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> was a mere trick of the first presidency, it is extremely improbable that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> would have betrayed his intention to <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName> by using the remarks that he made only two days before the event. Moreover, apart from other considerations, <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">it is impossible to reconcile the latter theory with the shrewd and far-sighted policy of this able leader, who well knew that his militia were no match for the army of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and who would have been the last one to rouse the vengeance of a great nation against his handful of followers.</seg></seg><ref target="n0054">54</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="Lee"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was convicted of murder in the first degree, and being allowed to select the mode of his execution, was sentenced to be shot. The case, was appealed to the supreme court of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, but the judgment was sustained, and it was ordered that the sentence should be carried into effect on the 23d of March, 1877.<ref target="n0055">55</ref> <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, and others who had also been arraigned for trial, were soon afterward discharged from custody.</seg></seg></p>

<p>A few days before his execution, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> made a <choice>
<orig>con- 

<note xml:id="n0053">53 <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Sept. 20, 1876; confirmed in the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, in Mormonism Unveiled, 361, 365-7.</note>

<note xml:id="n0054">54 In a sworn statement made at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">S. L. City</placeName>, Oct. 24, 1884, <persName key="Woodruff, Wilford">Wilford Woodruff</persName> states that he was present when <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had an interview with <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> in the autumn of 1857; that the latter was deeply affected, shed tears, and said he was sorry that innocent blood had been shed. A copy of it will be found in The Mountain Meadows Massacre, 51-3, a republished lecture by Elder <persName key="Penrose, Charles William">C. W. Penrose</persName> (<placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">S. L. City</placeName>, 1884).</note>

<note xml:id="n0055">55 Reports of the proceedings at the second trial will be found in <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Mormonism Unveiled, 302-78; The <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, Sept. 20, 27, 1876; <persName key="Beadle, John H.">Beadle</persName>'. Western Wilds, 515-19. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">In passing sentence, Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> remarked: 'The men who actually participated in the deed are not the only guilty parties. Although the evidence shows plainly that you were a willing participant in the massacre, yet both trials taken together show that others, and some high in authority, inaugurated and decided upon the wholesale slaughter of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the emigrants</seg>.'</seg></note>

<pb n="569" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.569"/> 

fession</orig><reg>confession</reg></choice>,<ref target="n0056">56</ref> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">in which he attempts to palliate his guilt, to throw the burden of the crime on his accomplices, especially on <persName key="Dame, William  H.">Dame</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, and to show that the massacre was committed by order of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham </persName> and the high-council. He also makes mention of other murders, or attempts to murder, which, as he alleges, were committed by order of some higher authority.<ref target="n0057" >57</ref> "I feel composed, and as calm as a summer morning," he writes on the 13th of March. "I hope to meet my fate with manly courage. I declare my innocence. I have done nothing designedly wrong in that unfortunate and lamentable affair with which I have been implicated. I used my utmost endeavors to save them from their sad fate. I freely would have given worlds, were they at my command, to have averted that evil. Death to me has no terror. It is but a struggle, and all is over. I know that I have a reward in heaven, and my conscience does not accuse me."</seg></p>

<p>Ten days later he was led to execution at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain Meadows</geogName>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">Over that spot the curse of the almighty seemed to have fallen. The luxuriant herbage that had clothed it twenty years before had disappeared; the springs were dry and wasted, and now there was neither grass nor any green thing, save here and there a copse of sage-brush or of scrub-oak, that</seg> 

<note xml:id="n0056">56 It will be found entire in <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Mormonism Unveiled, 213-92; and in part in <persName key="Beadle, John H.">Beadle</persName>'s Western Wilds, 519-23, <persName key="Stenhouse, Fanny">Stenhouse</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Tell It All</hi>, 633-48, the last of these versions being somewhat garbled. For other accounts and comments, see <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, March 28, 1877; 8. F. Post, March 22, 23, 24, 1877; San Buenaventura Signal, March 31, 1877; Sonoma Democrat, March 31, 1877; Napa County Reporter, Apr. 7, 1877; Los Angeles Weekly Express, March 24, 1877; Los Angeles Herald, March 24, 1877; Anaheim Gazette, march 24, 1877; Western Oregonian, Apr. 7, 1877; Portland Weekly Oregonian, Apr. 7, 1877.</note> 

<note xml:id="n0057">57 He mentions the case of an Irishman, whose throat was cut by <persName key="WEston, John">John Weston</persName>, near <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, in the winter of 1857-8; of <persName key="Keyes, Robert">Robert Keyes</persName>, whose assassination was attempted about the same time by <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>; of three <placeName type="settlement" key="California">California</placeName>-bound emigrants, who were suspected of being spies and were slain at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> in 1857. An attempt was made, he says, to assassinate Lieut <persName key="Tobin, William G.">Tobin</persName> in the same year. A young man (name not given) was murdered near <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> in 1854. At the same place <persName key="Laney, William">William Laney</persName> narrowly escaped murder, his skull being fractured with a club by <persName key="Carter, Barney">Barney Carter</persName>, son-in-law to <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>. <persName key="Anderson, Ramos">Ramos Anderson</persName>, a Dane, had his throat cut at midnight by <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and others near <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s Confession, in <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 272-83. Some of these cases are imputed to the Danites, but I find no mention of them in <persName key="Hickman, Bill">Hickman</persName>'s Destroying Angel, whose narrative covers the period 1850-65.</note>

<pb n="570" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.570"/> 

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">served but to make its desolation still more desolate. Around <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">the cairn that marks their grave</seg> still flit, as some have related, the phantoms of the murdered emigrants, and nightly reenact in ghastly pantomime the scene of this hideous tragedy.</seg></p>

<p>About ten o'clock on the morning of the 23d a party of armed men alighting from their wagons approached the site of the massacre. Among them were the United States marshal, <persName key="Nelson, William">William Nelson</persName>, the district attorney, a military guard, and a score of private citizens. In their midst was <persName key="Lee, John D.">John Doyle Lee</persName>. Over the wheels of one of the wagons blankets were placed to serve as a screen for the firing party. Some rough pine boards were then nailed together in the shape of a coffin, which was placed near the edge of the cairn, and upon it <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> took his seat until the preparations were completed. The marshal now read the order of the court, and, turning to the prisoner, said: "Mr <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, if you have anything to say before the order of the court is carried into effect, you can do so now." Rising from the coffin,<ref target="n0058">58</ref> he looked calmly around for a moment, and then with unfaltering voice repeated in substance the statements already quoted from his confession. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">"I have but little to say this morning," he added. "It seems I have to be made a victim; a victim must be had, and I am the victim. I studied to make <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s will my pleasure for thirty years. See now what I have come to this day! I have been sacrificed in a cowardly, dastardly manner. I cannot help it; it is my last word; it is so. I do not fear death; I shall never go to a worse place than I am now in. I ask the Lord my God, if my labors are done, to receive my spirit."</seg> A Methodist clergyman,<ref target="n0059">59</ref> who acted as his spiritual adviser, then knelt by his side and offered a brief prayer, to which he listened attentively. After shaking hands 

<note xml:id="n0058">58 "He first requested one <persName key="Fennemore, James">James Fennemore</persName>, who was taking photographs of the group in which <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> formed the central figure, to send a copy to each of his three wives, <persName key="Lee, Rachel">Rachel</persName>, <persName key="Lee, Sarah">Sarah</persName>, and <persName key="Fennemore, Emma">Emma Fennemore</persName> promised to do so.</note>

<note xml:id="n0059">59 "The Rev. <persName key="Stokes, George">George Stokes</persName>.</note>

<pb n="571" xml:id="mmm.uh.bancroft.1889.571"/> 

with those around him, he removed a part of his clothing, handing his hat to the marshal, who bound a  handkerchief over his eyes, his hands being free at his own request. Seating himself with his face to the firing party, and with hands clasped over his head, he exclaimed: "Let them shoot the balls through my heart. Don't let them mangle my body." The word of command was given; the report of rifles rang forth on the still morning air, and without a groan or quiver <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">the body of the criminal fell back lifeless on his coffin. God was more merciful to him than he had been to his victims.</seg><ref target="n0060">60</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n0060"><p>60 The body was afterward interred by relatives at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. Accounts of the execution will be found in <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, 383-90; <persName key="Stenhouse, Fanny">Stenhouse</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Tell It All</hi>, 627-31; <persName key="Stenhouse, Thomas B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>'s Western Wilds, 524-5; S. L. City Tribune, March 31, 1877; S. L. Herald, March 28, 1877; <hi rend="italic">S. F. Bulletin</hi>, March 24, 1877; S. F. Post, March 24, 1877; Oakland Tribune, March 24, 1877; Los Angeles Weekly Express, March 31, 1877; Los Angeles Reporter, March 23, 24, 1877; Sonoma Democrat, March 31, 1877; Anaheim Gazette, March 31, 1877; Mariposa Gazette, March 31, 1877; Jacksonville (Or.) Dem. Times, March 31, 1877. Portraits of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> will be found in the frontispiece of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, and in <persName key="Stenhouse, Fanny">Stenhouse</persName>'s Tell It All, facing p. 632; cuts representing the execution in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., facing p. 630; Beadle's Western Wilds, 525; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">Mormonism Unvailed</hi>, facing p. 384.</p>

<p><persName key="Lee, John D.">John Doyle Lee</persName> was a native of <placeName type="settlement" key="Kaskaskia, IL">Kaskaskia</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Illinois">Ill.</placeName>, where he was born in 1812. After engaging in the several occupations of mail-carrier, stage-driver, farmer, soldier, and clerk, he joined the Mormon church at Far West in 1837. At <placeName type="settlement" key="Nauvoo, IL">Nauvoo</placeName> he was employed as a policeman, one of his duties being to guard the person and residence of <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Jos. Smith</persName>. After the migration he was one of those who laid out and built up the city of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>. He was later appointed probate judge of <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron co.</placeName>, and elected a member of the territorial legislature, holding the former position at the time of the massacre.</p>

</note>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>