<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Great Salt Lake Trail</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                    <author><forename>Henry</forename> <surname>Inman</surname> and </author>
		    <author><forename>William</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Cody</surname> <addName>["Buffalo Bill"]</addName></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.wa.inmancody.1898</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m" type="main">The Great Salt Lake Trail</title>
                    <author><forename>Henry</forename> <surname>Inman</surname> and </author>
		    <author><forename>William</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Cody</surname> <addName>["Buffalo Bill"]</addName></author>
                    <publisher>Crane &amp; Company</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Topeka, KS</pubPlace>
                    <extent>135-162</extent>
                    <date when="1898">1898</date>
		    <note type="source">Henry Inman and William F. Cody. <hi rend="italic">The Great Salt Lake Trail</hi>.
 Topeka, KS: Crane &amp; Company, 1914. 135-162.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>western_americana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
	    <change when="2011-09-06"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt"</name> Encoding Enhancement</change>
            <change when="2010-08-03"><name>Rosie Hanneke</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>

<text>
<body>
<div1 type="chapter">
 
<pb n="135" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.163"/>

<head>CHAPTER VII</head>

    <p><hi rend="center">Mountain Meadows Massacre&#8212;Indians Attack the Wagons&#8212;Lee Offers Protection&#8212;Ambushed by Lee&#8212;Lee Flies to the Mountains&#8212;Mormon Church Acquitted&#8212;Execution of John D. Lee&#8212;Temporary Toll-Bridges&#8212;Indian Raids on Cattle Ranches&#8212;Stuttering Brown&#8212;Graves Along the Trail</hi></p>

<figure xml:id="www.wa.inmancody.1898.191.figure">
<p>John D. Lee</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">he</hi> most terrible fate that ever befell a caravan
on the Old Trail was that known to history as the Mountain Meadows Massacre.</p>

<p>The story of this damnable, outrageous, and wholesale murder is as follows:&#8212;</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">In the spring of 1857</seg> a
band of emigrants numbering <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one hundred and thirty-six</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">from
<placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName></seg> and <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">set out for
Southern <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The party had about
six hundred head of cattle, thirty wagons, and thirty
horses and mules. At least thirty thousand dollars worth
of plunder was collected by the assassins after the
massacre.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Owing to the impending war between the United States
and the Mormons</seg>, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">the Saints had been ordered not to
furnish any emigrant trains with supplies.  In view of

<pb n="136" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.164"/>
    
this fact the leaders of the train found it difficult to get
provisions for the party after reaching the territory
occupied by that sect. The party reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>
and camped about the end of July, but finding the 
Mormons in so unfriendly a mood, decided to break camp
and move on. Continuing their journey, they proceeded
to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver City</placeName>, thence to <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, where they obtained a
scanty supply of provisions.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Arriving at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, they succeeded in purchasing
about fifty bushels of wheat, which was ground at a mill
belonging to <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, formerly commander of the
fort at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, but then Indian agent, and in charge of
an Indian farm near <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">About thirty miles to the southwest of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> are the
<geogName type="valley" key="Mountian Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, which form the divide between
the waters of the Great Basin and those which flow into
the Colorado. At the south end of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, which 
are four to five miles in length and one in width, but here
run to a narrow point, is a large stream, the banks of
which are about ten feet in height. Close to this stream
the emigrants were encamped <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">on the 5th of September</seg>,
almost midway between two ranges of low hills some four
hundred yards apart.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">It was Saturday evening</seg> when the trains encamped at
<geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. On the Sabbath they rested, and at
the usual hour one of them conducted divine service as
had been their custom throughout the journey.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">At dawn on the following morning </seg>while the camp-fires
were being lighted, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">they were fired upon by Indians</seg>,
or white men disguised as savages</seg>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">more than twenty
were killed or wounded</seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">their cattle having been driven
off</seg> by the assailants who had crept on them under cover
of darkness. The men now ran for their wagons, pushed
them together so as to form a corral, and dug out the
earth deep enough to sink them to the hubs; then in the

<pb n="137" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.165"/>
    
centre of the enclosure they made a rifle-pit large enough
to contain the entire company. Thereupon the attacking
party, which numbered from three to four hundred, 
withdrew to the hills, on the crest of which they built parapets,
whence they shot down all who showed themselves outside 
the intrenchment.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">The emigrants were now in a state of siege, and had
little hope of escape as all the outlets of the valley were
guarded. Their ammunition was almost exhausted, many
of their number were wounded, and their sufferings from
thirst had become intolerable. Down in the ravine and
within a few yards of the corral was the stream of water,
but only after sundown could any of the precious liquid
be obtained, and then at great risk, for <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">this point was
covered by the muskets of the Indians, who lurked all
night among the ravines waiting for their victims</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">On the morning of the fifth day of the siege</seg>, a wagon
was seen approaching, accompanied by an escort of 
Mormon soldiers. When near the intrenchment the company
halted, and one of them, <persName key="Bateman, William">William Bateman</persName> by name, was
sent forward with a flag of truce. In answer to this 
signal a little girl, dressed in white, appeared in an open
space between the wagons. Half-way between the 
Mormons and the corral, <persName key="Bateman, William">Bateman</persName> was met by one of the 
emigrants named <persName key="Hamilton">Hamilton</persName>, to whom he promised protection 
for his party on condition that their arms were surrendered,
assuring him that they would be conducted safely to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar
City</placeName>. After a brief interview each returned to his 
comrades.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">It was arranged that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> should conclude terms
with the emigrants, and he immediately went into their
camp. Bidding the men pile their arms into the wagon,
<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">to avoid provoking the Indians</seg>, he placed in them the
wounded, the small children, and a little clothing.
While thus engaged, a man rode up with orders from

<pb n="138" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.166"/>
    
Major <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, an officer of the Mormon army, to hasten,
as <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Indians threatened to renew the attack</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">The emigrants were then hurried away, the men and
women following the wagons, the latter in front. All were
in single file, and on each side of them the militia were
drawn up two deep, with twenty paces between their lines.
Within two hundred yards of the camp, the men were
halted until the women approached a copse of scrub-oak,
about a mile distant, and near which, it appears, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the
Indians were in ambush</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">The men now resumed their march, the militia forming
in single file, each one walking by the side of an emigrant,
and carrying his musket on the left arm. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">As soon as the
women were close to the ambuscade, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, who was in
charge of the detachment, gave a signal, which had 
evidently been prearranged, by saying to his command, "Do
your duty"; and the horrible butchery commenced.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Most
of the men were shot down at the first fire. Three only
escaped from the valley; of these, two were quickly run
down and slaughtered; the third was slain at Muddy
Creek, some fifty miles distant</seg></seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The women and those of the children who were on foot
ran forward some two or three hundred yards, when they
were <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">overtaken by Indians</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">among whom were some
Mormons in disguise</seg>. The women fell on their knees,
and with clasped hands sued in vain for mercy, clutching
the garments of their murderers. Children pleaded for
life, but <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">the steady gaze of innocent childhood was met
by the demoniac grin of the savages, who brandished over 
them uplifted knives and tomahawks.</seg> Their skulls were
battered in, or their throats cut from ear to ear, and, while
still alive, the scalp was torn from their heads. Some of
the little ones met with a more merciful death, one, an
infant in arms, being shot through the head by the same
bullet that pierced its father's heart. Of the women

<pb n="139" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.167"/>
    
none were spared, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">of the children only those who were
not more than seven years of age</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">To two of Lee's wagoners was assigned the duty, so
called, of slaughtering the sick and wounded. Obeying
their instructions, they stopped their teams and 
despatched their unfortunate victims. Some were shot;
others had their throats cut.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">The massacre was now completed, and after <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">stripping
the bodies of all articles of value</seg>, Brother <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and his
associates went to breakfast, returning after a hearty meal
to bury their dead.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">It was a ghastly sight that met their eyes on their
return, and one that caused even the assassins to shudder
and turn pale. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The bodies had been entirely denuded by
the Indians. Some of the corpses were horribly mangled
and nearly all of them scalped. The dead were piled in
heaps in a ravine near by and a little earth thrown over
them.</seg> This was washed off by the first rains, leaving the 
remains to be devoured by wolves and coyotes.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">It was not until two years after the massacre that they
were decently interred, by a detachment of United States
troops sent for that purpose from Camp Floyd.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">On arriving at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, the soldiers found
skulls and bones scattered for the space of a mile around
the ravine, where they had been dragged by the wolves.
Nearly all of the bodies had been gnawed by those ghouls
of the desert, so that few could be recognized, as their 
dismembered skeletons were bleached by the sun. Many of
the skulls had been crushed by the butts of muskets, or
cloven with tomahawks; others were shattered by 
firearms discharged close to the head.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">A few remnants of apparel, torn from the backs of
women and children as they ran from their merciless 
pursuers, still fluttered among the bushes, and near by were
masses of human hair, matted and trodden in the earth.</seg></p>

<pb n="140" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.168"/>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">Over the last resting-place of the victims was erected
a cone-shaped cairn, twelve feet high. Against its 
northern base was a slab of rough granite with the following
inscription: "Here <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">120 men, women, and children</seg> were
massacred in cold blood, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">early in September, 1857</seg>. <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">They
were from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>.</seg>" Surmounting the cairn was a cross
of cedar, inscribed with the words: "Vengeance is mine; I
will repay, saith the Lord."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The survivors of the awful slaughter were seventeen
children, from two months to seven years of age, who
were carried, on the evening of the massacre, by <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D.
Lee</persName> and others to the house of <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>, and 
afterward placed in charge of Mormon families at various
points in the territory. All of them were recovered in
the summer of 1858, with the exception of one, who was
rescued a few months later, and though thinly clad, they
bore no marks of ill-usage. In 1859 they were conveyed
to <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, the Congress of the United States having
appropriated ten thousand dollars for their rescue and
restoration to relatives.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Those concerned in the massacre had pledged
themselves by the most solemn oaths to stand by each other,
and ever <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">to insist that the deed was done entirely by
Indians. For several months this was the accepted theory,
but when it became known that some of the children had
been spared, suspicion at once pointed elsewhere, for
among all the murders committed by the Utes, there was
not a single instance of their having shown any such
mercy.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Moreover, it was ascertained that an armed party
of Mormons had left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and had returned with
spoil, and that the savages complained of having been 
unfairly treated in the division of the booty.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">It is claimed that when <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> discovered that
the United States authorities suspected him as being the
principal actor in the awful tragedy, he left the valley of

<pb n="141" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.169"/>
    
the Great Salt Lake, and hid himself in one of the ca&#241;nons
of the Colorado,<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> where he remained for years suffering
that terrible anxiety which comes to all fugitives from
justice, sooner or later, and which is said by those who
have experienced it to be absolutely unbearable.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">In 1874, under the provisions of what is legally known
as the "Poland Bill," whereby the better administration of
justice was subserved, the Grand Jury was instructed to
investigate the Mountain Meadows Massacre, and find bills
of indictment against <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>,
<persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, and others. Warrants were issued for
their arrest, and after a vigorous search <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>
were captured, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> having been discovered in a hog-pen
at a small settlement on the Sevier River.</seg></seg></p>

<p>On the 23d of July, 1875, the trial was begun, at
<placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver City</placeName>, in Southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. Much delay ensued,
however, by the absence of witnesses, and by the fact that
<persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had promised to make a full confession, and turn
state's evidence. His statement was not accepted by the
court, and the case was brought to trial on the 23d of
July, with the expected result, that the jury, eight of
whom were Mormons, failed to agree.</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was then tried a second time, and it was proved
that the Mormon Church had nothing to do with the
massacre ; that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in fact, had acted in direct opposition

<note type="footnote"><hi rend="superscript">1</hi> He took refuge in the Grand Ca&#241;on of the Colorado River; his hiding-place was three miles from any possible pass, and he kept a faithful 
adherent constantly on guard. When any one was seen approaching the
pass, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was immediately signalled and forthwith repaired to a cave,
where he remained until it was discovered whether the intruder was
friend or foe. If not a friend, he kept to his cave until the party had
left, then returned to his house. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> followed this life for five or six
years, until he became so weary of dodging, and running from supposed
enemies, that he finally returned to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. I saw his cave and
house some years ago when, in company with General <persName key="Miles, N. A.">N. A. Miles</persName> and
others, I made a pleasure trip to the Grand Ca&#241;on. —<persName key="Cody, William F.">W. F. C<hi rend="smallcaps">ody</hi></persName>.</note>

<pb n="142" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.170"/>

to the officers of the Church. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">It was shown that he was
a villain and a murderer of the deepest dye; that with
his own hands, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">after inducing the emigrants to surrender
and give up their arms</seg>, he had shot two women and
brained a third with the butt-end of his musket, and had
cut the throat of a wounded man whom he had dragged
from one of the wagons</seg>; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">that he had gathered the
property of the emigrants and disposed of it for his own
benefit.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">It was further proved that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> shot two or
three of the wounded, and that <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">when two girls, who had
been hiding in the brush, were brought into his presence
by an Indian after the massacre, the latter asked what
was to be done with them, to which <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> replied, "They 
are too old to be spared." "They are too pretty to be
killed," answered the chief. "Such are my orders," said
<persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, whereupon the Indian shot one</seg>, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, dragging
the other to the ground, cut her throat.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was convicted of murder in the first degree, and,
having been allowed to select his own method of 
execution, was sentenced to be shot. The case was appealed
to the supreme court of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName>, but the judgment
was sustained, and it was ordered that the sentence be
carried into effect on the 23d of March, 1877. The
others who had been tried were discharged from custody.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">A short time before his execution <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> made a
confession in which he attempted to palliate his guilt by
throwing the burden of the crime on his accomplices,
especially on <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, and to show that the
massacre was committed by order of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and
the High Council, all of which was absolutely false.</seg></p>

<p>On the 13th of March he wrote: "I feel as composed
and as calm as a summer morning. I hope to meet my
fate with manly courage. I declare my innocence. I 
have done nothing designedly wrong in that unfortunate
and lamentable affair with which I have been implicated.

<pb n="143" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.171"/>

I used my utmost endeavours to save them from their sad
fate. I freely would have given worlds, were they at my
command, to have averted that evil. Death to me has no
terror. It is but a struggle, and all is over. I know
that I have a reward in heaven, and my conscience does
not accuse me."</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">Ten days later he was led to execution at the
<geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. Over that spot the curse of the Almighty
seemed to have fallen. The luxuriant herbage that had
clothed it twenty years before had disappeared; the
springs were dry and wasted, and now there was neither
grass nor any green thing, save here and there a copse of
sage-brush or scrub-oak, that served but to make its
desolation still more desolate. It is said that the 
phantoms of the murdered emigrants still flit around the cairn
that marks their grave, and nightly re&#235;nact in ghastly
pantomime the scene of this hideous tragedy.</seg></p>

<p>About ten o'clock on the morning of the 23d a party of
armed men, alighting from their wagons, approached the
site of the massacre. Among them were the United
States marshal, <persName key="Nelson, William">William Nelson</persName>, the district attorney, a
military guard, and a score of private citizens. In their
midst was <persName key="Lee, John D.">John Doyle Lee</persName>. Blankets were placed over
the wheels of one of the wagons, to serve as a screen for
the firing party. Some rough boards were then nailed
together in the shape of a coffin, which was placed near
the edge of the cairn, and upon it <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> took his seat until
the preparations were completed. The marshal now read
the order of the court, and, turning to the prisoner, said,
"Mr. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, if you have anything to say before the order of
the court is carried into effect you can do so now."</p>

<p>Rising from his coffin, he looked calmly around for a
moment, and then with unfaltering voice repeated the
statements already quoted from his confession. "I have
but little to say this morning," he added. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">"It seems I

<pb n="144" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.172"/>

have to be made a victim; a victim must be had, and I
am the victim. I studied to make <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s will
my pleasure for thirty years. See now what I have come
to this day! I have been sacrificed in a cowardly, 
dastardly manner. I cannot help it; it is my last word; it
is so. I do not fear death; I shall never go to a worse
place than I am now in. I ask the Lord my God, if my
labours are done, to receive my spirit."</seg></p>

<p>A Methodist clergyman, who acted as his spiritual
adviser, then knelt by his side and offered a brief prayer,
to which he listened attentively. After shaking hands
with those around him, he removed a part of his 
clothing, handing his hat to the marshal, who bound a 
handkerchief over his eyes, his hands being free at his own
request. Seating himself with his face to the firing party,
and with hands clasped over his head, he exclaimed:
"Let them shoot the balls through my heart. Don't let
them mangle my body."</p>

<p>The word of command was given, the report of the
rifes rang forth on the still morning air, and without a
groan or quiver the body of the criminal fell back 
lifeless on his coffin.</p>

<p>God was more merciful to him than he had been to his
victims.<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>

<!-- Remaining Section Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows

<p>Once one of Russell, Majors, &amp; Waddell's trains, upon
arriving at the Little Blue River below Kearney, en route
to Fort Laramie, had a little skirmish with the Sioux.
One of the party, who was going to the Fort to erect a
sawmill for the government,<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> tells about it as follows: &#8212;</p>

<p>"I had travelled ahead of the train a mile or more, had
gotten off my mule, laid down awhile, and I believe fell
asleep. On awaking I saw three Indians coming out of
the brush on the creek bottom; I took a glance at them,

-->

<note type="footnote"><hi rend="superscript">1</hi> See Bancroft's <hi rend="italic">Pacific States</hi>.</note>
<note type="footnote"><hi rend="superscript">2</hi> Washington E. Hinman.</note>
           
<!-- Remaining Section Not Relevant to Mountain Meadows

<pb n="145" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.173"/>

and quietly stood where I was. After a while they 
approached me; I mounted my mule and held my loaded
shot-gun before me across the saddle, with my finger on
the trigger. Two formed themselves in front of me and
one behind. I paid no special attention to them, but they
immediately began to make signs in relation to swapping
their horses for my mule. I merely pointed to the U. S.
on the shoulder of the animal, indicating that it was not
my property. They quickly saw they couldn't scare me,
though I didn't know but what they were making up
their minds to kill me; finally, however, without any 
further demonstration they 
rode off one at a time,
and left me, where I 
remained until my train
came up.</p>

<figure xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.173.figure">
<p>Hairy Bear.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

<p>"When we made camp 
that afternoon a good-
sized band of Cheyennes 
and Arapahoes gathered 
around with their usual 
salutations of 'How? 
How?' I suggested to 
the wagon-master to 
boil some old coffee-
grounds after we had 
eaten our dinner, and 
with some sugar and 
crackers or something 
of that character, give 
them to the Indians, which was done. In the afternoon
we moved out on the road toward Kearney and ahead of
us was a train going unloaded to the same place. As
we strung out on the trail I noticed that the chief of
the band, I think he was known as 'Hairy Bear' of the

<pb n="146" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.174"/>
Cheyennes, and all of his warriors were riding along,
one opposite nearly every driver. I told the wagon-
master that he had better stop the train and tell the
Indians they must take either one end of the road or the
other, as it was evident they were getting ready for a row.
Upon discovering that we were 'up to' their little job,
they went ahead.</p>

<p>"At dark, after we had encamped again, the assistant
wagon-master of the train in front came to us and told of
a little scrap he had with these same Indians. One of
them at first undertook to snatch the handkerchief off his
neck; another Indian had shot two or three arrows
after a teamster, then they rode off.</p>

<p>"Our train went on five miles, where we were going to
camp, when a messenger was sent by the commanding
officer at the fort suggesting that the two caravans camp
together, which we did. In the morning, when we
started out, I rode ahead on my mule as usual, and when
I had got about half-way to the fort I saw the white
shoulder-blade of a buffalo setting up on end about fifty
yards from the road. I rode out and picked it up; it was
standing on end with a little wisp of grass wrapped
around it; on the face of it were three men painted red.
The broad end of the blade in the ground was marked
out like a fort, with little black spots, meaning tracks of
soldiers, and a man in black was there with his rifle
drawn, and resting across one of the red men's necks.
Another was shot below the shoulder-joint, and one had
his arm broken. Painted in red, right up toward the
joint, was a wolf trotting from it. This indicated that the
Indians had had a fight; three of them had been wounded,
one in the back, one in the neck, and one had his arm
broken. There were also three spears, the points of
which were stuck in the ground, indicating that three
Indians were dead and had no more use for the weapons.</p>

<pb n="147" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.175"/>

<p>"I took the bone to the fort and there the interpreter
told what it all meant. I discovered it to be a valuable 
history of what was going on: the Cheyennes and Arapahoes
who had been with us had separated; the Arapahoes had
gone away and tried to steal some ponies; they would be 
along pretty soon. All this occurred after the Arapahoes
had separated from the Cheyennes. The latter had placed
the shoulder-blade of the buffalo on the trail, to prevent
their making the mistake of going to the fort, where,
after their trouble with the train, the soldiers would 
make it hot for them; but as I had found their message
first, their plan was frustrated.</p>

<p>"Later on the Indians came to the fort, and one of the
teamsters who had been wounded happened to be there,
and he picked out the very Indian who had shot him.
The commanding officer directed the sergeant of the
guard to arrest the savage, which he did, and proceeded
to put him in irons. While fastening on a ball and
chain, the Indian struck the soldier on the head who was
holding him. Upon this the commanding officer told one
of the guards to shoot him, which the man did very
promptly. The bullet went clear through the Indian,
and shot one of the interpreter's fingers off. After this
little incident, there was a general free-for-all fight, in
which the Indians were badly worsted. After this battle
the Indians went south and were not troublesome for
some time."</p>

<p>When the snow began to melt from the mountain peaks
in the spring the little insignificant creeks swelled up and
for a few weeks were transformed into raging torrents,
too deep or too dangerous to ford. At such seasons the
few ranchmen who were in the country built temporary
bridges across them, hardly ever exceeding fifty feet in
length. While the streams were high, these bridges
were a veritable gold—mine from the revenue paid by

<pb n="148" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.176"/>

the freighters as toll. In order, however, to make their
toll lawful, every bridge-owner was required to possess
himself of a charter from the secretary of the territory,
and approved by the governor. This official document
simply authorized the proprietor to charge such toll as he
saw fit, which was always extravagantly high,&#8212;usually
five dollars for each team of six yoke of cattle and
wagon. These ranchmen also kept an assortment of
groceries and barrels of whiskey, for the latter of which
the teamsters were always liberal customers.</p>

<p>It very often happened, through ignorance of the law
or from ignoring it, that these ranchmen took out no
charter, because its possession was so rarely questioned.</p>

<p>At the trail-crossing of Rock Creek was one of these
frontier toll-bridges. In the spring of 1866 two trains
were travelling in company, one in charge of a man
known as Stuttering Brown, because of an impediment
in his speech. He was a man of undoubted 
courage, and determined. When angry, he indulged in
some of the quaintest and wittiest original expressions
imaginable; but if you laughed at him, he became very
much offended, as he was particularly sensitive about the
impediment of his speech. Still, he was a man who 
appreciated a joke, and enjoyed it even if it was upon
himself.</p>

<p>Brown's train comprised twenty teams, and the other
twenty-six. His train happened to be in the lead that
day, and as they neared the bridge, Brown rode back to
the other wagon-master and said:&#8212;</p>

<p>"B-B-Billy, wh-what are you g-g-going to do about
p-p-paying t-t-toll on this b-b-bridge?"</p>

<p>He answered that if the fellow had a charter, he would
be compelled to pay; otherwise he would not, as probably
the charges were exorbitant. Brown argued they might
have some trouble with the ranchman if pay was refused,

<pb n="149" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.177"/>

as they generally had a pretty tough crowd around them
who were ready for any kind of a skirmish.</p>

<p>His friend called attention to the fact that together
they had fifty-five men, well armed on account of
probable Indian troubles. They were all good fighters,
and they would ask for no greater fun than cleaning out
the ranch, if it was discovered that the proprietor had
no charter.</p>

<p>Brown returned to the bridge, where the ranchman
stood preparing to collect his toll, which was five dollars
a team in advance. This would require one hundred 
dollars from Brown and a hundred and thirty from the other
train. Brown refused point blank to pay the bill, and
the ranchman asked him upon what grounds.</p>

<p>Brown's reply was:&#8212;</p>

<p>"Y—Y-You h-h-haint g-g-got no ch—ch-charter." The
ranchman answered him that he had, and if he would go
back to the ranch with him, he would show it. The
ranch was only a few hundred yards away.</p>

<p>Brown accompanied him, and in a short time returned
to the train. His friend asked him if the charter was
all right, to which Brown replied in the affirmative, 
saying that he had settled for his outfit, and that his friend
had better do the same, which he accordingly did.</p>

<p>After crossing the bridge, the other wagon-master
noticed that Brown was very much amused about 
something, occasionally indulging in loud bursts of laughter.
His friend inquired the cause of his mirth, but he refused
to tell.</p>

<p>When they arrived at the camping-ground that 
evening, and after corralling the trains and placing out the
proper guards, Brown invited his friend to take supper
with him. While eating he was asked what had so
amused him during the afternoon. He said that when
he went up to the ranch to see the bridge charter, he

<pb n="150" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.178"/>

rode to the door, sat on his mule, and asked the ranchman
to trot out his charter and be d&#8212;d quick about it.</p>

<p>The man went into a back room and pretty soon returned, shouting:&#8212;</p>

<p>"You stuttering thief, here it is! What do you think
about it?"</p>

<p>Brown looked up and found that he was peering into
the muzzle of a double-barrelled gun, probably loaded
with buck-shot. The ranchman was pointing it directly
at his head, with both triggers cocked. Brown saw he
was in earnest, and asked if that was the charter. The 
ranchman replied that it was.</p>

<p>His friend then asked, "What did you do, Brown?"</p>

<p>"N-N-Not much. J-J-Just t-t-told him, th-th-that's
good, and settled."</p>

<p>Some years afterward, when Brown was part owner and
superintendent of the Black Hills stage-line, he was 
waylaid and killed by the Indians, while on a return trip
from Custer City. Thus ended the career of one of the
bravest and best of the men on the frontier.</p>

<p>One of the most famous of temporary toll-ferries was
over the trail-crossing of Green River. It was owned by
Bill Hickman, a Mormon, and as the river was seldom
fordable he reaped a rich harvest of gold from the 
emigrant trains. His prices for crossing teams depended
upon the ability of their owners to pay, varying from five
to twenty dollars each. The old ford may still be seen
just below the station of Green River on the Union 
Pacific Railroad.</p>

<p>During the preparation for the Mormon war the supply-
trains of the government were constantly harassed by
that people. The genius of campaigning by destroying
trains was Major Lot Smith. One evening, at the head
of forty men, after riding all night, he came in sight of a
westward-bound government train. On coming up to it

<pb n="151" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.179"/>

he ordered the drivers to turn round and go back on their
trail. They obeyed promptly, but as soon as Smith was
out of sight, they wheeled around and travelled west
again. During the day a party of Mormon troops passed
them, and taking all of the freight out of the wagons, left
them standing there.</p>

<p>Smith was afterward informed by his scouts that a 
caravan of twenty-six wagons was approaching. Upon this
information he halted his men and, after eating, started
again at dusk, approached the train while it was in camp
at a place near Simpson's Hollow, and ambushed his
party for several hours. Meanwhile, he learned that
there were two trains, each of twenty-six wagons; but in
fact as was afterward discovered there were really three
of seventy-five wagons in all.</p>

<p>About midnight, while only a few of the teamsters
were gathered around their camp-fire, some of them
drinking, some smoking, they suddenly saw what seemed
to be an endless procession of armed and mounted men
emerge from the darkness.</p>

<p>Smith, quietly coming up, asked for the captain of the
outfit, whose name was Dawson. As a majority of the 
teamsters were asleep, their guns fastened to the covers
of the wagons, and any resistance almost hopeless, 
Dawson stepped forward, surrendered, and told his men to
stack their arms and group themselves on a spot 
designated by Smith. Smith dealt successively with the other
trains in like manner. Then, after lighting two torches,
he handed one of them to a Gentile in his party, known
as Big James, remarking at the same time, "It is 
eminently proper for a Gentile to spoil a Gentile."</p>

<p>Riding from wagon to wagon, Smith's men set fire to
the covers, which rapidly caught in the crisp mountain
air, and were soon all ablaze. Dawson, meanwhile, was
ordered by Smith to the rear of the trains to take out

<pb n="152" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.180"/>

provisions for his captors, and when everything was fairly
burning he and his party rode away, first informing his
panic-stricken captives that he would return as soon as
he had delivered the provisions to his comrades near by,
and instantly shoot any one who should make any attempt
to extinguish the flames.</p>

<p>The destruction of these supply-trains was a severe
blow to the army of occupation; both troops and animals
suffered severely in consequence of the loss of provisions.</p>

<p>The year 1865 was fruitful of Indian depredations
along the Old Trail, particularly that portion which ran
through the Platte Valley. The Sioux and Cheyennes
allied themselves in large bands against the whites, and
raided the beautiful region from one end to the other.
Theirs was a trail of blood like that of Attila, "The
Scourge," and their fiendish acts rivalled those of that
monster of the Old World.</p>

<p>On the south side of the Platte River, about a hundred
and twenty-five miles from Denver, were located, 
successively, three ranches, known as the Wisconsin, the 
American, and Godfrey's.</p>

<p>On the morning of the 19th of January, of the year above
mentioned, a company of cavalry, marching from Denver,
passed along by the Wisconsin Ranch a little before nine
o'clock. As the Indians were on the war-path, and upon
request of the proprietor, the captain of the company
promised to send back ten men of his troop, to help defend
the property, as they were going to their station a few
miles east of there.</p>

<p>The cavalry had hardly disappeared from view across
the divide when the savages began their attack. The
captain of the cavalry, hearing the continuous firing, 
immediately returned with his command, and at once a fierce
battle took place a short distance from the ranch. The
troops retreated and went into camp at Valley Station.</p>

<pb n="153" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.181"/>

<p>There were seven white persons living on the ranch
at that time: Mr. Mark M. Coad, P. B. Danielson, his
wife and two children, besides two hired men. They
fought the Indians until five o'clock in the afternoon
without any outside assistance, and had killed several.
About noon the savages set fire to the haystack and stable,
which caused a dense smoke to settle over the house in
which the besieged were sheltered.</p>

<p>As the fight progressed, the Indians seemed determined
to have the building at any hazard; so they cut a large
amount of wood and piled it against the back door, with
the intention of burning it down so as to gain an entrance.
The door was blockaded with sacks of grain, to prevent
the bullets from coming into the room, and while the
savages were placing the wood on the outside, the men
quietly removed the sacks of grain. When the besiegers
were ready to kindle the fire, the door was swung open,
and Mr. Coad, springing to the opening as it swung back,
killed three of the Indians, and wounded several more with
his two pistols, then jumped back and the door was closed.</p>

<p>The daring act was performed so quickly that the
savages were instantly demoralized. They dared not
return the shots for fear of killing some of their own
party who were attempting to enter the house.</p>

<p>After the door was again closed the Indians regained
their senses, and a perfect shower of bullets rained against 
the house. The savages, now discouraged from the 
suddenness and effect of Mr. Coad's attack, and the loss of
so many of their number, retreated to their camp and
hostilities ceased for the time.</p>

<p>While this battle was in progress at the Wisconsin
ranch, another fight was going on at the American
ranch, twelve miles east. This ranch was occupied by
the Messrs. Morrissey, one of whom had his wife, two
children, and six or eight hired men.</p>

<pb n="154" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.182"/>

<p>It was subsequently shown that the men must have
fought very desperately, as they were found locked arm
in arm with the savages, holding their pistols or knives in
their hands. The ranch was looted of its valuables and
burned. The whites were all killed, excepting Mrs. 
Morrissey and her two children, who were taken prisoners
and carried off by the Indians, but shortly afterward were
surrendered to the government. Early in the morning of
the same day the Indians attacked the Godfrey ranch.
There were living there Mr. Godfrey, better known as
Old Ricket; his wife; his daughter, a girl of fourteen
years; and two other white men.</p>

<p>They fought the savages for several hours, and finally,
seeing that they stood no chance of capturing the place,
the Indians determined to burn it; so they set fire to the
haystack which stood near the building. After the 
Indians had lighted the stack, Mr. Godfrey's little daughter
rushed out of the door with a bucket of water, 
extinguished the flames, and returned safely into the house, 
notwithstanding the shower of bullets and arrows that rained
all around her.</p>

<p>The Indians just then, somehow learning that the
American ranch had been taken, and there was a chance 
for them in the division of the spoils, withdrew all their
force and went down there.</p>

<p>From there they went on to the Wisconsin ranch,
which had not been captured, for the purpose of 
re&#235;nforcing the besieging party at that place. The besieged had
succeeded in sending a messenger during the day to the
commanding officer of the troops at Valley Station, asking
for assistance to enable them to get away from the ranch,
well knowing that the savages would return in the 
morning with re&#235;nforcements. The captain sent up a 
detachment of fifteen men, and escorted the people of the ranch
down to the Station. The next morning Mr. Coad, with

<pb n="155" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.155"/>
    
a detachment of troops as escort, and several wagons,
started for the purpose of taking away the goods to a
place of safety. When approaching the ranch they
found it in the possession of the Indians; and the troops,
seeing the strength of the savage force, knew that it would
be worse than useless to attempt to drive them away; so
they returned to the Station. Thus three of the finest
ranches on the trail at that time were destroyed.</p>

<p>One of the most disastrous and effectual raids by the
savages during the year 1865 was the burning and 
sacking of Julesburg, which was within rifle-shot of Fort 
Sedgwick, on the South Platte River, in what is now Weld
County, Colorado.</p>

<p>There the government established a military 
reservation, comprising sixty-four square miles, in the exact
centre of which the fort was located. The reservation
extended across the river, and included the mouth of Pole
Creek, a small tributary of the Platte, which debouches
into it from the north.</p>

<p>The original Julesburg, at that time,<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> was a mere 
hamlet of crude frame buildings, and but for the proximity of
Fort Sedgwick it would have been destroyed long before
it was.</p>

<p>On the morning of the 2d of February, the men at the
stage station, called Julesburg, discovered a small band of
Indians in the valley to the east of them, who were
evidently out on the war-path, as they had all their 
paraphernalia on, were finely mounted, hideously painted, and
profusely decorated with feathers. Possessing a fair
knowledge of the savage character and rightly conceiving
the intention of the savages, the station employees 

<note type="footnote"><hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The present Julesburg, until a few years ago, was called "Denver Junction"; the old town was situated a mile west on the opposite side of
the river, and the Julesburg of 1867 was five miles farther west, north of
the Platte, and is now known as Weir.</note>

<pb n="156" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.184"/>

incontinently left for the fort for safety, and to give the alarm
of the presence of the Indians.</p>

<p>Captain O'Brien, who was in command of Fort 
Sedgwick, had already had some experience in savage warfare;
and, although his force was extremely small, immediately
upon receipt of the intelligence that hostile Indians were
in the vicinity and that the overland stage station was in
danger, he sounded boots and saddles. Thirty-five soldiers
re&#235;nforced by volunteer citizens were soon on the trail of
the savages, led by the gallant captain.</p>

<p>The government scouts had that morning reported that
there were no Indians near, and consequently no 
apprehension of danger entered the minds of either soldier or
civilian; little did they surmise that just out of sight
over the divide more than two thousand of the painted
devils were hiding.</p>

<p>The small band of savages that had entered the valley,
and which had been first seen by the station men, were
pursued for some distance, when they separated and rode
out into the sand-hills. At almost the same instant, while
the soldiers were after them, swarms of savages began to
pour into the valley in the rear of the troops, about a
half a mile west of them. They soon massed in great
numbers, and rapidly closed every avenue of escape,
riding in bands and giving vent to the most horrid 
war-whoops and unearthly yells as they saw their vantage.</p>

<p>Captain O'Brien ordered his troopers to dismount, and,
enjoining his men to keep cool, to make every shot tell, 
turned upon the Indians and opened fire where they were
thickest. There ensued one of the most sanguinary
struggles, considering the few soldiers engaged, that the
plains have ever witnessed.</p>

<p>"Load and fire at will" was the order, and the 
repeating rifles of the soldiers made awful havoc; the slaughter
immediately in front of the white men was indeed terrible,

<pb n="157" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.185"/>
    
and the Indians, demoralized at the manner in which their
ranks were being decimated, hurriedly fell back. This
permitted the troops to make considerable advance in the
direction of the fort before they again halted.</p>

<p>Pressed on each flank and in rear, the troops were 
compelled to divert their fire to those points, but when the
progress of the savages was again stayed, they once more
concentrated their shots where they were densely massed
in front. It appeared as if every ball found its victim.
The discharges were so rapid, and the aim so careful, that
the Indians had to give way before it, permitting the
soldiers to advance once more. Thus they fought step
by step, with great loss, but brave to the last degree.</p>

<p>It was a fortunate matter that the savages were armed
principally with bows and arrows, there being very few
rifles among them. Had it been otherwise, had the
Indians been armed with repeating rifles, as were the
whites, it is probable that not a single soldier would 
have been left to tell the story. The Indians filled the
air with flights of arrows, but woe to the Indian who
came within range of the deadly rifles! Many shafts
with spent force fell harmlessly among the soldiers.
Many inflicted slight wounds, and some were fatal.
Some of the whites were killed by bullets, some by
arrows.</p>

<p>Re&#235;nforcementsfrom the fort finally opened an avenue
of escape for the remaining whites, and eighteen of the
forty men who went out in the morning came back; the
rest were killed, scalped, and mutilated by the savages!
Their bodies, however, were recovered and buried on the
side of the bluff just south of the fort, and headboards
with appropriate inscriptions mark the final resting-p1ace
of each.</p>

<p>When they found that a part of their prey would
escape, the Indians began to turn their attention to

<pb n="158" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.186"/>
    
pillaging at the stage station. One house contained a
general assortment of groceries and outfitting goods.
These they loaded upon their ponies and carried over
the river. They then disappeared among the hills, 
leaving all the buildings on fire.</p>

<p>The stage company had a large amount of grain and
supplies stored at the station. These were burned, and a
treasure-coach with fifty thousand dollars in money was
captured.</p>

<p>As soon as Captain O'Brien reached the fort, he ordered
out the field-pieces and commenced shelling the enemy.
Being a very expert gunner, he directed the fire of the
guns so effectively as to kill a large number of savages.
A crowd of redskins had gathered round some open boxes
of raisins and barrels of sugar, when a shell burst in the
midst of them, killing thirteen, as was afterward admitted
by some of the Indians present. They also admitted the
loss of more than a hundred warriors during the fight.</p>

<p>In January, 1867, Mr. J. F. Coad, now of Omaha, had
a contract with the United States army to supply all
the government military posts between Julesburg and
Laramie with wood. He left home about the 17th of the
month, and was escorted by a company of soldiers, who
were en route to Fort Laramie, as far as forty miles
beyond Julesburg, where he left them, and proceeded up
Pole Creek, thence to Lawrence's Fork, where his men
and wagons were, to commence work on his contract.</p>

<p>On the morning after his arrival at his wagon-camp,
Mr. Coad and three of his employees, while loading wood
about a mile and a half from camp, were attacked by
about forty Indians, who came charging down the valley
and prevented their retreat to the ranch. Seeing that
they were entirely cut off and without any hope of 
assistance, they immediately concluded that their only 
escape from death was to run for their lives, and get back

<pb n="159" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.187"/>
    
into the hills, if possible, believing that on account of the
steep and rugged trail the savages could not pursue them.</p>

<p>It was fearfully cold, the thermometer ranging about
twenty-five degrees below zero. Just as they started to
put their plan in motion, another band of Indians was
coming up the valley. These joined the others, and bore
down on the white men.</p>

<p>On arriving at the base of the hill up which the white
men were climbing, the Indians dismounted and started
on foot after them. Seeing their tactics, Mr. Coad and
his companions took off all their superfluous clothing and
threw it away, notwithstanding the severity of the 
temperature. One of the men, in passing near a ledge of
rock, discovered a hiding-place under it, dropped down
and crawled in, filling his tracks with dirt as he backed
into the cave. The Indians in trailing the party passed
by this rock, returned to it, and held a council. They
then went back to their horses. The other white men
secreted themselves in a ca&#241;on, built a fire, and there
remained until long after dark.</p>

<p>Left in the wagon-camp were three other men, who had
a hard fight with the Indians from about eleven o'clock
in the morning until three in the afternoon. They were
inside of the cabin, and managed to keep the savages at a
safe distance by firing at them through the crevices 
whenever they came within rifle-shot. The Indians kept
riding in a circle around the cabin for several hours, and,
finding they could not dislodge the three brave men, they
abandoned the attempt, after losing one of their ponies,
which received a rifle-bullet in his foreleg.</p>

<p>Some of the wood-choppers who had been at work a
mile and a half up the valley also had an exciting 
experience during the day with the savages, but came out 
unharmed.</p>

<p>After the entire party of white men assembled in camp

<pb n="160" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.188"/>

that night, a council was held, and it was determined to
send a messenger to the commanding officer of the post
at Julesburg, stating the condition of affairs and the
number of Indians supposed to be in the vicinity.</p>

<p>The next morning Mr. Coad and his men gathered
what cattle they could find, intending to leave for the
fort. They started, got on top of the divide, and
camped for the night. A raging blizzard set in, one of
those terrible storms of snow and wind characteristic of
the region, and the cattle sought shelter from the fearful
weather by returning to the valley which they had left
the day before, and where there was plenty of timber.
The party was able, however, to hold a few head. So they
hitched them up to the mess-wagon and returned to their
old camp, intending to wait until the messenger they had
sent to the fort should arrive with troops; but they were
not sure he had gone safely through.</p>

<p>The next morning Mr. Coad started east on the divide
on the only horse the Indians had left him, and about nine
o'clock that night he met Lieutenant Arms, of the Second
Cavalry, in command of Company E of that regiment.</p>

<p>Lieutenant Arms told him that he had met a large
war-party of savages about four o'clock that afternoon,
and was detained fighting them until after dark, when
they disappeared and went south, at a point about ten
miles west of Sidney. Lieutenant Arms had captured
several head of cattle and two of Mr. Coad's horses from 
the Indians in this engagement.</p>

<p>Mr. Coad returned with the troops to the camp on
Lawrence's Fork, arriving there at two o'clock in the
morning. The temperature that night was thirty degrees
below zero, and the troops suffered terribly from the 
extreme cold during their march. After arriving in the 
timber and getting something to eat, all turned in in their
blankets and rested until daylight the next morning. As

<pb n="161" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.189"/>

soon as breakfast was disposed of, the command started
on their return march, crossed the divide which they had
travelled over the previous night, and at three o'clock
in the morning reached Pole Creek, where they rested
until daylight. As soon as the day dawned they started
south, endeavouring to find the trail of the Indians. The
weather was extremely cold, the thermometer ranging
about thirty degrees below zero. In the afternoon, while 
on the divide, the snow being very deep, the command
was completely lost, and wandered aimlessly for several
hours, not knowing which course to take. Finally, when
it was nearly dark, they came within sight of Pole Creek,
immediately recognized the locality, and were saved.</p>

<p>At night, after travelling all the next day, they reached
a ranch about thirty-five miles west of Julesburg, where
they stopped and were made comfortable. It was 
discovered, after the command had thawed out, that out of
thirty-six men thirty were more or less frozen; some had
frozen noses, some their ears, some their toes, and two
had suffered so badly their feet had to be amputated. On
the following day an ambulance arrived from Julesburg,
to bring in the men who were in the worst condition.
Those who were able mounted their horses and reached
the post all right.</p>

<p>During those early years, before the growth of the
great states beyond the Missouri, a mighty stream of 
immigration rushed onward to the unknown, illimitable
West. Its pathway was strewn with innumerable graves
of men, women, and little children. Silence and oblivion 
have long since closed over them forever, and no one can
tell the sad story of their end, or even where they lay
down. Occasionally, however, the traveller comes across
a spot where some of these brave pioneers succumbed to
death. One of the most noted of these may be seen
about two miles from the town of Gering, on the Old

<pb n="162" xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.190"/>

Trail, in what is now known as Scott's Bluffs County,
Nebraska. Around the lonely grave was fixed a wagon-
tire, and on it rudely scratched the name of the occupant
of the isolated sepulchre, "Rebecca Winter," and the 
date, 1852. The tire remains as it was originally placed,
and, as if to immortalize the sad fate of the woman, many
localities in the vicinity derive their names from that on
the rusty old wagon tire: "Winter Springs," "Winter
Creek Precinct," and the "Winter Creek Irrigation
Company"!</p>

<figure xml:id="mmm.wa.inmancody.1898.190.figure">
<p>Julesberg 1865</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>
-->
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
