<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902">
    <teiHeader>
	 <fileDesc>
	    <titleStmt>
		 <title level="m" type="main">Special Report of the Mountain Meadow Massacre</title>
		 <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
	         <author><forename>James</forename> <forename type="middle">Henry</forename> <surname>Carleton</surname></author>
                 <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
             </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
		              <idno>mmm.doc.carleton.1902</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

	<notesStmt>
	    <note type="summary"></note>
	</notesStmt>

	<sourceDesc>
	    <bibl>
	        <title level="m">Special Report of the Mountain Meadow Massacre</title>
	     <title level="s">US House. 57th Cong., 1st sess. House Doc. 605, Serial 4377</title>
	        <author><forename>James</forename> <forename type="middle">Henry</forename> <surname>Carleton</surname></author>
		       <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
		       <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
	        <extent></extent>
		       <date when="1859">May 25, 1859</date>
	     <note type="source">James Henry Carleton. <hi rend="italic">Special report of the Mountain Meadow Massacre, by J. H. Carleton, Brevet Major, United States Army, Captain, First Dragoons</hi>. US House. 57th Cong., 1st sess. Washington, DC: GPO, 1902. House Doc. 605, Serial 4377.</note>
	    </bibl>
	</sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

     <profileDesc>
	<textClass>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
	     <term>government_document</term>
	     </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
		<term></term>
	    </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="action">
		<term></term>
	    </keywords>
	</textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
     	<change when="2011-08-18"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enhancement</change>
     	<change when="2011-05-31"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept Highlighting</change>
     	<change when="2009-10-27"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Encoding enhancement, validation</change>
     	<change when="2009-10-21"><name>Kelsey F. Harris</name> Initial Encoding</change>
     </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body>

<pb n="1" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.001"/>

<div1 type="doc">
<head type="main">MOUNTAIN MEADOW MASSACRE.</head>
 <milestone unit="section" rend="horbar"/>

<div2>
<opener>
<dateline>
Congress of the United States,<lb/>
In the House of Representatives,<lb/>
<date when="1902-05-10"><hi rend="italic">May 10, 1902</hi></date>
</dateline>
</opener>

<p><hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That there be printed as a House document 5,000 copies of the Special Report of the Mountain Meadow Massacre, as compiled by <persName key="Carleton, James Henry">J. H. Carleton</persName>, brevet major, United States Army, captain, First Dragoons.</p>

<closer>
<salute>Attest:</salute><lb/>
<signed><hi rend="right">A. McDowell,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Clerk.</hi></hi>
</signed>
</closer>
</div2>

<milestone unit="section" rend="horbar"/>

<div2>
<head>SPECIAL REPORT OF THE MOUNTAIN MEADOW MASSACRE, BY <persName key="Carleton, James Henry">J. H. CARLETON</persName>, BREVET MAJOR, UNITED STATES ARMY, CAPTAIN, FIRST DRAGOONS.</head>

<milestone unit="section" rend="horbar"/>

<opener>
<dateline>
Camp at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic"><placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah Territory</placeName>, <date when="1859-05-25">May 25, 1859</date>.</hi>
</dateline>
</opener>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">M<hi rend="smallcaps">AJOR</hi>: <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">When I left <placeName type="settlement" key="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</placeName>, the 23d ultimo, General <persName key="Clarke, Newman S.">Clark</persName>, commanding the Department of <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, directed me to bury the bones of the victims of that terrible massacre which took place on the ground <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in September 1857</seg>.</seg> The fact of this massacre of (in my opinion) <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">at least 120 men, women and children</seg>, who were on their way <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">from the <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">State of <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg> to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>, has long been well known.</seg> I have endeavored to learn the circumstances attending it, and have the honor to submit the following as the result of my inquiries on this point:</p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Government">Dr. <persName key="Brewer, Charles">Brewer</persName>, United States Army, whom I met with Captain <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Campbell</persName>'s command on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara River</geogName> on the 15th instant, informed me that as he was going up the <geogName type="waterway" key="Platte River">Platte River</geogName> on the 11th of June 1857, he passed a train of emigrants near O'Fallons Bluffs. The train was called "Perkin's train," a man named <persName key="Perkins, George">Perkins</persName>, who had previously been to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, having charge of it as conductor; that he afterwards saw the train frequently; the last time he saw it was at Ash Hollow, on the North Fork of the <geogName type="waterway" key="Platte River">Platte</geogName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain"><persName key="Brewer, Charles">The Doctor</persName> says the train consisted of, say, 40 wagons. There were a few tents besides, which the emigrants used in addition to these wagons when they encamped. There seemed to be about 40 heads of families, many women, some unmarried, and many children. A doctor accompanied them. The train seemed to consist of respectable people, well to do in the world. They were well dressed, were quiet, orderly, genteel; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">had fine stock</seg>; had three carriages long, and other evidences which went to show that this was one of the finest trains that had been seen to cross the plains.</seg> It was so remarked upon by the officers who were with the doctor at that time. From reports afterwards received, and comparing the dates with the probable rate of travel, he believed this was the identical train which was destroyed <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>.</p>

<pb n="2" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.002"/>

<p>I could get no information of these emigrants of a date anterior to this. Here seems to be given the first glimpse of their number, character, and condition; and an authentic glimpse, too, if the train destroyed was the one seen by the doctor, of which there can hardly be a doubt. The doctor was confirmed in his belief that the train he saw was the one destroyed, by many reasons. Among them one fact seemed to be very convincing. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">He observed a carriage in the train in which some ladies rode, to whom he made one or more visits as they journeyed along. There was something peculiar in the construction of the carriage and its ornaments&#8212;its blazoned stag's head upon the panels, etc. This carriage, he says, is now in the possession of the Mormons</seg>. Besides, he afterwards heard as a fact that this train had been entirely destroyed.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The people who owned it would not have been likely to sell such an important part of their means of transportation midway their journey.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">The road upon which these emigrants were seen by Dr. <persName key="Brewer, Charles">Brewer</persName> crosses the <geogName type="mountain" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</geogName> through the South Pass, and thence goes on down into the Great Basin to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>; and thence southward along the western base of the <geogName type="mountain" key="Wahsatch Mountains">Wahsatch Mountains</geogName> to what is called the rim of the basin. Here the "divide" is crossed, when it descends upon the valley of the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara">Santa Clara</geogName> affluent toward <geogName type="waterway" key="Colorado River">the Colorado</geogName>. <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore City, UT">Fillmore City</placeName> is upon one of the many streams which run westward down from the <geogName type="mountain" key="Wahsatch Mountains">Wahsatch Mountains</geogName> into the basin. It is about 140 miles from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City">Salt Lake City</placeName>; then upon another stream, 90 miles farther south is <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan City</placeName>; then upon still another stream, 18 miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, is <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>; then to a settlement on <geogName type="waterway" key="Pinto Creek">Pinto Creek</geogName> is 24 [miles] thence to <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house, on the northern slope of the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, 6 miles.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">From <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house over the rim of the basin to the southern point of the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, where there is a large spring, is 4 miles 1,000 yards. This swell of land or watershed, called the rim of the basin, runs west across nearly midway <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the valley called the Mountain Meadows</geogName>. This valley runs north and south; its northern portion is drained toward the basin, its southern toward the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara</geogName>. Down on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara</geogName> is a Mormon settlement called "The Fort." Here some 30 families reside. It is 34 miles from <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, East of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, say 18 miles, on the east slope of the <geogName type="mountain" key="Wahsatch Range">Wahsatch Range</geogName>, drained by <geogName type="waterway" key="Virgin River">Virgin River</geogName>, is the town of <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, of 100 families; and farther down the <geogName type="waterway" key="Virgin River">Virgin River</geogName>, 12 miles from "The Fort," on the Santa Clara is <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington City, UT">Washington City</placeName>, also of 100 families. The Santa Clara joins the Virgin River near <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington City, UT">Washington City</placeName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p>The Pah Vent Indians live near <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore City, UT">Fillmore City</placeName>. The Pah Ute Indians are scattered along from <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> southward to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Colorado River">Colorado</geogName>.</p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hamblin">The train of emigrants proceeding southward from <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore City, UT">Fillmore City</placeName> toward the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName> are next seen, so far as my inquiries go, by a Mr. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>, a leading Mormon, who has charge of "The Fort," on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara">Santa Clara</geogName>, and resides there in the winter season, but who has a cattle ranch and a house, where he lives in the summer time, at the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. I here give what he said, and which I wrote down, sentence by sentence, as he related it. He told me he had given the same information to Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>.</seg></p>

<floatingText>
<body>
<p>About the middle of August, 1857, I started on a visit to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>. At <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>, 8 miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore City</placeName>, I encamped with <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">a train of emigrants who said they were mostly from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">There were, in my opinion, not over 30

<pb n="3" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.003"/> 

wagons. There were several tents, and they had from 400 to 500 head of horned cattle, 25 head of horses, and some mules.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Unattributed"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">This information I got in conversation with one of the men of the train.</seg> The people seemed to be ordinary frontier "homespun" people, as a general thing. Some of the outsiders were rude and rough and calculated to get the ill will of the inhabitants. Several of the men asked me about the condition of the road and the disposition of the Indians, and where there would be a good place to recruit their stock.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">I asked them how many men they had. They said they had between forty and fifty "that would do to tie to."</seg> I told them I considered if they would keep a good lookout that the Indians did not steal their animals half the number would be safe, and that the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName> was the best place where they should stop. The most of these men seemed to have families with them. They remarked that this one train was made up near <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> of several trains that had crossed the plains separately, and, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">being Southern people, had preferred to take the southern route</seg>. This was all of importance that passed between us, and I went on my journey and they proceeded on theirs. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">On my way back home, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore City</placeName>, <seg type="Source" subtype="WordofMouth">I heard it said</seg> that that company&#8212;meaning the train referred to&#8212;had poisoned a small spring at Corn Creek where I had met them.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">There was some considerable excitement about it among the citizens of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName> and among the Pah-Vent Indians who live within 8 miles of that place. I was told that eighteen head of cattle had died from drinking the water; that six of the Pah-Vents had been poisoned from eating the flesh of the cattle that died, and that one or two of these Indians had also died. Mr. <persName key="Robinson, ">Robinson</persName>, a citizen of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, whose son was buried the day I got there, said that the boy had been poisoned in "trying out" the tallow of the dead cattle. I am satisfied that he believed what he said about it. I thought at the time that the spring had been poisoned as stated.</seg><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">I encamped that night with a company from <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName>, who told me that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">a company from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg> had all been killed off <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">except seventeen children</seg>.</seg></p>

<p>I afterwards met, between <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> and <placeName type="settlement" key="Pine Creek, UT">Pine Creek</placeName>, Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H."><choice><sic>Daim</sic><corr>Dame</corr></choice></persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, who confirmed what these people from <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName> had said. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">He further stated that the Indians were collecting on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> with a determination to "wipe out" another company of emigrants which was several days in rear of the first. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">He mentioned that the Indians had supplied themselves with the arms and ammunition from <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the train destroyed</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName></seg>.</seg></seg></seg> After consulting with him he advised me to go forward and spare no pains in trying to prevent their carrying their purpose into execution, and he gave me an order to press into service any animal I might require for that purpose. I got a horse at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> about 8 o'clock that evening, and the next evening at <geogName type="waterway" key="Pinto Creek">Pinto Creek</geogName>, 83 miles distant, I met Mr. <persName key="Leavett, Dudley">Dudley Leavett</persName>, from the settlements on the Santa Clara.</p>

<p>I told him what I had heard. He told me it was true, and that all the Indians in the southern country were greatly excited and "all hell" could not stop them from killing or from at least robbing the other train of its stock. He further stated that several interpreters from the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara</geogName> had gone on with this last train. I told him to return and get the best animal he could find at my ranch and go on as fast as he could and endeavor to stop further mischief being done. That if the Indians ran off the stock of the train, for himself and all the interpreters to go and recover it, if possible, and prevent further depredations. He left me under these instructions.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">The next morning, which, I think, was the 18th of September</seg>, 1857, I arrived at my ranch, 4 miles from <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>. Here I had left my family. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">I found at the ranch <persName key="Dunlap, Rebecca "><persName key="Dunlap, Sarah "><persName key="Dunlap, Louisa">three little white girls</persName></persName></persName> in the care of <persName key="Hamblin, Sarah Priscilla Leavitt">my wife</persName>, the oldest six or seven years of age, the next about three, and the next about one The youngest had been shot through one of her arms below the elbow by a large ball, breaking both bones and cutting the arm half off. My wife having a young child of her own and these three little orphans besides, my home appeared to be anything but cheerful.</seg> About 1 or 2 o'clock that day I came down to <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">the point where the massacre had taken place</seg>, in the company with an Indian boy named <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert</persName>, who had been brought up in my family.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><persName key="Hamblin, Albert">The boy</persName> told me that the inhabitants from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> had come down and buried the murdered people in three large heaps, which he pointed out to me; the boy showed me <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">two girls</seg> who had run some ways off before they were killed. The wolves had dug open the heaps, dragged out the bodies, and were then tearing the flesh from them. I counted nineteen wolves at one of these places. I have since leaned from the people who assisted in burying the bodies that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">there were 107 men, women, and children found dead upon the ground. I am satisfied that all were not found.</seg> The most of the bodies were stripped of all their clothing, were then in 

<pb n="4" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.004"/>

a state putrefaction, and presented a horrible sight. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">There was no property left upon the ground except one white ox, which is still at my ranch</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">The following summer, when the bones had lost all their flesh, I reburied them, assisted by a Mr. <persName key="Fuller, ">Fuller</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">The Indians have often told me that they made an attack on the emigrants between daylight and sunrise as the men were standing around the camp fires, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">killing and wounding 15 at first discharge</seg>, which was delivered from the ravine near the spring close to the wagons and from a hill to the west. That the emigrants immediately corralled their wagon and threw up an intrenchment to shelter themselves from the balls. When I first saw the ditch it was about 4 feet deep and the back about 2 feet high. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The Indians say they then run off the stock</seg> but kept parties at the spring to prevent the emigrants from getting to the water, the emigrants firing upon them every time they showed themselves, and they returning the fire. This was kept up for six or seven days. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The Indians say that they lost but one man killed and three or four wounded.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">At the end of six or seven days</seg>, they say a man among them who could talk English called to the emigrants and told them if they would go back to the settlements and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">leave all their property, especially their arms</seg>, they would spare their lives, but if they did not do so they would kill the whole of them. The emigrants agreed to this and started back on the road toward my ranch. About a mile from the spring there are some scrub-oak bushes and tall sage growing of each side of the road and close to it. Here a large body of Indians lay in ambush, who, when the emigrants approached, fell upon them in their defenseless condition and with bows and arrows and stones and guns and knives <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">murdered all, without regard to sex or age</seg>, except <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">a few infant children, seventeen of which have since been recovered</seg></seg>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Indians"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">This is what the Indians told me nine days after the massacre took place. From the position of the bodies this latter part of their story seems to be corroborated</seg>, and I should judge that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the women and children were in advance of the men when the last attack upon them was made</seg>. When I buried the bones last summer, I observed that about one-third of the skulls were shot through with bullets and about one-third seemed to be broken with stones.</seg></p>

<p>The train I sent <persName key="Leavett, Dudley">Leavett</persName> to protect had gotten as far as the canyon, 5 miles beyond the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, when the Indians made a descent upon its loose stock, driving off, as the immigrants have since said, 280 head of cattle. <persName key="Leavett, Dudley">Leavett</persName> and the other interpreters recovered between 75 and 100 head, which were brought back to my ranch. Of these the Indians afterwards demanded and stole some 40 head, and last January I turned over to a Mr. <persName key="Lane, ">Lane</persName> from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> the balance.</p> 

<p>These are all the facts within my knowledge connected with the destruction of one and the passing along of the other of those two trains.</p>
</body>
</floatingText>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hamblin">This <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName> seems to be a man of considerable importance, and noted among the Mormons in this southern part of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. He is about 50 years of age, and although with but little education, is a shrewd, intelligent, thinking man. Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, I heard, was of the opinion <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> was acting in good faith, and gave what he really believed was a true account of the massacre and of <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">the Mormon part taken in it</seg>. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> has two wives, one about 40 or 50 years of age, a sister of a Mormon named <persName key="Judd, Hiram">Hiram Judd</persName>, who lives at <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house at the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, and another wife of about 18, a sister of the <persName key="Leavett, Dudley">Dudley Leavett</persName> of whom he speaks.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hamblin"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> is, and has for a long time been Indian subagent for the Pah-Utes. He speaks their language well and has great influence with them.</seg> He told me the church had granted him a piece of land 10 miles square, which covers the whole of the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>&#8212;the best grazing tract in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah Territory</placeName>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">It is quite a significant fact that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">this ranch whereon the massacre took place</seg> is well stocked with cattle, among which the white ox is acknowledged to be.</seg></seg> Mr. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> and his story will be further considered upon at another place in this report. His eldest wife came to my camp and stayed there with her husband the night of the 19th instant. The next morning I wrote down, word by word as she related it, her account of the massacre. Her husband took good care to be present at the time, and also took very good care 

<pb n="5" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.005"/>

to give her occasional promptings, although it has been perceived he was at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> when the facts she related occurred. Her story was as follows:</seg></p>

<floatingText>

<body>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hamblin"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">I was residing 4 miles north of this spring at the ranch <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in the fall of 1857. Early in September of that year, about the 1st</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">a large train of wagons&#8212;I could not tell exactly how many; think about 50</seg>&#8212;passed by our house. None of the people stopped. There may have been a man who came and inquired the way to the spring; it was about noon. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">The next morning a man came back from the train to the house to see if I could sell him some butter and cheese. I had none</seg> and he stayed but a short time, saying his people had camped at the spring, where they would stay a while to recruit their stock. I heard no more about the people of the train until <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Monday morning before daylight</seg>, when <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">I heard a great number of guns firing at this spring. This firing was kept up until evening, after dusk, when the firing again began, but not so rapidly as before.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hamblin"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">This lasted, say, fifteen minutes, and I think there were some shots fired during the night. Sometimes I could not hear them so plainly as at others, owing to the changing winds.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">After the firing of the first morning, some white men came to our house and said that the Indians had attacked the train because <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">the emigrants</seg> had poisoned a spring near <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName></seg>. There was but one man about our house. He name was <persName key="Tullis, David">David Tullis</persName>. He is an Englishman and now lives at "The Fort" on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara">Santa Clara</geogName>. There was an Indian boy, <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert</persName>. <persName key="Tullis, David">Tullis</persName> was herding the cattle and <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert</persName> the sheep. The white men who stopped at our house and told us about the excitement among the Indians said they had been here at the spring and tried to stop the fighting, but that the Indians had become enraged and were determined to kill the emigrants</seg>; that they were gathering for this purpose from all quarters.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hamblin"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Indians were frequently passing and repassing our house. They said I need not be afraid; they were friendly to me and would not hurt me, but that they would kill the emigrants.</seg> This firing and people passing to and fro continued about a week. Several people from <placeName type="state" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName> and other places gathered about and said they were trying to stop it. I noticed among them <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>. He was at my house two or three times during the week. At length, between sundown and dark of the last day, I heard a fire greater than before and toward our house. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">In about an hour a wagon drove up to our house having seventeen children in it, the most of them crying. <persName key="Dunlap, Sarah">One, a girl about a year old, had been short through the arm</persName>, and another girl, about 4 years old, had been wounded in the ear; their clothes were bloody. The wagon was driven up to the door by a man named <persName key="Shurtz, Carl">Shurtz or Shirts</persName>, a son-in-law of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Hamblin"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> seemed to have the distributing of the children. <persName key="Dunlap, Sarah">The little girl who was shot through the arm</persName> could not be moved. She had two sisters, <persName key="Dunlap, Rebecca">Rebecca</persName> and <persName key="Dunlap, Louisa">Louisa</persName>, one 7 and the other 5, who seemed to be greatly attached to her. I persuaded <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> not to separate them, but to let me have all three of them. This he finally agreed to and the children stayed with me and I nursed <persName key="Dunlap, Sarah">the wounded child</persName> until it recovered, though it has lost forever the use of its arm. The next day after the last massacre <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and the rest started up the road with all the rest of the children in a wagon, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Indians scattered off</seg></seg>. This is all I know personally on the subject</seg>.</p>

</body>

</floatingText>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Mrs. <persName key="Hamblin, Sarah Priscilla Leavitt">Hamblin</persName> is a simple-minded person of about 45, and evidently looks with the eyes of <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">her husband</persName> at everything. She may really have been taught by the Mormons to believe it is no great sin to kill Gentiles and enjoy their property. Of the shooting of the emigrants, which she had herself heard, and knew at the time what was going on, she seemed to speak without a shudder, or any very great feeling</seg>; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">but when she told of the 17 orphan children who were brought by such a crowd to her own house of one small room there in the darkness of night, two of the children cruelly mangled and the most of them with their parents' blood still wet upon their clothes, and all of them shrieking with terror and grief and anguish, her own mother heart was touched. She at least deserves kind consideration for her care and nourishment of <persName key="Dunlap, Sarah"><persName key="Dunlap, Rebecca"><persName key="Dunlap, Louisa">the three sisters</persName></persName></persName>, and for all she did <persName key="Dunlap, Sarah">for the little girl "about 1 year old who had been shot through one of her arms,</persName> below</seg>

<pb n="6" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.006"/>

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">the elbow, by a large ball, breaking both bones and cutting the arm half off."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Indians">A Snake Indian boy called <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert Hamblin</persName>, but whose Indian name was a word which meant "hungry," who is now about 17 or 18 years of age, says that Mr. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName> bought him beyond where <orgName type="military" key="Camp Floyd">Camp Floyd</orgName> is located, and that he has lived with Mr. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> about six years here and about three years up north. He was sent by Mr. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> to my camp, at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, on the 20th day of May, 1859, and in speaking of the massacre <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at this place</seg> related what follows in very good English:</seg></p>

<floatingText>

<body>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">In the first part of September, a year and a half ago</seg>, I was at Mr. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s ranch, 4 miles from here. My business was to herd sheep. I saw a train come along the road and pass down this way. It was near sundown. I drove the sheep home and went after wood, when I saw the train encamp at this spring from a high point of land where I was cutting wood.</p>

<p><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">When the train passed me I saw <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a good many women and children</seg>.</seg> It was night when I got home. Another Indian boy named <persName key="John">John</persName>, who lives at the Vegas and talked some English, was with me. He lived with a man named <persName key="Knight, Sam">Sam Knight</persName>, at Santa Clara. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">After the train had been camped at this spring three nights, the fourth day in the morning, just before light, when we were all abed at the house, I was waked up by hearing a good many guns fired.</seg> I could hear guns fired every little while all day until it was dark. Then I did not know what had been done. During the day, as we&#8212;<persName key="John">John</persName> and <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">I</persName>&#8212;sat on a hill herding sheep, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">we saw the Indians driving off all the stock and shot some of the cattle</seg>; at the same time <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">we could see shooting going on down around the train; emigrants shooting at the Indians from the corral of wagons and Indians shooting at them from the tops of hills all around. In this way they fought on for about a week.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">I asked an Indian what he was killing those people for. He was mad, and told me unless I kept "my mouth shut" he would kill me. Three men came down from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> to our house while the fighting was going on. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">They said they came after cattle.</seg></seg> Other men passed to and fro from Santa Clara to our house during the nights. The three men from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> stayed about the house a while "pitching horseshoe quoits" while the fighting was on, when they afterwards went back to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. <persName key="Leavett, Dudley">Dudley Leavett</persName> came up from Santa Clara in the night while the emigrants were camped here; but he did not see them. He went on to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> to buy flour. When he got to the house we told him the emigrants were fighting here. One afternoon, near night, after they had fought nearly a week, <persName key="John">John</persName> and <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">I</persName> saw the women and children and some men leave the wagons and go up the road toward our house. There were no Indians with them.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><persName key="John">John</persName> and <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">I</persName> could see where the Indians were hid in the oak bushes and sage right by the side of the road a mile or more on their route; and I said to <persName key="John">John</persName>, <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">I</persName> would like to know what the emigrants left their wagons for, as they going into "a worse fix than ever they saw." The women were on ahead with the children. The men were behind. Altogether 'twas a big crowd. Soon as they got to the place where the Indians were hid in the bushes each side of the road the Indians pitched right out onto them and commenced shooting them with guns and bows and arrows, and cut some of the men's throats with knives. The men run in every direction, the Indians after them, and yelling whooping. Soon as the women and children saw the Indians spring out of the bushes they all cried out so loud <persName key="John">John</persName> and <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">I</persName> heard them.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">The women scattered and tried to hide in the bushes, but the Indians shot them down; two girls ran up the slope toward the east about a quarter of a mile; <persName key="John">John</persName> and <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">I</persName> ran down and tried to save them; the girls hid in some bushes. A man, who is an Indian doctor, also told the Indians to kill them. The girls then came out and hung around him for protection, he trying to keep the Indians away. The girls were crying out loud. The Indians came up and seized the girls by their hands and their dresses and pulled and pushed them away from the doctor and then shot them.</seg> By this time it was dark, and the other Indians down by the road had got nearly through killing all the others. They were about half an hour killing the people from the time they first sprang out upon them from the bushes.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Some time in the night <persName key="Tullis, David">Tullis</persName> and the Indians brought some of the children in a wagon up to the house. The children cried nearly all night. <persName key="Dunlap, Sarah">One little one, a baby, just commencing to walk around, was shot through the arm.</persName> One of the girls had been hit through the ear. Many of the children's clothes were bloody. The next

<pb n="7" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.007"/>

morning we kept three children and the rest were taken to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName></seg>; also <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">the next morning the train of wagons went up to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> with all the goods. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Indians</seg> got all the flour. Some of it I saw buried this side of <geogName type="waterway" key="Pinto Creek">Pinto Creek</geogName>. There were two yoke of cattle to each wagon as they passed up. The rest of the stock had been killed, to be eaten by <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Indians</seg>, while the fight was going on, except some which were driven over the mountains this way and that</seg>.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">The Indians stripped naked the dead bodies; that is, all the men; some of the women had their underclothes left. There were a good many men who came over from <geogName type="waterway" key="Pinto Creek">Pinto Creek</geogName> "and about" and stayed around the house while the fight went on. I saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> there about the house during that time&#8212;he lives in <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>&#8212;and <persName key="Robinson, Richard">Richard Robinson</persName>, <persName key="Coleman, Prime">Prime Coleman</persName>, <persName key="Thornton, Amos">Amos Thornton</persName>, Brother <persName key="Dickinson, ">Dickinson</persName>, who all live at Pinto Creek. <persName key="Thornton, Amos">Thronton</persName> I saw at the house. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">When father (<persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>) came back, I came down with him onto the ground. The bodies were all buried then, so we could not see any. There were plenty of wolves around. The two girls had been buried also, and I did show them to father. The Indians buried the bodies taking spades from the wagons. The people from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> came down three days after the massacre, but the Indians had buried all the bodes before they came.</seg> This is all I know about it.</seg></p>

</body>

</floatingText>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">This <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert Hamblin</persName> is nearly a grown man in point of size, and from appearance and bearing has evidently had engrafted upon his native viciousness all the bad traits of the community in which he lives. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Two of the children</seg> are said to have pointed him out to Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> as an Indian whom they saw kill <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">their two sisters</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">His story is artfully made up; evidently part truth and part falsehood. <persName key="Leavitt, Dudley">Leavitt</persName> could not have passed up from "the fort" to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> without knowing where the emigrants were besieged, as the road runs near the spring where their corral was, and between it and some hills occupied by the Mormons and Indians. That <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert</persName> staid upon a neighborhood hill "herding sheep" day after day while the fight lasted, and then went up to the house of nights to go to sleep, can not be true. That Mormons were passing and repassing upon the road, day and night, and did not know what was going on is simply absurd to one conversant with the surroundings of the place. In this Indian's statement that some of the Mormons at the house were "pitching horseshoe quoits," a glance is given at the fiendish levity with which the murdering, day by day, of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">this artfully entrapped party of gentile men, women, and children</seg> was regarded. This pitching of "horseshoe quoits" was during the time when dropping shots from the Indians and the other Mormons concealed around the springs and behind the crest of hills kept back <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the perishing emigrants</seg> from water. There was time enough for some to go up to <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house for refreshments. No danger of the emigrants getting away. It was all safe in that quarter. "There is time enough for us to have a quiet game of quoits. The other boys will take care of matters down there."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The general will hardly fail to observe the discrepancy between <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s statement and that of <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert</persName> in relation to the burial of the two girls and in relation to the burial of the bodies of the others who had been murdered. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> says the people from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> buried them; <persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert</persName> that the Indians did it, taking spades from the wagons, not a likely thing for bona fide Indians to do.</seg></seg></seg> My own opinion is that the remains were not buried at all until after they had been dismembered by the wolves and the flesh stripped from the bones, and then only such bones were buried as lay scattered along nearest the road.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><persName key="Hamblin, Albert">Albert</persName> had evidently been trained in his statement. He gave much of it after cross-questioning, keeping always the Mormons in the background and the Indians conspicuously the prominent figures and actors,

<pb n="8" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.008"/>

as <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> and <persName key="Hamblin, Sarah Priscilla Leavitt">his wife</persName> had endeavored to do. It was not until I told him that <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> and <persName key="Hamblin, Sarah Priscilla Leavitt">his wife</persName> had informed me that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> and other Mormons were there and had asked him how it was possible he had not seen them, that he recollected about "Brother" <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and "Brothers" <persName key="Coleman, Prime">Prime Coleman</persName>, <persName key="Thornton, Amos">Amos Thornton</persName>, <persName key="Robinson, Richard">Richard Robinson</persName>, and "Brother" <persName key="Dickinson, ">Dickinson</persName> from <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto Creek, UT">Pinto Creek</placeName>. He too had fallen into the general custom of the people and called every man <q>"brother."</q></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">I questioned other Mormons in relation to the massacre, but many of them said they had moved from he northern part of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> since it took place; others, that they were harvesting at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, and at "the Fort," and knew nothing of it until it was all over. Even "Brother" <persName key="Coleman, Prime">Prime Coleman</persName> told me he was harvesting near <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> just before that time with Brother <persName key="Nell, Benjamin">Benjamin Nell</persName>, but when the massacre took place he was down on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy River</geogName> with Brother <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Ira Hatch</persName> to keep down disturbances there among the Indians. (The <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> is 163 miles from <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, on the road to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>; he had to pass <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName> to get there.) He said that as he and <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> were coming back they saw in the sand the tracks of three men who wore fine boots. This was at the Beaver Dams (between <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName> and the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> and 50 miles from <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>).</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">He and <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> were frightened at this sign, were afraid of robbers, and did not stop, even for water, until they reached the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara</geogName>, 20 miles off. At <geogName type="valley" key="Pine Valley">Pine Valley</geogName>, near <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, they first heard of the massacre. There is no doubt but that all three of these men were active participants in the butchering <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName></seg>. The foregoing is the Mormon story of the massacre. As it took place on <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s ranch and within the hearing of his family, it was impossible for them to be <q>"out harvesting"</q> or <q>"up north"</q> or <q>"down on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>."</q> He himself had gone to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. At least, he says so; but even this, I think, needs proof. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Some account had to be made up, and the one most likely to be believed was that the whole matter had been started by the Indians and carried out by them, because the emigrants had poisoned a spring near <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore City</placeName>. Mr. <persName key="Rodgers, William">Rodgers</persName>, United States deputy marshal, who accompanied Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> in his tour to the south, told me the water of the spring referred to runs with such volume and force <q>"a barrel of arsenic would not poison it."</q></seg></seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">When <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Mormons say the Indians were the murderers</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">they speak with no sympathy of the sufferers, but rather in extenuation of the crime by saying the emigrants were not fit to live; that <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">besides poisoning the spring</seg> <q>"they were impudent to the people on the road; robbed their henroosts and gardens, and <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">were insulting to the church</seg>; called their oxen '<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>,' '<persName key="Kimball, Heber">Heber Kimball</persName>,' etc., and altogether were a rough ugly set that ought to have been killed anyway."</q></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">But there is another side to this story. It is said that some two years since Bishop <persName key="Pratt, Parley P."><choice><sic>Pearley</sic><corr>Parley</corr></choice> Pratt</persName> was shot in the Cherokee Nation near <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> by the <persName key="McLean, Hector">husband</persName> of <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">a woman</persName> who had run off with that saintly prelate. The Mormons swore vengeance on the people of <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, one of whom was this injured husband. The wife came on to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> after the bishop was killed and still lives there.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">About this time; also, the Mormon troubles with the United States commenced, and the most bitter hostility against the Gentiles became rife throughout <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> among all the Latter-Day Saints. It will be recollected that even while <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">these emigrants were pursuing their <choice><orig>jour-

<pb n="9" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.009"/>

ney</orig><reg>journey</reg></choice> overland to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg> Colonel <persName key="Alexander, Edmund Brooke">Alexander</persName> was following upon their trace with two or more regiments of troops ordered to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> to assist, if necessary, in seeing the laws of the land properly enforced in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">that Territory</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSGreed"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">This train was undoubtedly a very rich one. It is said the emigrants had nearly nine hundred head of fine cattle, many horses and mules and one stallion valued at $2,000; that they had a great deal of ready money besides.</seg> All this the Mormons in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> saw as the train came on.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The Mormons knew the troops were marching to their country, and a spirit of intense hatred of the Americans and toward our Government was kindled in the hearts of this whole people by <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, <persName key="Hyde, Orson">Orson Hyde</persName>, and other leaders, even from the pulpits</seg>.</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Here, opportunely, was a rich train of emigrants&#8212;American Gentiles&#8212;that is, the most obnoxious kind of Gentiles&#8212;and not only that, but <seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">these Gentiles were <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, where the saintly <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> had gained his crown of martyrdom.</seg> Is not here some thread which may be seized as a clew to this mystery so long hidden as to whether or not the Mormons were accomplices in the massacre? <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">This train of <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> Gentiles</seg> was doomed from the day it crossed through the South Pass and had gotten fairly down into the meshes of the Mormon spider net, from which it was never to become disentangled.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> informed me that about this time <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, preaching in the tabernacle and speaking of the trouble with the United States, said that up to that moment he had protected emigrants who had passed through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, but <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">now he would turn the Indians loose upon them</seg>.</seg> It is a singular point worthy of note that this sermon should have been preached just as the rich train had gotten into the valley and was now fairly entrapped; a sermon good, coming from him, as a letter of marque to these land pirates who listened to him as to an oracle. The hint thus shrewdly given was not long in being acted upon.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">From that moment these emigrants, as <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">they journeyed southward</seg> were considered the authorized, if not legal prey of the inhabitants. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">All kinds of depredations and extortions were practiced upon them. At <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> they took some wheat to the mill to be ground. The miller went to ask the bishop if he might grind this grain for the damned Gentiles. The bishop replied, <q>"Yes, but do you take double toll."</q> This shows the spirit with which they were treated.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSApostates">These things are now leaking out; some of those who were then Mormons have renounced their creed, and through them is learned which taken in connections with the facts that are known, serves to develop the truth.</seg> It is said to be a truth that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> sent letters south, authorizing, if not commanding, that the train should be destroyed.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">A Pah-Ute chief, of the Santa Clara band named "<persName key="Jackson">Jackson</persName>," who was one of the attacking party, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">had a brother slain by the emigrants from their corral by the spring</seg>, says that <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">orders came down in a letter from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName></seg> to the same effect was brought down to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Virgin River">Virgin River</geogName> band by a man named <persName key="Huntingdon, ">Huntingdon</persName>, who I learn, is a Indian interpreter and lives at present at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><persName key="Jackson">Jackson</persName> says there were 60 Mormons led by Bishop <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>,

<pb n="10" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.010"/>

of <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, and a prominent man in the church named <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, who lives at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. That they were all painted and disguised as Indians. That this painting and disguising was done at a spring in a canyon about a mile northeast of the spring where the emigrants were encamped, and that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> led and directed the combined force of Mormons and Indians in the first attack, throughout the siege, and at the last massacre.</seg> The Santa Clara Indians say that the emigrants could not get to the water, as the besiegers lay around the spring ready to shoot anyone who approached it. This could easily have been done. Major <persName key="Prince, Henry">Henry Prince</persName>, paymaster, U.S.A., and Lieutenant <persName key="Ogle, Charles H.">Ogle</persName>, First Dragoons, on the 17th instant, stood at the ditch which was in the corral and placed some men at the spring 28 yards distant, and they could just see the men's heads, both parties standing erect. This shows how vital a point the assailants occupied; how close it was to the assailed, and how well protected it was from a fire coming from the direction of the corral.</seg></p>

<p>The following account of the affair is, I think, susceptible to legal proof by those whose names are known, and who, I am assured, are willing to make oath to many of the facts which serve as links in the chain of evidence leading toward the truth of this grave question: By whom were these <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">120 men, women and children</seg> murdered?</p>

<floatingText>

<body>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">It was currently reported among the Mormons at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, in talking among themselves, before the troops ever came down south (when all felt secure of arrest or prosecution), and nobody seemed to question the truth of it&#8212;that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a train of emigrants of fifty or upward of men&#8212;mostly with families</seg></seg>&#8212;came and encamped <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at this spring at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in September, 1857</seg>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">It was reported in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and was not, and is not doubted&#8212;even by the Mormons&#8212;that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higby</persName> (the first resides in <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, the last two at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>), were the leaders who organized a party of fifty or sixty Mormons to attack this train.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">They had also all the Indians which they could collect at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, and <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington City, UT">Washington City</placeName> to help them, a good many in number. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">This party then came down, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">at first the Indians were ordered to stampede the cattle and drive them away from the train</seg>. They then commenced firing on the emigrants; this firing was returned by the emigrants; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one Indian was killed, a brother of the chief of the Santa Clara Indians, another shot through the leg, who is now a cripple at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. There were without doubt a great many more killed and wounded.</seg> It was said the Mormons were painted and disguised as Indians. The Mormons say the emigrants fought <q>"like lions"</q> and that they saw they could not whip them by any fair fighting.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">After some days fighting the Mormons had a council among themselves to arrange a plan to destroy the emigrants. They concluded, finally, that they would send few down and pretend to be friends and try and get the emigrants to surrender. <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> and three or four others, headmen, from <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington City, UT">Washington</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar</placeName>, and <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> (<persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higby</persName> from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>), had their paint washed off and, dressing in their usual dress, took their wagons and drove down toward the emigrant's corral as if they were just traveling on the road on their ordinary business. The emigrants sent out a little girl toward them. She was dressed in white and had a white handkerchief in her hand, which she waved in token of peace. The Mormons with the wagons waved one in reply, and then moved on to the corral. The emigrants then came out&#8212;no Indians or others being in sight at this time&#8212;and talked with these leading Mormons with the three wagons.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">They talked with the emigrants an hour or an hour and a half, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">told them that the Indians were hostile, and that if they gave up their arms it would show that they did not want to fight</seg>; and if they, the emigrants, would do this they would pilot them back to the settlements. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The emigrants had horses which had remained near their wagons; the loose stock, mostly cattle, had been driven off&#8212;not the horses.</seg> Finally the emigrants agreed to these terms and delivered up their arms to the Mormons with whom they had counseled. The women and children then started back toward <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house, the men following with a few wagons that they had hitched up. On arriving at the Scrub Oaks, etc., where the other <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">Mormons and the Indians lay concealed</seg>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higby</persName>, who had been one of those who had inveigled

<pb n="11" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.011"/>

the emigrants from their defenses, himself gave the signal to fire, when a volley was poured in from each side, and the butchery commenced and was continued until it was consummated.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The property was brought to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> and sold at public auction. It was called in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and is so called now by the facetious Mormons, <q>"property taken at the siege of Sebastopol."</q> The clothing stripped from the corpses, bloody and with bits of flesh in it, shredded by the bullets from the persons of the poor creatures who wore it, was placed in the cellar of the tithing office (an official building), where it lay about three weeks, when it was brought away by some of the party; but witnesses do not know whether it was sold or given away. It is said the cellar smells of it even to this day.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">It is reported that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Smith</persName> (the latter lives in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>) went to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> immediately after the massacre and counseled with <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> about what should be done with the property. They took with them the ready money they got from the murdered emigrants and offered it to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>. He said he would have nothing to do with it. He told them to divide the cows and cattle among the poor. They had taken some of the cattle to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> when they went up, and after the talk with <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> they sold these to the merchants there. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> told <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> that the Indians would not be satisfied if they did not have a share of the cattle.</seg> <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> left it to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> to make the distribution. One or two of the Mormons did not like it that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had this authority, as they say he swindled them out of their share. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was the smartest man of the lot.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The wagons, carriages, and rifles, etc., were distributed among the Mormons. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> has a carriage reported to be one of them. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Indians have but few of the rifles.</seg></seg></seg></p>

</body>

</floatingText>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">Much of this seems to be corroborated by a man named <persName key="Whitlock, Alma">Whitelock</persName>, a dentist, now at <orgName type="military" key="Camp Floyd">Camp Floyd</orgName>. <persName key="Whitlock, Alma">Whitelock</persName> says he was told by a Mormon, who acknowledged that he was present at the massacre, but who is now in <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, <q>"that orders to destroy the emigrants first came from 'above'"</q> (<placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>), and that a party of armed men under the command of a man named <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, who was then a bishop in the church, but who has since (as <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> says) been deposed, left the settlements of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver City</placeName> (north of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>), <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan City</placeName>, and <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> on what was called <q>"a secret expedition,"</q> and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">after an absence of a few days returned, bringing back strange wagons, cattle, horses, mules, and also household property.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">There is legal proof that this property was sold at the official tithing office of the church.</seg> <persName key="Whitelock, Alma">Whitelock</persName> says that this man could not report the detail of the massacre without tears and trembling. He said he was so horrified at these atrocities he fled away from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">This man said he saw children clinging around the knees of the murderers, begging for mercy and offering themselves as slaves for life could they be spared. But their throats were cut from ear to ear as an answer to their appeal.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">There are now wagons, carriages, and cattle in possession of the Mormons which can be sworn to, it is said, as having belonged to these emigrants by those who saw them upon on the plains.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Two hundred and forty-eight head of cattle were sold on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Jordan River">Jordan River</geogName> after the arrival of the Army to United States commissaries by Mormons, and it is said that they can be traced as having come through the hands of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Hooper, William H.">Hooper</persName>, who was Mormon secretary of state, and were without doubt the cattle taken from the emigrants. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The Indians are supposed to have gotten but few of the arms.</seg> Others are seen in the hands of the Mormons which are believed to have been captured at the time of the massacre. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Pah-Ute Indians on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy River</geogName> said to me that they know the Mormons had charged them with the massacre of the emigrants</seg> but, said they, "Where are the wagons, the cattle, the clothing, the rifles, and other property belonging to the train? We have not got them or had them. No;

<pb n="12" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.012"/>

you find all these things in the hands of the Mormons." There is some logical reasoning in that, creditable at least to the obscure minds of miserable savages, whatever be the truth.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">But there is not the shadow of a doubt that the emigrants were butchered by the Mormons themselves, assisted doubtless by the Indians. The idea of letting the emigrants come on to an obscure quarter of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, amid the fastness of the mountains, with a formidable desert extending from that point to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, over which a stranger to the country could not possibly, without sustenance, escape with his life; to a point where the Indians were numerous enough to lend assistance, and who could plausibly be charged with the crime in case, in the future, any people should give trouble by asking ugly questions on the subject, exhibits consideration as to future contingencies of which these miserable Indians, at least, are entirely, incapable.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Besides, <q>"fifty men that would do to tie to"</q> in a fight, all well armed and all expert in the use of the rifle, could have whipped ten time their number of Pah-Ute Indians armed only with the bow and arrow. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> himself, their agent, informed me that to his certain knowledge in 1855 there were but three guns in the whole tribe. I doubt if they had many more in 1857. The emigrants were to be destroyed with as little loss to the Mormons as possible, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">no one old enough to tell the tale was to be left alive</seg>. To effect this the whole plan and operations, from beginning to end, display skill, patience, pertinacity, and forecast, which no people here at that time were equal to except the Mormons themselves. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> says three men escaped. They were doubtless herding when the attack was made, or crept out of the corral at night.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The fate of one of these he had never learned. He must have been murdered of the road or perished of hunger and thirst in the mountains. At all events he never went through to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> or he would have been heard from. One got as far as the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy River</geogName>, ninety-odd miles from the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. There the Indians cut his throat. The other got as far as <choice><sic>Los</sic><corr>Las</corr></choice> Vegas, 45 miles still further toward <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, where he arrived totally naked, some Indians having stripped him of his clothes. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> said an acquaintance of his coming from that way had seen by marks in the sand where the Indians had thrown him down and where they had been struggling when he was stripped. The <choice><sic>Los</sic><corr>Las</corr></choice> Vegas Indians cut his throat likewise. The Mormons had a fort at <choice><sic>Los</sic><corr>Las</corr></choice> Vegas, now abandoned, but which was occupied at that time.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Here is something which seems to point toward the "Tracks in the sand of three men who wore fine boots" which brothers <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Ira Hatch</persName> and <persName key="Coleman, Prime">Prime Coleman</persName> saw at the Beaver Dams, and at which they became so frightened that did not stop to get water, although there was none other within 20 miles. During this <q>"Siege of Sebastapol,"</q> or after the final massacre, it was doubtless discovered that the three emigrants had escaped, and brothers <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> and <persName key="Coleman, Prime">Coleman</persName>, perhaps two Mormons named Young, were sent in pursuit to cut them off on the desert or to get the Indians to do it. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> talks Pah-Ute like a native, and is now an interpreter of their language whenever needed. One of the Youngs, who now lives at Cotton Farm, near the confluence of the Virgin and Santa Clara, tells this story of the emigrants murdered on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName></seg></p>

<pb n="13" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.013"/>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">He and his brother, each on horseback and leading a third horse, were traveling from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, as he says, to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. Just before they arrived at <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy River</geogName> they met one of the emigrants on foot. He had been wounded; was unarmed and without provisions or water. It was at daybreak. He had traveled already nearly 100 miles from <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>. He seemed to be terror stricken. His mind was wandering. He talked incoherently about the massacre and of his purposes. Under the awful scenes he had witnessed, the pain of his wound, and the privations he had endured his senses had given away. They told him of the long deserts ahead of which, if he pursued his way, he would certainly perish. They persuaded him to return with them; mounted him on their lead horse, and so came on to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, where they stopped to prepare breakfast. One of the Youngs laid his coat, containing in its pocket $300, all their money, on a bush, and commenced frying some cakes at a fire which had been kindled.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The Indians gathered around in great numbers. The chief would seize the cakes from the pan as fast as they were done, and eat them. At last one of the Youngs struck the chief with a knife, whereupon all the Indians rose to kill the three men. Young says he and his brother drew their revolvers, and holding them on the Indians, kept them at a distance until they got to their horses, and mounted, and were out of arrow shot. They then looked back for the emigrant who had seemed, as he sat abstracted by the fire, hardly to comprehend what was going on. He had not left the spot where he sat. Three or four Indians had him down and were cutting his throat. They, themselves, then made off, leaving coat, money, and all their provisions.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">This is their story, but the truth doubtless was the Youngs, <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> and <persName key="Coleman, Prime">Coleman</persName>, had followed up the man; had found him beyond the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, brought him back, and then set the Indians upon him. The fate of these three men seems to close the scenes of this terrible tragedy on all the grown people of that fine train which was seen journeying prosperously forward at O'Fallon Bluffs on the 11th of the preceding June. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="SexualViolence">There were doubtless atrocious episodes connected with the massacre of the women which will never be known. Mr. <persName key="Rodgers, William">Rodgers</persName>, the deputy marshal, told me that Bishop <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> is said to have taken a beautiful young lady away to a secluded spot. There she implored him for more than life. She, too, was found dead. Her throat had been cut from ear to ear.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The little children whom we left with this <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> distributing [them] at <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house after that sad night have at length been gathered together and are now either at Indian Farm, 12 miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore City</placeName>, or at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> in the custody of Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>, United States Indian agent. There are 17 in number. Sixteen of these were seen by Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, Lieutenant <persName key="Kearney, William">Kearney</persName>, and others, and gave the following information in relation to their personal identity, etc. The children were varying from 3 to 9 years of age, 10 girls, 6 boys, and were questioned separately.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The first is a boy named <persName key="Sorrow, John Calvin">Calvin</persName>, between 7 and 8; does not remember his surname; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">says he was by his mother when she was killed, and pulled the arrows from her back until she was dead; says he had two brothers older than himself, named <persName key="Sorrow, Henry">Henry</persName> and <persName key="Sorrow, James">James</persName>, and three sisters, <persName key="Sorrow, Nancy">Nancy</persName>, <persName key="Sorrow, Mary">Mary</persName>, and <persName key="Sorrow, Martha">Martha</persName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The second is a girl, who does not remember her name. The others say it is Demurr.</seg></p>

<pb n="14" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.014"/>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The third is a boy named <persName key="Taggit, Ambrose Mirem">Ambrose Miriam Tagit</persName>; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">says he had two brothers older than himself and one younger. His father, mother, and two elder brothers were killed</seg>, his younger brother was brought to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>; says he lived in <placeName type="county" key="Johnson County, Arkansas">Johnson County</placeName>, but does not know in what State; says it took one week to go from where he lived to his grandfather's and grandmother's, who are still living in the States.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The fourth is a girl obtained of <persName key="Morris, John">John Morris</persName>, a Mormon, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. She does not recollect anything about herself.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Fifth. A boy obtained of <persName key="Grove, E. H.">E. H. Grove</persName> says that the girl obtained of <persName key="Morris, John">Morris</persName> is named <persName key=" , Mary">Mary</persName> and is his sister.</seg></p>	

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The sixth is a girl who says her name is <persName key="Prudence Angeline">Prudence Angelina</persName>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Had two brothers, <persName key=" , Jessee">Jessee</persName> and <persName key=" , John">John</persName>, who were killed</seg>. Her father's name was <persName key=" , William">William</persName> and she had an uncle <persName key=" , Jessee">Jessee</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The seventh is a girl. She says her name is <persName key="Hown/Korn, Francis">Francis Harris, or Horne</persName>, remembers nothing of her family.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The eighth is a young boy; too young to remember anything about himself.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The ninth is a boy who says his name is <persName key="Huff, William H.">William H. Huff</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Then tenth is a boy who say his name is <persName key="Francher, Kit Carson Charles">Charles Francher</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The eleventh is a girl who says her name is <persName key="Huff, Nancy Sophronia">Sophronia Huff</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The twelfth is a girl who says her name is <persName key=" , Betsey">Betsey</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The thirteenth, fourteenth, and fifteenth are three sisters named <persName key="Dunlap, Rebecca">Rebecca</persName>, <persName key="Dunlap, Louisa">Louisa</persName>, and <persName key="Dunlap, Sarah">Sarah Dunlap</persName>. These three sisters were the children obtained of <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">I have no note of the sixteenth.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The seventeenth is a boy who was but six weeks old at the time of the massacre. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s <persName key="Hamblin, Sarah Priscilla Leavitt">wife</persName> brought him to my camp on the 19th instant. The next day they took him on to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> to give him up to Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>. He is a pretty little boy, and hardly dreamed he had again slept upon the ground where <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">his parents</seg> had been murdered.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">These children, it is said, could not be induced to make any developments while they remained with the Mormons, from fear, no doubt, having been intimidated by threats. Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>, it is said, came southward for them under the impression that he would find them in the hands of the Indians. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Mormons say the children were in the hands of the Indians and were purchased by themselves for rifles, blankets, etc., but the children say they have never lived with the Indians at all. The Mormons claimed of Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> sums of money, varying from $200 to $400, for attending them when sick, for feeding and clothing them, and for nourishing the infants from the time when they assumed to have purchased them from the Indians.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Murderers of the parents and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">despoilers of their property</seg>, these Mormons&#8212;rather these relentless, incarnate fiends&#8212;dared even to come forward and claim payment for having kept these little ones barely alive; these helpless orphans whom they themselves had already robbed of their natural protectors and support. Has there ever been an act which at all equaled this in devilish hardihood, in more than devilish effrontery? Never, but one; and even then the price was but <q>"30 pieces of silver."</q></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">On my arrival at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, the 16th instant, I encamped near the spring where the emigrants had encamped, and where they had intrenched themselves after they were first fired upon. The ditch they there dug is not yet filled up.</seg></seg></p>

<pb n="15" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.015"/>

<p>The same day Capt. <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Reuben P. Campbell</persName>, United States Second Dragoons, with a command of three companies of troops came from his camp on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara</geogName> and encamped there also. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> and Deputy Marshal <persName key="Rodgers, William">Rodgers</persName> had come down from <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> with Captain <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Campbell</persName>, and had been inquiring into the circumstances of the massacre. The judge can not receive too much praise for the resolute and thorough manner with which he pursues his investigation.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">On his way down past this spot, and before my arrival, Captain <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Campbell</persName> had caused to be collected and buried the bones of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">26 of the victims</seg>. Dr. <persName key="Brewer, Charles">Brewer</persName> informed me that the remains of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">18 were buried in one grave, 12 in another, and 6 in another</seg>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">On the 20th instant I took a wagon and a party of men and made a thorough search for others amongst the sage bushes for at least a mile back from the road that leads to <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> himself showed Sergeant <persName key="Fritz, ">Fritz</persName> of my party a spot on the right-hand side of the road where he had partially covered up a great many bones. These were collected, and a large number of others on the left-hand side of the road up the slope of the hill, and in the ravines and among the bushes. I gathered many of the disjointed bones of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">34 persons</seg>. The number could easily be told by the number of pairs of shoulder blades and by lower jaws, skulls, and parts of skulls, etc.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">These, with the remains of 2 others gotten in a ravine to the east of the spring, where they had been interred at but little depth&#8212;34 in all&#8212;I buried in a grave on the northern side of the ditch. Around and above this grave I caused to be build of loose granite stones, hauled from the neighboring hills, a rude monument, conical in form and 50 feet in circumference at the base and 12 feet in height. This is surmounted by a cross hewn from red cedar wood. From the ground to the top of cross is 24 feet. On the transverse part of the cross, facing toward the north, is an inscription carved deeply in the wood: "Vengeance is mine: I will repay, saith the Lord." And on a rude slab of granite set in the earth and leaning against the northern base of the monument there are cut the following words:</seg></seg></p>

<floatingText>

<body>

<p>Here <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">120 men, women and children</seg> were massacred in cold blood <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">early in September, 1857</seg>. <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">They were from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>.</seg></p>

</body>

</floatingText>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">I observed that nearly every skull I saw had been shot through with rifle or revolver bullets. I did not see one that had been "broken in with stones." Dr. <persName key="Brewer, Charles">Brewer</persName> showed me one, that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">probably of a boy of 18</seg>, which had been fractured and slit, doubtless by two blows of a bowie knife or other instrument of that character.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">I saw several bones of what must have been very small children. Dr. <persName key="Brewer, Charles">Brewer</persName> says from what he saw he thinks some infants were butchered. The mothers doubtless had these in their arms, and the same shot or blow may have deprived both of life.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">The scene of the massacre, even at this late day, was horrible to look upon. Women's hair, in detached locks and in masses, hung to the sage bushes and was strewn over the ground in many places. Parts of little children's dresses and of female costume dangled from the shrubbery or lay scattered about; and among these, here and there, on every hand, for at least a mile in the direction of the road, by 2 miles east and west, there gleamed, bleached white by the weather, the skulls and other bones of those who had suffered. A glance into the wagon when all these had been collected revealed a sight which can never be forgotten.</seg></p>

<pb n="16" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.016"/>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">The idea of the melancholy procession of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">that great number of women and children, followed at a distance by their husbands and brothers</seg>, after all their suffering, their watching, their anxiety and grief, for so many gloomy days and dismal nights at the corral, thus moving slowly and sadly up to the point where <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">the Mormons and Indians</seg></seg> lay in wait to murder them; these doomed and unhappy people literally going to their own funeral; the chill shadows of night closing darkly around them, sad precursors of the approaching shadows of a deeper night, brings to the mind a picture of human suffering and wretchedness on the one hand, and of human treachery and ferocity upon the other, that can not possibly be excelled by any other scene that ever before occurred in real life.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">I caused the distance to be measured from point to point on the scene of this massacre. From the ditch near the spring to the point upon the road where <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the men were attacked and destroyed</seg>, and where their bones were mostly found, is 1 mile 565 yards. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">Here there is a grave where Captain <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Campbell</persName>'s command buried some of the remains. To the next point also marked by a similar grave made by Captain <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Campbell</persName></seg>, and where <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the women and children</seg> were butchered; a point identified from their bones and clothing having been found near it, it is 1 mile 1,135 yards. To the swell across the valley called the Rim of the Basin, is 1 mile 1334 yards. To <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s house, 4 miles 1049 yards.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">Maj. <persName key="Prince, Henry">Henry Prince</persName>, United States Army, drew a map of the ground about the spring where the entrenchment was dug, and embracing the neighboring hills behind which the Mormons had cover. On the crest of these hills are still traces of some rude little parapets made of loose stones and loopholed for rifles. Marks of bullets shot from the corral are seen upon these stones. I inclose this map, and also a drawing of the valley as it appears looking northward from a point below the spring; and another drawing giving <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">a near view of the monument</seg>. These latter are not so good as I could wish for, but they will serve to give a tolerably correct idea of what they are intended to represent. They were made by Mr. <persName key="Moeller, ">Moeller</persName>, who has lived many years among the Mormons.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Extra-legalViolence">In pursing the bloody thread which runs throughout this picture of sad realities, the question of how this crime, that for hellish atrocity has no parallel in our history, can be adequately punished often comes up and seeks in vain for an answer. Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> says that with Mormon juries the attempt to administer justice in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this Territory</placeName> is simply a ridiculous farce. He believes <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> ought at once to be put under martial law. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">This may be the only practicable way in which even partial punishment can be meted out to these Latter-Day devils.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">But how inadequate would be the punishment of a few, even by death, for this crime for which nearly the whole Mormon population, from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> down, were more or less instrumental in perpetrating. There are other heinous crimes to be punished besides this. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Extra-legalViolence">Martial law would at best be but a temporary expedient.</seg> Crime is found in the footsteps of the Mormons wherever they go, and so the evil must always exist as long as the Mormons themselves may exist. What is their history? What their antecedents? Perhaps the future may be judged by the past.</seg></p>

<pb n="17" xml:id="mmm.doc.carleton.1902.017"/>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">In their infancy as a religious community they settled in <placeName type="county" key="Jackson County, MO">Jackson County</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Mo.</placeName> There in a short time, from the crimes and depredations they committed, they became intolerable to the inhabitants, whose self-preservation compelled them to rise and drive the Mormons out by force of arms.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">At <placeName type="settlement" key="Nauvoo, IL">Nauvoo</placeName> again another experiment was tried with them. The people of <placeName type="state" key="Illinois">Illinois</placeName> exercised forbearance toward them until it literally "ceased to be a virtue." They were driven thence as they had been from <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName>, but fortunately this time with the loss on their part of those two shallow impostors, but arrant miscreants, <persName key="Smith, Hyrum"><persName key="Smith, Joseph">the brothers Smith</persName></persName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">The United States took no heed of these wholesome lessons taught by <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="Illinois">Illinois</placeName>. The Mormons were permitted to settle amid the fastnesses of the <geogName type="mountain" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</geogName>, with a desert on each side, and upon the great thoroughfare between the two oceans. Over this thoroughfare our citizens have hitherto not been able to travel without peril to their lives and property, except, forsooth, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> pleased to grant them his permission and give them his protection. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><q>"He would turn the Indians loose upon them."</q></seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The expenses of the army in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, past and to come (figure that), the massacre <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>, <seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">the unnumbered other crimes, which have been and will yet be committed by this community</seg>, are but preliminary gust of the whirlwind our Government has reaped and is yet to reap for the wind it has sowed in permitting the Mormons ever to gain foothold within our borders.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Extra-legalViolence"><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">They are an ulcer upon the body politic. An ulcer which it needs more that cautery to cure. It must have excision, complete and thorough extirpation, before we can ever hope for safety or tranquility. There is no rhetorical phrase made by a flourish of the pen, but it really that will prove to be an earnest and stubborn fact. This brotherhood may be contemplated from any point of view, and but one conclusion can be arrived at concerning it. The Thugs of India were an inoffensive, moral, law-abiding people in comparison.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">I have made this a <hi rend="italics">special report</hi>, because the information here given, however crude, I thought to be of such grave importance it ought to be put permanently upon record and deserved to kept separate and distinct from a report on the ordinary occurrences of a march. Some of the details might, perhaps, have been omitted. But there has been a great and fearful crime perpetrated, and many of the circumstances connected with it have long been kept most artfully concealed.</seg></p>

<p>But few direct rays even now shine in upon the subject. So that however indistinct and unimportant they may at present appear to be, even the faint side lights given by these details may yet lend assistance in exploring some obscure recess of the matter where the great truths, that should be diligently and persistently sought for, may yet happily be discovered.</p>

<closer><salute>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient servant.</salute><lb/>
<signed><hi rend="right"><persName key="Carleton, James Henry">JAMES HENRY CARLETON</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Brevet Major, U.S.A., Captain in the First Dragoons.</hi>
</hi></signed>
<signed>Maj. <persName key="Mackall, W. W.">W. W. MACKALL</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rend="right"><hi rend="italic">Assistant Adjutant-General, U.S.A., <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, Cal.</hi></hi></signed>
</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>