<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.nyt.18580803">
    <teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
	    <titleStmt>
		<title level="m" type="main">Utah</title>
		<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
		<author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
		 <idno>mmm.news.nyt.18580803</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
 
	    <notesStmt>
		<note type="summary"></note>
	    </notesStmt>
 
	     <sourceDesc>
		<bibl>
  		    <title level="j">New York Times</title>
		    <title level="a" type="main">Utah</title>
		    <publisher></publisher>		    
		    <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		    <date when="1858-08-03">August 3, 1858</date>
 		</bibl>
	    </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
 
         <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
	<textClass>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
	        <term>newspaper</term>
	    </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
		<term></term>
	    </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="action">
 		<term></term>
	    </keywords>
 	</textClass>
    </profileDesc>
 
    <revisionDesc>
	<change when="2011-08-09"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enhancement</change>
	<change when="2011-04-27"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept Highlighting</change>
	<change when="2010-02-18"><name>Kelsey F. Harris</name> Initial Encoding</change>
	<change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>
 
</teiHeader>
 
<text>
 
<body>

<div1 type="newspaper">
    
    <pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.nyt.18580803.001"/>
 
<head type="main">UTAH.</head>
<milestone unit="horbar" />
<head type="sub">General Description of Salt Lake Valley.</head>
<milestone unit="horbar" />
<head type="sub">Narrative of an American Citizen held as a prisoner of war.</head>
<milestone unit="horbar" />
<head type="sub">VIEW OF MORMON AFFAIRS</head>

<div2>
<head type="sub"> From Our Own Correspondent<lb/>
Great Salt Lake City, Saturday, June 26, 1858.<lb/>
General View Of The Salt Lake Valley.</head>
 
<p>There has been no other time, during many
years, probably, in which the valleys of the mountains
could have been viewed by a stranger to so
great an advantage as the present.  You are already
aware that your correspondent emerged from
<geogName type="mountain" key="Wasatch Mountains">Wasatch Mountains</geogName> to the great table overlooking
<geogName type="waterway" key="Great Salt lake">SaltLLake</geogName> in the midst of a severe rain storm.  A
shower of an hour's duration, at this season of advanced
verdure, was never known here before during
the occupation of this region by the <orgName type="religion" key="LDS">Church of the
Latter-Day Saints</orgName>.  It came upon them just as their
crops of grain and grasses were up finely under the
influence of the Summer sun, having derived their
needed moisture from the Winter snows and Spring
rains.  But this moisture was now exhausted, the
earth had begun to be parched, and the time had arrived
when the tedious labor of irrigation must be
undergone to save the crops.  Just then came the
three or four days' rain, settling and fastening the
dust, reviving the grass, raising the drooping heads of
the now-forming grain, and clothing the whole country
in its most beauteous garb of green.  Viewed from
the point where the pass of the mountains opens on
the plain, the scene was enchanting beyond descriptions
upon the day of my arrival; dripping with rain
though I was, chilled and weary with a long ride on
horseback after a comfortless night's bivouac in the
storm, I could not help checking my pony, and gazing
awhile, with profoundest admiration, upon the enchanting
scene.  But I have already given you a general
idea of the appearance of the city and valley, from
the "bench" overlooking them.  The term "bench"
as you are probably aware, is applied to level and
smooth elevations of land lying above the valleys&#8212;the
same which are sometimes designated as steppes.
The bench here is covered with gravelly soil, bearing,
however, a thin coat of grass and weeds.  It
slopes down gradually from the mountain base to the
site of the city.  The <geogName type="mountain" key="Wasatch Mountains">Wasatch range</geogName> realizes to the
traveler the idea of mountains more perfectly than
many other ridges of greater altitude, for the reason
that they rise almost perpendicular from the plains.</p>

<p><placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">The City</placeName>, lying upon the western slope their
base, is regular in shape, laid out in squares, or
blocks, of ten acres each, nine of which form a ward,
governed in detail by a Bishop of the Church.  The
streets are about eighty feet in width, intersect each
other at right angles, are generally planted with
shade-trees brought from the mountains, and are
watered by little streams, conducted on each side in
shallow graveled ditches, by which the water is
brought from the mountains.  The popular idea
that the City is six miles square is certainly erroneous
&#8212;at least its buildings do not extend over a 
space more than three or four miles long, by two
and a half broad.  The buildings do not stand close
together.  Every house nearly has a large garden
attached, and sometimes there are only two or three
buildings to a square.  In this way dwellings for
perhaps ten thousand people are extended over the
surface I have named.  The buildings are all constructed
of the same material&#8212;a well-molded but
sun dried brick, and of a light clay blue.  The walls
are laid up evenly in line, and are pleasant to the
eye.  The neighborhood affords great abundance of
limestone, as well as of plaster of Paris, for finishing.
The dwellings generally are very simple, a
story, or story and half high-though those of the
poorer classes are little more than mud hovels, and
there are a few belonging to the higher Priesthood
which are spacious and elegant, and furnished, when
open, I am assured, with much richness and taste.</p>

<p>The most casual observer cannot fail to be struck
by the fact that this people have done wonders to
build such a city in the comparatively short period of
their sojourn here.  Surely, the task was an unpromising
one in the beginning, for the soil must have
been barren and forbidding.  The streets have been 
graded and graveled where they needed it, many
acres of gravel bed having been redeemed and are
now in cultivation, and miles upon miles of canals,
dykes, and ditches made for purposes of irrigation as
absolutely essential to the raising of crops.  Without
irrigation nor an ear of corn, or wheat, nor a hill of
potatoes could be grown here; and so far as the V<geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">alley
of Salt Lake</geogName> is concerned, I can now say from
personal observation, that there is not arable land
enough to support decently the population already
ere, even by dint of the most laborious industry&#8212;
more than half of the land is full of saleratus, or covered
by gravel or salt-water.  Among the spurs of
the <geogName type="mountain" key="Wasatch Mountains">Wasatch</geogName>, lying nearest to the city, is one known
as <geogName type="mountain" key="Ensign Peak">Ensign Peak</geogName>.  It is estimated to rise to the height
of over tow thousand feet above <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName>.  I supposed
it far higher, when it cost me three hours' hard
labor, the other day, to reach its summit.  That attained,
I had a glorious view of the valley below, with
the <geogName type="waterway" key="Jordan River">Jordan</geogName>&#8212;the outlet of <geogName type="waterway" key="Utah Lake">Utah Lake</geogName>, far to the south
&#8212;winding, like a silver thread through the emerald
bottoms, away off towards its debouch into <geogName type="waterway" key="Great Salt Lake">Salt Lake</geogName>.
The Lake, too, is plainly visible from the Peak for a
distance of thirty or forty miles, and on a clear day
the white shore of the desert, bounding it on the
West, is easily discernible, though, probably, forty
five miles distant.</p>

<p>We have often heard of the great wall <q>"surrounding"</q>
the city.  This too is a little imaginative, for
the wall has never been even commenced in some
places.  At most, the wall extends two thirds around
the settlement.  It is a miserably poor affair, consisting
of the sod and gravel piled up to a heigh
varying from 3 to 8 feet, provided with embrasures
at intervals pierced for cannon.  It never could have
been proof against the lightest of artillery, and is now
fast falling to ruin, crumbling and washing away
with every Spring thaw or rain.  <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">Its estensible purpose
when erected was defence against Indians.  A
glance shows us the insincerity of such a pretence, for
even if the entire population of the valley had been
numerous enough to defend the wall during a siege at
every point on its contemplated length of twenty-
four miles, the heights upon the north and west command 
it so completely that riflemen upon the hill
could send their bullets across it with all ease.</seg>  Even
the Mormons themselves now admit that the real object
in building the wall was to furnish labor to the
thousands of idle men who were here in 1854, and
who would have been dangerous to the existence of
Mormon theocracy, had not this plan of keeping
their hands employed been devised.  You can have
little appreciation of the deserted appearance of the
city upon our arrival, with scarce a building open
and nobody in town except the guard of two or three
hundred who were left to take care of the property
and apply the incendiary torch upon order.</p>

<p>There were only two females in the city when the
Gentiles entered, and even they were sent away at
once; so that today there are absolutely no ladies
here except the wife of <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Governor Cummings</persName> and a 
lady who spent the Winter at <orgName type="military" key="Camp Scott">Camp Scott</orgName> and who
returned in our company.  There are now here
probably five hundred men, the number having been
increased by farmers who came up from their families
to look after the crops.  The house windows
still remain boarded up, and the gardens are luxuriant
with the weeds that have checked out all more
useful vegetation.  It would be difficult to imagine a
scene of sadder desolation than that presented by this
city now.  Indeed it looks as though some terrible
pestilence had swept over its face, leaving the traces
of it dread path vividly marked as the course
of a tornado through a vigorous well-grown
forest.  The workshops in Temple Block have all
been despoiled of their roofs, and the foundations of
the Temple covered with sods to hide them from
the gaze of Gentile curiosity.  Temple Block, as is
already known, is the square devoted to the construction
of the great Mormon Temple, now in process
of erection.  It is surrounded by a superior wall
of stone, covered with a plastic, and some ten or
twelve feet high; within the walls stand not only
the wreck of extensive workshops, but the "Bowery"
&#8212;or present church-meeting house-also, and
the Endowment House, that scene of horrible mysteries
which the initiated apostates from among the
"Saints" unite in denouncing as the hell of hells.
The "Bowery" is also closed up now.  It is an extensive
building, fully capable, I should think, of
seating three thousand persons, as claimed by it
constructors.</p>

<p>The square adjoining Temple Block, is occupied<cb n="2" />
chiefly by the <q>" Tithing House"</q> and two of <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM
YOUNG</persName>'s palatial residences, including the celebrated
"Lion" house, which he constructed with especial
reference to the accommodation of an extensive and
well-regulated harem. The "Lion" house is two
stories and a half high, with a row of twelve Gothic
gabled windows on each side, to the upper story,
each window opening, it is said, into a separate
room. Directly alongside this building, and connecting 
with it by a range of offices, is another of liberal
proportions, in which <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName> chiefly domiciles himself 
and the elder Mrs. YOUNG, who is divided off
from her numerous rivals by a high fence. This
building is surmounted by the <q>"Bee Hive"</q> emblem
of the Territory;&#8212;but a profane wretch at my elbow
insists, that the more fitting location for this emblem
of industry, would be upon the Lion House aforesaid.
I neither ask his reasons for the suggestion, nor discuss 
its soundness.</p>

<p>The tithing stores and <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S <q>"domestic institutions" </q>
are surrounded by a fine and impenetrable wall
of cobble-stones laid in cement, rising to a height of
ten feet, three feet thick at the base and one foot thick
at the top. This wall is divided into sections by columnar 
buttresses, which rise above the wall about
two feet each, and are designed eventually to form
pedestals for a collection of statues. The walls are
entered by heavy gates, constructed so that no outsider 
could hope to got a peep at the mysteries inclosed, 
nor any discontented female hope to escape
from the grounds without the friendly aid of a turnkey. 
Indeed, the whole establishment has very much
the air of the desperate nunnery of the romances,
the walls of which are understood to bury forever
from the world those females who once pass their
portals. Within this wall, too, <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName> has extensive
stables and barns, sufficient in size for a stud of fifty
or sixty horses. The dwelling which he first constructed 
for his own use, and which is now occupied
by one of his children, stands on the lower edge of
the bench on the square east of that containing the
Zion house. This building is the best located, and is
altogether the cosiest house of the group. Back of it
stands another of <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S spacious barns, looking
much more like a large country church. Opening the
gate by which it is approached we read the injunction, 
<q>"Shepherds, feed your flocks."</q></p>

<p>Near by is a small saw mill, which is rim exclusively 
for the purpose of cutting <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S fire wood.
The grounds about <persName key="Young, Brigham">YOUNG</persName>'s dwellings are not extensive 
nor elegant, although kept in the finest order.
They are filled chiefly with fruit trees, strawberry
beds, and kitchen gardens, They are carefully guarded, 
and strangers are generally excluded, although
your correspondent was favored with an opportunity
to ramble over them, and to luxuriate at some length
in the luscious mysteries of the strawberry beds.</p>

<p>The square, north of <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S, is occupied chiefly
by the group of a dozen houses, occupied by <persName key="Kimball, Heber C.">HEBER
C. KIMBALL</persName> and his polygamous family. These, also,
are surrounded by expensive and impenetrable walls.
The dwellings of the <persName key="Young, Brigham">YOUNGS</persName>, and other leading
men in the church, are generally fine, exhibiting in
all their surroundings a vast amount of the hardest of
later wrung from the people. This fact is evident to
the most superficial observer. <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName> is immensely 
rich, yet has he not toiled, and one cannot fail to
see that this is no country in which a man may become 
wealthy without labor or adventure, for scarce a
blade of tame grass can be had without effort. <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S 
grounds occupy a site formerly covered by hard
gravel, and every inch of soil has been carted upon
it from a distance. The same is true of <persName key="Kimball, Heber C.">HEBER
C. KIMBALL</persName>'S
but the people, in their blind fanaticism, bow their
necks readily to the yoke, and seem quite content to
remain poor, that their prophets and priests may roll
in wealth. On every hand, too, we see evidences of
<persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S policy of keeping his people hard at work.
I do not exaggerate in the least, when I say that it is
with the utmost difficulties that the masses can eke
out an existence by the most laborious industry; for
their tithes and taxes, paid in work, time and produce, 
take so largely from their means, and their soil
is naturally so barren, that nothing less than the
closest application saves them from starving. I would
not be misunderstood. Their crops of grain and of
vegetables are superior, when not cut off my insects,
but the labor of reclaiming the soil and of irrigation,
is so great as to absolutely forbid the cultivation of
more than a small patch of land by each. On this
score, it is clear that the most shameful imposition
is practiced upon proselytes in the east and in the old
world, who are continually urged to come to "Zion,"
a land flowing with milk and honey, and assured that
the earth here yields abundantly upon slight wooing.
Thus thousands have been deceived into abandoning
comfortable homes, and bringing their families here
to suffer all the pangs of keenest poverty. If those
who contemplate coming here will but send some
trusty agent in advance to examine and make honest
reports, fewer families will finally decide to come
here, where they must necessarily wear out a
wretched existence.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">SALT LAKE.</head>

<p>Among the natural curiosities of this region, <geogName type="waterway" key="Great Salt Lake">Great
Salt Lake</geogName> is preeminent. It has already been so
fully described that I can add nothing new. A party
of us visited it a day or two ago, and tested its saline
virtue, floating like logs upon its surface, and strangling 
desperately when a drop or two of the brine succeeded 
in penetrating nostrils or mouth. This inland
sea certainly is among the most remarkable facts in the
geography of the world. If I remember aright, <persName key="Stansbury, Howard">Capt.
STANSBURY</persName>'S soundings make it only thirty-five feet
deep in its deepest part. Three rivers&#8212;the <geogName type="waterway" key="Weber River">Weber</geogName>,
the <geogName type="waterway" key="Bear River">Bear</geogName> and the <geogName type="waterway" key="Jordan">Jordan River</geogName>&#8212;all empty into it, pouring 
large bodies of fresh water into the basin continually; 
nevertheless, although it has no visible outlet, 
the water of <geogName type="waterway" key="Great Salt Lake">the Lake</geogName> maintains its character of
strongest brine unimpaired. Standing upon the jutting 
point of Black Rock, distance eighteen miles
from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City">the City</placeName>, and looking thence down upon the
water, it seems of a bluish white color in body,
though quite clear when taken up in a glass. The
salt-boilers upon the banks state that four buckets of
water will usually make one of salt, and a clearer,
purer article could not be desired. I tried a bath,
and found it impossible to sink; wading out far
enough to bring the water up to one's arm-pits, it becomes 
impossible to keep one's feet upon the sandy
bottom, so buoyant is the water. Lay upon your
back, double up your limbs, and lock your arms
around your knees and you bob around in the ceaseless swell
of the Lake like a stray cork. The water
is so excessively salt as to be bitter. A drop in one's
eye is painful as would be the same amount of tobacco 
juice, and the greatest care is necessary to prevent 
strangulation if the swimmer <q>"ships"</q> the
smallest mouthful.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSApostates">We found only one salt-boiler at work. All the rest
had "gone South," as we were informed by the now
solitary monarch of the spot, Mr. <persName key="Warn">Warn</persName>, formerly
of Salem, Mass. At his shanty, near the Black Rock
on the shore of the lake, we found his wife&#8212;an intelligent 
and practical woman from Cushing, Me.,
and a pretty little flaxen-haired daughter nine or ten
years of age, bringing vividly to the mind of your
correspondent a blue eyed, brown-haired little one
two or three thousand miles away in a happier land
It is a sad sight to witness a naturally bright child
growing up in such a spot, without a companion of
her own years, or any means of education. <persName key="White">Mr.
WHITE</persName> and his wife came here several years ago, undoubting 
disciples of the Mormon faith. Some time
since they lost several head of cattle, the responsibility 
for which they traced directly to <persName key="Young, Phineas">PHINEAS
YOUNG</persName>, a nephew of the Prophet. <persName key="White">WHITE</persName> did not
hesitate to accuse him of the theft, and to demand
justice. In response he was told by his priestly
leaders to <q>"shut up,"</q>&#8212;and as he persisted in scandalizing 
the Church by making oath that the Prophet's 
nephew was a thief, he was cut off from the
Church. This, however, had no terrors for him, as
he and his wife had already become satisfied by the
<q>"fruits"</q> of Mormonism, that the tree was vicious
and corrupt, They assured us that even within a
few days post, since the arrival of the Governor and
the arrangement made by the Peace Commissioners,
the Mormon Bishops have been engaged in driving 
the people away from his neighborhood,
some of them being reluctant to go South, but
were afraid to <q>"disobey Council."</q> The effort was
made to send the WHITES away, but they positively
refused, notwithstanding they were told very distinctly 
by the Bishop that the fractious Apostates
would be put out of harm's way. <persName key="White">Mr. WHITE</persName> states,
upon his own knowledge, that very many families
went South under orders, who were loth to do so
grumbling audibly at the tyranny to which they submitted. 
I am assured that not a few of the people
have been made to believe that Batons, as <q>"Governor," </q>
has the right to order them where he will.
We have abundant evidence of these tyrannical orders 
to leave the city. I saw in Emigration Canon
yesterday several apostatizing families, who had
come up from the South. They desired to stop in
this city and await the arrival of the army, but the<cb n="3" />
<q>"Saints"</q> told them positively that they would allow
no women to be in town while the army was
here, and so compelled them to start to the Eastward.
These and a dozen other families similarly
situated, who are now camped on the <q>"bench,"</q> will
come in here with the army and test the question
with their persecutors.</seg></p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">THE HOT SPRINGS.</head>
      
<p>Returning from, this digression, I must say
a word of the Hot and Warm Springs.
The former boil up out of the Valley at
the foot of the mountain three miles above
the city; they are sulphurous, and of so high a tem-
perature as to be unendurable, Indeed there can be
little doubt that they would cook an egg, although I
have had no opportunity to try the experiment, A
story is told of a big Missourian; an emigrant to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, who, passing these Springs in 1850 stripped
for a bath. He had been assured that the Mormons
bathed here, and so when cautioned against trying
the experiment, swore that he'd be d&#8212;d
if he couldn't stand anything that the Mormons could. With this declaration he plunged
into the see thing pool. A yell of pain
brought the bye-standers to his aid. They dragged
him out,&#8212;for he was helpless to aid himself,&#8212;and
carried him to town, where he lay for weeks before
he was able to proceed on his journey. The Warm
Springs are just outside the city wall noon the North.
Their temperature is lower than that of the Hot
Springs, affording an exceedingly agreeable bath.
There is a bathhouse within the walls, supplied
from the springs, but, like all else here at this
time, has been broken up and left in ruins. Some of
the Gentiles not long since went in, as the house
was open, fixed up a bathing tub, and arranged it so
that it could be used; but this was too much of luxury 
for Gentile brethren, and some good Mormon
brethren accordingly cut off the water and destroyed
our plans of comfort. Fortunately they can't choke
the springs themselves, which well up out of the
ground, forming two or three natural basins, from 12
to 18 inches deal), in which we roll and plunge ad
libitum. The water is both sulphurous and saline,
very clear, and possessing cleansing qualities which
cannot but be healthy and invigorating to the skin.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">PEACE UNCERTAIN</head>
       
<p>Nobody has any confidence that the present season
of peace can last. Indeed, I venture the assertion
that if Commissioners <persName key="Powell, Lazarus">POWELL</persName> and <persName key="McCulloch, Benjamin">McCULLOCH</persName>&#8212;who
have fulfilled their duties here with prudence, judgment 
and fidelity&#8212;can be induced to give expression
to their views upon the subject, it will be found that
they have no idea that this people can live in peace
under the Constitution and laws of the Union, to
which they all <hi rend="italic">profess</hi> attachment the most profound.
We see the symptoms of collision on every hand
The Mormons themselves, though subdued, are surly,
gloomy and discontented. They are impudent, too,
in their manner and conversation, and will provoke
personal difficulties by their conduct, out of which a
general collision may spring at any hour. Get a
Mormon in conversation, and, ten to one, he will tell
you very soon how brave he is, and how they would
have whipped the Army if the President had not offered 
so large a price for peace. An amusing instance 
of this sort occurred between a private of <persName key="Magraw">MAGRAW</persName>'S 
company of volunteers and two Mormons, who
went out to camp the other day with produce to sell.
The soldier, after listening to their braggadocia
awhile, suggested that they numbered about the same
proportion to him that the Mormon army did to that
of the United States, that this was a fair opportunity
to test their relative strength, and that be intended to
whip them both for their impudence. The braggarts
were saved the flogging by the timely appearance of
an officer.</p>

<p>Again there are many Gentiles here and in the
neighborhood, who have long been under the heel of
Mormon oppression, suffering great loss and many
hardships, as well as personal indignities. These
begin to feel a little security now, and are turning
upon their persecutors with a good deal of bitterness.
One of them, a <persName key="McNeill">Mr. McNEILL</persName>, whose experience I
propose to note more at length before I close, meeting 
<q>"Adjutant-General"</q> <persName key="Ferguson, James">JAMES FERGUSON</persName>, last evening, 
in the presence of sundry Government officials
and others, denounced him bitterly as a scoundrel
who had oppressed him, and demanded of him satisfaction 
at any given number of paces, with weapons
to be selected. <persName key="Ferguson, James">FERGUSON</persName> did not accept the invitation. 
Scenes of this character will become more
and more frequent day by day, and fan the insane
zeal of not a few of the fanatics of these mountains
who seem anxious to be made <q>"martyrs for the
faith."</q></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">But polygamy is the rock on which they are most
certain to split. To any interference with it they
say they will not submit under any circumstances.
This I have been told repeatedly by the chiefs
among the Mormons here. They declare tha
come what may, they will recognize no attempt 
to break up the plurality system. They
admit that their legislature has passed no law
legalizing and establishing polygamy, and give as a
reason therefor the certainty that Congress would
disapprove and so annul such a law. This being so,
there can be little doubt that the old Mexican law on
that subject prevails here, and that polygamy can be
punished under it.</seg> At any rate, Judge <persName key="Eckles, Delana">ECKLES</persName> will
make the experiment, unless he should get instructions 
from <placeName type="state" key="Washington, D. C.">Washington</placeName> to the contrary, which is
hardly to be anticipated. The people themselves
evidently expect a collision to arise out of this
or some other cause, and I think they are
carefully considering the policy of leasing the country 
altogether, and going to some place where they
can wield the civil as well as ecclesiastical authority.
Meantime, a strong body of troops should always be
stationed near the city, ready for instant duty, to
maintain the laws and to prevent bloodshed by private 
hands.</p>

<p>Already the Mormon leaders here are at work to
get rid of a portion of the federal officials sent among
them, Major <persName key="Blair, S.M.">S. M. BLAIR</persName> told me that they had already 
petitioned for the removal of Judge <persName key="Eckles, Delana">ECKLES</persName>,
Postmaster. <persName key="Morrell, Hiram F.">MORELL</persName>, and Indian Agents <persName key="Hurt, Garland">HURT</persName> and
<persName key="Craig, William">CRAIG</persName>. <persName key="Eckles, Delana">ECKLES</persName> has excited their hostility by his official course in <orgName type="military" key="Camp Scott">Camp Scott</orgName> last winter, where he had
the unparalleled impudence to hold the Mormons to
be traitors, and to indicate his disposition to execute
upon them the laws against treason and sedition. The
other officials mentioned have been among them be-
fore; and of course as they drove them out by force,
it is annoying and humiliating to find them back
again. <persName key="Hurt, Garland">Dr. HURT</persName> certainly is a most honorable and
excellent gentleman, loved and respected by all who
know him, and one who has proven his patriotism
within a year past by desperate public service, in
which he has sacrificed comfort and health, and it is
to be feared, has even cut short his life. We shall see
now whether justice or the Mormons are strongest in
their influence over the Administration of <persName key="Buchanan, James">JAMES
BUCHANAN</persName>. <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Governor CUMMING</persName>, who seems to
have been taken into full communion by
the brethren, evidently sympathizes with them
in their kind intentions toward his brother
officials, and will, doubtless, exert his influence
in support of the petitions of removal, which, I
am inclined to think, he forwards by this mail. The
President, however, will be apt to await the return
of the Peace Commissioners before he acts upon the
petitions; and I am greatly in error if they do not
see, what every other <q>"Gentile"</q> here sees clearly,
that it is the <hi rend="italic">Governor</hi> who should be removed from a
position which he is utterly unfit to fill. His official
intercourse with the Mormons here is making smooth
sailing for himself at the present; but it will assuredly, 
in time, complicate the difficulties which cannot
be avoided. Firmness and dignity are required in
the Governor, but <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">CUMMING</persName> substitutes for these
vulgar familial fly. Besides, he is naturally excitable, 
and notoriously gets steam up to an alarming
point over the whisky-jug. He is not the man for
the position, and should be replaced forthwith by
some one who will command respect for himself, and
so be better able to exact respect for the Government
he represents. He is, withal, vain as a boy of 13, and
offensively imagines himself the embodiment of all
that is great and grand. There can be no question
that former Administrations have sent some appointees 
here, justly obnoxious to the people; and it is of
the highest importance that those who, in future, are
sent to preside over them should be unobjectionable
men in all respects, Probably the best mode of dealing 
with this people would be to repeal the organic
act altogether, and then appoint some such man as
Gen. <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">JOHNSTON</persName> both civil and military Governor.
<persName key="Blair">BLAIR</persName>, and others of the most influential men in this
community, do not hesitate to say, even today, that
they will be d&#8212;d if they will submit to have <persName key="Morrell, Hiram F.">MORELL</persName>, 
<persName key="Eckles, Delana">ECKLES</persName> &amp;Co. admininister the Post Office and
other offices of the Government here. They demand,
too, "as a right," a share of the offices for themselves
its well as the appointment of men to all of the offices,
whom they shall approve, and he adds that there are
a thousand who will jump when he gives the word. I
suggest that Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">BUCHANAN</persName> send his nomination here
for confirmation, rather than to the Senate of the
United States. It is rumored that <persName key="Blair">BLAIR</persName> rather expects 
to be appointed to Judge <persName key="Eckles, Delana">ECKLES</persName> place; and if
he falls to get it, I should not be surprised if Dr,
<persName key="Bernhisel, John M.">BERNHISEL</persName> is requested to resign, to give the Major a
chance to go to Congress.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">ADMISSION OF UTAH AS A STATE.</head>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">The Mormons have determined to make an earnest
effort for immediate admission into the Union, in order
that they may pass laws establishing the eminently
<q>"domestic institution"</q> of Polygamy, and so defy
interference therewith.</seg>  If they fail in that&#8212;as I take

<pb n="2" />

it for granted they must&#8212;they are likely to get out of
the country as quickly as they can. Notwithstanding
<persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName> so recently declared the determination of
himself or his people to <q>"live or die in these mountains,"</q> 
it is very evident that he has not altogether rejected 
the propositions made to him by Colonel <persName key="Kinney, John Fitch">KINNEY</persName> 
for the sale of 3,000,000 acres of land in Mosqueto. 
Messrs. <persName key="Cooper">COOPER</persName> and <persName key="Harbin">HARBIN</persName>, the Kinney Commissioners, 
are still at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> in consultation with
<persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>, and the chances are that he will make some
conditional arrangements. At least, such are the indications. 
If so, it is supposed that Major <persName key="Hunt, Garland">HUNT</persName>
the old Mormon pioneer&#8212;and another person will be
sent down to take a look at the country and report,
and if their report is favorable, that Missionaries will
be sent there to receive and look after the foreign immigration 
of proselytes, who will be directed to that
new Mecca, and he followed, in time, by all of the
faithful from this <q>"Zion"</q> as rapidly as they can get
means of transportation. All this, however, is very
vague and indefinite yet, and may never obtain further 
development.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">AMERICANS HELD AS PRISONERS OF WAR.</head>
     
<p>There are now in this city two American citizens,
who have been held, for months past, prisoners of
war, and treated, in some respects, most shamefully.
One of these is Mr. <persName key="McNeill, F. E.">F. E, McNEILL</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="New Orleans, LA">New Orleans</placeName>,
<placeName type="state" key="Louisiana">La</placeName>, who came to <orgName type="military" key="Fort Laramie">Fort Laramie</orgName> last year, as a guide
to the Fifth Infantry. He came from <orgName type="military" key="Fort Laramie">Laramie</orgName> to
<orgName type="military" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</orgName> in November last, with Rosser, &amp;
<persName key="Waddell">WADDELL</persName>'S team, and arrived in this city on the 1st
December, with several other teamsters, all of whom
proposed to proceed at once to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, from here.
<seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS"><persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> went to see <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM YOUNG</persName>, on learning
that no one could move safely without his aid and assistance
<persName key="Young, Brigham">YOUNG</persName> advised him not to go south, as the
Indians were very bad, but said that, if he insisted
upon going out of <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName>, he would give him and
his friends an escort eastward as far as <orgName type="military" key="Fort Laramie">Fort Laramie</orgName>.
The escort offered was to have been under the command 
of <q>"Cherokee THOMPSON,"</q> the scoundrel who
has been all Winter, and still is, a prisoner in Gen.
<persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">JOHNSTON</persName>'S camp, and whom <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName>, heard declare his intention to incite the Cheyennes to activity in
cutting off <q>"American"</q> travelers across the Plains.
It is a significant fact that this Southern route, on
which the Indians are so bad, according to <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S
account, is the same over which the <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> and
Salt Lake mail has been carried now for two and a
half years, by Mormons, without over having been interrupted in a single instance. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">Yet very many
travelers have there found graves, according to Mormon 
accounts, entirely by Indian hands! The fact
adds seeming corroboration to the charge so frequently 
made against the Mormons, of having a
secret understanding with the savages, by which they
receive aid in, tied immunity for, robbing and murdering 
others, so long as they let the Saints pass unmolested</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> had seen enough of the Saints already
to satisfy him that he must he very circumspect if
he hoped to escape with safety, so he concluded
not to accept an escort, and never called for it. After 
remaining in <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName> for a month or more,
during which time he traveled north a ways, to see the
people, he determined some time in January to start
for <orgName type="military" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</orgName>, which he did with three others, to
wit: <persName key="MIles, C. L.">Mr. C. L, MILES</persName>, of <placeName type="state" key="Michigan">Michigan</placeName>, &#8212; <persName key="Brown">BROWN</persName>, of
Southern <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName>, a one eyed and one-armed man,
and <persName key="Fadens, Henry C.">HENRY C. FADENS</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salem, MA">Salem</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Massachusetts">Mass</placeName>. This party
of four plunged at once into the mountains, where
they floundered about for 21 days in the snow, which
oft times was neck deep. For six days they were entirely 
without food. They were discovered at last
near <geogName type="waterway" key="Yellow Creek">Yellow Creek</geogName> by the Mormon out-post force
under Capt. <persName key="Winans">WINANS</persName>, brought back to this city, and
put in imprisonment, under a guard of eight armed
men <persName key="Brown">BROWN</persName>, however, escaped while at the Mormon 
station on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Weber River">Weber River</geogName>, and is understood
to have reached the Army in safety. After the prisoners 
had been in custody four weeks, the Mormons
wanted <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> to start for <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> with the
mall, which he refused to do, having been warned
by friendly apostate Mormons that he would assuredly 
be murdered if he went. Upon his refusal a
heavy ball and chain were put upon him, and he was
again confined. Subsequently he succeeded in getting 
the guard drunk one day, and then got the Captain 
to go with him to <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>'S. Not finding the
Prophet in he left a letter upbraiding him for his oppression. 
Half an hour later an order came from
<persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName> directing the fetters to be removed. When
Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">CUMMING</persName> first came into the city <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName>
again succeeded in getting his guard under the influence
of liquor, and then under pretence of going
after beer, slipped away from his custodians and proceeded 
to see the new Governor to claim his protection. 
He found <persName key="Stains">STAINS</persName>' house, where the Governor
was stopping, rigorously guarded,&#8212;but he pushed his
way in, told the Governor his own story briefly, and
claimed his protection. The Governor, who seemed
to be alarmed and fearful of personal danger, failed
to respond to his plea more than to take his name
down.  He also stated to the Governor that he could
tell him of some shocking murders perpetrated
by <orgName type="tribe" key="Snake">Snake Indians</orgName>, with the cognizance and under the
influence of prominent Mormons; and of cattle stealing 
under the direction of <persName key="West, Chauncey W.">CHAUNCEY W. WEST</persName>,
Bishop of Ogden. One case in particular, he mentions, 
is that of an <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrant, who got his
cattle back subsequently, by contracting with <persName key="West, Chauncey W.">WEST</persName> to
give him a portion of them for returning the remainders. 
A teamster, named <persName key="Rhodes">RHODES</persName>, who assisted in
driving the cattle, while at the Indian camp of <persName key="Simons, Ben">BEN</persName>
and <persName key="Simons, Jim">JIM SIMONS</persName>, was told by the Indians there that
prior to the robbery <persName key="West, Chauncey W.">WEST</persName> asked <persName key="Simons, Jim">JIM</persName> to undertake the running off of the cattle. <persName key="Simons, Jim">JIM</persName> replied by suggesting
to <persName key="West, Chauncey W.">WEST</persName> the propriety of running his own hand into
the fire, promising if it didn't burn him, he also might
be induced to try. The Indian cautioned him, however, 
that it would burn badly. Somebody else was
found to do the job, however, for the cattle were carried 
off immediately after, and the owner, besides
paying <persName key="West, Chauncey W.">WEST</persName> to find them for him, was also compelled 
to pay for their herding during the Winter.
<persName key="McNeil">McNEILL</persName> further states, that while on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Weber River">Weber River</geogName> during the Winter, some time, he saw the cattle
which, were stolen from <persName key="Gilbert">GILBERT</persName> &amp; <persName key="Gerrisu">GERRISU</persName>, and
<persName key="Radford, John">JOHN RADFORD</persName>, sutlers and merchants, while on the
plains last Fall, herding under the care of a Mormon
named <persName key="Thurston">THURSTON</persName>.</p>

<p>As Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">CUMMING</persName> could not or would not help.
<persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName>, he returned to his prison. This was on
Saturday. On Monday the Mormon guard renewed
the ball and chain upon their victim, an American
citizen, against whom no crime is alleged, and who
was only held as a prisoner of war, as was confessed
to me by prominent Mormons to whom I have addressed 
inquiries on the subject within the last day
or two.  On the midnight following the renewal 
of his fetters, <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> was suddenly
seized by an armed force under Adjutant-General
<persName key="Ferguson">FERGUSON</persName>, and sent to the Penitentiary in irons, while
his fellow prisoners were left in the City, in total ignorance 
of his fate. There can be no doubt of the
fact that this step was taken to prevent him from
again communicating with the Gentile Governor,
Three weeks later he was taken out of prison by an
armed guard, carried over two hundred and fifty miles
to the southward to the settlement of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, and
there turned loose in the vicinity of the most vicious
Indians in this region, without provisions or arms or
ammunition of any kind with which to help himself.
The point of his desertion he supposed to be about
400 miles distant from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, the road lying in
part across the Great Desert. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">He walked down as
far as the scene of the Mountain Meadows massacre,
where he saw the bones of the murdered emigrants
lying in heaps;</seg> but <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">no traces of the wagons or other
property belonging to them. <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSApostates">He saw in the care of
good Mormons in that neighborhood a large number
of cattle, which he was informed, by men who were
secretly apostates to the Church, were those taken
from the murdered emigrants.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">This corroborates the
testimony of certain Indians, referred to in a former
letter, who declared that the Mormons carried off the
cattle, although when they induced the Indians to go
into the massacre, they promised them that they
should have all the plunder except the wagons.</seg></seg> 
<seg type="Source" subtype="Unattributed">While upon this Subject, let me add
the testimony of a very intelligent gentleman who
has been traveling in the vicinity of the Mountain
Meadows massacre, and who wormed out of some of
his Mormon friends additional facts in connection
with that catastrophe.  <seg type="Source" subtype="Indians"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">According to these admissions 
the emigrants, finding themselves the subject of
a continuous succession of Indian attacks, which were
fast reducing and weakening them, (again confirming 
the Indian story of my former communication,)</seg> to
that extent, resolved to make a stand and prepare for
vigorous defence. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">They accordingly camped by a
little stream, made a corral with their wagons, the
wheels of which they sunk into the ground so as to
make a sort of breastwork, and in this position recieved 
<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">the assaults of their savage enemies under
<q>"Saintly"</q> leaders</seg>, determined to die there rather
than yield their, wives and children to the fury of
their asailiants,</seg> Thus they defended themselves
<hi rend="italic">nearly three weeks</hi>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">killing, it is estimated, over one
hundred of the enemy</seg>, and they were beaten at last
only by strategy&#8212;the assailants turning the stream of
water away from the besieged, and then killing them
as they came out one by one in search of the means of
quenching their maddening thirst.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">It is fully admitted
that this affair occured almost within sight
and sound of the Mormon settlements, and that the
Mormons knew day by day the progress of the fight.
Had the <q>"Saints"</q> been disposed to assist the little
band and save them, they could have sent even to<cb n="2" />

<placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City">Salt Lake City</placeName> for horsemen and had them upon the
ground within the first week of the siege&#8212;,for a hundred 
miles a day is no uncommon travel for these
mountaineers.</seg> The conclusion is irresistable that
they were content to see the Gentiles slaughtered
and when we have this evidence of the extent to
which their hearts were steeled against the pleadings
of the commonest claims of humanity, it is easy to
believe the declarations of the Indians that they engaged
in the affair under Mormon influence and leadership,</seg> 
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">I learn also that a number of the children of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the murdered emigrants</seg> are in the hands of Indians and Southern Mormons. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Dr. FORNEY</persName>, the Superintendent of Indian Affairs, designs
taking a trip southward very soon, with a view to
ransoming them and also of inquiring into the facts
relative to the massacre.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">I fear, however, that the
<persName key="Forney, Jacob">Doctor</persName> will never get at the bottom of the mystery&#8212;
for although apparently an honest man, who desires
to do his duty faithfully, he is exceedingly simple,
easily influenced, and completely disarmed of all
suspicion by the most superficial kindness. Already
he has been taken complete possessession of by this
people, and <hi rend="italic">upon their own testimony</hi>, is satisfied that they have been greatly abused and lied about, and that they are in reality among the most honest and
most pious people upon earth,&#8212;<seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">notwithstanding their
polygamy</seg>.</seg> Indeed, hath he and Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">CUMMING</persName> 
seem to be in the best possible frame of mind
for the sowing of Mormon seed, and I should not be
surprised if they became full converts to the doctrines 
of <persName key="Smith, Joseph">JOSEPH SMITH</persName> before another month passes.
I would be sorry to do the Doctor injustice&#8212;and
wish again to express my full conviction that he <hi rend="italic">desires to do right</hi>,&#8212;but he seems to me to be moulded of entirely too malleable material for an independent
and discriminating public officer among a people
whose system and practice are entirely at war with
the moral sentiment of the civilized and Christian
world.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">But I have unintentionally wandered from the history of Mr. <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName>, who on viewing the ghastly skeletons of his murdered countrymen, and obtaining
evidence of the fact that <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">they were victims no less
of Mormon than of Indian iniquity</seg>, determined at
once that it would be madness for him to attempt the
passage towards <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>.</seg> He accordingly returned 
at once to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake</placeName>, arriving here two or
three days ago, having walked two hundred and fifty
or three hundred miles in six days, supporting himself
on the way upon wild rabbits, which he killed with a
rifle furnished by <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSApostates">a sympathizing apostate Mormon in one of the southern settlements</seg>. On his way he learned that peace had been made&#8212;but, in any event,
he felt that his chance of life was better while wandering 
in the neighborhood of settlements than it
would be in plunging away from them into the southern 
wilderness, where there would be no witnesses
of any outrage to which it might be desired to subject
him. I add the following items upon the testimony
of <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName>, some of which you will recollect have
been already referred to by evidence from other
sources.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">Last Fall six young men, came into <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName> from <placeName type="st" key="California">California</placeName>, intending to go to the East through the camp, of the U. S. Army. They were arrested here,
searched, robbed of a portion of their personal property, 
and then sent southward, to return to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, 
escorted by a band of Danites, under <persName key="Rockwell, Orrin Porter">PORTER
ROCKWELL</persName>.  Arriving at one of the southern settlements, 
<persName key="Rockwell, Orrin Porter">ROCKWELL</persName> told the men to go ahead, and he
would soon overtake them They passed on, and
that night were attacked, and some, if not all of them,
were killed, by a party in ambush on their road.
This was related to <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> by men professing to be
privy to the facts, one of whom saw <persName key="Rockwell, Orrin Porter">ROCKWELL</persName> riding
back on a mule belonging to the travelers. This incident 
is probably the same narrated much more fully
in the story told by <persName key="James, Richard">RICHARD JAMES</persName>, in my letter of the
29th May, from <orgName type="military" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</orgName>.  It will be remembered,
that a man named <persName key="Yeates">YEATES</persName> was murdered in the
Mountains last Fall, as was supposed, because he
had sold ammunition to, the Army in hostility to Mormon 
interests. The horse of the murdered man is
now in the possession of a Mormon named <persName key="Conover">CONOVER</persName>
at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p>A young man, whose name <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> does not remember, 
came here from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> last year, and
went to board with a man named <persName key="Terry">TERRY</persName>, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>. Some time afterwards his revolvers were stolen 
from the house during the day-time, and his horse carried off from the field. <persName key="Terry">TERRY</persName> told him that they had been carried off by Indians, and he was never able to get any trace of them. On a Sunday evening,
a little subsequent to the thefts, <persName key="Terry">TERRY</persName> started for Church, as he said, and the young man went out with him&#8212;which is the last time the latter was ever seen alive. Three days later an Indian reported a corpse
lying three and a half miles below in the woods; which, upon examination, proved to be that of the young stranger; <hi rend="italic">and the next day <persName key="Terry">Terry</persName> was seen riding the stolen horse about town with the pistols of deceased in his belt!</hi> The facts of this case are certified by certain honest Mormons who knew them, who
denounce them privately, and will probably testify to them as soon as the protection of the army is afforded. 
One of these, an old gentleman named. <persName key="Warren">WARREN</persName>, for expressing his opinion on the subject
rather freely, was dragged out of his house in the night, and would probably have been murdered had not his son come to his rescue in the nick of time with one of Colt's revolving persuaders. Of such crimes as these the theocracy with which <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM YOUNG</persName> has practically displaced the Government and
laws of the Union takes no cognizance whatever. A Mr. <persName key="Rhoades">RHOADES</persName>, of <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, was stopped in broad daylight upon the streets in <placeName type="settlement" key="Ogden City, UT">Ogden City</placeName>, and robbed of his brestpin and finger-ring. He represented the
facts to Bishop <persName key="West, Chauncey W.">CHAUNCEY W. WEST</persName>, who took no notice of his complaint, nor made the least effort to ascertain who of his flock had thus earned their title to a call in the Penitentiary. A young man named <persName key="Miles, C. L.">C. L. MILES</persName>, was in the employ of Bishop <persName key="Andrus, Mellow">MELLOW ANDRUS</persName>,  of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cottonwood, UT">Cottonwood</placeName>, a settlement a few-miles from here, and boarded in his family. <persName key="Andrus, Mellow">ANDRUS</persName> had eight wives, of one of whom he became exceedingly jealous, suspecting her of improper intimacy, with <persName key="Miles, C. L.">MILES</persName>.
He did not profess to have any proof, but said to <persName key="Miles, C. L.">MILES</persName> one day that if he was sure his suspicion was well grounded he would not hesitate to shoot him and cut his wife's throat. <persName key="Miles, C. L.">MILES</persName> protested his innocence, but, becoming alarmed, ran away from <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName>, and attempted to reach the army. He was subsequently arrested, however, by the Mormon out-post
at <geogName type="waterway" key="Yellow Creek">Yellow Creek</geogName>, this side of <geogName type="waterway" key="Bear River">Bear River</geogName>, and brought back with several others, as already stated above. Upon his return he sent a Mormon to <persName key="Andrus, Mellow">ANDRUS</persName> to ask for his buffalo robe which he had left with him when he went off. <persName key="Andrus, Mellow">ANDRUS</persName> refused to deliver the robe, and told the messenger that he would kill <persName key="Miles, C. L.">MILES</persName> if he got where he was. The messenger, a man named <persName key="Sheen">SHEEN</persName>, who has the reputation of having murdered some one on <placeName type="settlement" key="Council Bluffs, IA">Council Bluffs</placeName> a year or two ago, replied significantly that he must murder <persName key="Miles, C. L.">MILES</persName> then, because he was in his charge, intimating that another opportunity might be made. Five or six days later <persName key="Miles, C. L.">MILES</persName> was sent North, under Mormon escort, to meet a party of Cailfornians whom the Mormons said were going West by the northern route, since which time nothing has been heard of him by Gentiles here. Do his friends in <placeName type="state" key="Michigan">Michigan</placeName> know anything more of his <persName key="Miles, C. L.">fate? If they have not heard from him of late, there can be no doubt that he, too, was murdered. Within a fortnight after MILES'</persName> departure <persName key="Andrus, Mellow">ANDRUS</persName> went to the house of his suspected wife's father in this city, and cut her throat, but <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName> has passed the occurrence by without even a word of rebuke. Contrast this single incident with the fact that Mormons have kicked and beaten Gentiles to death here in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, confessedly for imprudent denunciation of the doctrines and practices  of the "Saints!'' These facts were narrated coolly and with evident satisfaction, by full-fledged Mormons, to Mr. <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> and to a Mr. <persName key="Fabens">FABENS</persName>, whose narrative I will give hereafter. Mormons have also boasted to him that the mules lost by <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">General JOHNSTON</persName>'S picket-guard this Spring, during one night when Colonel <persName key="Kane, Thomas L.">KANE</persName> was in camp, were taken by the Mormon escort who accompanied him into <orgName type="military" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</orgName>, and were sent at once into <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName> by one of their number. General <persName key="Johnston, Alfred Sidney">JOHNSTON</persName> suspected the theft, and complained of it to Colonel <persName key="Kane, Thomas L.">KANE</persName> who, upon repeating the complaint to his Mormon friends, was answered by the suggestion that the mules had doubtless strayed away, and would turn up again. It is a favorite joke with the Mormons here, now that their treasonable robberies have been pardoned, to bay, with a contemptuous laugh, that the animals of <persName key="JohnSon, Albert Sidney">JOHNSTON</persName>'S army <q>"strayed"</q> into the herding grounds of the church.</p>

<p> Mr. <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> has had considerable opportunity for observation here, and confirms the declaration that there are large numbers of men and women ready to abandon this community as soon as they see an opportunity 
to do so safely, and to carry with them the means necessary for the long journey to the States. <persName key="Stewart, John M.">JOHN M. STEWART</persName>, one of the counselors of Bishop <persName key="Johnson, Aaron">JOHNSON</persName>, at Springville, attempted to escape to the Army this Spring&#8212;went up one canon towards the East, but lost way, and came down another canon back to <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName> when he was arrested and brought back. For this act of apostacy he was cut off from the Church, and his wife has abandoned him.</p>

<p><persName key="Fabens, William H.">Wm H. FABENS</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salem, MA">Salem</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</placeName>, is
another of the late prisoners of war in the Mormon
hards. He started from <geogName type="waterway" key="Missouri River">the Missouri</geogName> last year with
<persName key="Russell">RUSSELL</persName> &amp; <persName key="Waddell">WADDELL</persName>'S trains, with the intention 
of pushing on to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>. He<cb n="3" />
was with the trains burned on <geogName type="waterway" key="Green River">Green
River</geogName> last October, and arrived in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City">Salt Lake
City</placeName> with his own horses on or about the 21st
of October. Upon his arrival here he went to <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM YOUNG</persName>, told him of his desire to go to <placeName type="state" key=" California">California</placeName>,
and received from him a pass, which stated that he
was a <q>"teamster from the expedition against <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>,"</q>
and requested that he should be permitted to pass
freely. Noticing that the pass was different in form
from others issued by <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>, and which did not
state the former connection of those who held them
with <q>"the enemy,"</q> he was afraid to use it. He
started, however, for <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> by the Southern road,
in company with three others, <persName key="Donahue, James">JAMES DONAHUE</persName>, of <placeName type="county" key="Indiana County, PA">Indiana
County</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Pennsylvania">Penn</placeName>., and two Irishmen who had been
with <persName key="Russell">RUSSELL</persName>'S train, one of them called <persName key="Peter">PETER</persName>, and
the other <persName key="Jimmy">JIMMY</persName>. The party went down to <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>.
Here DONAHUE and <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> stopped a little while to
get feed for their horses, and the Irishman wont or
ahead. When <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> and his companion followed
they found the bodies of the Irishmen only four miles
below the town, lying on the roadside, entirely
stripped of clothing. They returned at once to <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, 
and were told that the murders were committed 
by Indians, but <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> states that he saw no
signs of Indians anywhere in the vicinity. Feeling
unsafe, <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> and <persName key="Donahue">DONAHUE</persName> rode back to <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName> 
hard as they could drive. Finding their horses
broken down they concluded to remain at that place
a while to recruit, so they hired a horse and proceeded 
to keep bachelors' hall. After they had been
here for a fortnight, a Mormon, named <persName key="Daly, Moses">MOSES DALY</persName>,
told <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> that his two sons were going to California, 
and offered to take him through safely if he
would give his horses for the service, and money to
buy provisions for the road. <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> agreed to the
terms, when the <persName key="daub">DAUB</persName> took the horses, sold them
immediately, and then went north to do business as
grain threshers. <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> went to the old man and
demanded the fulfillment of the contract or the value
of his horses. <persName key="Daly, Moses">DALY</persName> told him to hush up or he would
get into difficulty, and that many a man had
had his throat cut for far less than he had
said. From this time <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> found himself
the subject of continued surveillance of a sort of secret 
police. On the 8th of February he escaped
from <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName> and went to <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, from where he
started with the <persName key="Brown">BROWN</persName> alluded to in <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName>'S narrative, 
across the mountains towards <orgName type="military" key="Camp Scott">Camp Scott</orgName>.
In Weber Canon they met <persName key="McNeill">McNEILL</persName> and <persName key="Miles, Charles">CHARLES
MILES</persName>, and proceded together. When within twenty
or thirty miles of Camp, they were taken by the
Mormon outposts and brought back. The party were
entirely without arms, and were without provisions 
during several days. The day subsequent to their
capture, they were taken to the Weber, where they
were detained in a log hut five days. During the 4th
day, <geogName type="Brown" key="">BROWN</geogName>, who being a sort of cripple, was not
watched very closely, slipped out while his guard
were at <q>"evening prayer,</q>"(they forgot the scriptural
injunction to watch, and pray,) and it is understood,
made his way in safety to <orgName type="military" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</orgName>. <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName>
fully confirms the story of McNEILL in various
points, and especially in respect to the robbery and
murder of the young man who boarded with TERRY.
The fact that when the young man's body was found
several days after death, his clothes were still upon
him, presents abundant evidence that he was not
killed by Indians. A Mr. HENLETT, as well as Mr.
WARREN, knew the name of the murdered man, and
are both understood to be able to fasten the crime
upon his Mormon assassin. <persName key="Fabens, Willilam H.">FABENS</persName> was sent south
with McNEILL, shared his fortunes there and returned 
with him. He seems to be a of some education, 
and good natural abilities, but is physical endurance 
has been subjected to a serious test by his 
recent sufferings.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">INHOSPITABLE TREATMENT OF GENTILES</head>
     
<p>We are still living out of doors.  It is evident that
the people are pursuing a system of police, designed
to render the neighborhood unpleasant to the Gentiles.
Thus it is quite impossible yet to hire a room
anywhere.  So universal is this Mormon exhibition
of Christian charity which compels a man to sleep
out of doors who would gladly pay for shelter, that
we are entitled to consider it the result of something
else than accident,&#8212;although <q>"General"</q> <persName key="Ferguson">FERGUSON</persName>
requests me to state that the Church has not issued
any orders to the people directing them to close their
doors upon us.  As he evidently feels that such an
order would reflect discredit upon "the Church," I
wonder if it has occurred to him that an exhortation
to the people to exhibit at least savage hospitality towards
strangers whom they recognize as gentlemen,
would be a more practical method of saving "the
Church" from the suspicion which the General manifests
a desire to avoid.</p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">MISCELLANEOUS <choice><sic>?????</sic><corr>?</corr></choice></head>
     
<p>As Mr. <persName key="Loba, Frederick">FREDERICK LOBA</persName> has been assaulted by some
of your rivals, because of his narrative published in
the <orgName type="newspaper" key="New York Times">TIMES</orgName>, it is but just to him to say that I have
found no man where who ventures to make any specific
charge reflecting upon his character.  The worst
anybody will say of him is that they don't think him
as <q>"smart"</q> a man as he pretends to be,&#8212;but, so far
as I can judge, I have no found his equal here yet,
either in natural intelligence or scholastic acquirements.
I met here, a day or two ago, one of the victims
of the misrepresentations to which Mr. <persName key="Loba, Frederick">LOBA</persName> referred
as being continually made in Europe by the
Mormon missionaries, who assert there that the
ancient power of healing the sick, and the lame and
blind has been fully restored to the Prophets here in
<q>"<geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName>."</q> A young Englishman, affected with
paralysis, and having some little property, was converted 
to the faith, induced to cross the ocean and
traverse the plains to get to this modern pool of
Bethesda, where he fully expected to become whole
again. Of course, he was sadly disappointed.  When
the people went South, he was left here to starve 
and is subsisting now upon the charity of the Peace
Commissioners and others.</p>

<p> I omitted to mention sooner, that one of the causes
which make it difficult for families to leave this community 
after having lived some time in <geogName type="valley" key="Salt Lake Valley">the Valley</geogName>,
arises from the fact that they have no titles to their
lands, and so cannot leave then except by entirely
abandening all their property. The public lands here
have never been sold at all, and no man has a clear.
title to a single foot of it, even in this city. It would
be good policy for the Government to bring these
lands as quickly as possible into the market, issue
patents therefor to those entitled to preemptions
and so make basis for titles. When this is done,
the process of Mormon disintegration will be promoted, 
because dissatisfed Mormons can then set
readily and go away, while their places will often,
be supplied by Gentiles. It certainly is important
that the Federal Government should avail itself of
all proper means of allaying the exclusiveness of the
Mormon element by diffusing as widely as possible
its antidote.</p>

<p>It is not impossible that the will he quite a large
emigration from this region to the Pacific coast before 
Winter, if the road is found to be safe.
The Mormon horsemen, militia and missionaries,
tramping over the country in every direction, have
found a now route to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, which, seems to be a
much better route than any now in use. Its direction
is almost on a bee-line west from this City. It;
distances are estimated as follows :</p>

<p>To Black Rock on: <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>	        18 miles.<lb/>
Thence to <geogName type="valley" key="Scull's Springs Valley">Scull's Springs Valley</geogName>	30 miles.<lb/>
Thence to <geogName type="valley" key="Redding Springs Valley">Redding Springs Valley</geogName>	11 miles<lb/>
Thence to <geogName type="valley" key="March Springs Valley">March Springs Valley</geogName>	        18 miles.<lb/>
Here the road strikes <geogName type="valley" key="Reba Valley">Reba Valley</geogName>, in
  which there is an abundance of wood
  and water all the way down to the sink of
  <geogName type="waterway" key="Humboldt Bay">the Humboldt</geogName>, estimated to be a distance
  of					250 miles.<lb/>
At this point the route strikes the old California 
  road to <placeName type="settlement" key="Carson Valley, NV">Carson Valley</placeName>, supposed
  to be distant about	           50 miles.<lb/>
     Total                         380 miles.</p>

<p> If these estimates prove to be correct upon examination, 
it will be seen that the route hence to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> 
may be shortened nearly one-half, simply by
substituting a direct line for the circuitous one now
in use. It is hoped that the army here will avail
itself of an opportunity to make a satisfactory reconnoissance 
of it.</p>

<p> The new overland mail contracts are doing finely.
The mail which left <placeName type="settlement" key="St. Joseph, MO">St. Joseph's</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Mo.</placeName>, on the 5th of
June, arrived here on the evening of the 24th, nineteen 
and a half days' time, or two and a half less
than that stipulated in the contract. The conductor
states that with the arrangements now completed,
there will be no difficulty in making the time through
regularly in sixteen or eighteen days.	S.</p>
</div2>
 </div1>
 </body>
 </text>
 </TEI>