<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Story of Mormons from the Date of Their Origin to the Year 1901</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename>William</forename> <forename type="middle">Alexander</forename> <surname>Linn</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.anti.linn.1902</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!": The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m">The Story of Mormons from the Date of Their Origin to the Year 1901</title>
                    <author><forename>William</forename> <forename type="middle">Alexander</forename> <surname>Linn</surname></author>
                    <publisher>Macmillan &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
                    <extent>517-534</extent>
                    <date when="1902">1902</date>
                    <note type="source">William Alexander Linn. <hi rend="italic">The Story of Mormons from the Date of Their Origin to the Year 1901</hi>. New York, NY: Macmillan &amp; Co., 1902. 517-534.
                    </note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>anti-mormon_publication</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2010-11-16"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2009"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>
    <div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="517" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.568"/>

<head>CHAPTER XVI</head>
<head>THE MOUNTAIN MEADOWS MASSACRE</head>

<p><hi rend="smallcaps">WE</hi> may here interrupt the narrative of events subsequent to the restoration of peace in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName>, with the story of the most horrible massacre of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">white people</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSZealots">by religious fanatics</seg> of their own race that has been recorded since that famous St. Bartholemew's night in Paris&#8212; the story of the Mountain Meadows Massacre. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Committed on Friday, September 11, 1857, &#8212; four days before the date of <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s proclamation forbidding the United States troops to enter <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName></seg> &#8212;</seg> it was a considerable time before more than vague rumors of the crime reached the Eastern states. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">No inquest or other investigation was held by Mormon authority</seg>, no person participating in the slaughter was arrested by a Mormon officer; and, <seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">when officers of the federal government first visited the scene, in the spring of 1859, all that remained to tell the tale were human skulls and other bones lying where the wolves and coyotes had left them, with scraps of clothing caught here and there upon the vines and bushes. Dr. <persName key="Brewer, Charles">Charles Brewer</persName>, the assistant army surgeon who was sent with a detail to bury the remains in May, 1859, says in his grewsome report:</seg></seg>&#8212;</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">"I reached a ravine fifty yards from the road, in which I found portions of the skeletons of many bodies,&#8212;skulls, bones, and matted hair, &#8212; most of which, on examination, I concluded to be those of men. Three hundred and fifty yards further on another assembly of human remains was found, which, by all appearance, had been left to decay upon the surface; skulls and bones, most of which I believed to be those of women, some also of children, probably ranging from six to twelve years of age. Here, too, were found masses of women's hair, children's bonnets, such as are generally used upon the plains, and pieces of lace, muslin, calicoes, and other materials. Many of the skulls bore marks of violence, being pierced with bullet holes, or shattered by heavy blows, or cleft with some sharp-edged instrument."</seg><ref target="n0001">1</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n0001">1 Sen. Doc. No. .42, 1st Session, 36th Congress.</note>

<pb n="518" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.569"/>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">More than seventeen years passed before officers of the United States succeeded in securing the needed evidence against any of the persons responsible for these wholesale murders, and a jury which would bring in a verdict of guilty.</seg> Then a single Mormon paid the penalty of his crime. He died asserting that he was the one victim surrendered by the Mormon church to appease the public demand for justice. The closest students of the Mountain Meadows Massacre and of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s rule will always give the most credence to this statement of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>. Indeed, to acquit <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> of responsibility for this crime, it would be necessary to prove that the sermons and addresses in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Discourses</hi> are forgeries.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">In the summer of 1857</seg> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">a party was <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">made up in <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg> to cross the plains to Southern <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> by way of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">under direction of a Captain <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName>.<ref target="n0002">1</ref> This party differed from most emigrant parties of the day both in character and equipment. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">It numbered some thirty families, &#8212; about 140 individuals, &#8212; men, women, and children.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">They were people of means, several of them travelling in private carriages, and their equipment included thirty horses and mules, and about six hundred head of cattle</seg>, when they arrived in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. Most of them seem to have been Methodists, and they had a preacher of that denomination with them. Prayers were held in camp every night and morning, and they never travelled on Sundays. They did not hurry on, as the gold-seekers were wont to do in those days, but made their trip one of pleasure, sparing themselves and their animals, and enjoying the beauties and novelties of the route.</seg><ref target="n0003">2</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n0002">1 <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName> says that travelling the same route, and encamping near <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansans</seg>, was <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">a company from <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName></seg> who called themselves "Missouri Wildcats," and who were so boisterous that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansans</seg> were warned not to travel with them to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. <persName key="Whitney, Orson F.">Whitney</persName> says that the two parties travelled several days apart after leaving <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. No mention of <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">a separate company of Missourians</seg> appears in the official and court reports of the massacre.</note>

<note xml:id="n0003">2 <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName>, in his official report, says that he made the most careful inquiry regarding the conduct of the emigrants after they entered <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName>, and could testify "that the company conducted themselves with propriety." In the years immediately following the massacre, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">when the Mormons were trying to attribute the crime to Indians</seg>, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">much was said about the party having poisoned a spring and caused the death of Indians and their cattle. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> found that one ox did die near their camp, but that its death was caused by a poisonous weed.</seg> Whitney, the church historian, who of course acquits the church of any responsibility for the massacre, draws a very black picture of the emigrants, saying, for instance, that at Cedar Creek "their customary proceeding of burning fences, whipping the heads off chickens, or shooting them in the streets or private door yards, to the extreme danger of the inhabitants, was continued. One of them, a blustering fellow riding a gray horse, flourished his pistol in the face of the wife of one of the citizens, all the time making insulting proposals and uttering profane threats."</seg>&#8212;"History of Utah," Vol. I, p. 696.</note>

<pb n="519" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.570"/>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Every emigrant train for <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> then expected to restock in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">The Mormons had profited by this traffic, and such a thing as non-intercourse with travellers in the way of trade was as yet unheard of.</seg> But <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> was now defying the government, and his proclamation of September 15 had declared that "no person shall be allowed to pass or repass into or through or from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this territory</placeName> without a permit from the proper officer."</seg> To a constituency made up so largely of dishonest members, high and low, as <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> himself conceded the Mormon body politic to be, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">the outfit of these travellers was very attractive</seg>. There was a motive, too, in inflicting punishment on them, merely because <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">they were Arkansans</seg>, and the motive was this: &#8212;</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder"><persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley P. Pratt</persName> was sent to explore a southern route from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> in 1849. He reached <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName> from <placeName type="settlement" key="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</placeName> in the summer of 1851, remaining there until June, 1855. <seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">He was a fanatical defender of polygamy after its open proclamation, challenging debate on the subject in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, and issuing circulars calling on the people to repent as "the Kingdom of God has come nigh unto you."</seg> While in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> induced <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor">the wife</persName> of <persName key="McLean, Hector">Hector H. McLean</persName>, a custom-house official, the mother of three children, to accept the Mormon faith and to elope with him to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> as his ninth wife. The children were sent to her parents in <placeName type="state" key="Louisiana">Louisiana</placeName> by their father, and there she sometime later obtained them, after pretending that she had abandoned the Mormon belief. When <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> learned of this he went East, and traced his wife and <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> to <placeName type="settlement" key="Houston, TX">Houston</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Texas">Texas</placeName>, and thence to Fort Gibson, near <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>. There he had <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> arrested, but there seemed to be no law under which he could be held. As soon as <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> was released, he left the place on horse-back. <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName>, who had found letters from <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> to his wife at Fort Gibson which increased his feeling against the man,<ref target="n0004">1</ref> followed him on horseback for eight miles, and then, overtaking him, shot him so that he died in two hours.<ref target="n0005">2</ref> It was in accordance with</seg>

<note xml:id="n0004">1 <hi rend="italic">Van Buren Intelligencer</hi>, May 15, 1857</note>

<note xml:id="n0005">2 See the story in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> of May 28, 1857, copied from the <hi rend="italic">St. Louis Democrat</hi> and <hi rend="italic">St. Louis Republican</hi>.</note>

<pb n="520" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.571"/>

<seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">Mormon policy to hold every Arkansan accountable for <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName>'s death</seg>, <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">just as every Missourian was hated because of the expulsion of the church from that state</seg>.</p>

<p><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">When the company pitched camp on the river Jordan their food supplies were nearly exhausted, and their draught animals needed rest and a chance to recuperate. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">They knew nothing of the disturbed relations between the Mormons and the government when they set out, and they were astonished now to be told that they must break camp and move on southward. But they obeyed.</seg> At <placeName type="settlement" key="American Fork, UT">American Fork</placeName>, the next settlement, they offered some of their worn-out animals in exchange for fresh ones, and visited the town to buy provisions. There was but one answer&#8212;nothing to sell. Southward they continued, through <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Payson, UT">Payson</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Creek, UT">Salt Creek</placeName>, and <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, at all settlements making the same effort to purchase the food of which they stood in need, and at all receiving the same reply.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeIndian">So much were their supplies now reduced that they hastened on until Corn Creek was reached; there they did obtain a little relief, some Indians selling them about thirty bushels of corn.</seg> But at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, a larger place, non-intercourse was again proclaimed, and at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, through which led the road built by the general government, they were forbidden to pass over this directly through the town, and the local mill would not even grind their own corn. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">At Cedar Creek, one of the largest southern settlements, they were allowed to buy fifty bushels of wheat, and to have it and their corn ground at <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>'s mill.</seg> After a day's delay they started on, but so worn out were their animals that it took them three days to reach Iron Creek, twenty miles beyond, and two more days to reach <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, fifteen miles farther south.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">These "meadows" are a valley, 350 miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, about five miles long by one wide. They are surrounded by mountains, and narrow at the lower end to a width of 400 yards, where a gap leads out to the desert. A large spring near this gap made that spot a natural resting-place, and there the emigrants pitched their camp.</seg> Had they been in any way suspicious of Indian treachery they would not have stopped there, because, from the elevations on either side, they were subject to rifle fire. Their anxiety, however, was not about the Indians, whom they had

<pb n="521" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.572"/>

found friendly, but about the problem of making the trip of seventy days to <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, across a desert country, with their worn-out animals and their scant supplies. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Had Mormon cruelty taken only the form of withholding provisions and forage from this company, its effect would have satisfied their most evil wishers.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">On the morning of Monday, September 7</seg>, still unsuspicious of any form of danger, their camp was suddenly fired upon <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">by Indians</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">(and probably by some white men disguised as Indians)</seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Seven of the emigrants were killed in this attack and sixteen were wounded.</seg> Unexpected as was this manifestation of hostility, the company was too well organized to be thrown into a panic. The fire was returned, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one Indian was killed, and two chiefs fatally wounded.</seg> The wagons were corralled at once as a sort of fortification, and the wheels were chained together. In the centre of this corral a rifle pit was dug, large enough to hold all their people, and in this way they were protected from shots fired at them from either side of the valley. In this little fort they successfully defended themselves during that and the ensuing three days. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Not doubting that Indians were their only assailants</seg>, two of their number succeeded in escaping from the camp on a mission to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> to ask for assistance. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">These messengers were met by three Mormons, who shot one of them dead, and wounded the other; the latter seems to have made his way back to the camp.</seg></seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">The Arkansans</seg> soon suffered for water, as the spring was a hundred yards distant. Two of them during one day made a dash, carrying buckets, and got back with them safely, under a heavy fire.</seg><ref target="n0006">1</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">With some re&#235;nforcements from the south, the Indians now numbered about four hundred. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">They shot down some seventy head of the emigrants' cattle</seg>, and on Wednesday evening made another attack in force on the camp, but were repulsed. Still another attack the next morning had the same result. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">This determined resistance upset the plans of the Mormons who had instigated the Indian attacks. They had expected that the travellers would be overcome in the first surprise, and that their butchery would easily be</seg></seg></seg>

<note xml:id="n0006">1 <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> denies positively a story that the Mormons shot <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">two little girls who were dressed in white and sent out for water</seg>. He says that when <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansans</seg> saw a white man in the valley (<persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> himself) they ran up a white flag and sent two little boys to talk with him; that he refused to see them, as he was then awaiting orders, and that <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">he kept the Indians from shooting them</seg>.</seg></seg> "Mormonism Unveiled," p. 231.</note>

<pb n="522" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.573"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">accounted for as the result of an Indian raid on their camp.</seg> But they were not to be balked of their object. To save themselves from the loss of life that would be entailed by a charge on <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansans'</seg> defences, they resorted to a scheme of the most deliberate treachery.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">On Friday, the 11th</seg>, a Mormon named <persName key="Bateman, William">William Bateman</persName> was sent forward with a flag of truce. The other undisguised Mormons remained in concealment, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">the Indians had been instructed to keep entirely out of sight.</seg> The beleaguered company were delighted to see a white man, and at once sent one of their number to meet him. Their ammunition was almost exhausted, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">their dead were unburied in their midst</seg>, and their situation was desperate. <persName key="Bateman, William">Bateman</persName>, following out his instructions, told the representative of the emigrants that the Mormons had come to their assistance, and that, if they would place themselves in the white men's hands and follow directions, they would be conducted in safety to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, there to await a proper opportunity for proceeding on their journey.<ref target="n0007">1</ref> This plan was agreed to without any delay, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was directed by <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName>, major of the Iron Militia, and chief in command of the Mormon party, to go to the camp to see that the plot agreed upon was carried out, <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">Samuel McMurdy</persName> and <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Samuel Knight</persName> following him with two wagons which were a part of the necessary equipment.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">Never had a man been called upon to perform a more dastardly part than that which was assigned to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>. Entering the camp of the beleaguered people as their friend, he was to induce them to abandon their defences, give up all their weapons, separate the adults from the children and wounded, who were to be placed in the wagons, and then, at a given signal, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">every one of the party was to be killed</seg> by the white men who walked by their sides as their protectors. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> draws a picture of his feelings on entering the camp which ought to be correct, even if circumstances lead one to attribute it to the pen of a man who naturally wished to find some extenuation for himself: "I doubt the power of man being equal to even imagine how wretched I felt. No language can describe my feelings. My position was painful, trying, and awful; my brain seemed to be on fire; my nerves were for a moment unstrung; humanity was overpowering as I thought of</seg></seg>

<note xml:id="n0007">1 This account follows <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s confession, "Mormonism Unveiled," p. 236 ff.</note>

<pb n="523" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.574"/>

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">the cruel, unmanly part that I was acting. Tears of bitter anguish fell in streams from my eyes; my tongue refused its office; my faculties were dormant, stupefied and deadened by grief. I wished that the earth would open and swallow me where I stood."</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">When <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> entered the camp <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">all the people, men, women, and children</seg>, gathered around him, some delighted over the hope of deliverance, while others showed distrust of his intentions. Their position was so strong that they felt some hesitation in abandoning it, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says that, if their ammunition had not been so nearly exhausted, they would never have surrendered. But their hesitation was soon overcome, and the carrying out of the plot proceeded.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">All their arms, the wounded, and the smallest children were placed in the two wagons. As soon as these were loaded, a messenger from <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, named <persName key="McFarland, Daniel">McFarland</persName>, rode up with a message that everything should be hastened, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">as he feared he could not hold back the Indians</seg>. The wagons were then started at once toward <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and the two drivers accompanying them, and the others of the party set out on foot for the place where the Mormon troops were awaiting them, some two hundred yards distant. First went <persName key="McFarland, Daniel">McFarland</persName> on horseback, then <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the women and larger children</seg>, and then <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the men</seg>. When, in this order, they came to the place where the Mormons were stationed, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the men of the party</seg> cheered the latter as their deliverers.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">As the wagons passed out of sight over an elevation, the march of the rest of the party was resumed. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The women and larger children walked ahead, then came the men in single file</seg>, an armed Mormon walking by the side of <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">each Arkansan</seg>. This gave the appearance of the best possible protection. When they had advanced far enough to bring the women and children <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">into the midst of a company of Indians concealed in a growth of cedars</seg>, the agreed signal &#8212; the words, "Do your duty" &#8212; was given. As these words were spoken, each Mormon turned and shot <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansan</seg> who was walking by his side, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">Indians</seg> and other Mormons attacked <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the women and children who were walking ahead</seg>, while <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and his two companions killed <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the wounded and the older of the children who were in the wagons</seg>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The work of killing the men was performed so effectually that only two or three of them escaped, and these were overtaken and

<pb n="524" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.575"/>

killed soon after.</seg><ref target="n0008">1</ref> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Indeed, only the nervousness natural to men who were assigned to perform so horrible a task could prevent the murderers from shooting dead the unarmed men walking by their sides. With the women and children it was different. Instead of being shot down without warning, they first heard the shots that killed their only protectors, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">then beheld the Indians rushing on them with their usual whoops, brandishing tomahawks, knives, and guns</seg>. There were cries for mercy, mothers' pleas for children's lives, and maidens' appeals to manly honor; but all in vain. It was not necessary to use firearms; indeed, they would have endangered the assailants themselves. The tomahawk and the knife sufficed, and in the space of a few moments every woman and older child was a corpse.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">When <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and the men in charge of the two wagons heard the firing, they halted at once, as this was the signal agreed on for them to perform their part. <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName>'s wagon, containing the sick and wounded and the little children, was in advance, <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName>'s, with a few passengers and the weapons, following. We have three accounts of what happened when the signal was given, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s own, and the testimony of the other two at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s trial. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says that <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> at once went up to <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName>'s wagon, and, raising his rifle and saying, "O Lord my God, receive their spirits; it is for Thy Kingdom I do this," fired, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">killing two men with the first shot</seg>. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> admits that he intended to do his part of the killing, but says that in his excitement his pistol went off prematurely and narrowly escaped wounding <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName>; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">that <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName> then shot one man, and with the butt of his gun brained a little boy who had run up to him, and that the Indians then came up and finished killing all the sick and wounded. <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> testified that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> killed the first person in his wagon &#8212; a woman &#8212; and also shot two or three others. When asked if he himself killed any one that day, <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> replied, "I believe I am not upon trial. I don't wish to answer."</seg></seg>

<note xml:id="n0008">1 This is Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>'s and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> said he could have given the details of their pursuit and capture if he had had time. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">An affidavit by <persName key="Lynch, James">James Lynch</persName>, who accompanied Superintendent <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> on his first trip there in March-1859 (printed in Sen. Doc. No. 42), says that one of the three, who was not killed on the spot, "was followed by five Mormons who, through promises of safety, etc., prevailed upon him to return to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, where they inhumanly butchered him, laughing at and disregarding his loud and repeated cries for mercy, as witnessed and described by <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Ira Hatch</persName>, one of the five. The object of killing this man was to leave no witness competent to give testimony in a court of justice but God."</seg></seg></note>

<pb n="525" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.576"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName> testified that he saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> strike down a woman with his gun or a club, denying that he himself took any part in the slaughter. <persName key="Johnson, Nephi">Nephi Johnson</persName>, another witness at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s second trial, testified that he saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and an Indian pull a man out of one of the wagons, and he thought <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> cut the man's throat.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The only persons spared in this whole company were seventeen children, varying in age from two months to seven years. They were given to Mormon families in southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> &#8212;"sold out," says <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> in his report, "to different persons in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, Harmony, and Painter Creek. Bills are now in my possession from different individuals asking payment from the government. I cannot condescend to become the medium of even transmitting such claims to the department." The government directed <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> in 1858 to collect these children, and he did so. Congress in 1859 appropriated $10,000 to defray the expense of returning them to their friends in <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, and on June 27 of that year fifteen of them (two boys being retained as government witnesses) set out for the East from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> in charge of a company of United States dragoons and five women attendants. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> quotes one of these children, a boy less than nine years old, as saying in his presence, when they were brought to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, "Oh, I wish I was a man. I know what I would do. I would shoot <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>. I saw him shoot my mother."</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The total number in <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> party</seg> is not exactly known. The victims numbered more than 120. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils"><persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName> testified at the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> trial that, the following spring, he and his man buried "120 odd" skulls, counting them as they gathered them up.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">A few young women, in the confusion of the Indian attack, concealed themselves, but they were soon found. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> testified at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s second trial that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in a long conversation with him, soon after the massacre, told him that, when he rejoined the Mormon troops, an Indian chief brought to him two girls from thirteen to fifteen years old, whom he had found hiding in a thicket, and asked what should be done with them, as they were pretty and he wanted to save them. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> replied that "according to the orders he had, they were too old and too big to let go." Then by <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s direction the chief shot one of them, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> threw the other down and cut her throat. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> said that an Indian boy conducted him to the place where the girls' bodies lay,

<pb n="526" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.577"/>

a long way from the rest, up a ravine, unburied and with their throats cut.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">One of the little children saved from the massacre was taken home by <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName></seg>, and she said the murdered girls were her sisters. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="SexualViolence"><persName key="Burton, Richard F.">Richard F. Burton</persName>, who visited <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> in 1860, mentions, as one of the current stories in connection with the massacre, that, when a girl of sixteen knelt before one of the Mormons and prayed for mercy, he led her into the thicket, violated her, and then cut her throat.</seg></seg></seg><ref target="n0009">1</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">As soon as the slaughter was completed the plundering began. Beside their wagons, horses, and cattle,<ref target="n0010">2</ref> they had a great deal of other valuable property, the whole being estimated by Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> at from $60,000 to $70,000. When <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> got back to the main party, the searching of the bodies of the men for valuables began. "I did hold the hat awhile," he confesses, "but I got so sick that I had to give it to some other person." <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">He says there were more than five hundred head of cattle, a large number of which the Indians killed or drove away</seg>, while <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, leaders in the enterprise, drove others to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> and sold them. The horses and mules were divided in the same way.<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"> The Indians (and probably their white comrades) had made quick work with the effects of the women.</seg></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Their bodies, young and old, were stripped naked, and left, objects of the ribald jests of their murderers.</seg> <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says that in one place he counted the bodies of ten children less than sixteen years old.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">When the Mormons had finished rifling the dead</seg>, <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">all were called together and admonished by their chiefs to keep the massacre a secret from the whole world, not even letting their wives know of it, and all took the most solemn oath to stand by one another</seg> and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">declare that the killing was the work of Indians</seg>. Most of the party camped that night on <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, but <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> passed the night at <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>'s ranch.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">In the morning the Mormons went back to bury the dead. All these lay naked, "making the scene," says <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, "one of the most loathsome and ghastly that can be imagined." The bodies were</seg>

<note xml:id="n0009">1 "City of the Saints," p. 412.</note>

<note xml:id="n0010">2 <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Superintendent <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>, in his report of March, 1859, said: "Facts in my possession warrant me in estimating that there was distributed a few days after the massacre, among the leading church dignitaries, $30,000 worth of property. It is presumable they also had some money."</seg></note>

<pb n="527" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.578"/>

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">piled up in heaps in little depressions, and a pretence was made of covering them with dirt; but the ground was hard and their murderers had few tools, and as a consequence the wild beasts soon unearthed them, and the next spring the bones were scattered over the surface.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">This work finished, the party, who had been joined during the night by Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, Judge <persName key="Lewis, James">Lewis</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, and others of influence, held another council, at which God was thanked for delivering their enemies into their hands; <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">another oath of secrecy was taken, and all voted that any person who divulged the story of the massacre should suffer death</seg>, but that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> should be informed of it. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">It was also voted, according to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, that Bishop <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> should take charge of the plunder for the benefit of the church.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The story of this slaughter, to this point, except in minor particulars noted, is undisputed. No Mormon now denies that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the emigrants</seg> were killed, or that Mormons participated largely in the slaughter. What the church authorities have sought to establish has been their own ignorance of it in advance, and their condemnation of it later. In examining this question we have, to assist us, the knowledge of the kind of government that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> had established over his people &#8212; his practical power of life and death; the fact that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansans</seg> were passing south <hi rend="italic">from</hi> <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, and that their movements had been known to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> from the start and their treatment been subject to his direction; the failure of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> to make any effort to have the murderers punished, when a "crook of his finger" would have given them up to justice; <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">the coincidence of the massacre with <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s threat to Captain <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName>, uttered on September 9, "If the issue continues, you may tell the government to stop all emigration across the continent, for the Indians will kill all who attempt it"</seg>; <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence"><persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s failure to mention this "Indian outrage" in his report as superintendent of Indian affairs, and the silence of the Mormon press on the subject.</seg><ref target="n0011">1</ref> If we accept <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s plausible theory that, at his second trial, the church gave him up as a sop to justice, and loosened the tongues of witnesses against him, this makes that</seg>

<note xml:id="n0011">1 <persName key="Bancroft, Hubert Howe">H. H. Bancroft</persName>, in his "Utah," as usual, defends the Mormon church against the charge of responsibility for the massacre, and calls Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>'s charge to the grand jury a slur that the evidence did not excuse.</note>

<pb n="528" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.579"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">part of the testimony in confirmation of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement, elicited from them, all the stronger.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Let us recall that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> himself had been an active member of the church for nearly forty years, following it from <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, travelling penniless as a missionary at the bidding of his superiors, <seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">becoming a polygamist before he left <placeName type="settlement" key="Nauvoo, IL">Nauvoo</placeName></seg>, accepting in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> the view that "<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> spoke by direction of the God of heaven," and saying, as he stood by his coffin looking into the rifles of his executioners, "I believe in the Gospel that was taught in its purity by <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Joseph Smith</persName> in former days." How much <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> trusted him is seen in the fact that, by <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s direction, he located the southern towns of <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key=" Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, etc., was appointed captain of militia at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, was president of civil affairs at <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, probate judge of the county (before and after the massacre), a delegate to the convention which framed the constitution of the State of Deseret, a member of the territorial legislature (after the massacre), and <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">"Indian farmer" of the district including <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> when the massacre occurred.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s account of the steps leading up to the massacre and of what followed is, in brief, that, about ten days before it occurred, General <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, one of the Twelve, called on him at <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington City, UT">Washington City</placeName>, and, in the course of their conversation, asked, <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">"Suppose an emigrant train should come along through this southern country, making threats against our people and bragging of the part they took in helping kill our prophet, what do you think the brethren would do with them?"</seg> <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> replied: <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSReformation">"You know the brethren are now under the influence of the 'Reformation,' and are still red-hot for the Gospel.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The brethren believe the government wishes to destroy them.</seg> I really believe that any train of emigrants that may come through here will be attacked and probably all destroyed. Unless emigrants have a pass from <persName key="Young, Brigham"><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName></persName> or some one in authority, they will certainly never get safely through this country." <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Smith</persName> said that Major <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> had given him the same assurance. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">It was <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s belief that <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Smith</persName> had been sent south in advance of the emigrants to prepare for what followed.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Two days before the first attack on the camp, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was summoned to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac Haight</persName>, president of that Stake, second only to Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> in church authority in southern

<pb n="529" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.580"/>

<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and a lieutenant colonel in the militia under <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>. To make their conference perfectly secret, they took some blankets and passed the night in an old iron works. <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">There <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> told <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> a long story about Captain <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName>'s party, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">charging them with abusing the Mormons</seg>, burning fences, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">poisoning water</seg>, <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">threatening to kill <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and all the apostles, etc.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">He said that unless preventive measures were taken, the whole Mormon population were likely to be butchered by troops which these people would bring back from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>.</seg></seg> <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says that he believed all this. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">He was also told that, at a council held that day, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">it had been decided to arm the Indians and "have them give the emigrants a brush, and, if they killed part or all, so much the better.</seg>" When asked who authorized this, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> replied, "It is the will of all in authority," and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was told that he was to carry out the order. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The intention then was to have the Indians do the killing without any white assistance.</seg></seg></seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">On his way home <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> met a large body of Indians who said they were ordered by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, and Bishop <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, to kill and rob the emigrants, and wanted <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> to lead them. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">He told them to camp near the emigrants and wait for him; but they made the attack, as described, early Monday morning, without capturing the camp, and drove the whites into an intrenchment from which they could not dislodge them. Hence the change of plan.</seg></seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">During the early part of the operations, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says, a messenger had been sent to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> for orders. On Thursday evening two or three wagon loads of Mormons, all armed, arrived at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s camp in <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, the party including Major <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> of the Iron Militia, Bishop <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, and many members of the High Council. When all were assembled, Major <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> reported that <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>'s orders were that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">"all the emigrants must be put out of the way"</seg>; that they had no pass (<persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> could have given them one); <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">that they were really a part of <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnson</persName>'s army, and, if allowed to proceed to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, they would bring destruction on all the settlements in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</seg> All knelt in prayer, after which <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> gave <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> a paper ordering the destruction of all who could talk. After further prayers, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> said to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, "Brother <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, I am ordered by President <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> to inform you that you shall receive a crown of celestial glory for your faithfulness, and your eternal joy shall be complete." <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says that he was "much shaken" by this offer,

<pb n="530" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.581"/>

because of his complete faith in the power of the priesthood to fulfil such promises. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">The outcome of the conference was the adoption of the plan of treachery that was so successfully carried out on Friday morning.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">The council had lasted so long that the party merely had time for breakfast before <persName key="Bateman, William">Bateman</persName> set out for the camp with his white flag.</seg></seg><ref target="n0012">1</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Several days after the massacre, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> told <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> that the messenger sent to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> for instructions had returned with orders to let the emigrants pass in safety, and that he (<persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>) had countermanded the order for the massacre, but his messenger "did not go to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> at all." All parties were evidently beginning to realize the seriousness of their crime. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was then directed by the council to go to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> with a verbal report, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> again promising him a celestial reward if he would implicate no more of the brethren than necessary in his talk with <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>.<ref target="n0013">2</ref> On reaching <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> gave <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> the full particulars of the massacre, step by step. <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> remarked, "<persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac [Haight]</persName> has sent me word that, <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">if they had killed every man, woman, and child in the outfit, there would not have been a drop of innocent blood shed by the brethren; for they were a set of murderers, robbers, and thieves.</seg>"</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">When the tale was finished, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> said: "This is the most unfortunate affair that ever befell the church. I am afraid of treachery among the brethren who were there. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">If any one tells</seg></seg>

<note xml:id="n0012">1 <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Bishop <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, one of the indicted, in whose case the district attorney entered a nolle prosequi in order that he might be a witness at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s first trial, said in his testimony: "Coming home the day following their [emigrants'] departure from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, met <persName key="Allen, Ira">Ira Allen</persName> four miles beyond the place where they had spoken to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>. <persName key="Allen, Ira">Allen</persName> said, 'The die is cast, the doom of the emigrants is sealed.'" (This was in reference to a meeting in <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, when the destruction of the emigrants had been decided on.) "He said <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> had received orders from headquarters at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> to take men and go, and <persName key="White, Joel">Joel White</persName> would be wanted to go to Pinto Creek and revoke the order to suffer the emigrants to pass. The third day after, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> came to <persName key="McFarland, Daniel">McFarland</persName>'s house and told witness and others that orders had come in from camp last night. Things hadn't gone along as had been expected, and renforcements were wanted. <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> then went to <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> to get instructions, and received orders from <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">to decoy the emigrants out</seg> and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">spare nothing</seg> but the small children who could not tell the tale</seg>." In an affidavit made by this Bishop in April, 1871, he said: "I do not know whether said 'headquarters' meant the spiritual headquarters at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, or the headquarters of the commander-in-chief at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>."</seg> (Affidavit in full in "Rocky Mountain Saints," p. 439.)</note>

<note xml:id="n0013">2 <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">"At that time I believed everything he said, and I fully expected to receive the celestial reward that he promised me. But now [after his conviction] I say, ' Damn all such celestial rewards as I am to get for what I did on that fatal day.'"</seg>&#8212;"Mormonism Unveiled," p. 251.</note>

<pb n="531" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.582"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">this thing so that it will become public, it will work us great injury. I want you to understand now that you are <hi rend="italic">never</hi> to tell this again, not even to <persName key="Kimball, Heber C.">Heber C. Kimball</persName>. <hi rend="italic">It must</hi> be kept a secret among ourselves. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">When you get home, I want you to sit down and write a long letter, and give me an account of the affair, charging it to the Indians. You sign the letter as farmer to the Indians, and direct it to me as Indian agent. I can then make use of such a letter to keep off all damaging and troublesome inquirers." <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> did so, and his letter was put in evidence at his trial.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> then dismissed him for the day, directing him to call again the next morning, and that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> then said to him: "I have made that matter a subject of prayer. I went right to God with it, and asked him to take the horrid vision from my sight if it was a righteous thing that my people had done in killing those people <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>. God answered me, and at once the vision was removed. I have evidence from God that he has overruled it all for good, and the action was a righteous one and well intended."</seg><ref target="n0014">1</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">When <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> as a member of the constitutional convention, the next winter, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> treated him, at his house and elsewhere, with all the friendliness of old. No one conversant with the extent of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s authority will doubt the correctness of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement that "if <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> had wanted one man or fifty men or five hundred men arrested, all he would have had to do would be to say so, and they would have been arrested instantly. There was no escape for them if he ordered their arrest. Every man who knows anything of affairs in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> at that time knows this is so."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">At the second trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> a deposition by <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> was read, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> pleading ill health as an excuse for not taking the stand. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">He admitted that "counsel and advice were given to the citizens not to sell grain to the emigrants for their stock," but asserted that this did not include food for the parties themselves.</seg> He also admitted that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> called on him and began telling the story of the massacre, but asserted that he directed him to stop, as he did not want his feelings harrowed up with a recital of these details. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">He gave as an excuse for not bringing the guilty to </seg></seg><choice><orig>jus-

<note xml:id="n0014">1 For <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s account of his interview with <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, see "Mormonism Unveiled," pp. 252-254.</note>

<pb n="532" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.583"/>

tice</orig><reg>justice</reg></choice><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">, or at least making an investigation, the fact that a new governor was on his way, and he did not know how soon he would arrive.</seg> As <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> himself was keeping this governor out by armed force, and declaring that he alone should fill that place, the value of his excuse can be easily estimated. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>, at <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s trial, testified that he told <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName> "everything I could" about the massacre, and that <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence"><persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> said to him, "As soon as we can get a court of justice we will ferret this thing out, but till then don't say anything about it."</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Both <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName> and <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurphy</persName> testified that they took their teams <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg> under compulsion. <persName key="Johnson, Nephi">Nephi Johnson</persName>, another participant, when asked whether he acted under compulsion, replied, "I didn't consider it safe for me to object," and when compelled to answer the question whether any person had ever been injured for not obeying such orders, he replied, "Yes, sir, they had."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Some letters published in the <hi rend="italic">Corinne</hi> (<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>) <hi rend="italic">Reporter</hi>, in the early seventies, signed <persName key="Wandell, Charles W.">"Argus,"</persName> directly accused <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> of responsibility for this massacre. <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName> discovered that the author had been for thirty years a Mormon, a high priest in the church, a holder of responsible civil positions in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName>, and he assured <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName> that "before a federal court of justice, where he could be protected, he was prepared to give the evidence of all that he asserted." <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><persName key="Wandell, Charles W.">"Argus"</persName> declared that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">when <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansans</seg> set out southward from the Jordan, a courier preceded them carrying <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s orders for non-intercourse; that they were directed to go around <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName></seg> because it was feared that the military preparations at that place, Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>'s headquarters, might arouse their suspicion; and he points out that the troops who killed the emigrants were called out and prepared for field operations, just as the territorial law directed, and were subject to the orders of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, their commander-in-chief.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Not until the so-called Poland Bill of 1874 became a law was any one connected with the Mountain Meadows Massacre even indicted. Then the grand jury, under direction of Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName>, of the Second Judicial District of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, found indictments against <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, and others. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, who had remained hidden for some years in the canon of the Colorado,</seg><ref target="n0015">1</ref>

<note xml:id="n0015">1 <persName key="Inman, Henry">Inman</persName>'s "Great Salt Lake Trail" p. 141.</note>

<pb n="533" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.584"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">was reported to be in south <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> at the time, and Deputy United States Marshal <persName key="stokes, William">Stokes</persName>, to whom the warrant for his arrest was given, set out to find him. <persName key="stokes, William">Stokes</persName> was told that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had gone back to his hiding-place, but one of his assistants located the accused in the town of <placeName type="settlement" key="Panguitch, UT">Panguitch</placeName>, and there they found him concealed in a log pen near a house. His trial began at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, on July 12, 1875. The first jury to try his case disagreed, after being out three days, eight Mormons and the Gentile foreman voting for acquittal, and three Gentiles for conviction. The second trial, which took place at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, in September, 1876, resulted in a verdict of "guilty of murder in the first degree." <persName key="Beadle, John H.">Beadle</persName> says of the interest which the church then took in his conviction: "<persName key="Wells, Daniel H.">Daniel H. Wells</persName> went to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, furnished some new evidence, coached the witnesses, attended to the spiritual wants of the jury, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was convicted. He could not raise the money ($1000) necessary to appeal to the Supreme Court of the United States, although he solicited it by subscription from wealthy leading Mormons for several days under guard."</seg><ref target="n0016">1</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Criminals in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> convicted of a capital crime were shot, and this was <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s fate. It was decided that the execution should take place at the scene of the massacre, and there the sentence of the court was carried out on March 23, 1877. The coffin was made of rough pine boards after the arrival of the prisoner, and while he sat looking at the workmen a short distance away. When all the arrangements were completed, the marshal read the order of the court and gave <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> an opportunity to speak. A photographer being ready to take a picture of the scene, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> asked that a copy of the photograph be given to each of three of his wives, naming them. He then stood up, having been seated on his coffin, and spoke quietly for some time. He said that he was sacrificed to satisfy the feelings of others; that he died "a true believer in the Gospel of Jesus Christ," but did not believe everything then taught by <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>. He asserted that he "did nothing designedly wrong in this unfortunate affair," but did everything in his power to save the emigrants. Five executioners then stepped forward, and, when their rifles exploded, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> fell dead on his coffin.</seg></p>

<p>Major (afterward General) <persName key="Carleton, John Henry">Carlton</persName>, returning from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>

<note xml:id="n0016">1 "Polygamy," p. 507.</note>

<pb n="534" xml:id="mmm.anti.linn.1902.585"/>

in 1859, where he had escorted <persName key="Prince, Henry">a paymaster</persName>, passed through <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, and, <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">finding many bones of the victims still scattered around</seg>, gathered them, and erected over them a cairn of stones, on one of which he had engraved the words: "Here lie the bones of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">120 men, women, and children</seg> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, murdered <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">on the 10th day of September, 1857</seg>." In the centre of the cairn was placed a beam, some fifteen feet high, with a cross-tree, on which was painted: "Vengeance is mine, saith the Lord, and I will repay it." It was said that this was removed by order of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>.</seg><ref target="n0017">1</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n0017">1 <seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">"Humiliating as it is to confess, in the 42d Congress there were gentlemen to be found in the committees of the House and in the Senate who were bold enough to declare their opposition to all investigation. One who had a national reputation during the war, from Bunker Hill to <placeName type="settlement" key="New Orleans, LA">New Orleans</placeName>, was not ashamed to say to those who sought the legislation that was necessary to make investigation possible, that it was 'too late.'&#8212;"</seg> Rocky Mountain Saints," p. 456.</note>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>