<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.dac.18571027">
    <teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
	    <titleStmt>
		<title level="m" type="main">Later from the South</title>
		<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
		<author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
	    <idno>mmm.news.dac.18571027</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

	    <notesStmt>
		<note type="project">
From Will Bagley.<!-- ANY IMPORTANT INFORMATION ABOUT THE CREATION OF THE FILE THAT DOESN'T FIT WITH THE OTHER TAGS. -->
		</note>
		<note type="summary">Reports of the massacre from Los Angeles include the Powers and Warn letters.</note>
	    </notesStmt>

    	    <sourceDesc>
		<bibl>
		    <title level="a">Later from the South: The Massacre at Mountain Canon Confirmed.&#8212;More Indian Outrages, &amp;c.</title>
		    <title level="j">Daily Alta California</title>
		    <author>Editor Alta California</author>
		    <publisher>Daily Alta California</publisher>
		    <pubPlace>San Francisco, CA</pubPlace>
		    <date when="1857-10-27">1857-10-27</date>
		</bibl>
	    </sourceDesc>

	    </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

	<profileDesc>
	    <textClass>
	        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
	            <term>newspaper</term>
	        </keywords>
		<keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
		    <term>Mormon and Indian</term>
		</keywords>
		<keywords scheme="original" n="sympathy">
		    <term>Non-Mormon</term>
		</keywords>
	    </textClass>
	</profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
	<change when="2011-06-14"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept Highlighting Enhancement</change>
	<change when="2007-04-23"><name>Leslie Working</name> Initial Encoding</change>
	<change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>

<body><div1 type="newspaper">
    
<pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.dac.18571027.001"/>

<head type="main">LATER FROM THE SOUTH.</head>

<head type="sub">The Massacre at Mountain Canon Confirmed.&#8212;More Indian Outrages, &amp;c.</head> 
    
<p>By the arrival of the steamer Senator, we have received through Wells Fargo &amp; Co., <seg type="Source" subtype="Reprinted">the San Diego Herald of October 17th, and files of the Los Angeles Star to the 24th inst.</seg></p>

<p>THE MOUNTAIN CANON MASSACRE.&#8212;The report of the late terrible massacre of the emigrants <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">in southern Utah</seg>, is fully confirmed. We invite particular attention to our Los Angles letter, which appears below. It gives minute details of the dreadful massacre <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at the Mountain Canon</seg>, and also subsequent outrages on emigrants, together with other matters of general interest.</p>
<p>Our San Diego exchanges contain nothing of importance.</p>

<div2>
<head type="sub"><hi rend="bold">OUR LOS ANGELES CORRESPONDENCE.</hi></head>
<opener><dateline>Los Angeles, October 24, 1857.</dateline></opener>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The massacre of more than a hundred American citizens</seg> by Mormon traitors and Indians, has created a great excitement among all classes in our community, and <seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">we hope that the tocsin is now sounded that shall rouse the nation and compel the government to protect our countrymen from the additional danger which foreign territories.</seg></seg></seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">For long years outrage upon outrage has been committed and representations made imploring aid in that inhospitable region where nature herself is so repulsive as almost to forbid travel, but their calls have been unheeded.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Coverage" subtype="California"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Extra-legalViolence"><seg type="Source" subtype="PublicMind">Our whole community has been deeply moved. Many of them are waiting and wishing for a call, to go and abate the evils which arrest the weary traveler and consign him to an unknown and nameless grave, midway to his destination.</seg> Two large public meetings were held in this city last week, under the circus pavilion, at which speeches were made by several who had been at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, and resolutions were passed, which, I believe, express the sentiments of everybody here but Mormons. There is a sentiment of extermination, living and intense, growing in the minds of all true Americans, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">against the traitors who have planted themselves in our territory, and who have instigated the savages of the desert to slaughter and rapine.</seg></seg> <seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">Will the government make any effort to redeem its character for pusillanimity, in so long delaying to correct those monstrous evils? does there need hecatombs more of victims, before anything is done? <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSZealots">What further outrage and insult is needed to prove to our rulers that there is a band of armed traitors in our midst who are making indiscriminate war upon men, women and children,</seg> simply because they are Americans, who are more dangerous because they are blinded by fanaticism, and <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">who are instigating the savages to slay all who are not saints?</seg></seg> </seg><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">A terrible example seems necessary to prove to them the power of those they are thus taught to slaughter-an example so fearful that it shall be remembered in all their villages, and shall make them tremble with awe when they hear the American name.</seg></seg></seg></seg></p>

<p>The following statements (which I have already given to our public both in English and Spanish) I took down from the lips of the gentlemen named. The manner of these gentlemen was in their statements, which have been duly authenticated and forwarded by mail to Washington. They arrived in town on the 10th instant. It will be seen that they were not permitted to see anything of the massacre-that they were detained one day near <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, that they might not arrive at the time of the massacre, and that they drove all night that the scene of the massacre might not be examined. Notwithstanding these precautions, it can scarcely fail to convince the unprejudiced reader that all these men saw and heard, <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">goes to establish the complicity of the Mormons with the Indians in the wholesale butcheries reported-that if these Saints were not actually engaged in the slaughter, they must have stood pitilessly by, and encouraged <seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">the Indians, whose vindictive character they have so moulded as to make it unsafe for any American to travel in that region unless he be under their protection.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">George Powers</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Little Rock, AR">Little Rock</placeName>, left <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, and with his train, arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> in August. He says:</seg></p>

<q><p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers"><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">We found the <orgName type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints">Mormons</orgName> making very determined preparations to fight the <orgName type="military" key="United States Army">United States troops</orgName>, whenever they may arrive. On our way in, we met three companies of 100 men each, armed and on the road towards the pass above <placeName type="military_post" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName>. I was told at <placeName type="military_post" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName>, that at <placeName type="military_post" key="Fort Supply">Fort Supply</placeName>, twelve miles this side of <placeName type="military_post" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName>, there were 400 armed Indians awaiting orders; they also said that there were 60,000 pounds of flour stored at <placeName type="military_post" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName> for the use of their army. We found companies drilling every evening in the city. The Mormons declared to us that no U.S. troops should ever cross the mountains; and they talked and acted as if they were willing to take a brush with Uncle Sam.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We remained in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> five days, and then pushed on, hoping we might overtake <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">a larger train, which had started ten days ahead of us, and which proved to be the train that was massacred</seg>. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">We came on to <placeName type="military_post" key="Buttermilk Fort">Buttermilk Fort</placeName>, near the <geogName type="feature" key="Lone Cedar">Lone Cedar</geogName>, 175 miles, and found the inhabitants greatly enraged at the train which had just passed, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">declaring that they had abused the Mormon women, calling them w&#8212;s, &amp;c., and letting on about the men.</seg></seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">The people had refused to sell that train any provisions</seg>, and told us they were sorry they had not killed them there; but they knew it would be done before they got in. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">They stated further that they were holding the Indians in check until the arrival of their chief, when he would follow the train and cut it in pieces.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">We attempted to purchase some butter here; the women set it out to us, and as we were taking it away, the men came running and charging, and swore we should not have it, nor anything else, as we had misused them. They appeared to be bitterly hostile, and would hardly speak to us. We were unable to get anything we stood in need of. We camped at this place but one night.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>, we found plenty of <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">Indians</orgName>, who were all peaceable and friendly. We learned nothing of the train, except that it had passed that place several days before, and we were glad to find we had gained so much on them. The next place where we heard of the train was on our arrival at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver">Beaver</placeName>, 230 miles from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>. Here we learned that when the train ahead were camped at <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>, which was thirty-five miles back, and at which place we found the <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">Indians</orgName> so friendly, an ox died, and the Indians asked for it. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">Before it was given to them a Mormon reported that he saw an emigrant go to the carcass and cut in with his knife, and as he did so, would pour some liquid into the cut from a vial. The meat was eaten by the Indians, and three of them died, and several more were sick and would die. The people at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> seemed also to be incensed against the train, for the same reason as before reported. I asked an Indian at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> if there was any truth in the poisoned meat story; he replied in English, that he did not know-that several of the Indians had died, and several were sick. He said their water-melons made them all sick, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">he believed that the Mormons had poisoned them</seg>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We laid by at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> several days, as the <persName key="Farnsworth, Philo">Bishop</persName> told us it was dangerous for so small a company as ours to go on. Our train consisted of only three wagons, and we were hurrying on to join the larger one.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">While waiting here, the train of <persName key="Mathews, William">Wm. Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Sidney Tanner</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, came up, and I made arrangements to come on with them. We came on to <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and here we learned that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">the train ahead had been attacked by the Indians at the <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>, fifty miles from <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and had returned upon their road five miles, to a spring, and fortified themselves.</seg> We then drove out of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> five or six miles, and camped at what is called the Summit.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Next morning an express arrived from Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, President of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, requesting us not to proceed any further that day if we pleased; also that <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName> should return to <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and bring me along with them. We returned and a council was held, at which it was advised by Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, that I should go back to my own train, as they did not wish to have strangers in their train. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">He also stated, that at two o'clock that morning, he had received and express from the train ahead, stating they were surrounded by Indians, who had killed two or three of their number, and asking for assistance.</seg> While we were talking, an express came in from <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver">Beaver</placeName>, stating that the Indians had attacked my train in the streets of that place, and were fighting when he left. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">One reason given was, that ten miles the other side of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver">Beaver</placeName>, an emigrant train had shot an Indian, which greatly enraged them;</seg> that the people of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver">Beaver</placeName> went out in the night and brought the emigrants in, and were followed by the Indians, who made the attack after their arrival.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">On the receipt of this news, another private council was held, after which I was called in and told, that in consequence of the fight behind, it would be for their advantage to bring me through, provided I would obey council and the rules of the train. To this I assented, being anxious to get on, and asked what was required of me. Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> replied, that in passing through the Indian country, it might be necessary for me to be laid flat in a wagon and covered with blankets for two or three days, as <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">the Indians were deadly hostile to all Americans;</seg> that if I was seen, it would endanger the safety of the whole train. My friend Mr. <persName key="Warn, George">Warn</persName> was told that he would also go on, upon the same conditions.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, it seems, when it was 'for their interest' to bring us through, the elders had no control over the Indians, while at <placeName type="military_post" key="Buttermilk Fort">Buttermilk Fort</placeName>, they were able to restrain them, as they declared under great provocation.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">On Friday, the 18th of September,</seg> we left <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, some eighteen miles, about one o'clock. <seg type="Source" subtype="WordofMouth"><seg type="Source" subtype="Indians">During the afternoon,<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"> an express arrived from the Indians, stating that one of their warriors had run up and looked into the corral, and he supposed that 'only five or six of the emigrants were killed yet.' These were words of the expressman.</seg></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">The same night, four men were sent out from the train, and, as they pretended, to save, if possible, some of its members.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">I omitted to mention, in the proper place, that <seg type="Source" subtype="Dame">Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> informed me that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">the attack on the train commenced on Monday, the 14th of September</seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">I asked him if he could not raise a company and go out and relieve the besieged train. He replied that he could go out and take them away in safety, but he dared not&#8212;he dared not disobey counsel.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">On Saturday, at twelve o'clock we left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. About the middle of the afternoon, we met the four men who were sent out the night previous, returning in a wagon. <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName> held a council with them, apart, and when they left, <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_TannerMathews"><persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> told me the entire train had been cut off</seg>, and, as it was still dangerous to travel the road, they had concluded it was better for us to pass the spot in the night. We continued on, without much conversation, and about dusk met Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, (I did not know that he had left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>,) and three other white men, coming from the scene of slaughter, in company with a band of some twenty Indian warriors. One of the men in company with Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, was Mr. <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName>, President of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> said they had been out to see to the burying of the dead; but the dead were not buried. From what I heard, I believe the bodies were left lying naked upon the ground, having been stripped of their clothing by the Indians.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">These Indians had a two-horse wagon, filled with something I could not see, as blankets were carefully spread over the top</seg>. The wagon was driven by a white man, and beside him, there were two or three Indians in it! <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Many of them had shawls, and bundles of women's clothes were tied to their saddles. They were also all supplied with guns or pistols, besides bows and arrows. The hindmost Indians were driving several head of the emigrants' cattle.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> and Mr. <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName>, and their men, seemed to be on the best of terms with the Indians, and they were all in high spirits, as if they were mutually pleased with the accomplishment of some desired object. They thronged around us, and greeted us with noisy cordiality. We did not learn much from them.</seg> They passed on, and we drove all night in silence, and at daylight camped, and were told we were three miles beyond <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">the scene of slaughter</seg>. We lay by here two or three hours, to rest, and then drove all day-twenty miles-at night camping on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara River</geogName>, near the <placeName type="settlement" key="Chief Jackson's village">Chief Jackson's village</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS"><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Next morning, after driving a few miles, we stopped to water. <orgName type="native" key="Paiute"><persName key="Chief Jackson">Jackson</persName> and his band</orgName> soon came to us; and in a few minutes pointed out Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> as an American. The Mormon boys denied it, but the <orgName type="native" key="Paiute">Indians</orgName> were dissatisfied, and appeared restive. The <persName key="Chief Jackson">chief</persName> came up and accused me of being an American, appeared mad, stepped round, shook his head, and pulled his bowstring. He then sent several men on our road ahead. Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> advised us to leave there as quick as possible, as it was getting dangerous.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At <persName key="Chief Jackson">Jackson</persName>'s we engaged Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> to go on to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> as an interpreter. It was a fortunate circumstance for us that this Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> arrived at our camp at the very moment that we were wishing for him most. Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> told me he was an Indian missionary, and of great influence among them. He could do more with them than anybody else, and if he could not get me over the road, nobody could. Mr. <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName> had declared that he would not go on without Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName>, and pretended to be afraid of the dangers of the road.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Next morning Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> left us and went on to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>. About a day's drive the other side of the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, we met him returning in company with two young men, <persName key="Young, Cau"><persName key="Young, Henry T.">brothers Young</persName></persName>, horse thieves, who were escaping from justice in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, having been assisted in getting away by those who had them in custody. Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> stated that when he reached the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">he found the young boys in company with <persName key="Baker, Abel">an emigrant who had escaped the massacre</persName></seg>&#8212;that on his arrival, there was not an Indian in sight, and that he had to give the whoop to call them from concealment. He said in continuation, without appearing to notice the discrepancy, that on his arrival he found <orgName type="native" key="Paiute">the Indians</orgName> hotly pursuing the three men, and that they jumped upon the emigrant, and killed him before his eyes, before he could interfere to prevent it. He said he threw himself between the boys and Indians, and had great difficulty in saving them. The <orgName type="native" key="Southern Paiute">Indians</orgName> were in a great excitement, as he said, but that as  <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName> were Mormons, they could pass without danger.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We arrived at the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> the day after we met Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> and the <persName key="Young, Cau"><persName key="Young, Henry T.">Young boys</persName></persName>. We found here 30 or 40 Indians, and the mail riders from <placeName type="state" key="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</placeName>, who had come in that morning. The <orgName type="native" key="Paiute">Indians</orgName> were very friendly, and shook hands with everybody. No expression of hostility to Americans was heard, but this was accounted for on the ground that this was a Mormon train.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At the <geogName type="waterway" key="Vegas River">Vegas</geogName>, we found another band of Indians. The chief asked our interpreter whether our captain had brought him no word from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, whether he was nearly ready to fight the Americans yet; adding, that he was ready, had got his arrows poisoned, &amp;c.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At the Cottonwoods, 15 miles from the <geogName type="waterway" key="Vegas River">Vegas</geogName>, <persName key="Chief Brigham Young">the chief, called Brigham Young</persName>, said he was afraid of the emigrant train behind, and wished to know if they would shoot.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">On the 1st October, we arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, and I was advised by R. Matthews, who, I learned, was a President or Elder in that place, not to associate with the damned apostates, that they were cutthroats of the worst character. If I wished, they would give me constant work at their mill in the mountains, and I must be careful not to talk too much of what I had seen.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Whilst in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, I heard many persons express gratification at the massacre.<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution"> At the church services, on Sunday, Capt. <persName key="Hunt, Jefferson">Hunt</persName> occupied the pulpit, and, among other things, he said that the hand of the Lord was in it; it was right! The prophecies concerning <placeName type="state" key="Missour">Missouri</placeName> were being fulfilled, and they would all be accomplished.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution">Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Matthews</persName> said the work had just begun, and it should be carried on until Uncle Sam and all the boys that were left should come to Zion and beg for bread.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">I did not stay in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, because it did not appear to be a free country, for I am an American, and like freedom of thought and speech.</seg></p></q>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">P. M. Warn</persName>, of Bergen, Genesse County, New York, who was a fellow-traveler with Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName> on that fatal journey, corroborates the statements of <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>, so far as he was acquainted with the facts, and gives the following additional particulars, which did not come under the observation of Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>:</p>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> states that there was a coolness between himself and Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Matthews</persName>, arising from the frankness with which he expressed his opinions, and, in consequence of this, he was not treated with as much confidence as Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>.</p>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake,</placeName> via Independence, on the 7th of August last, and remained until the 26th, on which day he started for California, as a passenger in <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName>'s train. <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">He states that on his journey through the settlements, which was a week or ten days subsequent to the passage of the murdered train, he at various places heard the same threats of vengeance against them, <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">for their boisterousness and abuse of Mormons and Mormonism, as was reported, and these threats seemed to be made with the intention of preparing the mind to expect a calamity, and also, when a calamity occurred, it would appear to fall upon transgressors, as a matter of retribution.</seg></seg></p>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> says, according to his memorandum: <q><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">On the 5th of September we encamped at <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">Here I had a conversation with the Indian agent, concerning the poisoning of the ox. He said that six Indians had died; that others were sick and would die. Upon one of them, the poison had worked out all over his breast, and he was dead next morning, as reported.</seg> Afterwards, I conversed with an Indian, said to be the war chief <persName key="Ammon">Ammon</persName>, who spoke good English. I inquired how many of <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">his tribe</orgName> had died from eating the poisoned animal. He replied not any, but some were sick. He did not attribute the sickness to poison, nor did he give any reason for it. His manner and that of all his people towards us, was not only friendly, but cordial; and he did not mention the train which had been doomed. Besides the Mormon train, there were camped at this place two or three emigrant trains, amounting to fifteen or eighteen wagons, with whom the <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">Indians</orgName> were as friendly as with ourselves. From <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>, nothing of importance occurred more than is related by Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>, until we arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">Here the four men, spoken of by Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>, (and among whom I recognized Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>) arrived at our camp; they wished to get fresh animals, that they might go on that night to the besieged party.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">This was Friday night, the night on which the slaughter was completed.</seg> They rested an hour or two, and took refreshments. In the conversation which ensued, one of our party said, 'Be careful, and don't get shot, Mr. <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName>.' Mr. H. replied, 'We shall have no shooting;' emphasizing the we, and throwing up his head, as if he meant to imply that the shooting would be all over before he arrived. They left us in good spirits.</seg></q></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSGreed"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">One reason that may be assigned for the massacre of this train is, that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">it was known to be in possession of considerable valuable property</seg>, and this fact excited the cupidity of the Mormons. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">It was said they had over 600 head of stock, besides mules &amp;c. They were well supplied with arms and ammunition, and element of gain which enters largely into all Mormon calculations.</seg> The train was composed of families who all seemed to be in good circumstances, and as they were moving to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, their outfit indicated that they might be in possession of considerable funds. </seg></seg><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">The men were very free in speaking of the Mormons; </seg>their conduct was said to have been reckless, and they would commit little acts of annoyance for the purpose of provoking the Saints. Feeling perfectly safe in their arms and numbers, they seemed to set at defiance all the powers that could be brought against them, and they were not permitted to feel the dangers that surrounded them, until they were cut off from all hope of relief.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> states, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">in speaking of the emigrant who escaped, and was killed at the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, that at <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="waterway" key="Painter Creek">Painter Creek</geogName>, some six or seven miles on the other side of the place of massacre</seg>, a Mormon told him that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">one of the little girls who was taken back, and who is about six years old, said that she saw her mother killed by an arrow, and that her father had escaped to California.</seg></seg> This was before <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> joined the train. The matter of the escape was talked over by the Mormon captains, and Mathews made the remark, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">'If the man comes into our train, he shall not be received!'</seg></seg></p>

<p>The following statement is made to me by Mr. <persName key="Mogridge, Henry">Henry Mogridge</persName>, with the request that I would give it publicity. He is a young man, and was once in high favor with the powers at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>. He says if called upon, he will make oath to the truth of his charges. He says:&#8212;</p>

<q><p>In November, 1853, I resided at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, and was sent for to attend a council. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">At the council I was solicited to take a mission to the <orgName type="native" key="Green River Indians">Green River Indians</orgName>. I did not consent, because I had just returned from <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and the southern settlements, which I had been appointed to locate. Although not a member of the council, I was permitted to remain, and heard the charge given to the missionaries to those Indians by <persName key="Richards, Willard">Willard Richards</persName>, now dead. First they were to establish missions, then they would form treaties and alliances with the Indians; the elders, both married and single, must marry squaws, particularly the daughters of chiefs. Such ties as these could not be broken, and the Indians would be under their control forever.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">At that time, war against the United States was anticipated, and they professed according to the Book of Mormon, to use the Indians 'as the Lord's battle-ax.' A time would come when they would be of great service to the Saints, from their knowledge of the mountains. They were to teach the doctrines of Mormon, and baptize them into the church-they were also to monopolize all trade with them, and influence them to keep out the Gentiles.</seg></p>

<p>These missionaries did not at that time, go so far as <geogName type="waterway" key="Green River">Green River</geogName>, but remained in the vicinity of <placeName type="military_post" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName>, to watch the movements of the mountaineers, who were gathering there, indignant that <persName key="Bridger, Jim">Bridger</persName> had been driven off. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">In the following spring several other missionaries were sent to different parts of the territory. <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">P. P. Pratt</persName> was sent to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara</geogName> for similar purposes.</seg></p>
<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">I had been an eye-witness to the baptism of scores of Indians at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and other southern settlements. The doctrines taught, are invariably, that the Americans are enemies to the Mormons and Indians, and they must kill them whenever they can find them.
</seg></p>

<p>The <orgName type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints">Mormons</orgName> have a school wherein the young men of the church are taught the different Indian dialects. These dialects are reduced to a system, and are printed in books. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">Many of the Mormon elders and missionaries have Indian wives, and are raising families of half-breeds.</seg></p>

<p>I have frequently heard <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> declare that he could clean out the United States with the <orgName type="native" key="Shoshone">Shoshonees (Snake)</orgName> and <orgName type="native" key="Ute">Utahs</orgName>, and that he intended to do it.</p>

<p>At <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="waterway" key="Painter Creek">Painter Creek</geogName>, which is but six or seven miles, on the other side of the scene of slaughter</seg>, there is a settlement of some fifteen or twenty families of Mormons. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">The people there knew of the beginning and end of the slaughter, but not one of them went to the assistance of the train.</seg></p></q>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> states that, <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">two days before arriving at <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, a man named <persName key="Hyde, William">Bill Hyde</persName>, whom he learned was a noted Danite, and who is badly reported of in this town, joined the train, having come through with the mail. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">This <persName key="Hyde, William">Hyde</persName> reported that he went and saw the bodies lying scattered about upon the ground, most of them stripped naked-only a few of them being partially clothed. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> and <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName>, he said, staid there to bury the dead, but the bodies were so much decayed they could not endure the stench, and after throwing a few into a hole and covering them lightly with sage, the two Presidents departed. Decomposition must have been very rapid, to have produced so offensive results, the morning after the massacre!</seg></seg></p>

<p><persName key="Hyde, William">Hyde</persName> also related to his Mormon brethren, that on arriving at the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara</geogName>, where formerly there was a Mormon settlement, and is now occupied by the <persName key="Chief Jackson">Chief Jackson</persName>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">he saw in the hands of that chief, a little book, or journal, the name, <q><persName key="Jones, Milum John (?)">Wm. B. Jones</persName>, Caldwell County, Missouri</q>.</seg> He offered to purchase it, but the chief refused to part with it. This is the first intimation we have that will in any manner serve to identify the train. Not a word, nor a sign, except this, has been given, which will rescue from oblivion the name or residence of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">those hundred and eighteen travelers,</seg> and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">the only monument left of them is their bones whitening upon the desert.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">How were these deaths compassed? and who did it? <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">It is charged upon the Indians, by Mormons</seg>. But what Indians? These two gentlemen have related all they saw along the whole route. Except the band of twenty, they met returning from the massacre, in company with nearly as many more white men, they say distinctly that they saw no Indians, going or coming; and at the various villages, from <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName> to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, they saw no suspicious movements among them-no preparations for attack-no rejoicing-no trophies of victory, except those already named, in possession of <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>'s party. Those who were dressed as Indians in that party all talk English, and were on terms of equality with the Presidents. Is there any significance in this?</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Honea">Since the above was written, the statement of Mr. <persName key="Honea, S. B.">Hones</persName>, concerning the outrages upon the last train heard of, has been made, and we have the following item which seems to identify the massacred train:</seg></p>

<p><q><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Honea"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">The train which has been so cruelly massacred, was under the charge of <persName key="Baker, John T.">Captain Baker</persName>, familiarly known as 'Uncle Jack,' from <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">Carroll County, Arkansas</seg> - <persName key="Edwards, Silas">Silas Edwards</persName> and <persName key="Baker, George W.">William Baker</persName>, son of the captain, are also known to have been in the train. </seg><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">At <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, Mr. <persName key="Honea, S. B.">Hones</persName> saw President <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName> riding a large bay horse which he recognized as having belonged to Mr. <persName key="Edwards, Silas">Silas Edwards</persName>.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Was informed by <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName>, that young <persName key="Baker, Abel">Baker</persName> had an opportunity of escaping, went a short distance but returned; was afterwards wounded in the arm; again escaped from the massacre, and had proceeded about ten miles this side of the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, when he met the <persName key="Young, Cau"><persName key="Young, Henry T.">Youngs</persName></persName> who had escaped from <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernadino</placeName>. He was advised to return to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, which he did, when he was met by <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> and the Indians, and by them cruelly murdered</seg></seg></seg></q></p>
</div2>

<div2>
<head type="sub">Another Emigrant Train Robbed on the Salt Lake Road.</head>

<p>On the 17th inst., another of the back trains of emigrants was heard from. Considerable anxiety has been manifested at their non-arrival. It was said that the foremost ones would wait for those in the rear, and thus form one company. It was also felt that the declarations of <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Hunt, Jefferson">Hunt</persName>, <q>that the work of vengeance was at last begun,</q> were significant of death to more than those who fell at <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadow</geogName></seg>. The intelligence we here have brought by nine men who arrived on the 17th from their train.<seg type="Source" subtype="Unattributed">They state that, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, the emigrants deemed it advisable for their safety to employ Mormon guides to conduct them <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">through to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>. After much trouble, they hired eight guides, paying them in advance &#36;1815. In addition, they also hired an Indian. The guides and this Indian were on the most familiar terms during the journey. On their arrival at the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, there was no Indian in sight. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">The savage they had <unclear>hired</unclear> when the enemies of Americans rushed out from concealment, to the number of two or three hundred, and attacked the stock of the emigrants, who drew their weapons to defend <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">their property</seg>. On seeing this, the guides said to them: <q>If you fire a gun we will leave you instantly.</q> Upon this they desisted, believing their guides were about to interfere in their behalf.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The enemy, who is reported to have been dressed and painted like bad looking Indians, succeeded in driving of 326 head of cattle and 5 horses. The guides, except the veritable <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName>, already spoken of by <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName> and <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName>, followed the Indians, having previously borrowed several revolvers from the emigrants. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName>, who bids fair to become infamous, remained until the rest had gone out of sight, when, saying he would go after the cattle, he also left, and neither guide, revolvers, cattle nor Indians, were afterwards heard of.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">When these men left the train it was nearly destitute of provisions, having been unable to purchase anything in the Mormon settlements.</seg> They state that the object of the thieves seemed to be to steal and plunder, as they made no attack upon the lives of the company. The men who brought this intelligence were ten days on the road, having left the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> on the 7th, and arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName> on the 17th instant. The last three days they traveled without provisions. They came in on foot&#8212;the distance being 250 miles. Immediately on their arrival, two relief trains were sent out from <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, by the two parties there, each one vieing who should outdo the other in their charitable work.</p>

</div2>
<div2>
<head type="sub">A Voice from San Bernardino.</head>

<p>The Independent <q>"Party of <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>"</q> had a meeting the other day. This party is respectable as to numbers, and embraces more than one-third of the people; the majority being Saints. Their resolution is herewith annexed, and forms an interesting link in this veritable history:</p>
   
<floatingText>
<body>
<opener>FORT REGULATOR,<lb/>
<dateline><placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, <date when="1857-10-17">Oct. 17, 1857</date>.</dateline></opener>

<p>Whereas, the officers of this county are all <orgName type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints">Mormons</orgName>, or their firm supporters; and they, the <orgName type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints">Mormons</orgName>, are the sworn enemies to our government; and the officers and sureties are irresponsible men; and the most of them are preparing to leave for <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>, Utah Territory; we therefore deem it unsafe to trust them with the public revenue; and in consideration of the foregoing, it was unanimously</p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Extra-legalViolence">Resolved, That we, the independent citizens of <placeName type="county" key="San Bernardino County">San Bernardino County, California</placeName>, will not pay taxes or revenue to any person now in office in this county, and that we will assist and defend each other, if any officer in this county should proceed to enforce payment by virtue of his office.</seg></p>
<closer><signed><persName key="Van Leuvan, Frederic">FREDERIC VAN LEUVAN</persName>, President</signed><lb/>
<signed><persName key="Ferguson, Charles">CHARLES FERGUSON</persName>, Clerk.</signed></closer>
</body>
</floatingText>

<p>Just while we were greatly interested in the report of these outrages, there arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="San Pedro">San Pedro</placeName>, a vessel from Australia, with over seventy converts, the fruits of the labors of a fellow named Wall, who is recognized by persons here as a Danite from Fillmore, and as they say, one of the biggest rascals alive. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Anti-MormonAction">He came to town the night of the meeting and remained till morning, when he was waited upon by a committee (self constituted) who greeted him in such a decided manner, that he was glad to escape, declaring that he had too much regard for his own life to endanger it by remaining here. The deluded wretches he was conducting to Zion were all women and children but nineteen.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="Anti-MormonAction">Our citizens at first proposed to re-convert this crowd and thus save them from some of the miseries to which they are about to subject themselves, but they are allowed to go on their mournful journey uninformed.</seg></p>

<p>There are few local items of interest. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Extra-legalViolence"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">Public attention has been much engrossed by these outrages, and almost everyone of those particularly who have been on the Salt Lake road generally winds up with <q>Let Government call for volunteers&#8212;I should like to take a turn at those fellows!</q> Were a call made, half of our population would respond, so bitter is their experience. The general opinion here with intelligent men who know the audacity of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, is that the small force which are advancing upon Utah, will all be cut off.</seg></seg></p>

<p>One more item. One of the speakers at our meeting said that the arms of <placeName type="State" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> are a beehive, protected by a lion rampant, at whose feet is the American eagle, couchant, and badly plucked.</p>

<p>There is a good deal of dissatisfaction among our farmers, at the negligence of the Agent of Agricultural Fair, Mr. Ferguson. He came here, spent considerable time in searching for a boarding house, looked at two or three vineyards, and left. The corn and tobacco planters, at the Monte, were not pleased at this neglect. Three cornfields, two fields of tobacco, and one patch of immense onions would have been offered for premiums. I send you a specimen of the tobacco raised by Mr. Marshall, and which was prepared for the Fair. I eschew tobacco, but it seems to me there is a very agreeable aroma to this. You, perhaps are a judge of the weed. If so, give us a judgement.</p>

<p>On the 17th inst., it was reported in town that the <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName> people are purchasing large quantities of powder of our merchants, to be sent to Salt Lake. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">This report, taken in connection with others, that arms and powder had been recently forwarded to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City,. UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, via <placeName type="settlement" key="San Diego, CA">San Diego</placeName>, and also that five hundred destination shows that the <orgName type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints">Mormons</orgName> are making good use of their time, in preparing to meet Uncle Sam's forces. . . .</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">I nearly omitted to tell you that I am informed by a person who saw the document, that Capt. <persName key="Hunt, Jefferson">Hunt</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, has written by this steamer to the Governor, for rifles and ammunition to suppress insurrection in that county, and also <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">to fight Indians!</seg> This is all pretence. All the rifles and ammunition they receive are instantly forwarded to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, where the majority of these people are expected soon to depart.</seg></p>

<closer><persName key="Wallace ('Yo Mismo'), William ">Yo Mismo</persName>.</closer>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
