<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.las.18571010.2a">
    <teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
	    <titleStmt>
	        <title level="m" type="main">The Late Horrible Massacre</title>
		<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
		<author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
		<idno>mmm.news.las.18571010.2a</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

	    <notesStmt>
		<note type="summary">The accounts of Powers and Warn make up the bulk of the report.</note>
	    </notesStmt>

	<sourceDesc>
	    <bibl>
		<title level="a">The Late Horrible Massacre.</title>
		<title level="j">Los Angeles Star</title>
		<author>Editors, Los Angeles Star</author>
		<publisher>Los Angeles Star</publisher>
		<pubPlace>Los Angeles, CA</pubPlace>
		<date when="1857-10-10">1857-10-10</date>
	    </bibl>
	</sourceDesc>

	</fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

	<profileDesc>
	    <textClass>
	        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
	            <term>newspaper</term>
	        </keywords>
		<keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
		    <term>Both</term>
		</keywords>
		<keywords scheme="original" n="sympathy">
	            <term>Non-Mormon</term>
		</keywords>
	    </textClass>
	</profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
	<change when="2011-06-21"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept Highlighting Enhancement</change>
	<change when="2007-04-21"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Initial Encoding</change>
	<change when="2006-03-02"><name>Leslie Working</name> Model Encoding</change>
	<change when="2004-01-01"><name>Will Bagley</name> Original transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>


<body>


<div1 type="newspaper">
    
    <pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.las.18571010.2a.001"/>


    <head>The Late Horrible Massacre.</head>

<p>In the early part of the week, an intense excitement pervaded out citizens on learning that parties had arrived in town, who corroborated the statements previously made in regard to <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the horrible massacre of one hundred and eighteen persons,</seg> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">on the <placeName type="route" key="Salt Lake Route">Salt Lake route</placeName> to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg></seg>; and placards were posted throughout the city, calling a public meeting of the citizens to be held at the Circus Pavilion, on the Plaza, on Monday evening, to hear the statements of the parties alluded to, and to adopt such measures, in view of the facts, as should be deemed advisable. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">Accordingly, at the time appointed, a very large number of our citizens assembled, deeply impressed by the awful tragedy which had been enacted on the borders of our State, and anxious that such a representation of the facts in the case should be made to the authorities in Washington, as should compel them to take immediate steps to discover the perpetrators and instigators of the foul outrage, and inflict on them condign punishment.</seg> We need not here more particularly refer to the proceedings of the meeting, as they are reported elsewhere; but as we have obtained the statements of Messrs. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName> and <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName>, the gentlemen above alluded to, which contain the nearest approach to an account of the massacre that can be given at present, we prefer to add them here, rather than in the report of the meeting.</p>

<p>The statements were drawn up, at the dictation of the parties, by Mr. <persName key="Wallace, W. A.">W. A. Wallace</persName>, who read them to [t]he meeting, and from whom we obtained them, through the chairman of the meeting, Mr. <persName key="Whitman, George N.">G. N. Whitman</persName>.</p>

<p>These documents exhibit a deplorable picture of the working of Mormonism, which, if correct, show the leaders of this <orgName type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints">sect</orgName> to be actuated by the most atrocious designs towards their fellow-citizens of the Union. We hope for the sake of our common humanity, that the character of this people may be redeemed from the black catalogue of crime here preferred, and that it will yet appear that <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">they are not the fiends incarnate they are represented</seg>, but that they used all possible diligence to prevent the late massacre, and that they act in good faith to preserve the lives of such of their fellow citizens as, from necessity or choice, travel through their <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Territory</placeName>&#8212;the common property of the citizens of the Union.</p>

<p>As each will draw his own conclusions from the narrative, without further comment we give the statements of Messrs. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName> and <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName>, regarding the late Massacre of the Plains.</p>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">George Powers</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Little Rock, AR">Little Rock</placeName>, left Arkansas, and with his train arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> in August. He says:&#8212;<lb/></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We found the <orgName type="religious" key="Church of Jesus Christ of Later-day Saints">Mormons</orgName> making very determined preparations to fight the United States troops, whenever they may arrive. On our way in, we met three companies of 100 men each, armed and on the road towards the pass above <placeName type="settlement" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName>. I was told at <placeName type="settlement" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName>, that at Fort Supply, twelve miles this side of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName>, there were 400 armed Indians awaiting orders; they also said that there were 60,000 pounds of flour stored at <placeName type="settlement" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</placeName> for the use of their army. We found companies drilling every evening in the city. The Mormons declared to us that no U.S. troops should ever cross the mountains; and they talked and acted as if they were willing to take a brush with Uncle Sam.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We remained in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> five days, and then pushed on, hoping we might overtake <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">a larger train, which had started ten days ahead of us, and which proved to be the train that was massacred.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">We came on to <placeName type="military_post" key="Buttermilk Fort">Buttermilk Fort</placeName> near the lone cedar, 175 miles, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">found the inhabitants greatly enraged at the train which had just passed, declaring that they had abused the Mormon women, calling them w&#8212;s, &amp;c,</seg> and letting on about the men.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">The people had refused to sell that train any provisions</seg>, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">told us they were sorry they had not killed them there; but, they knew it would be done before they got in.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">They stated further, that they were holding the Indians in check until the arrival of their chief, when he would follow the train and cut it in pieces.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We attempted to purchase some butter here; the women set it out to us, and as we were taking it away, the men came running and charging, and swore we should not have it, nor anything else, as we had misused them. They appeared to be bitterly hostile, and would hardly speak to us. We were unable to get anything we stood in need of. We camped at this place but one night.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>, we found plenty of <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">Indians</orgName>, who were all peaceable and friendly. <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">We learned nothing of the train, except that it had passed that place several days before,</seg> and we were glad to find we had gained so much on them. <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">The next place where we heard of the Train was on our arrival at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, 230 miles from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>.</seg> Here we learned, that when the train ahead were camped at <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>, which was thirty-five miles back, and at which place we found the Indians so friendly, an ox died, and the <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">Indians</orgName> asked for it. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">Before it was given to them, a Mormon reported that he saw an emigrant go to the carcass and cut it with his knife, and as he did so, would pour some liquid into the cut from a phial. The meat was eaten by the <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">Indians</orgName>, and three of them died, and several more were sick and would die.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">The people of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> seemed also to be incensed against the train, for the same reason as before reported.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">I asked an Indian, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, if there was any truth in the poisoned meat story; he replied in English, that he did not know, that several of the <orgName type="native" key="Pahvant">Indians</orgName> had died and several were sick; he said their water melons made them all sick, and he believed that the Mormons had poisoned them.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We laid by at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> several days, as the <persName key="Farnsworth, Philo">Bishop</persName> told us it was dangerous for so small a company as ours to go on. Our train consisted of only three wagons, and we were hurrying on to join the larger one.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">While waiting here, the train of <persName key="Mathews, William">Wm. Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Sidney Tanner </persName>of <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName> came up, and I made arrangements to come on with them. We came on to <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">here we learned that the train ahead <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">had been attacked by the Indians</seg>, at the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, fifty miles from <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">had returned upon their road five miles to a spring, and fortified themselves.</seg></seg> We then drove out of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> five or six miles, and camped at what is called the <geogName type="feature" key="the Summit">Summit</geogName>.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Next morning an express arrived from Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, President of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, requesting us not to proceed any further that day if we pleased; also that <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner </persName> should return to <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and bring me along with them. We returned, and a council was held, at which it was advised by Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, that I should go back to my own train, as they did not wish to have strangers in their train. He also stated, that at two o'clock that morning, he had received an express from the train ahead, stating <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">they were surrounded by Indians, who had killed <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">two or three of their number</seg></seg>, and asking for assistance. While we were talking, an express came in from <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, stating that <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Indians had attacked my train in the streets of <choice><sic>they</sic><corr>the</corr></choice> place, and were fighting when he left. One reason given, was that ten miles the other side of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">an emigrant train had shot an Indian, which greatly enraged them</seg>; that the people of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> went out in the night and brought the emigrants in, and were followed by the Indians, who made the attack after their arrival.</seg></seg></p>
	 
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">On the receipt of this news, another private council was held; after which I was called in and told, that in consequence of the fight behind, it would be for their advantage to bring me through, provided I would obey council and the rules of the train. To this I assented, being anxious to get on, and asked what was required of me. Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> replied, that in passing through the Indian country, it might be necessary for me to be laid flat in the wagon and covered with blankets, for two or three days, as <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">the Indians were deadly hostile to all Americans</seg>; that if I was seen, it would endanger the safety of the whole train. My friend Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName>, was told that he could also go on upon the same conditions.</seg></p>
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, it seems, when it was "for their interest" to bring us through, <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">the Elders had no control over the Indians; while at <placeName type="military_post" key="Buttermilk Fort">Buttermilk Fort</placeName>, they were able to restrain them, as they declared, under great provocation.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">On Friday, the 18th day of September, we left <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, some eighteen miles, about one o'clock. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">During the afternoon, an express arrived from the Indians, stating that one of their warriors had run up and looked into the corral, and he supposed that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">"only five or six of the emigrants were killed yet."</seg> </seg>These were the words of the expressman. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">The same night, four men were sent out from <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, to go and learn what was the fate of the train, and, as they pretended, to save, if possible, some of its members.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">I omitted to mention, in the proper place, that Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> informed me that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">the attack on the train commenced on Monday, the 14th of September.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">I asked him if he could not raise a company, and go out and relieve the besieged train. He replied, that he could go out and take them away in safety, but he dared not; he dared not disobey counsel.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">On Saturday, at twelve o'clock, we left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. About the middle of the afternoon, we met the four men who were sent out the night previous, returning in a wagon. <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_TannerMathews"><persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner </persName> held a council with them apart, and when they left,<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"> <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> told me the entire train had been cut off;</seg> and as it was still dangerous to travel the road, they had concluded it was better for us to pass the spot in the night.</seg> We continued on, without much conversation, and about dusk met Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, (I did not know that he had left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>) and three other white men, coming from the scene of the slaughter, in company with a band of some twenty Indian warriors. One of the men in company with Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>, was Mr. <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName>, President of Cedar City. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> said they had been out to see to the burying of the dead; but the dead were not buried. From what I heard, I believe the bodies were left lying naked upon the ground, having been stripped of their clothing by the Indians.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">These Indians had a two-horse wagon; filled with something I could not see, as blankets were carefully spread over the top. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The wagon was driven by a white man, and beside him there were two or three Indians in it!</seg> Many of them had shawls, and bundles of women's clothes were tied to their saddles. They were also all supplied with guns or pistols, besides bows and arrows. The hindmost Indians were driving several head of the emigrants' cattle.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName> and Mr. <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName>, and their men, seemed to be on the best of terms with the Indians, and they were all in high spirits, as if they were mutually pleased with the accomplishment of some desired object.</seg></seg> They thronged around us, and greeted us with noisy cordiality. We did not learn much from them. They passed on, and we drove all night in silence, and at daylight camped, and were told <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">we were three miles beyond the scene of the slaughter</seg>. We lay by here two or three hours to rest, and then drove all day, twenty miles, at night camping on the <geogName type="waterway" key="Santa Clara River">Santa Clara River</geogName>, near the <placeName type="settlement" key="Chief Jackson's village">Chief Jackson's village</placeName>.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence"><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Next morning, after driving a few miles, we stopped to water. <persName key="Chief Jackson">Jackson</persName> and <orgName type="native" key="Paiute">his band</orgName> soon came to us; and in a few minutes pointed out Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> as an American. The Mormon boys denied it, but the <orgName type="native" key="Paiute">Indians</orgName> were dissatisfied, and appeared restive. The <persName key="Chief Jackson">Chief</persName> came up and accused me of being an American; appeared mad; stepped round; shook his head, and pulled his bowstring. He then sent several men on our road ahead. Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> advised us to leave there as quick as possible, as it was getting dangerous.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At <placeName type="settlement" key="Chief Jackson's village">Jackson's</placeName>, we engaged Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> to go on to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> as an interpreter. It was a fortunate circumstance for us that this Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> arrived at our camp at the very moment that we were wishing for him most.<seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"> Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> told me he was an Indian missionary, and of great influence among them. He could do more with them than anybody else; and if he could not get me over the road, nobody could.</seg> Mr. <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName> had declared that he would not go on without Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName>, and pretended to be afraid of the dangers of the road. </seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Next morning, Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> left us and went on to the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>. About a day's drive, the other side of the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, we met him returning in company with two young men, <persName key="Young, Cau"><persName key="Young, Henry T.">brothers Young</persName></persName>, horse-thieves, who were escaping from justice in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>; having been assisted in getting away by those who had them in custody. Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> stated, that when he reached the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> he found the young boys, in company with <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><persName key="Baker, Abel">an emigrant who had escaped the massacre</persName></seg>. That on his arrival, there was not an Indian in sight, and that he had to give the whoop to call them from concealment. He said in continuation, without appearing to notice the discrepancy, that on his arrived he found <orgName type="native" key="Paiute">the Indians</orgName> hotly pursuing the three men; and that they jumped upon the emigrant and killed him before his eyes, before he could interfere to prevent it. He said he threw himself between the boys and the Indians, and had great difficulty in saving them. The Indians were in a great excitement, as he said, but that as <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName> were Mormons, they could pass without danger.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">We arrived at the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName> the day after we met Mr. <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName>, and the <persName key="Young, Cau"><persName key="Young, Henry T.">brothers Young</persName></persName>. We found here 30 or 40 Indians, and the mail riders from <placeName type="settlement" key="Los Angeles, CA">Los Angeles</placeName>, who had come in that morning. The Indians were very friendly, and shook hands with everybody. No expression of hostility to Americans was heard, but that was accounted for on the ground that this was a Mormon train.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At the <geogName type="waterway" key="Vegas River">Vegas</geogName> we found another band of Indians. The chief asked our interpreter whether our captain had brought him no word from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, whether he was nearly ready to fight the Americans yet; adding that he was ready, had got his arrows poisoned, &amp;c &amp;c.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">At the Cotton Woods, 15 miles from the <geogName type="waterway" key="Vegas River">Vegas</geogName>, <persName key="Chief Brigham Young">the chief, called Brigham Young</persName>, said he was afraid of the emigrant train behind, and wished to know if they would shoot.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">On the 1st October, we arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, and <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSApostates">I was advised by Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName>, who I learned, was a President or Elder in that place, not to associate with the damned apostates, that they were cut throats of the worst character.</seg> If I wished, they would give me constant work at their mill in the mountains, and I must be careful not to talk too much of what I had seen.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS">Whilst in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName> I heard many persons express gratification at the massacre. At the church services on Sunday, Capt. <persName key="Hunt, Jefferson">Hunt</persName> occupied the pulpit, and among other things, he said that the hand of the Lord was in it; whether it was done by white or red skins, it was right! The prophesies concerning Missouri were being fulfilled, and they would all be accomplished.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers"><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Mr. Matthews said the work had just begun, and it should be carried on until Uncle Sam and all his boys that were left, should come to Zion and beg for bread.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">I did not stay in <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San Bernardino</placeName>, because it did not appear to be a free country, for I am an American, and like freedom of thought and speech.</seg></p>
	
<p>Thus far the narrative of Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>.</p>
	
<p>On being asked, if he did not at any time express any feeling, in the company, at the wholesale massacre of his countrymen. <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">He replied, it was not safe to express an opinion. The men he was with were unscrupulous, and would not have hesitated to kill him for any unguarded words. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">When the <orgName type="native" key="Paiute">Indians</orgName> passed by him, wearing the garments of American women</seg>, and seeming to exult in their crimes, his blood boiled, but he dared not speak; and after they were gone, he asked <persName key="Mathews, William">Matthews</persName>, with earnestness, why it had been done. <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_TannerMathews"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><persName key="Mathews, William">Matthews</persName> replied, that he must not grieve or take on, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="SexualViolence">for the women were all prostitutes, that their bodies had been examined by President <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName></seg>, and this ought to console him.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution"><persName key="Mathews, William">Matthews</persName> rejoiced greatly at the massacre, and considered it the beginning of long delayed vengeance.</seg></seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Powers">Mr. <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName> regretted it, and seemed to be deeply grieved.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">It is supposed that one hundred and eighteen (118) persons were killed of whom fifty six (56) were men</seg>, and that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">fifteen (15) children were taken back to Cedar City&#8212;of whom, not one was over six years old.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">It was reported, that but one Indian was killed.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">P. M. Warn</persName>, of Bergen, Genesee county, New York; who was a fellow-traveler with Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>, on that fatal journey, corroborates the statements of <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>, so far as he was acquainted with the facts, and gives the following additional particulars, which did not come under the observation of Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>:</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> states that there was a coolness between himself and Mr. <persName key="Mathews, William">Matthews</persName>, arising from the frankness with which he expressed his opinions, and in consequence of this, he was not treated with as much confidence as Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>.</seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, via <placeName type="settlement" key="Independence">Independence</placeName>, on the 7th of April last, and remained until the 26th, on which day he started for California, as a passenger in <persName key="Mathews, William">Matthews</persName> and <persName key="Tanner, Sidney">Tanner</persName>'s train. He states, that on his journey through the settlements, which was a week or ten days subsequent to the passage of the murdered train,<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution"> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">he every where heard the same threats of vengeance against them, for their boisterousness and abuse of Mormons and Mormonism, as was reported, and these threats seemed to be made with the intention of preparing the mind to expect a calamity</seg>, and also when a calamity occurred, it should appear to fall upon transgressors, as a matter of retribution.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p>Mr. Warn says according to his memorandum, <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn"><q>On the 5th of September we encamped at <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">Here I had conversation with the Indian agent, concerning the poisoning of the ox. He said that six Indians had died; that others were sick and would die. Upon one of them, the poison had worked out all over his breast, and he was dead next morning, as reported. Afterwards, I conversed with an Indian, said to be the war chief <persName key="Ammon">Ammon</persName>, who spoke good English. I inquired how many of his tribe had died from eating the poisoned animal. He replied not any&#8212;but some were sick. He did not attribute the sickness to poison, nor did he give any reason for it.</seg> His manner, and that of all his people towards us, was not only friendly, but cordial; and he did not mention the train which had been doomed. Besides the Mormon train, there were camped at this place two or three emigrants trains, amounting to fifteen or eighteen wagons, with whom the Indians were as friendly as with ourselves. From <geogName type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn Creek</geogName>, nothing of importance occurred more than is related by Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>, until we arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. Here the four men, spoken of by Mr. <persName key="Powers, George">Powers</persName>, (and among whom I recognized Mr. <persName key="Dame, William">Dame</persName>,) arrived at our camp; they wished to get fresh animals, that they might go on that night to the besieged party. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">This was on Friday night, the night on which the slaughter was completed.</seg> They rested an hour or two, and took refreshments. In the conversation which ensured, one our party said, 'be careful, and don't get shot, Mr. <persName key="Haight, Isaac">Haight</persName>.' Mr. <persName key="Haight, Isaac">H.</persName> replied, &#34;we shall have no shooting;&#34; emphasizing the we, and throwing up his head, as if he meant to imply that the shooting would be all over before he arrived. They left us in good spirits.</q></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSGreed">One reason that may be assigned for the massacre of this train, is, that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">it was known to be in possession of considerable valuable property, and this fact excited the cupidity of the Mormons. It was said, they had over 400 head of stock, besides mules, &amp;c. They were well supplied with arms and ammunition, an element of gain which enters largely into all Mormon calculations. The train was composed of families who all seemed to be in good circumstances, and as they were moving to California, their outfit indicated that they might be in possession of considerable funds.</seg></seg></seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">The men were very free in speaking of the Mormons; their conduct was said to have been reckless, and they would commit little acts of annoyance for the purpose of provoking the saints. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSRetribution">Feeling perfectly safe in their arms and numbers, they seemed to set at defiance all the powers that could be brought against them. And they were not permitted to feel the dangers that surrounded them, until they were cut off from all hope of relief.</seg></seg></p>
	
<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Warn">Mr. <persName key="Warn, P. M.">Warn</persName> states, in speaking of the emigrant who escaped and was killed at the <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="waterway" key="Painter Creek">Painter Creek</geogName>, some six or seven miles on the other side of the place of massacre</seg>, a Mormon told him that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"><seg type="Source" subtype="Children">one of the little girls who was taken back, and who is about six years old, said that she saw her mother killed by an arrow, and that her father had escaped to California</seg></seg>.  This was before <persName key="Hatch, Ira">Hatch</persName> joined the train. The matter of the escaped was talked over by the Mormon captains, and <persName key="Mathews, William">Mathews</persName> made the remark, If the man comes into our train, he shall not be received!</seg></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>