<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">History of Salt Lake City</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename>Edward</forename> <forename type="middle">W.</forename> <surname>Tullidge</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.uh.tullidge.1886</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m">History of Salt Lake City</title>
                    <author><forename>Edward</forename> <forename type="middle">W.</forename> <surname>Tullidge</surname></author>
                    <publisher>Star Printing Company</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Salt Lake City, UT</pubPlace>
                    <extent>140-44; 157-65; 225-238; 238-245</extent>
                    <date when="1886">1886</date>
                    <note type="source">Edward W. Tullidge. <hi rend="italic">History of Salt Lake City.</hi> Salt Lake City, UT: Star Printing Company, 1886, 140-144, 157-165, 225-238, 238-245.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>utah_history</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-06-21"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2009"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>

<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="140" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.140"/>

<head>CHARLES W. PENROSE</head>

<p><persName key="Penrose, Charles W.">Charles William Penrose</persName>, one of the foremost citizens of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and one whose name is a synonym for rapid thought and untiring activity, was born at Camberwell, London, England, on the 4th of February, 1832, and is a scion of well known Cornish families, who were stockholders of tin mines. Being naturally of a studious and inquiring turn of mind, with quick perception and remarkable memory, he speedily mastered at school the common rudiments of education. He read the Scriptures when only four yers old, and was well versed in the doctrines of the Bible, the wonderful sayings and predictions of the Savior, and the ancient Prophets and Apostles. This paved the way for his acquaintance with, and his subsequent acceptance of, Mormonism, which, from its Scriptural character, its reasonable and substantial doctrines, feasible theories, and sound practical results, attracted his attention while a mere lad, and, in due time, after he had thoroughly investigated and compared its teachings with the Bible, numbered him among its converts.</p>

<!--The following section is not relevant to the Mountain Meadows Massacre:

<p>He joined the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in London, May 14, 1850, and is the only member of his father's family who has ever embraced the faith. His scriptural attainments and spiritual inclinations soon brought him under notice of the presiding authorities of the London Conference, and in January, 1851, when not yet nineteen years old, he was ordained an Elder, and two months later was sent on a mission to Maldon, in Essex, to preach the Gospel, "break new ground," and build up branches of the church. This movement was much in opposition to the wishes of his friends, and to his own pecuniary interests, as he had been offered, on condition of his remaining home, a life situation at in a government office. Shutting his eyes to the gilded bait of temptation, he took up the cross of the master, and literally "without purse or scrip," taking not not a penny in his pocket, nor even a change of dress, started out afoot upon his mission as a servant of the Lord.</p>

<p>With bleeding feet but undaunted heart, he reached the town of Maldon, having slept out of doors for the first time in his life the chilly night previous. He was an utter stranger in the place, wed the first "Mormon" Elder to visit that region of the country. He met with much opposition, but steadily worked his way in the town of Maldon and the country round about, and succeeded in raising up branches of the Church in Maldon, Danbury, Chelmsford, Colchester and other places, baptizing a great number of persons of both sexes, many of whom are now in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and being instrumental, by the laying on of hands, in the restoration to health of many persons afflicted with disease. He possessed the gift of healing to a remarkable degree, and several of the cures per-formed were of a miraculous order. He labored for seven years in poor agricultural districts,  <choice><orig>open-

<pb n="141" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.141"/>

ing</orig><reg>opening</reg></choice>
new missionary fields, building up branches, suffering many hardships and trudging on foot between three and four thousand miles every year. It was during this period, on the 21st of January, 1885, that he married Miss Lucetta Stratford, of Maldon, sister of Bishop Edward Stratford of Ogden, who with all the family he had brought into the Church. Elder Penrose was next called to pre-side over the London Conference, and subsequently over the Cheltenham Pastorate, consisting of the Cheltenham. Worcestershire and Herefordshire Conferences; and later over the Birmingham Pastorate, consisting of the Birmingham, Warwickshire, Staffordshire and Shropshire Conferences. His pen, ever brilliant and keen, at this time was almost as busy as his ready tongue. He wrote many theological articles for the <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>, principal Church organ of the European mission, and out of the silken and golden threads of his poetical thoughts and emotions, wove the fabric of those beautiful songs of Zion which have cheered the hearts and fired with patriotism and holy zeal the drooping souls of thousands.</p>

<p>In the year 1861, after over ten years of gratuitous and successful service in the ministry, he was released from his labors and emigrated to America. He crossed the sea in the sailing ship <hi rend="italic">Underwriter</hi>, assisting in the charge of 620 passengers, and living with them in the steerage during the thirty days passage from Liverpool to New York. He also helped to care for them during the journey through the States and up the Missouri river. He crossed the plains, driving his own ox team, with his family and his wife's relatives, and was eleven weeks on the toilsome way.</p>

<p>Arriving in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> he settled in Farmington, Davis County, and for the first time in his life went to work in the fields, climbing the mountains for firewood, and laboring at the hardest kind of physical work, for which he was naturally unfit, and teaching school in the winter. He made headway, however, and acquired a small home. During his three years residence there, he was ordained one of the presidents of the 56th quorum of Seventies. In the fall of 1864, at the solicitation of Apostle E. T. Benson, he removed to Cache Valley and again labored for a home, teaching school in the winter. He had scarcely more than secured some land, a log cabin and lot, when he was called, in April, 1865, to go to England on a mission, and was notified to be in Salt Lake City by the first of May, prepared with means to carry him on his journey.</p>

<p>In company with forty other missionaries, in charge of Captain Wm. B. Preston, Elder Penrose set out upon his second journey across the plains, with mule teams, but walking most of the way. They were thirty-six days in reaching Omaha. The Indians were very hostile at the time, and people were killed before and behind the little band of missionaries, but they got through in safety, despite many fears and predictions to the contrary, and reaching New York, sailed for Liver-pool. Elder Penrose arrived in England, labored first among the colliers in Lancashire, with success, and on the first of February, 1866. was sent to preside over the Essex Conference, which he had built up several years before. On the 6th of June following he was appointed to preside over the London Conference. He traveled all over the British Isles and visited Paris during the great exposition. The last two years of his mission he assisted to edit the <hi rend="italic">Millennial Star</hi>, under President F. D. Richards; also preaching on Sundays in different places, baptizing many in Liverpool, and helping to ship many companies of emigrating Saints. At the close of the emigration season of 1868, he was released from his mission and sailed for home; taking rail from New York to Point of Rocks, and thence by stage line to Salt Lake City, arriving in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> after an absence of three and a half years.</p>

<p>He next engaged in mercantile pursuits, with W. H. Shearman, in Logan, under the firm name of Shearman &amp; Penrose, and did a fine business until the co-operative movement was instituted, when the whole stock was turned over to the new institution. On the first of May, 1869, Mr. Penrose became secretary and treasurer of the Logan Co-operative Institution, and bookkeeper for the store. He acted as a home missionary, traveling and preaching on Sundays, often in company with Apostle Benson ; was a member of the high council, and took an active part in all Church movements in the county.</p>

<p>In January, 1870, he resigned his position in the Co-operative Institution, bade adieu to Logan and took up his residence in Ogden, having been invited by Apostle F. D. Richards to take editorial charge, under his supervision. of the Ogden <hi rend="italic">Junction</hi>, which had just been started as a semi-weekly, This was an occupation for which he was peculiarly well fitted, not only by nature&#8212;which undoubtedly designed him for a journalist&#8212;but by education and experience ; and the paper which he did so much to build up and render popular, and which lived and prospered as long as he was connected with it, will be long remembered for the interest and pointed vigor, the "snap and ginger" of his pungent writings, He was assistant editor one year, and was then made editor-in-chief. and afterwards business manager as well. He started the <hi rend="italic">Daily Junction</hi> in September, 1872, and

<pb n="142" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.142"/>

much of the time was its editor, local, business manager, and traveling agent, and&#8212;to use his own terse expression&#8212;was "worked half to death."</p>

<p>Having previously become naturalized, he was elected, February 13. 1871, a member of the Ogden City Council. He took active part in all the affairs and improvements of the municipality&#8212;as long as he remained in Ogden, and he was re-elected to the council every term; his name was found on both tickets whenever there were two parties in the field. He served, in all, four terms, and before the expiration of the last one had removed to Salt Lake City. At the organization of the Weber Stake of Zion he was ordained a High Priest and made a member of the High Council,&#8212;and remained so for a long time alter his removal from Ogden. He also acted as a home missionary bath in aS take and Territorial capacity.</p>

<p>His political record in the municipality having won him influence and the confidence of his associates and the people generally, he was chosen delegate from Weber County to the Constitutional Convention of 1872, being elected by the popular vote on February 5th, of that year. He helped to frame the Constitution of the State of Deseret and the memorial to Congress, being on the committees having that work in hand. The same year he represented Weber County in the Democratic Territorial Convention, which was composed of both Mormons and Gentiles, and nominated for his wing of the party, Hon. George Q. Cannon as delegate to Congress, making a pointed speech in the convention. He was a member and secretary of the People's County Central Committee, and a live worker in all political movements, making speeches and using his influence in -every way for the success of the People's party. During the same period, he was busily engaged in ecclesiastical affairs under President Richards.</p>

<p>In August, 1874, he was elected a member of the Legislature, representing Weber County in the Territorial Assembly. He took an active part in all general measures, introduced a number of bills, drafted public documents, and rendered other valuable service for which his literary ability and native legal acumen well qualified him. At the same time he wrote all the editorials and reports of the Legislature for the Ogden <hi rend="italic">Junction</hi>. In 1875 he found himself so overworked that he resigned the business management of the <hi rend="italic">Junction</hi>, but continued as editor, and did all the literary work, local and telegraph included, for both the daily and semi-weekly issues. He also continued ac-live in municipal and Church affairs.</p>

<p>In the fall of 1876, Mr. Penrose went to California to represent Thomas and Esther Duce, mother and son, in the adjustment of a pecuniary issue. In September of that year the Duces had been shot by a Wells, Fargo &amp; Co 's guard who dropped his gun, a double-barrelled weapon loaded with slugs ; the whole contents being fired into them. Thomas was literally riddled, and his mother was shot through the windpipe. Mr. Penrose, assisted the doctor to dress the wounds; both patients recovered. The company disclaimed responsibility for the accident, but Mr. Penrose met&#8212;with the managers in San Francisco, prevailed on them and obtained five thousand dollars compensation for the Duces.</p>

<p>In June, 1877, by request of President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, he came to Salt Lake City and became connected with the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, under the general editorial management of Hons. George Q. Cannon and <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>. Jr. The Junction Company keenly felt his loss, and offered to give him the paper entirely. On the organization of the Deseret Newt Company. at the first meet-of the Board of Directors held September 3d, 1880, C. W. Penrose was made editor-in-chief of that veteran journal, and still remains so. He became a home missionary of the Salt Lake Stake, and traveled and preached in many places.</p>

<p>At a special election in 1879. held for the purpose of filling the vacancy caused by the death of Hon. A. P. Rockwood, member elect of the Legislature for Salt Lake County, Hon. C. W. Penrose was the people's choice for that office, which he filled with credit to himself and to the satisfaction of his constituents. He served during the session of 1880 on various important committees, including the judiciary, and introduced many bills, among them a bill to take away all political disabilities from women. The bill created no end of discussion, comment and debate, its author making able and pithy speeches in its favor, and finally it passed both houses but was vetoed by the Governor. Following is one of his speeches on this question which will serve to show his style:</p>

<p>"<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> is the home of liberty for all, and peculiarly the sanctuary for women; here all her rights are popularly acknowledged and accorded Here she is protected and defended. Here the conventionalities which have kept her in bondage for ages are thrown aside by the force of an enlightened estimate of her capabilities and an enlarged view of her claims is an integral part of the body politic. The right to vote has already been conferred upon her. The laws of the nation declare her a citizen equal with man ; the laws of this Territory give her equal rights with man at the polls. This has

<pb n="143" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.143"/>

worked no injury to ant, but will necessarily result in good. For the power of the suffrage will develop thought, and its responsibilities give occasion for reflection, and the enlarged capacities of women which will be the natural consequence, will be transmitted to her offspring, and benefits will thus accrue to the Stare in the coming generation.</p>

<p>"None of the disasters predicted by the opponents of woman suffrage have occurred in this Territory. The women have exercised their power in wisdom, and have shown their fitness for the trust reposed in them. They have not been degraded nor polluted in the waters of politics, and are just as good wives, mothers, sisters, cousins and aunts, as before receiving the elective franchise. Recently they have had some voice in our caucuses and conventions and nominating committees, and who can say truthfully that this has been in any way inimical to the community. Giving them the right to vote without the right to a voice in the arrangement of a ticket or platform on which to vote, would be partial and inconsistent.</p>

<p>"Having done so much for woman's cause, why halt in timid hesitation before the last barrier to her politicial freedom? The word 'male' in our statutes, defining the qualifications of citizens for holding offices, is a relic of the old system of woman's vassalage. It is a standing reflection upon her sex. It is a plain assertion of her inferiority. It says, virtually, no matter how wise, intellectual, honest, thrifty, able and gifted a woman may be, she is not fit to be entrusted with the responsibilities of the smallest office in the gift of the people. If this is not its meaning, then it is a selfish declaration that all the honors and emoluments of every office shall be reserved to the stronger sex, because man has the power to elbow woman out into the cold and keep her there. There are some offices for which women are not adapted. But are there not also some offices for which many men are not adapted? Yet no man, however inefficent, is debarred by statutory provisions from such positions. But woman is shut out from all and this purely and solely because she is woman.</p>

<p>"The good sense of the great body of electors of both sexes must determine what those offices may be, and as in the case of men, which persons are the most competent to fill them. The bill will not secure a single office to a single woman&#8212;or a married one, either. But it will break down in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> a wall which is in the way of the march of progress, and every stone and brick of which will yet be entirely removed in every nation that is really civilized.</p>

<p>"Massachusetts and other States have commenced the work. Women there can not only vote on school matters. but hold official positions on school boards and other State educational organizations. They have the same privileges in <placeName type="state" key="Kansas">Kansas</placeName>. In <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. where the elevation of woman as man's companion, not his slave, is the prevailing social theory, she cannot, under the law, hold any office of any kind whatever. Cache County would have elected a lady to the office of County Superintendent of Schools, one who has proven to the people her ample qualifications for the post. But the law forbade it. Salt Lake County contemplated nominating a talented lady for the office of County Treasurer, but the disability which this bill seeks to remove stood grimly in the way.</p>

<p>"It is not asked that certain offices be set apart for either sex. We are simply requested to remove this ugly and staring brand of woman's politicial inferiority from our statute book. To render it possible for women to fill such offices as they may be fitted to occupy with honor to them-selves and profit to the people.</p>

<p>"Now, I do not cite these as sample offices to which women should be elected, but merely to refer to these facts in illustration of the subject and to show reasons why the discriminating and egotistical word 'male' should be expunged from the statutes relating to qualifications for office. Used in this light, it is a slur on our wives and sisters and mothers. It is a vestige of the barbaric estimate of the gentler sex. Away with it ! Blot it out with the pen of a progressive age and the ink of advanced ideas! Let it go with its companion that once stood in the way of woman suffrage, but was swept into the limbo of antiquated measures by the besom of the act of 1870. Give to the women of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>&#8212;there are no better in the world&#8212;full, perfect and complete political liberty."</p>

<p>Mr. Penrose was re-elected and served in the Legislative session of 1882 ; he was chairman of the committee on claims, and did a great deal of work on various committees; being particularly useful in drafting public documents and correcting errors in the framing of bills. He was elected to the constitutional convention and helped to frame the Constitution of the State of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, which was making another effort&#8212;under a change of name from 'Deseret'&#8212;for its long withheld right of admission into the Union. He also assisted to prepare the memorial to Congress. All this time he was performing editorial work for the Dereret News.</p>

<p>The death of David O. Calder, in the summer of 1884 caused; a vacancy in the Presidency of the Salt Lake Stake of Zion, which was filled August 2d, 1884, Elder Penrose being then appointed,

<pb n="144" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.144"/>

at the quarterly stake conference, second counselor to President Angus M. Cannon. His voice was often heard in the Tabernacle and in other congregations of the Saints; he was an ever ready and apparently unfailing fountain of instruction. As one of the Presidency of the Salt Lake Stake of Zion it was also a part of his duty and labors to sit in the High Council in judgment upon all matters before that tribunal.</p>

-->

<p>In the fall of 1883, in order to recuperate his energies, which were sorely taxed by overwork, <persName key="Penrose, Charles W.">he</persName> took a trip, in company with <persName key="Savage, C. R.">C. R. Savage</persName>, Esq., over the D. and R. G. Railway to <placeName type="settlement" key="Denver, CO">Denver</placeName>, thence through <placeName type="state" key="Colorado">Colorado</placeName>, south to <placeName type="state" key="New Mexico">New Mexico</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Arizona">Arizona</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, returning to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> via the Central Pacific route. He now resumed his manifold duties. He had previously written a valuable work entitled "Mormon Doctrine." In the fall of 1884, he delivered several Sunday evening lectures in the Twelfth Ward Assembly Hall, answering anti-Mormon objections and charges against the faith and practice of the Latter-day Saints. Chief of these lectures were those on "Blood Atonement" and the Mountain Meadows Massacre," completely refuting the common stories in relation thereto. Both lectures were published at the <hi rend="italic">Juvenile Instructor</hi> office. He continued to defend the "Mormon" cause politically and religiously, by press discussions as well as public speeches and private interviews with strangers. These vigorous labors excited the hostility of the anti-Mormon ring, and he was singled out, in the crusade under the Edmunds law, as a conspicuous target for their animosity. In the beginning of January, 1885, he was sent on a brief mission to the States, and during his absence his legal wife and family, down to a boy eight years old, were compelled to go before the grand jury. The wife refused to testify against her husband, but the evidence desired was extorted from the children.</p>

<!-- This section is Not Relevant to the Mountain Meadows Massacre.

<p>While in the States Elder Penrose was appointed on a mission to England, and forthwith bade farewell, by letter, to those he held most dear this side of the water, and once more crossed the bosom of the mighty deep. After a rough passage and safe landing at Liverpool, he was appointed by President D. H. Wells to preside over the London Conference, and assist editorially on the Millennial Star," He revived the work in London, his old field of labor, was gladly hailed by former acquaintances, wrote several articles for London papers, helped to ship emigrants of every company from Liverpool, and attended conferences with President Wells all over England Scotland and Wales. He also visited Ireland and preached in the open air in the city of Belfast to three thousand people. A great uproar ensued, followed by a spirited discussion in the Belfast papers. He visited Dublin and the Isle of Man, and from there went to the Lake District of England. He accompanied President Wells on his continental tour through Denmark. Sweden, Norway, Germany and Switzerland, preaching in Copenhagen, Christiania, Stockholm, Berlin and Berne, returning to England by way of Paris. He made a stir in several English towns and brought many persons into the Church, besides writing articles for the Star and also for the Deseret News to the interest of which he is devoted though in "exile."</p>

<p>He is still engaged in laboring and writing for the cause to which he has consecrated his time and talents for so many years. He has a firm and thorough belief in the truth and triumph of Mormonism, and is kept from the society of a loving family and a wide circle of cordial friends by the same merciless persecution which has thrust so many good men behind prison doors.</p>

<p>At the age of fifty-four he retains apparently all his original activity of mind and physical energies. Time and toil have made but moderate inroads upon his extraordinary vitality. This is all the more remarkable from his not being of a robust constitution&#8212;though of healthy physique and strictly temperate habits&#8212;and his persistent and almost incessant mental activity. It exemplifies anew the truth of the proverb that it is better to wear out than to rust away. Mr. Penrose is of a highly sensitive and nervous organization; quick to think, speak and act. His talents are so versatile it is almost a question as to "wherein kind nature meant him to excel." He is poetical, musical, has fine spiritual perceptions, and also leans to science and law. His forte is generally thought to be journalism, in which he shines with lustre, while as a preacher and polemical writer and debater he has but few equals. His talents and energy fit him eminently for a missionary, in which important calling he meets invariably with success. His practical experience in various walks of life gives him an insight into the thoughts and workings of all classes of society; his advice is sought in difficulty and doubt, and he wins his way easily to the hearts of his fellow-men. Charles W. Penrose is a remarkable man. Nature stamped him as such, and his life work, thus far, confirms the truth of her decree.</p>

-->

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">
<pb n="157" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.157"/>

<head>CHAPTER XVII.</head>

<head>THE PIONEER JUBILEE. CELEBRATION OF THEIR TENTH ANNIVERSARY. ARRIVAL OF MESSENGERS WITH THE NEWS OF THE COMING OF AN INVADING ARMY. THE DAY OF JUBILEE CHANGED TO A DAY OF INDEPENDENCE. CAPTAIN VAN VLIET AND THE MORMON PEOPLE.</head>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">The people were celebrating the twenty-fourth of July&#8212;the anniversary of the pioneers&#8212;in Big Cottonwood Canyon, when the news reached them of the coming of the troops to invade their homes.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">They had conquered the desert. Cities were fast springing up in the solitary places, where cities had never been planted before, and in valleys that had once been the bed of the great sea; civilization was spreading.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">A plentiful harvest was promised that year, and every circumstance of their situation seemed favorable, except the lack of postal communication with the

<pb n="158" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.158"/>

East. Their isolation, in this particular, had kept them in ignorance, up to that time, of the movements of the Government concerning them.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">On the 22d of July, 1857, numerous teams were seen wending their way, by different routes, to the mouth of Big Cottonwood Canyon, where they halted for the night. Next morning Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> led the van of the long line of carriages and wagons, and before noon the cavalcade reached the camp ground at the Cottonwood Lake, which nestles in the bosom of the mountain, 8,000 feet above the level of the sea. Early in the afternoon, the company, numbering 2,687 persons, encamped, and soon all were busy with the arrangements for the morrow. It will be seen, at a glance, that this was intended to be a pioneer's jubilee indeed; not in a city, but in primitive surroundings, suggestive of their entrance into these valleys ten years before.</seg></p>

<!--The following section is not relevant to the Mountain Meadows Massacre: 

<p>There were in attendance: Captain Ballo's band, the Nauvoo brass band, the Ogden City brass band, and the <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName> and Ogden martial bands; also, of the military, the 1st company of light artillery, under Adjutant-General James Ferguson; a detachment of four platoons of life guards and one platoon of the lancers, under Colonel Burton; and one company of light infantry cadets, under Captain John W. Young. Colonel J. C. Little was marshal of the day.</p>

<p>Early on the following morning the people assembled, and the choir sang:</p>

<p><hi rend="center">"On the mountain tops appearing."</hi></p>

<p>Then, after prayers the Stars and Stripes were unfurled on the two highest peaks, in sight of the camp, on two of the tallest trees. At twenty minutes past nine a. m., three rounds from the artillery saluted the First Presidency, and at a quarter past ten three rounds were given for the "Hope of Israel," Captain John W. Young, with his company of light infantry, answered ta*his last salute, and went through their military evolutions to the admiration of the beholders. This company numbered fifty boys, at, about the age of twelve, who had been uniformed by Governor Young.</p>

<p>At noon, Mayor A. O. Smoot, Elder Judson Stoddard, Judge Elias Smith, and O. P. Rockwell, rode into camp, the two former from the "States" (Missouri River), in twenty days. They brought news of the coming of the troops. It was the first tidings of war. Any other people in the world would have been stricken with a terrible fear; but not so these Mormon Saints. The well-known war cry of Cromwell, when he entered into battle, "The Lord of Hosts is with us!" was the undaunted explanation of every heart, and soon it was the burden of every speech.</p>

<p>In a moment the festive song was changed to the theme of war; the jubilee of a people swelled into a sublime declaration of independence. Never before did such a spirit of heroism so suddenly and completely possess an entire community. Men and women shared it alike. The purest and most graphic passage of Stenhouse's "Rocky Mountain Saints" is the description of this eventful day. It it worthy of quotation. He says:</p>

<p>"On the 24th of July, 1857, there were probably gathered at the lake about two thousand persons&#8212;men women, and children&#8212;in the fullest enjoyment of

<pb n="159" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.159"/>

social freedom. Some were fishing in the lake, others strolling among the trees, climbing the high peaks, pitching quoits, playing cricket, engaging in gymnastic exercises, pic-nicking, and gliding through the boweries that were prepared for the mazy dance. It was a day of feasting, joy, and amusement for the silver-haired veteran and the tottering child. The welkin rang with the triumphant songs of Zion, and these, accompanied by the sweet melody of many-toned instruments of music, thrilled every bosom with enthusiastic joy. Their exuberance was the pure outgushing of their souls' emotion, and owned no earthly inspiration, for their only beverage was the sparkling nectar of Eden, while their sympathies were united by a sacred and fraternal bond of affectionate love, which for the time rendered them oblivious of the artificial distinctions of social life. The highest and the lowest rejoiced together, rank and authority were set aside; it was a day in which the dreary past could be favorably contrasted with the joyous present, and hearts were made glad in the simple faith that the God of their fathers was their protector, and that they were his peculiar people.</p>

-->

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"But before the sun had crimsoned the snowy peaks that surrounded the worshiping, rejoicing Saints, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> was in possession of the news, and the people were listening with breathless attention to the most stirring, important address that ever their leader had uttered, for upon his decision depended peace or war.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> was undaunted. With the inspiration of such surroundings&#8212;the grandeur of the Wasatch range of the Rocky Mountains everywhere encircling him, the stately trees whose foliage of a century's growth towered proudly to the heavens, the multitude of people before him who had listened to his counsels as if hearkening to the voice of the Most High&#8212;men and women who had followed him from the abodes of civilization to seek shelter in the wilderness from mobs, prattling innocents and youths who knew nothing of the world but <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and who looked to him as a father for protection&#8212;what could he not say?"</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">To say that the Mormons were taken with astonishment would be to misstate the case. They had long looked for this issue. They had seen mobs marshaled against them from the <choice><sic>beginnimg</sic><corr>beginning</corr></choice>, but they had also been told by their Prophet <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Joseph Smith</persName>, early in his career, that "Some day they would see the United States come against them in war, and that the Lord should deliver them and bring glory to His name." Nothing more unlikely could have been uttered by this prophet of a few hundred disciples; as likely was it that the stars of heaven should make war upon the earth in impotent wrath. They were not even in a location at that time where this was possible. The very prophecy foreshadowed their removal to the mountains, as though to invite the nation to the issue; and its fulfillment bespoke a destiny in them superior to the destiny even of the United States. The nation was now coming against them, to verify the prophecy in the most literal manner. Hence, doubtless, the extraordinary trust and fortitude of the people, and the self-possession of their leaders. They had no doubt as to the issue, though how God would work out their deliverance they saw not fully.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Everything the Mormons did at that time was done in the most deliberate earnestness. Two messengers were immediately dispatched to England, to call home the American Elders in Europe, and ten thousand British Saints would

<pb n="160" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.160"/>

have gathered that year, had it been possible, to share the fate of their brethren and sisters in the mountains; but all emigration was, of course now cut off. Never was there so much enthusiasm in the foreign missions as then. One could judge of the sublime enthusiasm at home by that which animated the Saints abroad. Yet they saw a mighty nation moving against the handful in the mountains, and moving with a settled resolve to annihilate the Mormon power at once and forever, leaving no seed on American territory from which that power might re-germinate. The papers of America and Europe teemed with these anticipations. It was broadly suggested that volunteers from every State should pour into <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, make short work of the Saints, possess their cities, fill <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">their Territory</placeName> with a gentile population, and <seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">take their wives and daughters as spoil, thus breaking up the polygamic institution</seg>. For a time there was a prospect of this. Tens of thousands were eager for this thorough work of regeneration for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>; and, had the Government dared to encourage it, the attempt would have been made. For such a crusade, however, a civilized judgement could have found no excuse, not even on the plea of rebellion. At least, President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> was made to see this much, and to appreciate that he could only use United States regular troops, and these only in the guise of a <hi rend="italic">posse comitates</hi> to the new Governor.</seg></p>

<p>The sentiments that actuated the Mormon community at that time were of no doubtful tenor, as may be judged by the following extracts from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName>'s discourses to his people immediately after the receipt of the news.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"Liars have reported that this people have committed treason, and upon their misrepresentations <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President</persName> has ordered out troops to aid in officering <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this Territory</placeName>. If those officers are like many who have previously been sent here&#8212;and we have reason to believe that they are, or they would not come where they know they are not wanted&#8212;they are poor, broken down political hacks, not fit for the civilized society whence they came, and so they are dragooned upon us for officers. I feel that I won't bear such treatment (and that is enough to say,) for we are just as free as the mountain air. * * * This people are free; they are not in bondage to any Government on God's footstool. We have transgressed no law, neither do we intend so to do; but as for any nation coming to destroy this people, God Almighty being my helper, it shall not be! * *
* <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">We have borne enough of their oppression and abuse, and we will not bear any more of it, for there is no just law requiring further forbearance on our part.</seg> And I am not going to permit troops here for the protection of the priests and the rabble in their efforts to drive us from the land we possess. The Lord does not want us to be driven, for He has said, ' If you will assert your rights, and keep my commandments, you shall never again be brought into bondage by your enemies' * * * They say that the coming of their army is legal; and I say that it is not; they who say it are morally rotten. Come on with your thousands of illegally-ordered troops, and I promise you in the name of Israel's God, that they shall melt away as the snow before a July sun. * * * You might as well tell me that you can make hell into a powder-house as to tell me that they intend to keep an army here and have peace! * * * I have told you that if this people will live their religion all will be well; and I bare told you that if not there is any man or woman who is not willing to destroy

<pb n="161" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.161"/>

everything of their property that would be of use to an enemy if left, I would advise them to leave <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. And I again say so to-day; for when the time comes to burn and lay waste our improvements, if any man undertakes to shield his he will be treated as a traitor; for 'judgement will be laid to the line, and righteousness to the plummet.' * * * Now the faint-hearted can go in peace; but should that time come, they must not interfere. Before I will again suffer as I have in times gone by there shall not one building, nor one foot of lumber, nor a fence, nor a tree, nor a particle of grass or hay, that will burn, be left in reach of our enemies. I am sworn, if driven to extremity, to utterly lay waste this land in the name of Israel's God, and our enemies shall find it as barren as when we came here."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">It was at such a moment, as the picture suggests, that Capt. <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName> arrived in the city of the Saints. <persName key="Young, Brigham">The Governor</persName>, the Lieut. General, <persName key="Wells, Daniel H.">Daniel H. Wells</persName>, Adjt. General <persName key="Ferguson, James">Furguson</persName>, and the Apostles, received him with marked cordiality, but with an open programme, They took him into their gardens. The sisters showed him the paradise that their woman hands would destroy if that invading army came. He was awed by the prospect&#8212;his ordinary judgment confounded by such extraordinary examples. To the wife of <persName key="Carrington, Albert">Albert Carrington</persName>, in whose garden he was walking, in conversation with <persName key="Young, Brigham">the Governor</persName> and his party he exclaimed:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"What, madam! would you consent to see this beautiful home in ashes and this fruitful orchard destroyed?"</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"Yes!" answered Sister <persName key="Carrington, Rhoda Maria Woods">Carrington</persName>, with heroic resolution, "I would not only consent to it, but I would set fire to my home with my own hands, and cut down every tree and root up every plant!"</seg></p>

<p>The following extracts from conversations between Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> and Captain <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName>, on the 12th and 13th of September, 1857, will be of interest, insomuch as they were had previous to the receipt, in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, of the news of the Mountain Meadow Massacre. Their accuracy may be relied on, as they are transcribed from Apostle <persName key="Woodruff, Wilford">Woodruff</persName>'s private journal, and were originally recorded within a few hours of their occurrence, and are amply verified by many persons then present:</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution"><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName></hi>. We do not want to fight the United States, but if they drive us to it, we shall do the best we can; and I will tell you, as the Lord lives, we shall come off <choice><sic>conquerers</sic><corr>conquerors</corr></choice>, for we trust in Him. * * * God has set up his kingdom on the earth, and it will never fall. * * * We shall do all we can to avert a collision, but if they drive us to it, God will overthrow them. If they would let us alone and say to the mobs: 'Now you may go and kill the Mormons if you can, but we will have nothing to do with it,' that would be all we would ask of them; but for the Government to array the army against us, is too despicable and damnable a thing for any honorable nation to do, and God will hold them in derision who do it. * * * The United States are sending their armies here to simply hold us still until a mob can come and butcher us, as has been done before. * * * We are the supporters of the constitution of the United States, and we love that constitution

<pb n="162" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.162"/>

and respect the laws of the United States; but it is by the corrupt administration of those laws that we are made to suffer. If the law had been vindicated in <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName>, it would have sent Governor <persName key="Boggs, Lilburn">Boggs</persName> to the gallows, along with those who murdered <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Joseph</persName> and <persName key="Smith, Hyrum">Hyrum</persName>, and those other fiends who <choice><sic>accomplised</sic><corr>accomplished</corr></choice> our expulsion from the States. * * * Most of the Government officers who have been sent here have taken no interest in us, but, on the contrary, have tried many times to destroy us.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">Capt. <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName></hi> This is the case with most men sent to the Territories. They receive their offices as a political reward, or as a stepping-stone to the Senatorship; but they have no interest in common with the people. * * * This people has been lied about the worst of any people I ever saw. * * The greatest hold that the Government now has upon you is in the accusation that you have burned the United States records.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">"<hi rend="italic">President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName></hi>. I deny that any books of the United States have been burned! All I ask of any man is, that he tell the truth about us, pay his debts and not steal, and then he will be welcome to come or go as he likes. * * If the Government has arrived at that state that it will try to kill this people because of their religion, <hi rend="italic">no honorable man <choice><sic>shoald</sic><corr>should</corr></choice> be afraid of it.</hi> * * * We would like to ward off this blow if we can; but the United States seem determined to drive us into a fight. They will kill us if they can. A mob killed <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Joseph</persName> and <persName key="Smith, Hyrum">Hyrum</persName> in jail, notwithstanding the faith of the State was pledged to protect them. * * * I have broken no law, and under the present state of affairs I will not suffer myself to be taken by any United States officeri to be killed as they killed <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Joseph</persName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">Capt. <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName></hi>: I do not think it is the intention of the Government to arrest you, but to install a new governor in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>: I believe you tell the truth&#8212;that you believe this&#8212;but you do not know their intentions as well as I do. When you get away from here you will think off great many things that you have seen and heard: for instance, <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">people have accused us of colleaguing with the Indians against the Government: they were much afraid that <persName key="Smith, Joseph">Joseph Smith</persName> would go among the Indians, and they wanted to keep him away from them; but now they have driven us into their midst. I want you to note the signs of the times; you will see that God will chastise this nation for trying to destroy both the Indians and the Mormons. * * * If the Government persists in sending an army to destroy us, in the name of the Lord we shall conquer them. If they dare to force the issue, I shall not hold the Indians by the wrist any longer, for white men to shoot at them; they shall go ahead and do as they please. If the issue comes, you may tell the Government to stop all emigration across this continent, for the Indians will kill all who attempt it. And if an army <choice><sic>suceceds</sic><corr>suceeds</corr></choice> in penetrating this valley, tell the Government to see that it has forage and provisions in store, for they will find here only a charred and barren waste.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">Capt. <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName></hi>: * * * If our Government pushes this matter to the extent of making war upon you, I will withdraw from the army, for I will not have a hand in shedding the blood of American citizens.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName></hi>: We shall trust in God.      *      *      * Congress

<pb n="163" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.163"/>

has promptly sent investigating committees to <placeName type="state" key="Kansas">Kansas</placeName> and other places, as occasion has required; but upon the merest rumor it has sent 2,000 armed soldiers to destroy the people of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, without investigating the subject at all.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">Capt. <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName></hi>. The Government may yet send an investigating committee to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and consider it good policy, before they get through.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName></hi>. I believe God has sent you here, and that good will grow out of it. I was glad when I <choice><sic>heart</sic><corr>heard</corr></choice> you were coming.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">Capt. <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName></hi>. I am anxious to get back to <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName> as soon as I can. I have heard officially that General <persName key="Harney, William S.">Harney</persName> has been recalled to <placeName type="state" key="Kansas">Kansas</placeName> to officiate as Governor. I shall stop the train on Ham's Fork on my own responsibility.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName></hi>. If we can keep the peace for this Winter I do think there will something turn up that may save the shedding of blood."</seg></p>

<p>The reader cannot fail to perceive that the terrible butchery <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain Meadow</geogName></seg>&#8212;was farthest from <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s <hi rend="italic">policy</hi> at that time, to say nothing of humanitarian considerations.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">But, though Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> was aiming for some such consummation as that which came, he neither allowed himself nor his people to retreat a step from their chosen position. Indeed, in their stern fidelity to their cause was their only safety and successful outcome.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Captain <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName> thus reported to the commanding general of the army:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><hi rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ham's Fork</hi>, September 16, 1857.</hi></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<hi rend="italic">Captain</hi>: I have the honor to report, for the information of the commanding general, the result of my trip to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory of Utah</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"In obedience to special instructions, dated headquarters army for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, Fort Leavenworth, July 28, 1857, I left Fort Leavenworth, July 30, and reached Fort Kearny in nine travelling days, Fort Laramie in ten, and <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName> in thirty-three and a half. At Fort Kearny I was detained one day by the changes I had to make and by sickness, and at Fort Laramie three days, as all the animals were forty miles from the post, and when brought in all had to be shod before they could take the road. I traveled as rapidly as it is possible to do with six mule wagons. Several of my teams broke down, and at least half of my animals are unserviceable and will remain so until they recruit. During my progress towards <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> I met many people from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">that Territory</placeName>, and also several mountain men at Green river, and all informed me that I would not be allowed to enter <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and if I did I would run great risk of losing my life. I treated all this, however, as idle talk, but it induced me to leave my wagons and escort at Ham's Fork, 143 miles this side of the city, and proceed alone. I reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName> without molestation, and immediately upon my arrival I informed Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> that I desired an interview, which he appointed for the next day. On the evening of the day of my arrival Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, with many of the leading men of the city, called upon me at my quarters. The governor received me most cordially and treated me during my stay, which continued some six days, with the greatest hospitality and kindness.

<pb n="164" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.164"/>

In this interview <persName key="Young, Brigham">the governor</persName> made known to me his views with regard to the approach of the United States troops, in plain and <choice><sic>unmistakeable</sic><corr>unmistakable</corr></choice> language.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">"He stated that the Mormons had ben persecuted, murdered, and robbed in <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="Illinois">Illinois</placeName> both by the mob and State authorities, and that now the United States were about to pursue the same course, and that, therefore, he and the people of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> had determined to resist all persecution at the commencement, and that the <hi rend="italic">troops now on the march for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> should not enter the Great Salt Lake valley</hi>. As he uttered these words all those present concurred most heartily in what he said.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"The next day, as agreed upon, I called upon the governor and delivered in person the letter with which I had been entrusted. In that interview, and in several subsequent ones, the same determination to resist to the death the entrance of the troops into the valley was expressed by Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> and those about him.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"<seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution"><persName key="Young, Brigham">The governor</persName> informed me that there was abundance of everything I required for the troops, such as lumber, forage, etc., but that none would be sold to us. In the course of my conversations with the governor and the influential men in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, I told them plainly and frankly what I conceived would be the result of their present course. I told them that they might prevent the small military force now approaching <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> from getting through the narrow defiles and rugged passes of the mountains this year, but that next season the United States government would send troops sufficient to overcome all opposition. The answer to this was invariably the same: "We are aware that such will be the case; but when those troops arrive they will find <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> a desert. Every house will be burned to the ground, every tree cut down, and every field laid waste. We have three years' provisions on hand, which we will 'cache,' and then take to the mountains and bid defiance to all the powers of the government." I attended their service on Sunday, and, in course of a sermon delivered by Elder <persName key="Taylor, John W.">Taylor</persName>, he referred to the approach of the troops and declared they should not enter <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. He then referred to the probability of an overpowering force being sent against them, and desired all present, who would apply the torch to their own buildings, cut down their trees, and lay waste their fields, to hold up their hands. Every hand, in an audience numbering over 4,000 persons, was raised at the same moment. During my stay in the city I visited several families, and all with whom I was thrown looked upon the present movement of the troops towards their Territory as the commencement of another religious persecution, and expressed a fixed determination to sustain Governor Young in any measures he might adopt. From all these facts I am forced to the conclusion that Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> and the people of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> will prevent, if possible, the army for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> from entering their Territory this season. This, in my opinion, will not be a difficult task, owing to the lateness of tiie season, the smallness of our force, and the defences that nature has thrown around the valley of the Great Salt Lake.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"There is but one road running into the valley on the side which our troops are approaching, and for over fifty miles it passes through narrow canyons and over rugged mountains, which a small force could hold against great odds. I am

<pb n="165" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.165"/>

inclined however, to believe that the Mormons will not resort to actual hostilities until the last moment. Their plan of operations will be, burn the grass, cut up the roads, and stampede the animals, so as to delay the troops until the snow commences to fall, which will render the road impassable. Snow falls early in this region, in fact last night it commenced falling at Fort Bridger, and this morning the surrounding mountains are clothed in white. Were it one month earlier in the season I believe the troops could force their way in, and they may be able to do so even now; but the attempt will be fraught with considerable danger, arising from the filling up of the canyons and passes with snow. I do not wish it to be considered that I am advocating either the one course or the other. I simply wish to lay the facts before the general, leaving it to his better judgment to decide upon the proper movements. Notwithstanding my inability to make the purchases I was ordered to, and all that Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> said in regard to opposing the entrance of the troops into the valley I examined the country in the vicinity of the city, with the view of selecting a proper military site. I visited the military reserve, Rush Valley, but found it, in my opinion, entirely unsuitable for a military station. It contains but little grass, and is very much exposed to the cold winds of winter; its only advantage being the close proximity of fine wood. It is too far from the city, being between thirty-five and forty miles, and will require teams four days to go there and return.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">I examined another point on the road to Rush Valley, and only about thirty miles from the city, which I consider a much more eligible position. It is in Tuelle Valley three miles to the north of Tuelle city, and possesses wood, water, and grass; but it is occupied by the Mormons, who have some sixty acres under cultivation, with houses and barns on their land. These persons would have to be dispossessed or bought out. In fact there is no place within forty, fifty or sixty miles of the city suitable for a military position, that is not occupied by the inhabitants and under cultivation. On my return I examined the vicinity of Fort Bridger, and found it a very suitable position for wintering the troops and grazing the animals, should it be necessary to stop at that point. The Mormons occupy the fort at present, and also have a settlement about ten miles further up Black's Fork, called Fort Supply. These two places contain buildings sufficient to cover nearly half the troops now en route for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>; but I was informed that they would all be laid in ashes as the army advances. I have thus stated fully the result of my visit to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and trusting that my conduct will meet the approval of the commanding general, I am, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</seg></p>

<p><hi rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">STEWART VAN VLIET</hi>,</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Captain A. Q. M.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">"Captain Pleasanton,</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A. A. Adft Gen. Army for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, Fort Leavenworth.</hi> </p>

<p>"P. S.&#8212;I shall start on my return to-morrow, with an escort of ten men."</p>

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="225" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.225"/>

<head>CHAPTER XXV.</head>

<head>GOVERNOR GUMMING PLEADS WITH THE SAINTS. THEY RETURN TO THEIR HOMES. THE JUDGES. CRADLEBAUGHS COURT. HE CALLS FOR TROOPS. PROVO CITY INVADED BY THE ARMY. CONSPIRACY TO ARREST BRIGHAM YOUNG. GOVERNOR CUMMING ORDERS OUT THE UTAH MILITIA TO REPEL INVASION. TIMELY ARRIVAL OF A DISPATCH FROM GOVERNMENT STAYS THE CONFLICT. ATTORNEY-GENERAL BLACK'S REBUKE TO THE JUDGES. GENERAL JOHNSTONS FRIENDS DEMAND THE REMOVAL OF GOVERNOR CUMMING. THE SITUATION RECOVERED BY THE PATRIOTISM OF THOMAS L. KANE. DIVISION IN THE CABINET. PARALLEL OF THE BLAINE REMINISCENCE OF JERE S. BLACK.</head>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution"><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Return we now to the Saints in their flight. It had taxed their faith and their means to an absolute consecration of their all, and called forth as much religious heroism as did their first exodus from <placeName type="settlement" key="Nauvoo, IL">Nauvoo</placeName>. Gallant old Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> was almost distracted over this Mormon episode. He was not used to the self-sacrifices and devotion of the peculiar people whom he had taken under his official guardianship. They were more familiar than he with this part of their eventful drama. Familiarity had bred in them a kind of contempt for their own sufferings and privations. So they witnessed their new Governor's concern for them with a stoical humor. They were, indeed, grateful, but amused. They could not feel to deserve his pity, yet were they thankful for his sympathy. They sang psalms by the wayside. He felt like strewing their path with tears. He followed them fifty miles south, praying them, as would a father his wayward children, to turn back. But the father whom they knew better was leading them on.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"There is no longer danger. General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> and the army will keep faith with the Mormons. Every one concerned in this happy settlement will hold sacred
the amnesty and pardon of the President of the United States! By G&#8212;d, sirs, Yes."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Such was the style of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>'s pleadings with the "misguided" Mormons. But <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> replied with a quiet fixedness of purpose:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">"We know all about it, <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Governor</persName>. We remember the martyrdoms of the past! We have, on just such occasions, seen our disarmed men hewn down in cold blood, our virgin daughters violated, our wives ravished to death before our eyes. We know all about it, Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Gumming</persName>."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">It was a terrible logic that thus met the brave meditation of the fine old Georgian successor of Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, who coupled patriotism with humanity, and believed in the primitive faith that American citizens and American homes must be held sacred.</seg></p>

<pb n="226" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.226"/>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> alone could turn the tidal wave, and lead back the Mormon people to their homes. Had he continued onward to Sonora, Central America, anywhere&#8212;to the ends of the earth&#8212;this people would have followed him.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The Mormon leaders, with the body of the Church, were at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> on the evening of the 4th of July; General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> and his army being about to take up their quarters at Camp Floyd. It was on that evening that Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> informed his predecessor that he should publish a proclamation to the Mormons for their return to their homes.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"Do as <hi rend="italic">you</hi> please, Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>," replied <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName>, with a quiet smile. "To-morrow I shall get upon the tongue of my wagon, and tell the people that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> am going home, and they can do as they please."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">On the morning of the 5th, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> announced to the people that he was going to start for <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>; they were at liberty to follow him to their various settlements, as they pleased. In a few hours nearly all were on their homeward march.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">But scarcely had the people returned to their homes, ere they had abundant proof how much they could have trusted a united Federal power, in an anti-Mormon crusade, with an army at its service to subvert the civil and religious liberties of the people.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">The machinery of the Federal power was soon set in motion. Chief Justice <persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">Eckles</persName> took up his quarters at Camp Floyd; Associate Justice <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">Sinclair</persName> was assigned to the district embracing <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>; and Associate Justice <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> was assigned to the judicial supervision of all the southern settlements; and Superintendent of Indian Affairs, <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName>, and <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Alexander Wilson</persName>, U. S. District <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Attorney</persName>, entered upon the discharge of their duties.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">The <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Governor</persName> from the beginning assumed a pacific attitude, in which he was seconded by Superintendent <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> and District-Attorney <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Wilson</persName>. But the three Judges, in concert with the Marshal, united in the prosecution of past offences that had naturally arisen out of the condition of the hostility, just brought to a happy and peaceful issue.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">Sinclair</persName> convened the First, now the Third Judicial District Court in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName> in November, 1858, and in his charge to the Grand Jury he urged the prosecution of the leading men of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> for <hi rend="italic">treason</hi>, for intimidation of the courts, and <seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">for polygamy</seg>. President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s pardon, the Judge admitted, was "a public fact in the history of the country," but "like any other deed, it ought to be brought judicially by plea, motion or otherwise." In fine, Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">Sinclair</persName> wanted to bring before his court ex-Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, Lieut.-General <persName key="Wells, Daniel H.">Daniel H. Wells</persName>, and the leading Mormons generally, especially the Apostles, "to make them admit that they had been guilty of treason, and make them humbly accept from him the <persName key="Buchanan, James">President</persName>'s clemency." So explains Mr. <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">But it was something more radical and serious than a vainglorious effort to humble <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> to the footstool of a Federal Judge. It was an attempt to reopen in the courts the entire conflict which had so nearly come to the issue of war. U. S. District Attorney <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Wilson</persName>, however, would not present to the jury bills of indictment for treason, pleading that the Commissioners had presented

<pb n="227" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.227"/>

the pardon, and the people had accepted it, and the Governor had proclaimed that peace was restored to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"But the young Judge," relates Mr. <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>, "was more successful in his efforts to bring forward the charge of intimidating the courts. <seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">It could not be expected that the charge to the jury on polygamy would secure much attention. It was regarded little better than a grand farce to ask a Mormon jury to find indictments against their brethren for polygamy.</seg> The term of Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">Sinclair</persName>'s judicial service was a failure, only memorable for one thing&#8212;he sentenced the first white man who was ever hanged in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and he was a Gentile, to be executed <hi rend="italic">on a Sunday!</hi> Of course, the day had to be changed."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">But the most extraordinary judicial action, and that which continues the historical thread of those times, was in the important district assigned to Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>. <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">The criminal cases which he sought to investigate were those commonly known as the Potter and Parrish murders at <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName></seg>, and the Mountain Meadows Massacre <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">in Southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName></seg>. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">On the 8th of March, 1859, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> delivered an extraordinary address to the Grand Jury, and commenced extraordinary proceedings, which in their sequel nearly made <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> the seat of actual war between <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s troops and the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> militia under Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, and which was barely prevented by the timely interference of the General Government.</seg> The history of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, however, cannot follow in detail the entire history of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, only so far as its subject and action find therein its proper centre of unity. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">Suffice here to mark that Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> in his investigations and prosecutions aimed chiefly to implicate the leaders of the Mormon Church in all the criminal offenses and deeds of violence done within <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">In summing up the evidence in the case of the murders at <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>, the judge concluded with the following address:</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">"Until I commenced the examination of the testimony in this case, I always supposed that I lived in a land of civil and religious liberty, in which we were secured by the Constitution of our country the right to remove at pleasure from one portion of our domain to another, and also that we enjoyed the privilege of worshipping God according to the dictates of our own conscience. But I regret to say, that the evidence in this case clearly proves that, so far as <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> is concerned, I have been mistaken in such supposition. <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSApostates">Men are murdered here: coolly, deliberately, premediatatedly murdered&#8212;their murder is deliberated and determined upon by the church council-meetings, and that, too, for no other reason than that they had apostatised from your church, and were striving to leave <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">"You are the tools, the dupes, the instruments of a tyrannical church despotism. The heads of your church order and direct you. You are taught to obey their orders and commit these horrid murders. Deprived of your liberty you have lost your manhood, and become the willing instruments of bad men.</seg></p>

<p>"I say to you it will be my earnest effort, while with you, to knock off your ecclesiastical shackles and set you free."</p>

<p>It is easily to be seen that with such a grand jury, charged in this manner by such a judge, it was impossible to accomplish the ends of justice;&#8212;equally <choice><orig>im-

<pb n="228" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.228"/>

possible</orig><reg>impossible</reg></choice> whether they had been "the willing instruments" of a "tyrannical church," or a grand jury of honest, innocent men.</p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">In the course of one of these prosecutions, Judge <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> made a requisition upon General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> for troops to act as protection to certain witnesses, and also, in the absence of a jail, to serve as a guard over the prisoners. The mayor of <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> (<persName key="Bullock, Kimball">Kimball Bullock</persName>) protested that the presence of the military was an infringement upon the liberties of his fellow-citizens; but the judge answered that he had well considered the request before he had made it. A petition was sent to Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, and he asked General <persName key="Johnson, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> to withdraw the troops, asserting that the court had no authority to call for the aid of the military, except through him. The judges interpreted General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s instructions from the War Department adversely to the statement of <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">the Governor</persName>, and the troops were continued at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>. On the 27th of March (1859), <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">the Governor</persName> issued a proclamation protesting against the continuance of the troops at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, taking open ground against the action of the military commander.</seg></p>

<p>About this time was concocted a conspiracy to arrest <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>. It was proposed that a writ be issued for his apprehension. The officers entrusted with its execution presented themselves at the Governor's office, to request his co-operation. But Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> stoutly resisted the attempted outrage. He himself afterwards thus related this conspiracy to arrest his predecessor:</p>

<p>"They had 'got the dead wood on <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> this time,' so they said, as they unfolded to me their plans. If <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> resisted, General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s artillery was to make a breach in the wall surrounding his premises, and they would take him by force and carry him to Camp Floyd.</p>

<p>"I listened to them, sir, as gravely as I could, and examined their papers. They rubbed their hands and were jubilant; they 'had got the dead wood on <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>!' I was indignant, sir, and told them, 'by G&#8212;d, gentlemen, you can't do it! When you have a right to take <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, gentlemen, you shall have him without creeping through walls. You shall enter through his door with heads erect as become representatives of your government. But till that time, gentlemen, you can't touch <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> while I live, by G&#8212;d!'"</p>

<p>"Such was the story," says <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>, "told by <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">the Governor</persName> to <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">the author</persName> a few years later, and as he related it all the fire of his nature was depicted on his countenance and told unmistakably that he would have made good every word with his life."</p>

<p>The officers returned to Camp Floyd discomfited, and immediately the news was circulated that General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> would send two regiments of troops and a battery of artillery to enforce the writ for the apprehension of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName>.</p>

<p>The <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> of date May 25, 1859, gave to the country a graphic picture of affairs in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> at that moment:</p>

<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">our salt lake city correspondence.</hi></hi></p>

<p><hi rend="right">"<hi rend="smallcaps"><placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName></hi>, U. T., April 23, 1859.</hi></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"In my last letter I informed you of the threat of Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">Sinclair</persName> that he would hold court in this city during May, with three-fourths of the army now at

<pb n="229" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.229"/>

Camp Floyd, quartered in Union Square, ready to carry out his orders. The apprehension of a collision which that threat inspired measurably died away in the bosoms of the people generally, and the youthful judge was beginning to get credit for idle braggadocia, and his tongue was regarded as having only divulged what was in his heart to do, if he only could get the chance; but, alas! the day after the departure of the last mail from here, rumors of his intentions were in circulation at Camp Floyd, which leaves us no reason to doubt that his threat was no idle boast, but is in reality the fixed determination of his heart, to lead to a collision between the citizens and the troops. Of this Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> is apparently fully convinced, as also the other officials outside of the judicial clique. By the departure of the next mail, plans will be better developed, if not even then carried into execution, or at least attempted; and should you then hear of the eagerly-sought-for collision having taken place, it can be witnessed that we have not sought it, but that it is the deep-laid scheme of sutlers, degraded judges, and disappointed officers of our great republican army, for the sake of perishable gold, gratification of personal revenge, and the empty glory of swords to be crimsoned with the blood of fellow-citizens, who so love the liberty bequeathed to them by illustrious sires that they will fight for its maintenance, though their homes should be made desolate and their wives and children left without protectors in the land of freemen's inheritance.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"An express from Camp Floyd arrived here on Sunday night with the intelligence that two regiments were coming to the city to make arrests, and it was expected that they would have orders for forced marches, to come in upon us unawares. <hi rend="italic">Immediately on Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> being made acquainted with the report and circumstances, which leave no room to doubt of the plans of the judges, he notified General <persName key="Well, Daniel H.">D. H. Wells</persName> to hold the militia in readiness to act on orders. By two o'clock on Monday morning five thousand men were under arms</hi>. Had the United States' troops attempted to enter the city, the struggle must have commenced, for the Governor is determined to carry out his instructions. What has deferred their arrival here we know not; but now that this plan is known, a watchful eye is kept on the camp, and the shedding of blood seems inevitable. We have confidence in the overruling care of our heavenly Father; and what ever does take place, will eventually turn out for good.</seg></p>

<p>"Major &#8212; told me yesterday that General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> was resolved to carry out his orders, and he affirms that they are to use the military on the requisition of the judges, and not on the requisition of the Governor only. I have just learned that 500 soldiers were on the march to Sanpete settlement to arrest persons there whom the judges are seeking after. The judicial-military-inquisitorial farce played at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> satisfies everybody that it is not violated justice that seeks redress, but the madness of men drunken with whisky and vengeance, that seek satiety in blood. There is not an official in any settlement outside this city but what expects to be handled as were those at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>; and the only safety they have from judicial vengeance&#8212;not personal, but vengeance against the community&#8212;is in flight to the mountains. In the south, where the weather has been excellent for early agricultural operations this spring, the fields have been left uncultivated, and the seed that should be fructifying in the soil is still lying in the barn,

<pb n="230" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.230"/>

the end of which must be famine; for unless the <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Governor</persName> has power to restrain the judges from calling the military to act as a <hi rend="italic">posse comitates</hi>, no man of any influence will trust himself at home. We fear no judge of the United States. The Supreme Judge of all we fear, and in His fear we live, and earthly tribunals have no terror for us: but the insolence of men like <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> and <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">Sinclair</persName> and the despotism of their military aids drive the iron to our souls. The very latest news now in circulation in the city is that the judges have hired the Indians to scour the mountains in search of the persons that the Marshal and military have been unable to discover at home. What next? Shall a price be offered the red men of the forest for the scalps of our citizens? Oh, my God! what shall we be driven to? My heart sickens at the outrages to which we have been subjected, and I dread the future. Nothing shall be done on our part to hasten hostilities; but if it is impossible to avoid them, the responsibility is theirs.</p>

<p>"Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> has no disposition, nor has this community any, to screen any man or men from the punishment due for any crime or misdemeanor they may be accused of; but he will not suffer military terrorism to reign in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> over which he is Governor, and we are to a man ready to sustain him. We appeal to the American nation, and ask any man whose soul is not absorbed with the acquisition of perishable pelf only, what can we do more than we have done to preserve peace? and what course is open to us but to defend our rights as citizens of the Union?"</p>

<p>Happily at this juncture an official letter from <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName> decided that the military could only be used as a posse on a call from <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">the Governor</persName>. This communication from the U. S. Attorney-General is a valuable historical review of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> affairs at that juncture, by the U. S. Government itself:</p>

<p><hi rend="right">"<hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney-General's Office</hi>, May 17, 1859.</hi></p>

<p>"<hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>&#8212;The President has received your joint letter on the subject of the military force with which the Court for the Second District of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> was attended during the term recently held at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> City. He has carefully considered it, as well as all other advices relating to the same affair, and he has directed me to give you his answer.</p>

<p>"The condition of things in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> made it extremely desirable that the Judges appointed for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">that Territory</placeName> should confine themselves strictly within their own official sphere. The Government had a district attorney, who was charged with the duties of a public accuser, and a marshal, who was responsible for the arrest and safe-keeping of criminals. For the judges there was nothing left except to hear patiently the causes brought before them, and to determine them impartially according to the evidence adduced on both sides. It did not seem either right or necessary to <hi rend="italic">instruct</hi> you that these were to be the limits of your interference with the public affairs of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>; for the Executive never dictates to the Judicial department. The President is responsible only for the appointment of proper men. You were selected from a very large number of other persons who were willing to be employed on the same service, and the choice was grounded solely on your high character for learning, sound judgment, and integrity. It

<pb n="231" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.231"/>

was natural, therefore, that <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President</persName> should look upon the proceedings at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> with a sincere desire to find you in all things blameless.</p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation"><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"It seems that on the 6th of March last, Judge <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> announced to the commanding officer of the military forces that on the 8th day of the same month he would begin a term of the District Court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, and required a military guard for certain prisoners, to the number of six or eight, who were then in custody, and would be triable at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>. The requisition mentions it as a probable fact that 'a large band of organized thieves' would be arrested; but the troops were asked for without reference to them. Promptly responding to this call the commanding-general sent up a company of infantry, who encamped at the Court House, and soon afterwards ten more companies made their appearance in sight, and remained there during the whole term of the court. In the meantime, <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">the Governor</persName> of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, hearing of this military demonstration upon a town previously supposed to be altogether peaceful, appeared on the ground, made inquiries, and, seeing no necessity for the troops, but believing, on the contrary, that their presence was calculated to do harm, he requested them to be removed. The request was wholly disregarded.</seg></seg></p>

<p>"<seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration"><persName key="Cumming, Alfred">The Governor</persName> is the supreme Executive of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. He is responsible for the public peace. From the general law of the land, the nature of his office, and the instructions he received from the State Department, it ought to have been understood that he alone had power to issue a requisition for the movement of troops from one part of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> to another,&#8212;that he alone could put the military forces of the Union and the people of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> into relations of general hostility with one another. The instructions given to the Commanding-General by the War Department are to the same effect. In that paper a '<hi rend="italic">requisition</hi>' is not spoken of as a thing which anybody except <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">the Governor</persName> can make. It is true that in one clause the General is told that if the Governor, the judges, or the marshal shall find it necessary to <hi rend="italic">summon directly</hi> a part of the troops to aid either in the performance of his duty, he (the General) is to see the <hi rend="italic">summons</hi> promptly obeyed. This was manifestly intended to furnish the means of repelling an opposition which might be too strong for the civil posse, and too sudden to admit of a formal requisition by the governor upon the military commander. An officer finds himself resisted in the discharge of his duty, and he calls to his aid first the citizens, and, if they are not sufficient, the soldiers. This would be directly summoning a part of the troops. A <hi rend="italic">direct summons</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">requisition</hi> are not convertible terms. The former signifies a mere verbal call upon either civilians or military men for force enough to put down a present opposition to a certain officer in the performance of a particular duty; and the call is to be always made by the officer who is himself opposed upon those persons who are with their own hands to furnish the aid. A requisition, on the other hand, is a solemn demand in writing made by the supreme civil magistrate upon the commander-in-chief of the military forces for the whole or part of the army to be used in a specified service. In a Territory like <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, the person who exercises this last-mentioned power can make war and peace when he pleases, and holds in his hands the issues of life and death for thousands. Surely it was not intended to clothe each one of the judges, as well as the marshal and all his

<pb n="232" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.232"/>


deputies, with this tremendous authority. Especially does this construction seem erroneous when we reflect that these different officers might make requisitions conflicting with one another, and all of them crossing the path of the Governor.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"Besides, the matter upon which Judge <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>'s requisition bases itself was one with which the Judge had no sort of official connection. It was the duty the marshal to see that the prisoners were safely kept and forthcoming at the proper time. For aught that appears, the marshal wanted no troops to aid him, and had no desire to see himself displaced by a regiment of soldiers. He made no complaint of weakness, and uttered no call for assistance. Under such circumstances it was a mistake of the Judge to interfere with the business at all.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"But, assuming the legal right of the judge to put the marshal's business into the hands of the army without the marshal's concurrence, and granting also that this might be done by means of a requisition, was there in this case any occasion for the exercise of such power? When we consider how essentially peaceable is the whole spirit of our judicial system, and how exclusively it aims to operate by moral force, or at most by the arm of civil power, it can hardly be denied that the employment of military troops about the courts should be avoided, as long as possible. <hi rend="italic">Inter arma silent leges</hi>, says the maxim; and the converse of it ought to be equally true, that <hi rend="italic">inter leges silent arma</hi>. The President has not found, either on the face of the requisition or in any other paper received by him, a statement of specific facts strong enough to make the presence of the troops seem necessary. Such necessity ought to have been perfectly plain before the measure was resorted to.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"It is very probable that the Mormon inhabitants of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> have been guilty of crimes for which they deserve the severest punishment. It is not intended by the Government to let any one escape against whom the proper proofs can be produced. With that view, the district attorney has been instructed to use all possible diligence in bringing criminals of every class and of all degrees to justice. We have the fullest confidence in the vigilance, fidelity and ability of that officer. If you shall be of opinion that his duty is not performed with sufficient energy, your statement to that effect will receive the prompt attention of <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President</persName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"It is very likely that public opinion in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> is frequently opposed to the conviction of parties who deserve punishment. It may be that extensive conspiracies are formed there to defeat justice. These are subjects upon which we, at this distance, can affirm or deny nothing. But, supposing your opinion upon them to be correct, every inhabitant of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> must still be proceeded against in a regular, legal, and constitutional way. At all events, the usual and established modes of dealing with public offenders must be exhausted before we adopt any others.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"On the whole, <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President</persName> is very decidedly of opinion&#8212;</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"1. That the Governor of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> alone has power to issue a requisition upon the commanding-general for the whole or part of the army:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"2. That there was no apparent occasion for the presence of the troops at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"3. That if a rescue of the prisoners in custody had been attempted, it

<pb n="233" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.233"/>


was the duty of the marshal, and not of the judge, to summon the force which might be necessary to prevent it:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"4. That the troops ought not to have been sent to <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> without the concurrence of the Governor, nor kept there against his remonstrance:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"5. That the disregard of these principles and rules of action has been in many ways extremely unfortunate.</seg></p>

<p><hi rend="right">"I am, very respectfully, yours, &amp;c,</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="right"><persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">J. S. BLACK.</persName></hi></p>

<p>"<hi rend="italic">Hon. J. <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, Hon. <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">C. E. Sinclair</persName>, Associate Judges, Supreme Court, <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName></hi>."</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">A great Constitutional pronouncement like the foregoing from a jurist so distinguished as Attorney-General <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Jeremiah S. Black</persName>, given by the direction of <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President of the United States</persName>, was too authoritative and potent to be set aside. Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> had clearly won the victory over his rivals, at least in the Constitutional aspects of his position.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">The anti-Mormon influence everywhere was now invoked to have Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> removed, and for a time this was under consideration in the Cabinet. The probabilities were all against the Governor being retained, but a fine stroke of strategy, executed by Col. <persName key="Kane, Thomas L.">Thos. L. Kane</persName>, recovered his position. <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName>, who was present as reporter for the <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi>, relates the circumstance thus:</seg></p>

<p>"Soon after the return of Col. <persName key="Kane, Thomas L.">Kane</persName> to the Eastern States, that gentleman was invited to deliver a lecture before the Historical Society of <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> upon 'The Situation of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.' Though in very feeble health, and unprepared for such a lecture, his devotion to what he no doubt sincerely believed to be the welfare of the Mormons and the honor of the Government, overcame all impediments, and the lecture was delivered. In that audience were two Mormon elders listening eagerly for a sentence that might help "the cause" in the West. By previous arrangement the agent of the Associated Press was to be furnished with a notice of the lecture, and thus a dispatch next morning was read everywhere throughout the Union to the effect that there was a division among the Mormons, that some were eager for strife, others for peace, but that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> was on the side of peace and order, and was laboring to control his fiery brethren. This was a repetition of a part of the diplomacy of the Tabernacle. Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> was complimented by the gallant Colonel as a clear-headed, resolute, but prudent executive, and the very man for the trying position.</p>

<p>"Before such an endorsement, sent broadcast over the Republic, coming from the lips of the gentleman who had warded off the effusion of blood, and saved the nation from the expense and horror of a domestic war, the Cabinet of Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> silently bowed, but they were terribly chagrined."</p>

<p>Apostle <persName key="Cannon, George Q.">George Q. Cannon</persName>, who was one of the "two Mormon elders" present at the lecture, relates this singular and quite dramatic episode of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> history with several additional points, which have a national significance. The story is told in an obituary sketch of <persName key="Kante, Thomas L.">Thomas L. Kane</persName>, with an affectionate simplicity that gives it a special value in the History:</p>

<pb n="234" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.234"/>

<p>"As I write, another illustration of his forgetfulness of self and his ardent zeal in behalf of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> comes to my mind. It was during the <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> administration. Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, who had been sent out by President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> with the army as Governor of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, did not work harmoniously with the army officers. Differences had arisen between them at the time they were in camp during the winter at Ham's Fork and Fort Bridger.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"These differences increased after they came into the valley, and the influence of the army people was used with the administration to have <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> removed. President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> was inclined to yield to the pressure of <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Albert Sidney Johnston</persName>'s friends. <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> at that time was quite an influential personage; in fact influences were being used to prepare the way for him to succeed General <persName key="Scott, Winfield">Winfield Scott</persName> as commander of the army of the United States.  President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> made inquiries of some of General <persName key="Kane, Thomas L.">Kane</persName>'s friends as to how the removal of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> would be received by him. He heard of this, and, though at the time confined to his room with an attack of pleurisy, saw that something must be done to prevent the removal of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, which he viewed at the time as a move that would be unfortunate to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. The Historical Society of <placeName type="settlement" key="New York City, UT">New York City</placeName>&#8212;a very influential society&#8212;had solicited him to deliver a lecture upon <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> affairs; but he had postponed accepting the offer. He saw that this was the opportune moment to deliver it, and though suffering from severe pain he resolved to go to <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> and deliver the lecture. His friends tried to dissuade him from the step, as they felt that he was endangering his life. But he was determined to go, and wrote to the President of the Society, who was pleased to accept the proffer of the lecture. Accompanied by his physician, he traveled from <placeName type="settlement" key="Philadelphia, PA">Philadelphia</placeName> to <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName>, delivered the lecture, in which he eulogized Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, and gave him the praise that was due to him for his conduct after reaching <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and the next morning there appeared in all the newspapers of the country, through the associated press, a brief epitome of the lecture, commending Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>'s administration of affairs. It had the effect to turn the scale in <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>'s favor. President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> relinquished the idea of removing him, and he remained Governor until he had served out his full term. I was in the East at the time and familiar with all the circumstances, and I was deeply impressed with the General's conduct on that occasion."</seg></p>

<p>There is to be discerned in these two statements a division growing up in the views and purposes of the members of <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s Cabinet at that critical juncture of our national affairs, which is capitally presented in Mr. <persName key="Blaine, James G.">Blaine</persName>'s great book of reminiscences, in which he presents, on the one side, <persName key="Floyd, John B.">John B. Floyd</persName>, Secretary of War with President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> preparing the way for secession; on the other, Gen. <persName key="Cass, Lewis">Lewis Cass</persName>, Secretary of State, and Attorney-General <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Jeremiah S. Black</persName>, taking the alarm both for the Democracy and the Union, and setting their faces against the secession movement, which General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Albert Sidney Johnston</persName> was fated to represent as one of its chiefest military captains. Mr. <persName key="Blaine, James G.">Blaine</persName> has not intended any reference to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, but that which he describes touching a division in the Cabinet, relative to our national affairs, is strangely to be traced at the same moment in the Cabinet over <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> affairs. So far as secession and Secretary <persName key="Floyd, John B.">Floyd</persName> is concerned, the statement of ex-Delegate <persName key="Cannon, George Q.">Cannon</persName> suggests a very striking

<pb n="235" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.235"/>

parallel to the <persName key="Blaine, James G.">Blaine</persName> reminiscences of the state of <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s Cabinet at that juncture.</p>

<p>The historical pertinence of the case is the more striking from the fact that it was subsequent to the decision of the Attorney-General against the Judges' and General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s action. After the receipt of that dispatch a mass meeting of Gentiles was held at Camp Floyd, on the 23rd of July, at which the Judges and the Indian Agent&#8212;Dr. <persName key="Hurt, Garland">Garland Hurt</persName>&#8212;were present, and in which they took a prominent part. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">An address was penned, rehearsing all the crimes charged to the Mormons, asserting that they were as disloyal after the <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President</persName>'s pardon as when they were in arms in Echo Canyon, that <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President</persName> was deceived and badly advised, and had done a great wrong in withdrawing the protection of the military from the courts.</seg></p>

<p>Thus it would seem that there was before the country, emanating from <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> and his friends, who were seeking to make him commander-in-chief of the armies of the United States, not only a demand for the removal of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, but a virtual impeachment of the Attorney-General as an ill-adviser on <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> affairs, for it was undoubtedly <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Jeremiah S. Black</persName> who had given the new impulse to the <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> movement, as represented in General <persName key="Kane, Thomas L.">Kane</persName> and Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, and his Constitutional decision had most likely saved <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName> from the "baptism of blood," and made valid <persName key="Buchanan, James">the President</persName>'s pardon. But it seems that he would have failed at last, in his revision of the <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> policy touching <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, had not <persName key="Kane, Thomas L.">Thomas L. Kane</persName> risen from his couch and, in his noble regard for the honor of his country, made valid the proclamation of peace and pardon which had been granted in the august name of the American Republic.</p>

<p>A supplementary page from Mr. <persName key="Blaine, James G.">Blaine</persName>'s great book may be given here to illustrate the reorganization of the <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> Cabinet, by Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName>, and the radical change in its policies, so strongly marked both in the affairs of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> and the greater affairs of the nation; and a bankrupt U. S. Treasury will be very suggestive of Secretary <persName key="Floyd, John B.">Floyd</persName>'s expenditure of from fourteen to twenty millions of dollars on the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> Expedition:</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName> entered upon his duties as Secretary of State on the 17th of December&#8212;the day on which the disunion convention of <placeName type="state" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</placeName> assembled. He found the malign influence of Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s message fully at work throughout the South. Under its encouragement only three days were required by the convention at <placeName type="settlement" key="Charleston, South Carolina">Charleston</placeName> to pass the ordinance of secession, and four days later Governor <persName key="Pickens, Francis Wilkinson">Pickens</persName> issued a proclamation declaring '<placeName type="state" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</placeName> a separate, sovereign, free and independent State, with the right to levy war, conclude peace and negotiate treaties.' From that moment Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName>'s position towards the Southern leaders was radically changed. They were no longer fellow-Democrats. They were the enemies of the Union to which he was devoted, they were conspirators against the Government to which he had taken a <choice><sic>selemn</sic><corr>solemn</corr></choice> oath of fidelity and loyalty.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName>'s change, however important to his own fame, would prove comparatively fruitless unless he could influence Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> to break with the men who had been artfully using the power of his Administration to destroy the

<pb n="236" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.236"/>

Union. The opportunity and the test came promptly. The new 'sovereign, free and independent' government of <placeName type="state" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</placeName> sent commissioners to <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName> to negotiate for the surrender of the national forts and the transfer of the national property within her limits. Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> prepared an answer to their request which was compromising to the honor of the Executive and perilous to the integrity of the Union. Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName> took a decided and irrevocable stand against the President's position. He advised Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> that upon the basis of that fatal concession to the disunion leaders he could not remain in his Cabinet. It was a sharp issue, but was soon adjusted. Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> gave way and permitted Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName> and his associates, <persName key="Holt, Joseph">Holt</persName> and <persName key="Stanton, Edwin M.">Stanton</persName>, to frame a reply for the Administration.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"<persName key="Davis, Jefferson">Jefferson Davis</persName>, Mr. <persName key="Toombs, Robert A.">Toombs</persName>, Mr. <persName key="Benjamin, Judah P.">Benjamin</persName>, Mr. <persName key="Slidell, John">Slidell</persName>, who had been Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s intimate and confidential advisers, and who had led him to the brink of ruin, found themselves suddenly supplanted, and a new power installed in the White House. Foiled and no longer able to use the National Administration as an instrumentality to destroy the national life, the secession leaders in Congress turned upon the President with angry reproaches. In their rage they lost all sense of the respect due to the Chief Magistrate of the nation, and assaulted Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> with coarseness as well as violence. Senator <persName key="Benjamin, Judah P.">Benjamin</persName> spoke of him as 'a senile Executive under the sinister influence of insane counsels.' This exhibition of malignity towards the misguided President afforded to the North the most convincing and satisfactory proof that there had been a change for the better in the plans and purposes of the Administration. They realized that it must be a deep sense of impending danger which could separate Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> from his political associations with the South, and they recognized in his position a significant proof of the desperate determination to which the enemies of the Union had come.</seg></p>

<p>"The stand taken by Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName> and his loyal associates was in the last days of December, i860. The reorganization of the Cabinet came as a matter of necessity. Mr. <persName key="Floyd, John B.">John B. Floyd</persName> resigned from the War Department, making loud proclamation that his action was based on the President's refusal to surrender the national forts in Charleston Harbor to the secession government of <placeName type="state" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</placeName>. This manifesto was not necessary to establish <persName key="Floyd, John B.">Floyd</persName>'s treasonable intentions towards the Government; but, in point of truth, the plea was undoubtedly a pretense, to cover reasons of a more personal character which would at once deprive him of Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s confidence. There had been irregularities in the War Department tending to compromise Mr. <persName key="Floyd, John B.">Floyd</persName>, for which he was afterwards indicted in the District of Columbia. Mr. <persName key="Floyd, John B.">Floyd</persName> well knew that the first knowledge of these shortcomings would lead to his dismissal from the Cabinet. Whatever Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s faults as an Executive may have been, his honor in all transactions, both personal and public, was unquestionable, and he was the last man to tolerate the slightest deviation from the path of rigid integrity.</p>

<p>"Mr. <persName key="Thomspon, Jacob">Thompson</persName>, the Secretary of the Interior, followed Mr. <persName key="Floyd, John B.">Floyd</persName> after a short interval. Mr. <persName key="Cobb, Howell">Cobb</persName> had left the Treasury a few days before General <persName key="Cass, Lewis">Cass</persName> resigned from the Cabinet, and had gone to <placeName type="state" key="Georgria">Georgia</placeName> to stimulate her laggard

<pb n="237" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.237"/>

movements in the scheme of destroying the Government. His successor was <persName key="Thomas, Philip Francis">Philip Francis Thomas</persName>, of <placeName type="state" key="Maryland">Maryland</placeName>, who entered the Cabinet as a representative of the principles whose announcement had forced General <persName key="Cass, Lewis">Cass</persName> to resign. The change of policy to which the <persName key="Buchanan, James">President</persName> was now fully committed forced Mr. <persName key="Thomas, Philip Francis">Thomas</persName> to retire after a month's service. He frankly stated that he was unable to agree with the <persName key="Buchanan, James">President</persName> and his other advisers 'in reference to the condition of things in <placeName type="state" key="South Carolina">South Carolina</placeName>,' and therefore tendered his resignation. Mr. <persName key="Thomas, Philip Francis">Thomas</persName> adhered to the Union and always maintained an upright and honorable character; but his course at that crisis deprived him subsequently of a seat in the United States Senate, though at a later period he served in the House as Representative from <placeName type="state" key="Maryland">Maryland</placeName>.</p>

<p>"Mr. <persName key="Cobb, Howell">Cobb</persName>, Mr. <persName key="Floyd, John B.">Floyd</persName> and Mr. <persName key="Thompson, Jacob">Thompson</persName> had all remained in the Cabinet after the Presidential election in November, in full sympathy, and so far as possible in co-operation with the men in the South who were organizing resistance to the authority of the Federal Government. Neither those gentlemen, nor any friend in their behalf, ever ventured to explain how, as sworn officers of the United States, they could remain at their posts consistently with the laws of honor&#8212;laws obligatory on them not only as public officials who had taken a solemn oath of fidelity to the Constitution, but also as private gentlemen, whose good faith was pledged anew every hour they remained in control of the departments with whose administration they had been intrusted. Their course is unfavorably contrasted with that of many Southern men (of whom General <persName key="Lee, Robert E.">Lee</persName> and the two <persName key="Johnston, Joseph E."><persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnstons</persName></persName> were conspicuous examples), who refused to hold official positions under the national Government a single day after they had determined to take part in the scheme of disunion.</p>

<p>"By the reorganization of the Cabinet the tone of Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName>'s administration was radically changed. Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName> had used his influence with the President to secure trustworthy friends of the Union in every department. <persName key="Stanton, Edwin M.">Edwin M. Stanton</persName>, little known at the time to the public, but of high standing in his profession, was appointed Attorney-General soon after Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName> took charge of the State Department. Judge <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName> had been associated with Stanton personally and professionally, and was desirous of his aid in the dangerous period through which he was called to serve.</p>

<p>"<persName key="Holt, Joseph">Joseph Holt</persName>, who, since the death of <persName key="Brown, Aaron V.">Aaron V. Brown</persName> in 1859, had been Postmaster-General, was now appointed Secretary of War, and <persName key="King, Horatio">Horatio King</persName>, of <placeName type="state" key="Maine">Maine</placeName>, for many years the upright first assistant, was justly promoted to the head of the Post-office Department. Mr. <persName key="Holt, Joseph">Holt</persName> was the only Southern man left in the Cabinet. He was a native of <placeName type="state" key="Kentucky">Kentucky</placeName>, long a resident of <placeName type="state" key="Mississippi">Mississippi</placeName>, always identified with the Democratic party, and affiliated with its extreme southern wing. Without a moment's hesitation he now broke all the associations of a lifetime and stood by the Union without qualification or condition. His learning, his firmness and his ability were invaluable to Mr. <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> in the closing days of his administration.</p>

<p>"General <persName key="Dix, John A.">John A. Dix</persName>, of <placeName type="state" key="New York">New York</placeName>, was called to the head of the Treasury. He was a man of excellent ability, of wide experience in affairs, of spotless character and a most zealous friend of the Union. He found the Treasury bankrupt,

<pb n="238" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.238"/>

the discipline of its officers in the South gone, its orders disregarded in the States which were preparing for secession. He at once imparted spirit and energy into the service, giving to the administration of this department a policy of pronounced loyalty to the Government. No act of his useful and honorable life has been so widely known or will be so long remembered as his dispatch to the Treasury agent at <placeName type="settlement" key="New Orleans, LA">New Orleans</placeName> to take possession of a revenue cutter whose commander was suspected of disloyalty and of a design to transfer his vessel to the Confederate service. Lord <persName key="Nelson, Horatio">Nelson</persName>'s memorable order at Trafalgar was not more inspiring to the British Navy than was the order of General <persName key="Dix, John Adams">Dix</persName> to the American people, when, in the gloom of that depressing winter, he telegraphed South his peremptory words: 'If any man attempts to haul down the American flag, shoot him on the spot.'</p>

<p>"Thus reconstructed, the Cabinet as a whole was one of recognized power, marked by high personal character, by intellectual training, by experience in affairs, and by aptitude for the public service. There have been Cabinets perhaps more widely known for the possession of great qualities; but, if the history of successive administrations from the origin of the Government be closely studied, it will be found that the reorganised Cabinet of President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> must take rank as one of exceptional ability."</p>

<milestone unit="section" rend="horbar"/>

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">

<head>CHAPTER XXVI.</head>

<head>JUDGE CRADLEBAUGH DISCHARGES THE GRAND JURY AND TURNS SOCIETY OVER TO LAWLESS RULE. THE INDIANS ENCOURAGED TO DEPREDATIONS ON THE SETTLEMENTS. A DARK PICTURE OF SALT LAKE SOCIETY. WHY GOVERNOR CUMMING DID NOT INVESTIGATE THE MOUNTAIN MEADOWS MASSACRE.</head>

<p>Having failed to obtain the indictment of the leaders of the Mormon Church, the judges resolved that they would close their courts and give society into the hands of the numerous desperadoes with which <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> now abounded. In discharging the grand jury, Judge <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> uttered one of the most remarkable passages to be found in the whole history of criminal jurisprudence:</p>

<p>"If it is expected," he said, "that this court is to be used by this community as a means of protecting it against the peccadilloes of Gentiles and Indians, unless this community will punish its own murderers, such expectations will not be realized. It will be used for no such purpose. When the people shall come to their reason and manifest a disposition to punish their own high offenders, it will then be time to enforce the law also for their protection. If this

<pb n="239" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.239"/>

court cannot bring you to a proper sense of your duty, <hi rend="italic">it can at least turn the savages held in custody loose upon you</hi>."</p>

<p>Accordingly Judge <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> dismissed the prisoners and adjourned his court "without day."</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">On his part <persName key="Hurt, Garland">D. Hurt</persName>, the Indian agent, had, both before and after the entrance of <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s troops, <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">spent his official service in inciting hostile Indians to commit depredations upon the Mormon settlements.</seg></seg></seg> This, indeed, was the specific charge which Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> reported to Secretary <persName key="cass, Lewis">Cass</persName> against Indian Agent <persName key="Hurt, Garland">Hurt</persName>, both as inimical to the peace of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> and interruptive of his own executive duties representing the Federal Government. Upon this Indian line of the history, <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, just prior to the entrance of <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s troops, writing to <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">T. B. H. Stenhouse</persName>, said:</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">"It has been the policy of Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> and our people to keep the Indians neutral, should a contest ensue. I read in the last papers received from the States loud boasts of having secured the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> and other Indians as allies against the Mormons. Strange as it may seem to civilized persons, all the reckless and unprincipled Indians of the mountains have been hired, with new guns, blankets, clothing, ammunition, paint, etc., to steal, rob, murder, and do anything else that can be done to destroy the Mormons. Indian agents have sent messengers to all the peaceable Indians to incite them to deeds of rapine and bloodshed. A number of scattering settlements have been attacked, and innocent blood stains the skirts of the present administration, whose agents have procured the murders.</seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">"I am an American, as you well know. I love my country, and hate to see her rulers trample under foot her glorious institutions, and re-enact barbarism more cruel than that inflicted by the King of Great Britain, through the hands of the red men upon the scattered settlements of the colonies, in the war of independence. We wish 'life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.'</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">"With 3,500 bayonets, rifles, revolvers, and heavy ordnance pointed at us, and within three days' march of our city, 4,500 more en route to reinforce them, carte blanche on the United States treasury, would seem enough to satisfy our most bitter persecutors, without hiring as allies the savage hordes of the deserts and mountains to murder, scalp, roast, and eat their fellow-citizens, because they forsooth differed on the subject of religion.</seg></p>

<lg type="poem">
<l>'Who can believe it!&#8212;the cause is rather odd&#8212;</l>
<l>Men hate each other for the love of God!'</l>
</lg>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">"You are aware that all the outrages in the country, heretofore, have been caused by men who are enemies to the inhabitants of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this Territory</placeName>&#8212;who have passed through our borders and recklessly shot at and otherwise abused the Indians.</seg></seg></p>

<p>"Experience shows that Indians, like Congressmen and Government officials, have their price."</p>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Mills, William G.">William G. Mills</persName>, writing to the same person, who at that time was a special attache of the <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> on <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> affairs, said:</p>

<pb n="240" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.240"/>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">"The officials and others among the troops are employing their influence and means to bribe the Indians to steal the cattle, and horses, and mules from the settlers here; and already some have succeeded in stealing, and have massacred several persons in the outer settlements. The cattle will be conveyed to the army. One poor fox skin from an Indian will be paid for with a quantity of powder, lead, caps, blankets, and shirts&#8212;more than a hundred times its value&#8212; in order to buy over the rude savages to rob from and murder those who have hitherto fed and clothed them. This is done whenever an Indian visits them. It is not, of course, bribing or buying the Indian&#8212;it is only paying for the fox or buckskin; and significant nods, winks, and signs accompanying the gift are easily interpreted, and robbery and murder are the result. Dr. <persName key="Hurt, Garland">Hurt</persName>, the Indian agent, who decamped from the Indian farm, to create an excitement in his favor, in pretence for personal safety&#8212;'The wicked fleeth when none pursueth'&#8212;has collected a band of Indians in Uintah Valley, among whom is the murderer <persName key="Tintic">Tintic</persName>, and placed himself as their chief at their head, to make an attack on the southern settlements, and promising not only blankets, powder, etc., but a share of the pillage, as the reward of their nefarious acts. Murder in the north is to be responded to by murder of quiet and peaceable citizens in the south. <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">Every mule and horse that the Indians steal is blamed on the Mormons, though the latter may be a hundred miles from the scene of action.</seg> A good supply of whisky is furnished to the Indians by the officers and others, and they seem to enjoy themselves well together. Drinking among the troops was carried on to excess during the winter, which was calculated to excite their bitterest feelings and to enter in every scheme to annoy and kill the citizens. White men and murderous Indians are 'hail fellows well met.'</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">"The Indians, by the presence of the troops, are emboldened to annoy the various settlements, because the Mormons would rather not fight. In <placeName type="county" key="Tooele County, UT">Tooele County</placeName>&#8212;the most westerly in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>&#8212;those Indians who were hitherto friendly have become excited by the conversations and bribes of the army, and have stolen about one hundred and fifty head of cattle and sixty horses, and fired upon the men who were guarding. At Salmon River settlement, two hundred and fifty head of cattle were stolen about the 4th of March, and several Mormons killed and scalped, and again attacked subsequently. It is expected that Dr. <persName key="Hurt, Garland">Hurt</persName> and his tribe will make an attack soon upon the southern settlements; but the people are prepared for every emergency, and will repulse them.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">"The war chiefs of several tribes of Indians, during the time of the excitement last fall and winter, applied personally to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> for his advice and permission to go out with their tribes and 'use up' the soldiers, which they deemed themselves amply capable to do; but he, in every instance, told them to keep away from the army and show no bad feelings whatever, and requested them to avoid killing the white men. I have seen the chiefs exhibit sanguine feelings in relation to killing the soldiers, but entirely softened down by the counsel and expressions of Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>. He wrote to <persName key="Simons, Ben">Ben Simons</persName>, the Delaware Indian, chief of the Weberites, in reply to a letter, to stand in a neutral position, neither take part with the Mormons nor the soldiers, in the event of a collision, and has

<pb n="241" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.241"/>

always endeavored to suppress that bloodthirsty spirit of the treacherous red men."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The action of the judges, in suspending altogether the administration of justice, and by semi-proclamation turning loose upon society the desperadoes, produced such a condition of things, compared with which the history of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName> was stainless before the onset of the <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> Expedition.</seg></p>

<p>Mr. <persName key="Stenhouse, T. B. H.">Stenhouse</persName> in his <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Saints</hi> has painted the dark picture of those times thus outlined and colored:</p>

<p>"With such a large body of troops there were, as usual, numerous camp-followers plying their <hi rend="italic">petit industries</hi>, gambling, thieving, and drinking. General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, with strict surveillance and severe military punishment, had been able to control them on the march and at Camp Scott; but when they found in the valleys of the Saints a wider and safer field for operations, they gave rein to their vilest passions, and a worse set of vagabonds never afflicted any community with their presence than did the followers of <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s army the inhabitants of the chief city of Zion. Quite a number of young Mormons&#8212;and some not-so young&#8212;became as reckless and daring as any of the imported Gentiles, and life and property for a time were very insecure in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">"The programme of the police authorities seemed to be to give the desperadoes the largest liberty, so that they might, in their drunken carousals, 'kill off each other,' and what they left undone invisible hands readily accomplished. During the summer and fall of 1859 there was a murder committed in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> almost every week, and very rarely were the criminals brought to justice.</seg></p>

<p>"The Mormon leaders taught the people to attend to their fields and workshops, keep out of 'Whisky Street,' and let 'civilisation' take its course. They had plenty of hard work to engage their attention, and no money, so that the business street was seldom visited by them, and they saw little of what was transpiring in their midst. The Church weekly paper took pride in reporting, as it occurred, 'another man for breakfast,' and with that' the people of God' were satisfied that 'the good work was rolling on.' Israel would one day be free from his oppressors.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">"The rioting and killing that were traceable occupied little more than passing attention, but the midnight work of invisible hands created a sensation of terror in the minds of all who were inimical to the priesthood. <hi rend="italic">The Valley Tan</hi>, notwithstanding its true boldness, felt the danger of the hour, and in one of its doleful wails ejaculated: 'How long, oh! how long are scenes like this to continue? * * * It would seem as if the insatiable demon and enemy of man must himself be gorged with the flow of human blood in our midst.'</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">* * * 'No man's life is secure as long as the scenes of violence and bloodshed, which have been of such frequent occurrence among us for months past, continue to be repeated, and the perpetrators escape unpunished or not detected.'</seg></p>

<p>"The bloody work continued, and finally terminated with the murder of <persName key="Brewer, ">Brewer</persName> and <persName key="Johnston, Joaquin">Joaquin Johnston</persName>, two intimate friends, who were shot at the same instant as they were walking home together. The author well remembers seeing

<pb n="242" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.242"/>

very early the next morning the marshal of the city and the chief of police who gravely informed him of the 'sad news'&#8212;'<persName key="Johnston, Joaquin">Johnston</persName> and <persName key="Brewer, ">Brewer</persName> had quarreled, and killed each other!' This story was feeble enough, but no one cared to question it: the people had got used to the record of scenes of blood.</p>

<p>"In the 'swift destruction' that fell upon the desperadoes, there was no mitigation of punishment on account of faith or family relationship, and very respectable Mormon families had to mourn the untimely end of boys who, before the entrance of the army, gave promise of lives of usefulness and honor. All the bad and desperate Mormons were not brought to judgment, but the pretext alone was wanting for carrying more extensively into execution the general programme. Resistance to an officer, or the slightest attempt to escape from custody, was eagerly seized, when wanted, as the justification of closing a disreputable career, and in more than one case of this <hi rend="italic">legal</hi> shooting, there is much doubt if even the trivial excuse was waited for. The <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> police then earned the reputation of affording every desperate prisoner the opportunity of escape, and, if embraced, the officer's ready revolver brought the fugitive to a 'halt,' and saved the country the expenses of a trial and his subsequent boarding in the penitentiary.  A coroner's inquest and cemetery expenses were comparatively light.</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">"With the troops themselves there was no collision. The Governor had requested General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> to withhold furlough from the soldiers, and few of them ever had the opportunity of visiting the City of the Saints. With some officers there had been, in the city, slight difficulties, which were, however, easily settled.</seg> Only one serious affair occurred, ending in the death of Sergeant <persName key="Pike, Ralph">Pike</persName>. This person was charged with violently assaulting <persName key="Spencer, Howard O.">a young Mormon</persName> and cracking his skull with a musket. During the Sergeant's trial in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, while on the public street at noon, passing to his hotel, <persName key="Spenser, Howard O.">a young man</persName> shot him down, and shortly afterward lie died. <persName key="Spenser, Howard O.">The young man</persName>, with the aid of others, escaped, and was never arrested. There was great excitement at Camp Floyd, but <persName key="Pike, Ralph">the Sergeant</persName>'s comrades were too far away to retaliate.</p>

<p>"From the time of the arrival of the troops in the valley, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> was personally very cautious, and never exposed himself to attack. For a long time he absented himself from the public assemblies, kept an armed door-keeper at the entrance of his residences, and by night was protected by an armed guard of the faithful. Every ward in the city took its turn in watching over the Prophet, and the floors of his offices were nightly covered with a guard, armed and equipped, and ready at a moment's notice to repulse the imaginary foe.</p>

<p>"During the day, when <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> ventured beyond the outer walls of his premises, half a dozen friends always accompanied him wherever he went. It is pleasing to add that no one ever so much as said to him an unbecoming word."</p>

<p>In this condition of society, and the antagonistic complication of affairs existing between the Governor and General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> and the Judges, is to be found the exact historical exposition why the Mountain Meadow Massacre was not brought to judgment and avenged years before the execution of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>.</p>

<p>Ex-Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> has often, yet most senselessly been reproved and held guilty for not causing an investigation of the tragedy in question, and bringing

<pb n="243" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.243"/>

its executors to justice immediately after the bloody deed was done. One of the questions and its answer from the deposition of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, taken at the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, bears directly upon this point:</p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">"Q. Why did you not as Governor institute proceedings forthwith to investigate the massacre and bring the guilty authors to justice?</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">"A. Because another Governor had been appointed by the President of the United States, and was then on the way here to take my place, and I did not know how soon he might arrive; and because the United States Judges were not in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. Soon after Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> arrived I asked him to take Judge <persName key="Cradelbaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, who belonged to the Southern District, with him, and I would accompany them with sufficient aid to investigate the matter and bring the offenders to justice."</seg></seg></p>

<p>But the action of the Judges, at the very onset, made it impossible for ex-Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> or Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> to move far in the matter. Though <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> had been Justice personified, had he proceeded he must have walked into the death-trap set for him.</p>

<p>The following editorial excerpt from the <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>, July 3rd, 1858, describes the case of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> before the entrance of the troops, which was more abundantly illustrated afterwards:</p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"The latest accounts from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> present the affairs of that Territory in rather a queer light. All the correspondents of the newspapers who write from Camp Scott most zealously contend that Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, in representing the Mormons as having submitted to his authority, has either been grossly deceived himself, or else is seeking to deceive the Government and the country. Possibly, as to this matter, the good people of Camp Scott, civil and military, judge the Mormons a little too much by themselves. If the disposition to obey the Governor and to second and sustain him in the exercise of his office is not greater within the valley than it seems to be at Camp Scott and Fort Bridger, the extent of the Governor's authority is certainly limited enough. Whether or not <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and his people have combined together, while seeming to acknowledge <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> as Governor&#8212;in fact to set aside and override his authority, at least it is very certain that such a combination exists in full force at Camp Scott, with Mr. Chief Justice <persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">Eckles</persName> at its head. <seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">Perhaps there is something in the air of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> that stimulates to treason, rebellion, and resistance to authority.</seg> Whether that be so or not, the authority of <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> as Governor seems just now quite as much in danger from the Chief Justice, the civil officers, and the army sent to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> at such an expense to place him and sustain him in the Governor's chair, as from those whose anticipated opposition to his authority led to such costly preparations to uphold it. In fact, it would seem that, on the question of due respect to <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>'s gubernatorial authority, the people inside the valley and those out of it had completely changed ground. The resistance to Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> is not now on the part of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and the Mormons generally, but on the part of Chief Justice <persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">Eckels</persName>, Marshal <persName key="Dotson, Peter K.">Dotson</persName>, General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, the camp, and the camp-followers.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">"In this resistance to the authority of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> and combination to reduce him, if possible, to a cipher, the recently arrived Peace <choice><orig>Commis-

<pb n="244" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.244"/>

sioners</orig><reg>Commissioners</reg></choice>, according to all accounts, have joined, actuated possibly by a feeling of jealousy that they should have been anticipated by Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> and the work of pacification taken out of their hands. Nor, if we are to believe the letters from the camp, do these gentlemen confine themselves merely to thwarting the policy of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> and nullifying his authority as Governor. They go, indeed, much further than that. The President's proclamation, of which they are the bearers, does not meet their approbation, or appear to them adapted to the exigencies of the case. They harmonize completely, we are told, with Judge <persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">Eckles</persName> and General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, and not content with upsetting and overriding the Governor, are resolved to upset and override the President too. The proclamation is, therefore, to be construed&#8212;by the help, we suppose, of that profound jurist, Judge <persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">Eckles</persName>&#8212;in conformity to their ideas. In other words, it is to be nullified and set aside.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">"We have heard a great deal heretofore about the danger of personal violence and loss of property to which the Gentiles in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory of Utah</placeName> have been exposed on the part of the Mormons. At present, the danger seems to be entirely the other way. Nothing can exceed the rancorous and even ferocious feelings against the Mormons with which the army at Camp Scott appears to be penetrated.</seg> They regard themselves as engaged not so much in a public service as in the prosecution of a private quarrel. They regard the Mormons as having subjected them to all the hard service of this campaign&#8212;as having kept them encamped all winter on short rations amid the mountains&#8212;as having derided, maligned, and insulted them; and even the very common soldiers are represented as having put on an air of offended dignity at the idea that the Peace Commissioners had arrived to snatch their intended victims from their revengeful grasp. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">This state of feeling on the part of the soldiers affords an abundant justification for Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>'s objections to their entry into the valley and for the dread and horror with which, the Mormons regard their presence there. If it be deemed proper or necessary to station troops in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, they ought to be some fresh <hi rend="italic">corps</hi>, and not a body of men filled with such hatred and prejudice. Let some of the troops now on their march across the plains be employed in this service, and the force now collecting under General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnson</persName> be sent in some other direction. That officer, however, would seem bent upon entering the valley, in spite of the remonstrances of Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>, whose authority over the troops he denies, with the very object, it would seem, of driving the Mormons to destroy their houses and to prevent them from gathering: their crops, thus subjecting thousands of women and children to the danger of starvation."</seg></seg></p>

<p>The Peace Commissioners, however, in the sequel accomplished their mission, but the breach between Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> and General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> and the Judges, extended, as we have seen, to the impeachment of his course and a demand from Camp Floyd for his removal.</p>

<p>But <seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">his inability to investigate</seg> and bring to justice the authors of the Mountain Meadow Massacre, during his term of office, is known to have been a thorn in Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName>'s side. After him no Governor could be specially held

<pb n="245" xml:id="mmm.uh.tullidge.1886.245"/>

responsible; and thus justice tarried long, impeded at the onset by the Judges themselves, which is the unmistakable import of Attorney-General <persName key="Black, Jeremiah S.">Black</persName>'s rebuke to them.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>