<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">History of Utah, Volume I</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename>Orson</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Whitney</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.uh.whitney.1892</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Reaction!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m">History of Utah, Volume 1</title>
                    <author><forename>Orson</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Whitney</surname></author>
                    <publisher>George Q. Cannon &amp; Sons Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Salt Lake City, UT</pubPlace>
                    <extent>689-728</extent>
                    <date when="1892">1892</date>
                    <note type="source">Orson F. Whitney. <hi rend="italic">History of Utah. Vol. I.</hi> Salt Lake City, UT: George Q. Cannon &amp; Sons Co., 1892. 689-710.
                    </note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>utah_history</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-07-12"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2009"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
<div type="chapter">
<pb n="689" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.689"/>

<head>CHAPTER XXXII.</head>

<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">AFTER "THE WAR"&#8212;THE FEDERAL COURTS IN OPERATION&#8212;JUDGE SINCLAIR SEEKS TO RENEW THE STRIFE&#8212;HE SENTENCES A MURDERER TO BE HUNG ON SUNDAY&#8212;JUDGE CRADLEBAUGH'S ADMINISTRATION&#8212;THE STORY OF THE MOUNTAIN MEADOWS MASSACRE&#8212; CRADLEBAUGH'S VAIN ATTEMPT TO FASTEN THE AWFUL CRIME UPON THE MORMON LEADERS&#8212;HE SUMMONS THE MILITARY TO HIS AID&#8212;THE COURT HOUSE AT PROVO SURROUNDED BY FEDERAL BAYONETS&#8212;THE CITIZENS PROTEST AND THE GOVERNOR PROCLAIMS AGAINST THE MILITARY OCCUPATION&#8212;A CONSPIRACY TO ARREST PRESIDENT YOUNG THWARTED BY GOVERNOR CUMMING&#8212;ATTORNEY&#8212;GENERAL BLACK REBUKES THE UTAH JUDGES&#8212;THE ANTI-MORMONS SEEK THE REMOVAL OF GOVERNOR CUMMING&#8212;COLONEL KANE TO THE RESCUE&#8212;HOW UTAH WAS AFFECTED BY JOHNSTON'S ARMY&#8212;HORACE GREELEY AT SALT LAKE CITY&#8212;MORE NEWSPAPERS&#8212;THE "VALLEY TAN" AND THE "MOUNTAINEER"&#8212;WILLIAM H. HOOPER DELEGATE TO CONGRESS&#8212;THE PONY EXPRESS&#8212;THE CIVIL WAR&#8212;CAMP FLOYD ABANDONED.</hi></hi></p>

<p>SOON after the arrival of the Federal officials who accompanied and immediately followed <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s army to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, the three judges, <persName key="Eckels, David R.">David R. Eckels</persName>, <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Charles E. Sinclair</persName>, and <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">John Cradlebaugh</persName>, were assigned to their respective districts, and the machinery of the United States courts was set in motion. Chief Justice <persName key="Eckels, David R.">Eckels</persName>, preferring the military atmosphere to which for several months he had been accustomed, took up his residence at Camp Floyd; Associate Justice <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName> was assigned to the Third Judicial District, which, as now, embraced <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, while Associate Justice <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, who was the last of the three to arrive, was appointed to the Second District, comprising the southern counties. The other officials were: <persName key="Hartnett, John">John Hartnett</persName>, Secretary; <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Alexander Wilson</persName>, United States Attorney; <persName key="Dotson, Peter K.">Peter K. Dotson</persName>, Marshal, and <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName>, Superintendent of Indian Affairs. It had been deemed proper by the authorities at <placeName type="state" key="Washington, D. C.">Washington</placeName> to separate the last-named office from that of Governor. All but one of the new officials were non-residents of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. The exception was the United States Marshal, Mr. <persName key="Dotson, Peter K.">Dotson</persName>.</p>

<pb n="690" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.690"/>

<p>Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName> opened court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> in November, 1858. His first move was not a reassuring one to the people, who, trusting in the pledge given by Governor Cumming and the Peace Commissioners, that the Federal representatives would keep faith with the citizens and hold sacred the amnesty extended by President Buchanan, had abandoned their exodus and returned to their homes and various avocations. It seemed to them an attempt to ignore or override the President's decree; to render null and void his offer of pardon which the people had accepted. In short, Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName>, in charging the grand jury of his court, urged them to indict ex-Governor Young, Lieutenant-General Wells and other prominent Mormons for treason; also for intimidation of court and for, polygamy. The Judge held that President Buchanan's pardon,' while it was "a public fact in the history of the country," "ought to be brought judicially by plea, motion or otherwise." This meant that the decree of the Chief Magistrate of the nation was not to have full force and effect until he, <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Charles E. Sinclair</persName>, appointed by said Chief Magistrate an Associate Justice of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, had sat upon it and pronounced it valid; or, as Mr. Stenhouse puts it, "he wanted to bring before his court <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and the leading Mormons to make them admit that they had been guilty of treason, and make them humbly accept from him the President's clemency."<ref target="n01">*</ref></p>

<p>The vain-glorious attempt failed, as it deserved to do. A sensible man, one not so anxious to re-open the wound then healing, to renew the strife which had just been brought to a close, was the United States Attorney, <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">Alexander Wilson</persName>. He refused to present to the jury bills for indictments for treason, on the ground that the President's pardon had been presented by the Peace Commissioners and accepted by the people, whereupon peace had been proclaimed by the Governor of the Territory. An indictment was secured against <persName key="Ferguson, James">James Ferguson</persName> for intimidation of court, the act of which occurred in Judge Stiles' district at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> in 1854, and grew

<note xml:id="n01">* The Rocky Mountain Saints," page 402.</note>

<pb n="691" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.691"/>
    
out of the rivalry existing between the Federal and Territorial officers and tribunals referred to in a former chapter. The case against Mr. Ferguson never came to judgment. As to polygamy, there being no law against the practice,&#8212;for it was not until 1862 that Congress legislated against polygamy as "bigamy,"&#8212;the grand jury failed to return any indictments on that score.</p>

<p>The only other act of Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName>'s that causes his name to be remembered in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>&#8212;barring his collusion with other officials to secure the arrest of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> on a trumped-up, baseless charge of counterfeiting&#8212;was his sentencing a man who had committed murder to be executed on the Sabbath. This man was Thomas H. Ferguson, a non-Mormon, who, while drunk, had shot and killed his employer, Alexander Carpenter, another non-Mormon. The homicide occurred September 17th, 1859, and the execution&#8212;the day originally set having been changed&#8212;on Friday, the 28th of October.<ref target="n02">*</ref> Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName> was quite a young man, which may partly account for some of his idiosyncrasies.</p>

<p>Meantime Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> had begun operations in the Second Judicial District. This court convened at Provo on the 8th of March, 1859. The seat of the Second District was at Fillmore, the former capital of the Territory, and it was there, on the first Monday of November, 1858, that Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> should have opened court. Such was the appointment made for him before his arrival by Judges Eckels and <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName>, constituting a majority of the supreme bench of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, empowered by Congress to arrange those matters. The appointment was made in August, 1858, but Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> did not arrive upon the scene of his labors until the first week in November. This was probably his reason for not

<note xml:id="n02">* Said the condemned man on the scaffold: "I was tried by the statutes of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah Territory</placeName>, which give a man the privilege of being shot, beheaded or hanged. But was it given to me? No, it was not. All Judge <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName> wanted was to sentence some one to be hanged, then he was willing to leave the Territory; and he had too much whiskey in his head to know the day he sentenced me to be executed on, and would not have known, if it had not been for the people of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> laughing at him. It would have been on Sunday. A nice Judge to send to any country!"</note>

<pb n="692" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.692"/>

beginning on time; but why he did not open court at the place appointed, but arbitrarily changed it from <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName> to <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, in the absence of an avowed reason must be surmised. We surmise, therefore, that it was in order to be nearer Camp Floyd; it being the design of Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, in inaugurating the extraordinary proceedings by him contemplated, to call to his aid the strong arm of the military. That design, as we shall see, was strictly carried out.</p>

<p>Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> proposed to investigate, among other things, the Mountain Meadows massacre, referred to previously. The facts relating to this terrible tragedy, as gathered from the most reliable sources,&#8212;some of which have never before been drawn upon,&#8212;will now be laid before the reader.</p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">The summer of 1857 </seg>furnished the bloodiest page in all the history of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. The theme is approached by the chronicler with shuddering, and its recital must fill the heart of every reader with horror. There is a crime that is worse than murder&#8212;a massacre; and massacre never assumes form so horrid as when <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">its victims are defenseless</seg>,&#8212;most dreadful of all when with the slain mingles the blood of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">helpless women and innocent children</seg>.</p>

<p>About midsummer of the year mentioned a large body of <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri"><placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName></seg> and <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrants</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">en route to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>, reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">They traveled in two separate parties, and were <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">well provided with stock, implements and the supplies constituting the usual emigrant outfit</seg>.</seg> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">For some days after their arrival, during which time they had repairs made in their vehicles and had their animals shod, they were in doubt as to which route of the two then commonly used to the Coast they should follow. At length <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> party</seg> decided, probably upon the advice of General <persName key="Rich, Charles C.">Charles C. Rich</persName> who was familiar with both, to take the northern route, which, it will be remembered, crossed Bear River and proceeded along the Humboldt. They started, but made only a few days' journey,&#8212;it was afterwards learned that they went no farther than Bear River&#8212;when for some reason, probably because southern <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> was their destination, the majority concluded to return

<pb n="693" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.693"/>

and take the southern route, leading through southwestern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. Proceeding southward through the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> settlements, the two companies, one of which, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the Arkansas party</seg>, was led by a man named <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName>, and the other, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">the <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> party</seg>, was under command of a Mr. <persName key="Dukes, William C.">Dukes</persName>, became separated by several days' journey. It is known that <persName key="Dukes, William C.">Dukes</persName>' company were delayed some time near <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>. Here they had trouble with the Indians, one of whom they had shot. Being attacked, they corralled their wagons and sought protection in a rifle pit. Two of them were wounded, but the Indians were soon placated through the intervention of officers of the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> militia, who distributed to them liberal contributions of beef. <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName>'s party in the meantime kept moving ahead, and had penetrated the Indian country and were beyond the line of settlements before <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">the Missouri company</seg> advanced from this camp.</seg></p>

<p>It was a time of great anxiety if not of intense excitement in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">News had just come that the troops sent by President <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> were nearing <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, and every express brought reports of the brutal and infamous threats with which the camps of the soldiery resounded. In their wagons, they declared, were the ropes with which the Mormon leaders were to be hanged. <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">With their recent experiences in <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="Illinois">Illinois</placeName> fresh in their minds, the settlers were naturally in a state of the utmost anxiety as to the developments of the future.</seg> Martial law was all but declared in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and the people were fully warned as to the exceeding gravity of the situation. Under the circumstances it was their plain duty to watch for signs of hostility on the part of emigrants or others who sought to pass through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">Whatever may have been the conduct of these companies when they encountered the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> outposts on the east, there seems to be no question that not long after their arrival in Salt Lake Valley they gave abundant evidence of their hostility and vindictiveness. During their entire journey through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> they appear to have conducted themselves in the most offensive manner. They swaggered through the towns, declaring their intention, as soon

<pb n="694" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.694"/>

as they should have conveyed their women and children to a place of safety, to return with military force sufficient to complete such destruction of the Mormons as the United States soldiery might leave unfinished. <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">They averred that the murdered leaders of the Church had received but tardily their deserts, and gave the impression, if they did not positively boast, that in their company were hands that had been reddened with the Prophet's blood.</seg> Nor were their offenses confined to harrowing and insulting words. They acted like a band of marauders, preying upon the possessions of those whose country they traversed, and committing all manner of petty indignities upon person and property. Still graver crimes were charged against them by the Indians. They were said not only to have wantonly shot some of the braves, but were known to have <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">left poisoned beef where the savages would be likely to get it. Several deaths, attributed to this cause, occurred among the Indians near <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, and numbers of their animals perished through drinking water from springs poisoned by the emigrants when about to break camp</seg>.</seg></p>

<p>One result of this deliberate policy of exasperation was the attack by Indians on the rear party, the <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> contingent, at its camp near <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>. Dissuaded at that time from their design to take summary revenge for the atrocities committed against them, the Indians hung on the horizon of their foe, as the latter drove out past the last settlements, and when in the very heart of the Indian country the attack was renewed. Again the services of the Mormons, two or three of whom had been detailed to overtake and accompany the emigrants as guides and interpreters, stood the besieged in good stead. The enraged savages were bought off with the loose stock of the company, agreeing to leave unmolested the teams and wagons and take no life. These emigrants resumed their journey and reached their destination in safety.<ref target="n03">*</ref>

<note xml:id="n03">* Soon afterwards the Indians were persuaded by the president of the Southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> Indian mission&#8212;<persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>&#8212;to surrender the stock, and all that had not been killed was delivered by him to an agent who came to receive it in response to his notification that it was held subject to his order.</note>

<pb n="695" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.695"/>

For the leading party, however, a horrible fate was reserved. Though in the main composed of families that bore the appearance of respectability, <seg type="Blame" subtype="MissouriWildCats">there was a rough and lawless element in their ranks that lost no opportunity of exhibiting its bitterness and destructiveness.</seg> <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">Against this company, as stated, was laid the fearful charge of injecting poison into the carcass of one of their oxen,<ref target="n04">*</ref> first having learned that the Indians would be likely to eat the meat, and of throwing packages of poison into the springs. In other ways they contrived to render themselves obnoxious to the settlers and hateful to the natives.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">It is hinted, too, that coming from the state and some even from the county in which one of the Apostles, <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley P. Pratt</persName>, had been assassinated only a short time before, the blood-thirsty talk of the emigrants had intensified the feeling their other conduct had aroused among the people.</seg> In the spring of this same year Apostle <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> had stood trial in <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> on the charge of having married the wife and abducted the children of <persName key="McLean, Hector">Hector McLean</persName>, a Louisianian by birth but then a resident of <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>. The charge was not sustained, and the defendant was acquitted. But <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName>'s threat of vengeance and the solicitation of friends impelled the Apostle to seek safety in flight. Undertaking to make his way alone on horseback through a wild and sparsely settled country, he was intercepted by accomplices of <persName key="McLean, Hector">McLean</persName> and held until the latter could come up and dispatch him. The assassin in his fury not only plunged his knife repeatedly into the body of his victim, but also shot him through the breast with a pistol snatched from the hand of a comrade. Neither principal nor accomplices in the tragedy were ever brought to justice, though the testimony at the coroner's inquest substantiated the facts here narrated.</seg> <ref target="n05">&#8224;</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n04">* This act was witnessed by men who camped near the emigrants at Corn Creek.</note>

<note xml:id="n05">&#8224; <seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder"><persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Parley P. Pratt</persName> was murdered near <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, May 13, 1857. <persName key="Cannon George Q.">George Q. Cannon</persName> was chosen to succeed him as one of the Twelve Apostles. His name was presented to the general conference of the Church by President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, April 7, 1860, and he was ordained August 26th of that year.</seg></note>

<pb n="696" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.696"/>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">As <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrants</seg> drew farther away from the larger and stronger towns and approached the isolated and straggling settlements on the southern and western border, they grew more defiant in language and actions. <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> was the last place of any consequence on the route. Here their customary proceeding of burning fences, whipping the heads off chickens or shooting them in the streets or private dooryards, to the extreme danger of the inhabitants, was continued. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Slander">One of them, a blustering fellow riding a grey horse flourished his pistol in the face of the wife of one of the citizens, all the time making insulting proposals and uttering profane threats.</seg> When the town marshal notified them that they were violating the city ordinances they set his authority at defiance, declaring they would fight before any of their party should be surrendered. They seemed to think they had completely intimidated the people, and as a parting threat told in some quarters that they were going to camp in <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain Meadows</geogName> until they should have fattened their beef animals so that an invading auxiliary force, expected from the west, would have plenty of supplies.</seg> It is probable that they had chosen <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName> as the last point for a prolonged halt through a suggestion given them by <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>, a member of <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>'s party, whom they had met at Corn Creek, now Kanosh, fifteen miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, about the 23rd of August. <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">Knowing of <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> as a pioneer in the southern country, the emigrants asked him about the road, and inquired as to a suitable place to rest and recruit their teams before crossing the desert. He suggested to them the south end of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, a few miles from his ranch, where there was plenty of good feed and water for the animals.</seg></p>

<p>Apostle <persName key="Smith, George A.">Smith</persName> was returning from a tour of the southern settlements, during which he had at almost every opportunity given pointed advice to the people on the crisis which seemed to be impending. He had only just returned to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> after a year's absence, and as some of his family lived in I<placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">ron County</placeName>, he had left <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> about the end of July to visit them. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">On this journey, both going and coming, he warned the people against wasting their

<pb n="697" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.697"/>

grain or using it for horse-feed, as crops had been short for several years. He advised against selling to emigrants for this purpose, but distinctly urged the duty of furnishing strangers with what bread-stuffs they needed for themselves and families. That these emigrants and others were able to supply themselves with the necessaries of life for their long journey was directly due to this humane counsel and its general acceptance.</seg> The fact that he had never heard of <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrants</seg> before he met them at Corn Creek, where he camped near them one night on his way back to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, and that he immediately started east and heard no more of them until he reached Bridger, appears to have escaped the notice of those who subsequently sought to associate him with the tragedy at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. He was as innocent of connection with that crime as a babe unborn.</p>

<p>The ill-starred company, traveling slowly, reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> and <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> in succession, passing the last-named place about the 27th or 28th of August. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Here, as at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, they were able to purchase grain, and though doubtless regarded with distrust, were treated with humanity. Proceeding a few miles farther they camped several days near some of the springs in the vicinity, trading stock with the settlers and buying more grain.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">Their insolent conduct continued, and yet they seemed loth to leave the last signs of civilization,&#8212;the society of a people whom they hated.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Meantime the Indians were becoming aroused at the reports which had reached them of this company's deeds at Corn Creek and other places. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The red men shared in no small degree the excitement of the whole country over the prospects of early war.</seg> No doubt the horses and herds of the emigrants were also something of a temptation to the savages.</seg></p>

<p><placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> was the most distant town from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> on the line of travel to southern <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, and for that reason the first point in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> which an expedition from that direction would reach. Their very remoteness made the settlers peculiarly alert and watchful for the first manifestations of that era of sanguinary distress that

<pb n="698" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.698"/>

was universally believed to be impending. It was accordingly the custom for the more prominent citizens to meet together frequently to discuss the situation and exchange ideas and suggestions as to what course should be taken with reference to any emergency. In their scattered condition,&#8212;many of them living on farms and ranches several miles distant,&#8212;it was no easy task to secure attendance at such a meeting except by previous appointment. Thus it happened that Sunday, when the people were accustomed to assemble for religious worship, came to be chosen for these brief consultations, the men folks meeting in council before the usual services began, or remaining a short time after they were concluded. Such was the case on Sunday, the 30th of August, the second or third day after the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> company had passed through. The conduct of that company in and near <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, and the knowledge of their lawlessness all along the line of previous settlements, associated with the ferocious threat that their early return as a mob of destroyers might be expected, caused earnest and even indignant allusion to them at this particular council. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">By some it was suggested that as they were about to enter the Indian country the savages would be likely to harass and plunder them to a degree that would prevent their promised return.</seg> It is probable that others were in favor of bringing them back and holding them as prisoners of war. What other suggestions, if any, were offered at the time is not known; but it is a fact that it was then and there resolved that the Indians should be held in check, and the emigrants permitted to pass in safety. A dispatch to that effect was sent shortly afterward by Lieutenant-Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> to the presiding official at Pinto [or Painter] Creek.</p>

<p>The messenger who delivered this order remembers that on his return he met the emigrants just breaking camp for the last time before entering the <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. He was accompanied on his errand of peace by <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>, then Bishop of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>; and they had scarcely set out from that place before they met <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, to whom they communicated the object of their journey. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was a major in the militia; never a bishop in the Church&#8212;as so

<pb n="699" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.699"/>

often asserted&#8212;but <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">acting at this time as farmer among the Indians, and doubtless possessing much influence with them</seg>. His response indicated that he was displeased with the peaceful decision of the council. But though the Indians were gathered in force and under much excitement, near Pinto, the emigrants pursued their way in safety past that point and went into camp at the south end of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, about forty miles from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>. These elevated pastures were almost on the water-shed, or "rim of the Basin;" and as they proved to be a pleasant, grassy spot, the emigrants planned to remain there and recuperate before venturing upon the desert. They had been unable to purchase wagon grease at the settlements&#8212;the settlers had none for themselves&#8212;and after reaching camp, which was probably about Thursday, September 3rd, they sent two men into the pines to make tar to be used as a substitute.<ref target="n06">*</ref></p>

<p>In the meantime two men were despatched from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> under military orders to visit the camp at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> and ascertain if possible what the real program and intentions of the party were. About the same time there was a general movement looking to a concentration of the Indians, though they do not seem to have massed at one point in any considerable number until Sunday, the 6th. The two messengers proceeded to <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s ranch, in the north end of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, from which place they twice visited the emigrants, on Saturday, the 5th, and Sunday, the 6th. They were civilly treated and informed that as soon as the two men who were making tar, and two others whom they intended sending back a few miles for some strayed cattle, returned, the company would vacate the Meadows. These latter men passed <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s Sunday morning, stopping there to water their horses.</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Sabbath passed in peace at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, but it was a day of excitement among the Indians congregated near <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Pinto</placeName>, by whom it had been arranged that after the emigrants started and while they were journeying along the Santa Clara in straggling order, they</seg>

<note xml:id="n06">* These men escaped the general massacre that followed, but are understood to have been pursued by Indians to the Muddy country, and there slain.</note>

<pb n="700" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.700"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">should be attacked and plundered. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Death was to be the portion of the men if they resisted</seg>, but <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">the women and children were to be spared</seg>. The attack was precipitated, however, by the bloodthirsty haste of one of the chiefs, who, dozing while the corn and potatoes were roasting for the evening meal, dreamed that his double-hands were filled with blood. Regarding this as a favorable omen, and rousing his braves, whose sanguinary temper, long restrained, now needed no whet, the hot and furious march for the emigrant camp was forthwith begun, the untasted supper being left in the embers. <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> appears to have been the only white man then with the savages.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">It was just at dawn on Monday, the 7th,</seg> when from the heights and ravines surrounding their camp a volley carried pain and death into the ranks of the emigrants. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Seven men were killed and sixteen wounded.</seg> Rudely aroused to the fate threatening them, the men rushed to the shelter of their wagons, and immediately began to entrench themselves by throwing up a slight bank of earth against their wagon wheels, and excavating a rifle pit in the center of their corral. Their defense was so stubborn and their movements so expeditious that the attacking party withdrew, and taking position on the adjacent hills, instituted a state of siege, meantime pouring in a deadly fire upon such of the hapless garrison as ventured outside the barricade for water. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">All told, the emigrants numbered about one hundred and thirty-seven; twenty-three were already killed or wounded, four were away at the pines and after the cattle, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">at least seventeen were children under seven years of age,&#8212;this number being spared the massacre that ensued.</seg> Of the remaining ninety-two or ninety-three a goodly proportion were probably women and maidens.</seg> The fighting strength of the company, including young and old, could not, therefore, have been very great. But they were nerved by desperation. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The besiegers had driven off their animals</seg>, so all thought of advance was idle. Equally futile was any hope of retreat. If they left their entrenchments it was to expose themselves to savage marksmanship, and they would have been

<pb n="701" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.701"/>

speedily cut down. No course was open save to remain and resist until possibly relief might come. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">During Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday they kept up the unequal conflict</seg>, their stock of ammunition running lower and lower, and their sufferings from thirst during the day being intense.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Only a few hours before this first attack was made, while the Indians were still believed to be under control at <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Pinto</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">the question of dealing with the emigrants on account of their continued ill behavior again came up for consideration at a council held in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName></seg>. There were present as usual&#8212;it being Sunday&#8212;the leading officers of the local militia and other prominent citizens. Up to that time there had been no demonstration against the emigrants, though it must have been known from the assembling and demeanor of the savages that they were planning a raid upon them. Again there were suggestions that the company be intercepted and brought back; having declared themselves as enemies, it was argued that they should be treated as such. Some there were, notably the fiery <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, who advocated an immediate attack upon the camp. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was not present, but <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">is said to have sent word that the Indians were growing restless and vehement.</seg> From all reports the debate was animated, if not heated. But at length the suggestion prevailed that a courier be sent to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> with dispatches detailing the provocation to hostilities that had been given, noting the Indian desire for revenge and asking his advice in regard to the situation. <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, in command of the <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> militia, was to write and forward the letter, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">instructions were to be sent to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> to pacify the Indians and keep them from attacking the emigrants.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Both dispatches were written, and on Monday afternoon they were put into the hands of riders who knew their contents, for delivery at their respective destinations. <persName key="Clewes, Joseph">Joseph Clewes</persName> carried the letter addressed by Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> to a resident of Pinto Creek, enclosing an order to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> to keep the Indians off the emigrants and protect them from all harm until further orders. Before this letter reached Pinto Creek, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and the Indians had left for <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>; and

<pb n="702" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.702"/>

before it was received by him there, as he afterwards acknowledged it was received, the first attack had been made. The Indians had tasted of blood, some of their own had been spilt, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the emigrants having killed several and mortally wounded others</seg>, and no human power could now check their fury.</seg></p>

<p>The dispatch to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> was carried by <persName key="Haslam, James H.">James H. Haslam</persName>, who, riding express and changing horses frequently, was able to reach <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> on the morning of Thursday, the 10th. Delivering his message, he was asked to come at 1 p. m. of the same day for a reply. On making his appearance at the hour named, and answering affirmatively the Governor's question whether he could stand the journey back, injunction was laid upon him not to spare horseflesh in returning with the reply, for "the Indians must be kept from the emigrants at all cost, if it took all of <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName> to protect them."<ref target="n07">*</ref> He reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> on Sunday, September 13th, and delivered the letter to Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, who, as he read it, cried like a child, and exclaimed: "Too late, too late!" The massacre had already taken place.</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">The messengers to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> and <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> could have scarcely started upon their errands when word came to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> that the Indians had attacked the emigrants at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>. From that time on, Indian and white runners came almost daily from the scene of strife. The first reports were that the Indians, several hundred in number, had attacked and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">slain some of the emigrants</seg>, and that men were needed to guard the remnant and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">bury the dead</seg>. It was upon this call to Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> that <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName>, a major of one of the battalions of militia, on Tuesday the 8th, set out with a body of men and wagons for <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>. His force was not numerous and the men were not all supplied with arms. Some were teamsters and others took along picks and spades. They reached their destination early Wednesday morning, only to find that there had been no such bloodshed as that reported, and that the emigrants were making good their defense. But they found an angry host of

<ref target="n07">* Haslam's affidavit.</ref>

<pb n="703" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.703"/>

Indians bent on bloodshed, and outnumbering ten to one their own forces. An attempt by the militia to assist the emigrants would have transferred to themselves the Indian attack. During that day and the next, awaiting further orders they lay in camp, near to but out of sight of the entrenched emigrants, who were on the other side of a small hill. Thursday brought slight reinforcements, but by this time more Indians had arrived upon the scene. The whites, who were from the Santa Clara country, believed, as did <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>'s men, that they were summoned there on an errand of mercy, to bury the dead and protect the survivers. But the fury of the Indians was uncontrollable. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> may have attempted, as he says, to restrain them. It is not improbable, however, that after some of the Indians had been wounded, and himself had had a narrow escape from the riflemen in the corral, he made no further attempt to check the assault. He exhibited bullet holes in his clothing and hat, where <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> marksmanship</seg> had given evidence of its accuracy. But the Indians for some reason were inclined to think that he and the white men were planning to cheat them of their prey. About the third day of the attack, two men from <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s ranch approached the scene of battle, and came upon some wounded savages. Companions of the latter at once surrounded the two, upbraiding them with <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s supposed desertion of the Indians' cause, and compelling them, probably in order to demonstrate whether a friendly understanding existed between the whites on both sides, to run the gauntlet of the emigrant fire. They were required to pass in full view and close range of the camp, down the hill, across the valley and up on the other side. To make the attempt seemed to court certain death, but to refuse the Indians was to invite the vengeance of a still more savage foe. They made the daring run and escaped unharmed, though bullets whistled past them thick and fast.</seg></seg><ref target="n08">*</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n08">* There is another statement to the effect that these two men, prior to making the run, were compelled to don Indian attire. This furnishes the only foundation for the story that the militia disguised themselves as Indians.</note>

<pb n="704" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.704"/>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">This was probably on Wednesday, the 9th</seg>, and in explaining how the emigrants came to fire upon the white men, we at once come upon the probable cause and explanation of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">the horrid massacre that ensued two days later</seg>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">We have seen that among none of the men <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName></seg> was there any other understanding than that the Indians had been engaged in bloody work, and were to be restrained from further operations of like character. This was the decision of every council that had been held. It was the substance of every dispatch sent and command issued.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">But it is said that after Monday's attack a couple of horsemen, coming upon the two emigrants who had been sent back after lost cattle, shot one of them, a young man named <persName key="Aden, William Allen">Aden</persName>, and pursued his companion with the same deadly intent. The latter, however, escaped the bullets sent after him and succeeded in making his way back to the corral. To his comrades his story must have conveyed the dreadful impression that white men were in league with the Indians. The slayers of <persName key="Aden, William Allen">Aden</persName> are supposed to have continued on to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, where they probably urged upon some congenial spirits that since the emigrants now believed the settlers were accessory to the Indian attack, the killing of all who could tell the tale must be accomplished.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">Prior to this tragic incident, two of the emigrants had endeavored, under cover of darkness, to break through <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Indian lines</seg> and carry a call back to the settlement for assistance. These men were met in the cedars during the night time by a small party commanded by <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, who had left <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> the same evening. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Both the emigrants were killed, one of them falling, it is said, by <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>'s own hand.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Meantime another council had been held, this time at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, the regimental headquarters. At this council, over which <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName> as Colonel presided, the whole matter was once more discussed. The men present, of whom there were quite a number, listened to reports brought from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> to the effect that the emigrants had been attacked and were then surrounded. The decision of this council, like that of the preceding ones, was that the company should

<pb n="705" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.705"/>

be protected, and assisted to pass on in safety. Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> and his associates, after this conference, returned to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, and he is understood to have sent a message to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">that if it took all the property of the emigrants to appease the Indians, they were to have it</seg>; no more blood should be shed.</seg></p>

<p>But <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, who was doubtless among those who had been informed of <persName key="Aden, William Allen">Aden</persName>'s murder, and had divined its effect upon the emigrants, was already at work collecting men to go to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">He, and by this time some others, cannot have been guiltless of bloody intentions. His act, on meeting the two emigrant messengers in the cedars, is proof enough of his temper. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">There is no doubt that until he reached <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> the fatal order for the massacre had not been received. When he arrived he conferred with the leaders, and then for the first time was there talk as to a plan of attack.</seg> He brought encouragement and strength to those, if any there were, who were bent upon destroying the company&#8212;which had been his own plan in all the councils held at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>&#8212;and he undoubtedly gave the impression that the superior officers of the militia had given orders to that effect. <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, who as major of battalion was in command of militia on the ground, was of equal rank with <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, though much younger in years. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was also major, but at this time devoted himself more especially to the Indian forces. It was <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, however, who seemed to have the direction of affairs, and it is not unlikely that <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> by his ardor and representations&#8212;he was the latest arrival from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>&#8212;had more influence in the subsequent councils than any one else.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">Finally, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">on Friday morning, the 11th</seg>, the details of the plan were adopted.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">Shortly after noon two wagons were ordered up near the emigrant corral; a flag of truce was sent forward, and the besieged party answered it with one of their own. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> advanced to meet their representative; there was a long parley; and at length <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and his wagons entered the corral. His proposition was that the company should give up their arms, loading them into these two wagons, and, leaving their outfits on the ground, accept the escort of

<pb n="706" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.706"/>

himself and associates back to places of safety. The terms were acceded to; the wagons were quickly loaded, some of the children, two or three women, and a couple of wounded men also finding places thereon. The march back toward <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> began, the women walking behind the wagons, and the men behind the women, the whole making a straggling procession, with the militiamen in single file on the right hand and well toward the rear.<ref target="n09">*</ref> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The Indians were invisible, being in ambush ahead and to the right of the militia. The precision that had been arranged for the scheme did not prevent a hitch, and as the column kept moving on beyond the point where the signal was to be given, the savages, impatient at the delay and fearful that they were to be robbed of their revenge, advanced stealthily, some creeping on all fours up to the line.</seg><ref target="n10">&#8224;</ref> At last a gun-shot was heard in front, and immediately a volley of death blazed forth from the bushes, and from some parts of the militia line. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">At the first fire nearly all the adults were killed. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Those who survived it were speedily dispatched. None but small children were spared.</seg></seg></seg></seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">The slaughter lasted but two or three minutes.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">It is not believed that indignities were put upon the corpses, and it is denied that any were scalped. The militia kept moving northward, and night soon threw its black mantle over the horrible scene. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">A few men were sent back to the emigrant corral to keep the Indians from plundering the wagons, but the redskins had made quick work of stripping the clothing off the bodies, and were already looting the camp. That night the air was full of the wild bellowings of the cattle and the triumphant shouts of the savages</seg>; and here and there along the</seg>

<note xml:id="n09">* <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">It is said that one of the emigrants, after starting out with the rest, turned back, saying that <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">treachery was intended.</seg> His comrades persuaded him to rejoin the party, which by this time was quite a distance in advance.</seg></note>

<note xml:id="n10">&#8224; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">The signal was to be the word "Halt!" spoken when part of the procession had crossed the slight ridge which should separate the men and militia at the rear from the wagons and women in front. But the officer who was to give it delayed in the hope that other orders might be received or other counsels prevail, until the point of attack had long been passed and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the Indians were threatening to break in indiscriminately and begin the slaughter.</seg></seg></seg></note>

<pb n="707" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.707"/>

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">trail the cold, white face of a murdered man or woman looked up into the dark, dumb sky. It was an accursed, hated spot.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Scarcely had the dreadful work ended when two men from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, riding as if for their lives, met the advancing column. They bore no dispatches, but had come on their own account to seek to check any attempt to overturn the decision of the <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> and <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> councils. They were fearful that danger was in store for the emigrants, and this suspicion was confirmed when they met a runaway from <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, who told them of the crime that was on foot. Spurring their jaded horses to renewed speed, they reached the spot. But it was too late. The deed was done. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Next morning, Saturday, the 12th</seg>, Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and Lieutenant-Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, arrived on the scene. They were horror-struck, and it is said became involved in a heated quarrel.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">In the meantime steps were taken to bury the bodies. The ground was dry and hard, but during the day all were interred where they lay, sometimes three or four in a grave.</seg><ref target="n11">*</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">The orphaned children, seventeen in number, ranging in age from three months to seven years, were taken to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName> and distributed among the families in the vicinity. They were well cared for, and during the following summer were surrendered to Indian Superintendent <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> who reported that "they were in better condition than children generally in the settlements in which they lived." In the year 1859 they were <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">sent back to <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, an appropriation for the purpose having been made by Congress.</seg></p>

<note xml:id="n11">* <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">The graves were in most cases shallow, but there is no truth in the story that the first rains washed away the soil and left the bodies exposed. The bones that were afterwards collected had been dug from their resting place by wolves, and gnawed and scattered by the ferocious beasts.</seg>

<seg type="Reaction" subtype="Commemoration">In the spring of 1859 a detachment of troops from Camp Floyd, sent out for the purpose, gathered up the scattered bones and buried them in one spot, erecting over them a rude cairn, against which leaned a slab bearing the inscription: "Here <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">120 men, women and children</seg> were massacred in cold blood, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">early in September, 1857</seg>." Surmounting the cairn was a cross bearing the words: "Vengeance is mine: I will repay, saith the Lord." Nothing remains now to mark the place of sepulchre. Cairn and cross have yielded to the action of the elements, and have crumbled and disappeared.</seg></note>

<pb n="708" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.708"/>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Of the property of the murdered emigrants, the larger part, including nearly all the stock, was taken by the Indians. The remainder was conveyed to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, arriving during the night of Sunday, the 13th.<ref target="n12">*</ref> Soon afterwards the property, consisting of some clothing, wagon covers, utensils, etc., was sold at auction at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, the ubiquitous <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> acting as chief salesman. Not a dollar of it, and not a single hoof of stock belonging to the ill-fated company ever came into the hands of President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> or the Church, all assertions to the contrary notwithstanding.</seg></p>

<p>Such are the facts relating to the most dreadful occurrence in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>'s history. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, one of the chief actors, told a different story when on the 29th of September he brought to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> a verbal report of the affair. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">He said that Indians surrounded, massacred and stripped the bodies of the adults of the party, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">sold the children to the settlers</seg>; that no white men were concerned in the massacre and that when he heard of it he took some of his neighbors and went and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">buried the bodies</seg>.<ref target="n13">&#8224;</ref> Among all save the actual participants there was the completest acceptance of the story that the crime was committed solely by Indians.</seg> <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">Scarcely had the bodies been buried when the leaders in the bloody work called their men together and under the most binding oaths pledged them to secrecy. For years the unholy promise was kept, and when at length the truth began to leak out, the names of men entirely innocent were mingled in fatal proximity with those of the guilty.</seg> Of the militia, ordered or lured to the scene of the massacre by <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, nearly all were young men who</seg>

<note xml:id="n12">* Next day <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationMissouri">the <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> party of emigrants</seg> passed through <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>. They had heard of the fate of their associates, but <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">believed it to be the work of Indians.</seg></note>

<note xml:id="n13">&#8224; <persName key="Woodruff, Wilford">Wilford Woodruff</persName>'s Diary.

Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> in his report as Superintendent of Indian Affairs to the Commissioner, January 6th, 1858, says: "I quote from a letter written to me by <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, farmer to the Indians in <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron</placeName> and <placeName type="county" key="Washington County, UT">Washington</placeName> counties: '<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">About the 22nd of September</seg> Captain <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName> &amp; Co. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">fell victims to the Indians' wrath</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">near <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Their cattle and horses were shot down in every direction: their wagons and property mostly committed to the flames</seg>.'"</note>

<pb n="709" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.709"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">acted in innocence of evil under military orders. In most instances they took no part whatever in the actual killing. It was not until 1870 that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s complicity was established; when upon investigation and recommendation of Apostle <persName key="Snow, Erastus">Erastus Snow</persName> made to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, it was moved and unanimously carried in a council of the Apostles held at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> be expelled from the Church, with a solemn ban against re-admission under any circumstances, and that his superior officer, <persName key="Haight, Issac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, for failing to restrain him and take prompt action against him, be also excommunicated. <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, one of the most guilty throughout the whole affair, left the Church soon after the massacre, and was ever after burning with anxiety to turn states evidence.</seg><ref target="n14">*</ref></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">As said, it was this awful crime, the Mountain Meadows massacre, that Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, of the Second District Court, sitting at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName> in March, 1859, sought to investigate.</seg></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">So interested was he in the matter that he had paid a personal visit to the scene of the massacre.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">Other criminal cases that came before him at the same session of court, were the Potter and Parrish murders, which occurred at <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>, six miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, in March, 1857. <persName key="Parrish, William R.">William R. Parrish</persName>, his son <persName key="Parrish, Beason">Beason</persName> and <persName key="Potter, G. D. (Duff)">G. G. Potter</persName> were the persons killed,&#8212;shot and stabbed to death on the night of the 14th of March. The verdict of the coroner's jury was "that they came to their deaths by the hands of an assassin or assassins to the jury unknown." Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, however, was determined to make the Mormon Church responsible for the crime; and not only for this, but <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">for the Mountain Meadows massacre</seg>, and in fact for nearly every other deed of blood or lesser depredation committed in his district.</seg> His zeal and that of his coadjutors in this direction caused Superintendent <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> to remark, in his report to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs in August, 1859: "I fear, and I regret to say it, that with certain parties here there is a greater anxiety to connect

<note xml:id="n14">* Though sometimes referred to as Bishop <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Smith</persName>, and his name appearing to an affidavit dated April 10th, 1871, as <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingon Smith, he was usually known as Klingensmith</persName>.</note>

<pb n="710" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.710"/>

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and other church dignitaries with every criminal offense, than diligent endeavor to punish the actual perpetrators of crime." In charging the grand jury of his court on March 8th of that year, Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> used the following language:</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">I will say to you, Gentlemen of the Grand Jury, that from what I learn, it has been some time since a court, having judicial cognizance in your district, was held. No person has been brought to punishment for some two years; and from what I have learned I am satisfied that crime after crime has been committed.</seg></p>

<milestone unit="section" rend="stars"/>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">In consequence of the Legislature not having provided proper means, there is not that aid given that is desired to enable the judiciary to prosecute its duties; but I will say that the Legislature, in my opinion, have legislated to prevent the judiciary from bringing such offenders to justice.</seg></p>

<milestone unit="section" rend="stars"/>

<p>They have provided the Probate Courts with criminal jurisdiction, and it would seem that the whole machinery was made so that they should be brought before that court and tried, and the fact that there is no additional legislation to provide for bringing them before this court, proves that it was done to prevent.</p>

<p>The Judge then proceeded to find fault with the Deseret News for indulging in certain strictures on the Federal courts, and with ex-Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> for an alleged similar cause. Finally he came to the Mountain Meadows massacre and <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">the Potter and Parrish affair</seg>, also mentioning the murder of one <persName key="Fobbs, Henry">Henry Fobbs</persName> at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salem City, UT">Pondtown</placeName>, and the killing of <persName key="Jones, Henry">Henry Jones</persName> and his mother at <placeName type="settlement" key="Payson, UT">Payson</placeName>.<ref target="n15">*</ref> He then said:</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">To allow these things to pass over gives a color as if they were done by authority. The very fact of such a crime as that of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain meadows">the Mountain Meadows</geogName> shows that there was some person high in the estimation of the people, and it was done by that authority; and <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">this case of the Parrishes shows the same</seg>, and unless you do your duty, such will be the view that will be taken of it.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">You can know no law but the laws of the United States and the laws you have here. No person can commit crimes and say they are authorized by higher authorities, and if they have any such notions they will have to dispel them.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">I saw something said in that paper of some higher law. It is perhaps not proper to mention that, but such teachings will have their influence upon the public mind.</seg></p>

<note xml:id="n15">* <persName key="Fobbs, Henry">Fobbs</persName> was said to have been killed by Indians while passing through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. <persName key="Jones, Henry">Jones</persName> and his mother were guilty of incest and were shot by an enraged mob of citizens, who pulled down the house in which they dwelt. Both events took place in 1857.</note>

<!-- The Remainder of this document is not Directly Related to the Mountain Meadows Massacre:

<pb n="unnumbered" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.711"/>

<figure xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.711.figure">
<p>Ruben Miller</p>
<figDesc>A black and white portrait of Ruben Miller.</figDesc>
</figure>

<pb n="711" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.712"/>

<p>While Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> was delivering his charge to the grand jury, a detachment of infantry from Camp Floyd, numbering about a hundred men, commanded by Captain Heth, entered and encamped without permission upon the grounds adjoining the building&#8212;the Provo Seminary&#8212;which was being used temporarily as a court house. These grounds, with the Seminary, belonged to the city. While the soldiers invested the outside premises, the officers took up their quarters in the lower part of the building. Amazed and alarmed at this high-handed proceeding, which was looked upon as an attempt to intimidate jurors, witnesses and other persons attending court, the citizens of Provo at once filed indignant protests against the presence of the troops, and petitioned the Mayor and City Council to order their removal. Thereupon the Mayor, B. K. Bullock, in behalf of the council, addressed a memorial to Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> setting forth the facts stated and respectfully praying him to cause the military force to be removed beyond the limits of the municipality.</p>

<p>To this memorial the Judge replied that the temporary location of the troops in the city was a movement well considered before it was determined upon; that they were there at his request, having been "kindly furnished" by the commanding general at Camp Floyd, and that their presence was a matter of necessity, to secure prisoners who were to be tried before the court; there being no jail in which to confine them. His Honor stated in the course of his communication that the soldiers were as quiet and orderly a set of men as he ever saw. " As to your remark about intimidation," said the Judge to the Mayor, "allow me to say that good American citizens have no cause to fear American troops."</p>

<p>Mayor Bullock and the City Council immediately rejoined, informing Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> that he was mistaken in asserting that there was no jail in Provo; that they had a place prepared for such purposes, and were both willing and able, as were the authorities of the County, to provide abundantly for the security and necessities of all prisoners. They also informed him that

<pb n="712" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.713"/>

through the drunkenness and supercilious conduct of some of his "quiet and orderly soldiers" several unpleasant circumstances had already occurred between them and the citizens. Against the needless and degrading use of the army as "a walking calaboose" and the superseding of the civil by the military power, the city authorities again protested, and renewed their request for the removal of the troops. All <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> County was now aroused and petitions and protests of a similar character began pouring in from every side. Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> paid no attention to them whatever, but kept the court house surrounded by soldiers while he awaited the desired action . of the grand jury, to wit: the indictment of the Mormon leaders for the crimes referred to in his extraordinary address. More troops soon appeared upon the scene. Eight companies of infantry, one of artillery and one of cavalry, under Major Paul, followed Heth's command from Camp Floyd, and were stationed within sight of the Provo court house.</p>

<p>Public excitement and indignation increased correspondingly, and the citizens of Provo, and not only they, but the people of the Territory at large, now appealed to Governor Cumming against this flagrant infringement of their liberties. That appeal was not in vain. The Governor, not being in sympathy with the course pursued by the Federal Judges, and recognizing the rightfulness of the people's cause, promptly requested General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> to order the troops removed. The General, however, who was not only in sympathy, but in collusion with the Judges, refused to comply, holding himself obligated by the instructions of the War Department to his predecessor, General Harney, to obey the summons, not only of the Governor but of the Judges, and even of the United States Marshal, for troops to aid them in the performance of their duties. In this view General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> was of course sustained by the Judges. Doubtless his antipathy to Governor Cumming had something to do with his refusal to honor the request. But the Governor, who was quite a positive character, and knew his own rights as well as those

<pb n="713" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.714"/>

of the people, did not propose to be trifled with. He forthwith issued the following proclamation :</p>

<p>Whereas, one company of the U. S. Infantry, under the command of Captain Heth, is now stationed around the Court House at Provo, where the Hon. John Cradlebaugh is now holding court, and eight additional companies of infantry, one of artillery, and one of cavalry, under the command of Major Paul, are stationed within sight of the Court House ; and,
Whereas, the presence of soldiers has a tendency, not only to terrify the inhabitants and disturb the peace of the Territory, but also to subvert the ends of justice, by causing the intimidation of witnesses and jurors; and,</p>

<p>Whereas, this movement of troops has been made without consultation with me, and, as I believe, is in opposition to both the letter and spirit of my instructions; and,</p>

<p>Whereas, Gen'l. <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, commander of the military department of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, has refused my request that he would issue the necessary orders for the removal of the above mentioned troops :</p>

<p>Now, therefore, I ALFRED CUMMING, Governor of the Territory of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, do hereby publish this my solemn protest against this present military movement, and also against all movements of troops incompatible with the letter and spirit of the annexed extract from the instructions received by me from government for my guidance while Governor of the Territory of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</p>

<p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and caused the seal of the
Territory to be affixed. Done at Great Salt Lake City, this
twenth-seventh day of March, A. D. eighteen hundred and fifty-
nine, and of the Independence of the United States the Eighty-
third.</p>

<p>JOHN HARTNETT,	By the Governor,</p>

<p>Secretary of State.	ALFRED CUMMING.</p>

<p>The following is the "extract" referred to in the foregoing proclamation :</p>

<p>It is your duty to take care that the laws are faithfully executed, and to maintain the peace and good order of the Territory, and also to support by your power and authority the civil officers in the performance of their duties. If these officers, when thus engaged, are forcibly opposed, or have just reason to expect opposition, they have a right to call such portions of the <hi rend="italic">posse comitatus</hi> to their aid as they may deem necessary. If circumstances should lead you to believe that the ordinary force at the disposal of such officers will be insufficient to overcome any resistance that may be reasonably anticipated, then you are authorized to call for such number of the troops as the occasion may require, who will act as a <hi rend="italic">posse comitatus</hi>, and while thus employed, they will be under the direction of the proper civil officer, <hi rend="italic">and act in conformity with the instructions you may give as the Chief Executive Magistrate of the Territory</hi>.</p>

<pb n="714" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.715"/>

<p>About the same time Judges <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName> and <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>&#8212;Judge Eckels seems to have been absent from the scene&#8212;addressed a joint letter to the United States Attorney-General in relation to the matter at issue. To the answer of that high functionary, which fully sustained Governor Cumming, and figuratively cuffed the ears of his opponents, reference will be made a little later.</p>

<p>Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, without waiting for the grand jury to present the indictments that he desired, and doubtless despairing of their intention so to do, began issuing bench warrants for the apprehension of certain persons suspected of complicity in the Springville murders. These warrants were served by the U. S. Marshal, accompanied by a squad of soldiers. Several men were arrested, among them some Mormon witnesses subpoenaed by the grand jury, and handed over to the keeping of the military. There were also a number of Indians and a few Gentiles in custody.</p>

<p>After waiting in vain two weeks for the grand jury to gratify him, Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> became angry, and summoning the members of that body before him, he discharged them, at the same time dismissing the prisoners then in custody and closing his court. He entered upon the docket these words: "The whole community presents a united and organized opposition to the administration of justice." In his final address to the grand jury, His Honor wrathfully said:</p>

<p>If it is expected that this court is to be used by this community as a means of protecting it against the pecadillos of Gentiles and Indians; unless this community will punish its own murderers, such expectation will not be realized. It will be used for no such purpose.</p>

<p>When this people come to their reason and manifest a disposition to punish their own high offenders, it will then be time to enforce the law also for their protection. If this court cannot bring you to a proper sense of your duty, it can at least turn the savages in custody loose upon you.</p>

<p>In summing up the evidence in the Springville cases, the Judge had thus expressed himself:</p>

<p>Men are murdered here.	Coolly, deliberately, premeditatedly murdered&#8212;their
murder is deliberated and determined upon by Church council meetings and that, too, for

<pb n="715" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.716"/>

no other reason than that they had apostatized from your Church and were striving to leave the Territory. You are the tools, the dupes, the instruments of a tyrannical Church despotism. The heads of your Church order and direct you. You are taught to obey their orders and commit these horrid murders. Deprived of your liberty, you have lost your manhood, and become the willing instruments of bad men.</p>

<p>The grand jury framed a reply, remonstrating against these insults and protesting against their untimely and dishonorable discharge. They stated that they were surrounded during their deliberations by a detachment of the army, and that army officers were quartered within hearing of the evidence of witnesses who were being examined in the jury-room; that they presented indictments for offenses against the laws of the United States, which indictments had been treated with contempt and the prisoners indicted liberated without trial; that witnesses subpoenaed by the grand jury had been treacherously arrested and the jury deprived of their evidence; but that notwithstanding they were thus trammeled by the court, they had honored their oath and were endeavoring to faithfully discharge their duties when they were dismissed by His Honor with a slanderous and insulting harangue.<ref target="n16">*</ref></p>

<p>Soon after the closing of the court, the troops investing Provo were withdrawn. And so ended Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>'s vain attempt&#8212;could it be otherwise than vain ?to saddle upon the Mormon Church, upon an entire community, crimes committed by a few individuals, for whose conduct that Church, that community, could not justly or reasonably be held responsible.</p>

<p>But the game was not yet played out. Another act of the drama remained; an act that came very near provoking a serious conflict, with General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> and the troops at Camp Floyd on one side, and Governor Cumming and the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> militia on the other.

<note xml:id="n16">* The members of the grand jury were : John Riggs (foreman), James Pace, William Meeks, Isaac Morley, Jr., Richard Sessions, D. D. McArthur, A. G. Conover, John Mercer, George W. Bean, Jesse McCauslin, John W. Turner, John Sessions, M. C. Kinsman, A. P. Dowdle, Martin H. Peck, James Smith, Lorenzo Johnson, William A. Follett, N. T. Guyman, John Harvey, Wilber J. Earl, Philander Colton and L. C. Zabriskie.</note>

<pb n="717" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.717"/>

A conspiracy had been concocted by the Federal officials for the arrest of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> on a charge of counterfeiting,&#8212;the trumped-up case mentioned previously. This attempt was made about the time that the troops were withdrawn from Provo. A young artist, an engraver, residing at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, had been employed by certain parties from Camp Floyd to duplicate a plate used by the Quarter-master of that post for notes drawn upon the assistant treasurers of the United States at St. Louis and New York. The artist, who was very clever, did his work well, but it is believed was not aware that he was committing a criminal act. This, however, did not suffice to shield him. The fraud being discovered, the principal, one Brewer, who had employed the engraver to make the plate, was arrested at Camp Floyd. He immediately turned states evidence, shifting the onus from his own shoulders to those of the artist, and also endeavoring to implicate President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> in the affair. The charge against the latter was absolutely groundless, but it suited the purpose of the conspirators, and was simply another attempt to make " some person high in authority" responsible for the misdeed of a comparatively obscure individual. A writ was issued for the arrest of the artist, and another for the apprehension of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>. The U. S. Marshal was to serve the writs, and if resisted, as it was fully expected he would be, General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s artillery was to make a breach in the wall surrounding the residence of the ex-Governor, who would be taken by force and carried to Camp Floyd.</p>

<p>Such was the program which certain officers from camp, entrusted with the service of the writs, laid before Governor Cumming, soliciting his co-operation in the matter. To the artist's apprehension, His Excellency offered no objection; in fact he helped to secure it; but to the arrest of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> on such a baseless charge he would not listen. Said the Governor to the officers: "When you have a right to take <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, gentle-men, you shall have him without creeping through walls, you shall enter by his door with heads erect, as becomes representatives of

<pb n="717" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.718"/>

your government. But till that time, gentlemen, you can't touch <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> while I live, by G&#8212;d."</p>

<p>Discomfited, the officers returned to Camp Floyd. It was now rumored that General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> would send two regiments and a battery of artillery to enforce the writ for the arrest of the Mormon leader. Governor Cumming promptly informed General Wells of this report, and directed him to hold the militia in readiness to repel the threatened assault. Five thousand men flew to arms in response to this order, and eagerly awaited the issue. But the regiments from Camp Floyd did not come. General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> had evidently changed his mind. Soon afterward the letter from the United States Attorney-General, in answer to Judges <persName key="Sinclair, Charles E.">Sinclair</persName> and <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> came to hand. That letter decided that the troops could be used as a posse to enforce the processes of the courts only upon the call of the Governor. The power of the judicial-military conspirators was thus broken. A few extracts from this letter of Judge Black's, which was dated May 17th, 1859, are here inserted. Said the great jurist to the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> judges:</p>

<p>The condition of things in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> made it extremely desirable that the judges appointed for that Territory should confine themselves strictly within their own official sphere. The Government had a district attorney, who was charged with the duties of a public accuser, and a marshal, who was responsible for the arrest and safe-keeping of criminals. For the judges there was nothing left except to hear patiently the cases brought before them, and to determine them impartially according to the evidence adduced on both sides.	*	*	*	*	*	*	*	*</p>

<p>The Governor is the supreme Executive of the Territory. He is responsible for the public peace. From the general law of the land, the nature of his office, and the instructions he received from the State department, it ought to have been understood that he alone had power to issue a requisition for the movement of troops from one part of the Territory to another,&#8212;that he alone could put the military forces of the Union and the people of the Territory into relations of general hostility with one another. The instructions given to the Commanding-General by the War Department are to the same effect. In that paper a "<hi rend="italic">requisition</hi>" is not spoken of as a thing which anybody except the Governor can make. It is true that in one clause the General is told that if the Governor, judges, or the marshal shall find it necessary to <hi rend="italic">summon directly</hi> a part of the troops to aid either in the performance of his duty, he (the General) is to see the <hi rend="italic">summons</hi> promptly obeyed. This was manifestly intended to furnish the means of repelling an opposition which might be too strong for civil posse, and too sudden to admit of a formal requisition of the

<pb n="718" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.719"/>

Governor upon the military commander. An officer finds himself resisted in the discharge of his duty, and he calls to his aid first the citizens, and, if they are not sufficient, the soldiers. This would be directly summoning a part of the troops. <hi rend="italic">A direct summons</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">requisition</hi> are not convertible terms.	*	*	*	*</p>

<p>In a Territory like <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, the person who exercises this last mentioned power can make war and peace when he pleases, and holds in his hands the issues of life and death for thousands. Surely it was not intended to cloth each one of the judges, as well as the marshal and all his deputies, with this tremendous authority. Especially does this construction seem erroneous when we reflect that these different officers might make requisitions conflicting with one another, and all of them crossing the path of the Governor.	*	*	*	*	*	*	*	*	*</p>

<p>On the whole the President is very decidedly of opinion&#8212;</p>

<p>1. That the Governor of the Territory alone has power to issue a requisition upon the commanding-general for the whole or part of the army ;</p>

<p>2. That there was no apparent occasion for the presence of the troops at Provo.</p>

<p>3. That if a rescue of the prisoners in custody had been attempted, it was the duty of the marshal, and not of the judge, to summon the force which might be necessary to prevent it ;</p>

<p>4. That the troops ought not to have been sent to Provo, without the concurrence of the Governor, nor kept there against his remonstrance;</p>

<p>5. That the disregard of these principles and rules of action has been in many ways extremely unfortunate.</p>

<p>A strong effort was now made by the anti-Mormons to have Governor Cumming removed, and another executive, more in harmony with their views and policies, appointed in his stead. To this end a mass meeting of Gentiles convened at Camp Floyd in the latter part of July. Among those present were the Federal Judges and Dr. Garland Hurt. An address was issued, accusing the Mormons of numerous crimes, declaring that they were still disloyal, and that President Buchanan had been deceived and had done a great wrong in withdrawing from the courts the protecting power of the military.</p>

<p>That same month these "disloyal Mormons" had celebrated, in response to the following order, the natal day of American liberty: </p>

<p><hi rend="center">SPECIAL ORDER NO. 2.</hi></p>


<p><hi rend="right">HEADQUARTERS NAUVOO LEGION,</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="right">Adjutant-General's Office, G. S. L. City, July 1st, 1859. </hi></p>

<p>Monday, the 4th, will be the eighty-third anniversary of the birth of American freedom. It is the duty of every American citizen to commemorate the great event ; not

<pb n="719" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.720"/>

in a boisterous revelry, but with hearts full of gratitude to Almighty God the Great Father of our rights.</p>

<p>The Lieutenant-General directs for the celebration in this city as follows :</p>

<p>1st.&#8212;At sunrise a salute of thirteen guns will be fired, commencing near the residence of His Excellency the Governor, to be answered from a point on South Temple Street, near the residence of President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>.</p>

<p>The national flag will be hoisted at the signal from the first gun, simultaneously at the residences of Governor Cumming and President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, at the office of the Territorial Secretary, and the residence of the United States Attorney. Captain Pitt's band will be stationed at sunrise opposite the residence of Governor Cumming, and Captain Ballo's band opposite the residence of President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>.</p>

<p>At the hoisting of the flags the bands will play the "Star Spangled Banner." </p>

<p>2nd.&#8212;After the morning salute the guns will be parked at the Court House till noon, when a salute of thirty-three guns will be fired.</p>

<p>3rd.&#8212;At sunset a salute of five guns, in honor of the Territories, will be fired and the flags lowered.</p>

<p>4th.&#8212;For the above service Lieutenant Atwood and two platoons of artillery will be detailed. Two six-pounder iron guns will be used for the salutes. Also a first lieutenant and two platoons of the 1st Cavalry will be detailed as a guard, and continue
on guard through the day. The whole detachment will be dismissed after the
sunset salute.</p>

<p>5th.&#8212;Col. J. C. Little, of the General's staff, will perform the duties of marshal of the day, with permission to select such deputies as he may require to assist him. The Declaration of Independence will be read by him from the steps of the Court House at noon.</p>

<p>6th.&#8212;The bands and the services to be performed by them will be under the direction of Col. Duzette.</p>

<p><hi rend="center">By order of</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="right">LIEUTENANT-GENERAL DANIEL H. WELLS,</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="right">ADJUTANT-GENERAL JAMES FERGUSON.</hi></p>

<p>Almost simultaneously with the effort put forth by local Gentiles for the removal of Governor Cumming, the friends of General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, at Washington, brought a strong pressure to bear upon President Buchanan for the same purpose. <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> at that time was quite an influential personage. His great military ability was recognized, and he was regarded as a very likely successor to the aged veteran, Winfield Scott, General-in-Chief of the United States Army. In fact, his friends at the capital were working to that end. To the influence exerted against Governor Cumming, who was looked upon as a foe to General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, and was indeed a very lion in his

<pb n="720" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.721"/>

path, President Buchanan would probably have yielded, had not that staunch friend of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, Colonel Thomas L. Kane, who also had great influence at the seat of government, and to whom the President felt particularly grateful for his recent services in the west, by a master-stroke of political strategy thwarted the scheme for the Governor's displacement.<ref target="n17">*</ref> Colonel Kane had been solicited by the Historical Society of New York City to deliver a lecture on <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> affairs, but had postponed the acceptance of the invitation. Hearing of the movement against Governor Cumming, and learning that President Buchanan had asked of a mutual friend how the proposed removal would be likely to affect Colonel Kane, the latter, being determined that Cumming, whom he regarded as a friend to the Territory, should be retained in office, saw that now was an opportune time to lecture in the metropolis on <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> affairs. Arrangements were forthwith concluded, and though suffering from an attack of pleurisy, the Colonel proceeded from Philadelphia to New York for that purpose. His effort was entirely successful. During the lecture he took particular pains to eulogize Governor Cumming for his wise and able administration, and declared him to be admirably fitted for the duties of his difficult and trying position. Next morning condensed reports of the lecture appeared in all the metropolitan newspapers and were scattered broad-cast over the country by the associated press. The result was that public opinion was turned completely in Cumming's favor, and President Buchanan, politic as ever, refused to remove him, and he was continued in office till the close of his term.</p>

<p>The advent of <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s army proved both a benefit and a detriment to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. The founding of Camp Floyd furnished a market for the products of farm, ranch and dairy, and the opportunity to

<note xml:id="n17">* President Buchanan in his message to Congress, December, 1858, says : " 1 cannot refrain from mentioning the valuable services of Colonel Thomas L. Kane, who, from motives of pure benevolence, and without any official character or pecuniary compensation, visited <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> during the last inclement winter for the purpose of contributing to the pacification of the Territory."</note>

<pb n="721" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.722"/>

profit by the presence of the troops was not lost sight of by the settlers in their vicinity. The merchants were naturally among the first to recognize and take advantage of the commercial chance thus afforded, and more than one contractor and middleman had good reason, from a worldly standpoint, to bless and not curse the coming of the army. In fact the community at large was greatly benefitted in a temporal way. Owing to the suspension of travel across the plains and the consequent breaking up of local business houses at the time of " the war," the people were destitute of many comforts which now, through trade with Camp Floyd, began to be re-supplied.<ref target="n18">*</ref> In exchange for flour, grain, beef, butter, eggs, poultry and dried fruits, the citizens obtained cash, clothing, tea, coffee, sugar and other necessaries. When Camp Floyd was evacuated, the government property, such as was not destroyed, was sold out at great sacrifice. Several <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> merchants there "made their start," and in a few years became very wealthy. Thus was the advent of the army of great material benefit to the Territory.</p>

<p>On the other hand evils were introduced into the community which, until then, it had never known. These, however, were more traceable to the crowds of camp-followersthose usual hangers-on to the skirts of an invading armythat came with the troops, than to the soldiers themselves. They were truly the off-scourings of civilization; thieves, gamblers and desperadoes of the worst type. Contact with such characters could not but have a debasing effect upon the morals of the people, especially the youth, some of whom became in time almost as bad and reckless as those whose evil examples they unhappily followed. Hitherto it had been the boast that <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> was almost entirely free from the vices which prevailed elsewhere. There was little if any drunkenness, no gambling, no

<note xml:id="n18">* During the troubles of 1857 the Mormon forces were instructed not to interfere with trains of merchandise belonging to Gentile or other business men in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, however, would not permit them to pass his lines, and detained them east of the Wasatch Mountains all winter. The result was a general breaking up of local merchants and consequent privations among the people.</note>

<pb n="722" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.723"/>

prostitution,&#8212;in short, none of the social evils which seem to be a concomitant of modern civilization, and are held by some sophists to be essential to the welfare of the communities they invariably corrupt and destroy. In those days it was said, and with perfect truth, that an unprotected woman might traverse the Territory from one end to another without being molested, without hearing an obscene word or witnessing an insulting gesture. But with the coming of the troops, or the camp-followers, this happy condition began to change, and before long it could with equal propriety be affirmed :</p>

<lg type="poem">

<l>Where rose aloft the voice of reverent prayer,</l>
<l>The horrid oath now rent the midnight air ;</l>
<l>O'er streets deserted ere the darkening night,</l> 
<l>The glare of sin sent forth its baleful light ;</l> 
<l>The grog-shop, held aloft from arm of law,</l> 
<l>Poured forth its poison with defiant maw ;</l>
<l>O'er walks where virtue long had wandered free,</l> 
<l>Staggered the drunkard, lurked the debauchee;</l>
<l>With watchful eye the gambler lay in wait</l>
<l>To lure his victim with a gilded bait,</l>
<l>While pimp and harlot ply their artful game</l>
<l>To drag our youth to dens of death and shame.<ref target="n19">*</ref></l>
</lg>

<p>Murders also became frequent. Now and then it was a peaceable and respectable citizen who fell a victim to the knife or bullet of the drunken desperado or midnight thief and assassin. Generally, however, it was the drunkards and desperadoes who slew each other, in which event "good riddance" was the common expression of public sentiment.</p>

<p>Among the homicides that occurred soon after the founding of Camp Floyd were the following: The shooting of Policeman <persName key="Cooke, William">William Cooke</persName>, in October, 1858, by a ruffian named McDonald, who succeeded in escaping; the killing of Sergeant <persName key="Pike, Ralph">Ralph Pike</persName> by <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Howard Spencer</persName>, in retaliation for an assault committed some time before. <persName key="Pike, Ralph">Pike</persName> had

<note xml:id="n19">* The Indians in the vicinity of Camp Floyd became very corrupt. Some of the tribes, notably the Goshutes and Sanpitches, through disease and drunkenness were almost destroyed.</note>

<pb n="723" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.724"/>

cracked <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Spencer</persName>'s skull with a musket, and brought him nigh to death's door. He barely recovered, but when he did, sought out his assailant and shot him dead. This tragedy occurred August 11th, 1859. <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Howard Spencer</persName> was a Mormon, and Sergeant <persName key="Pike, Ralph">Pike</persName> an officer from Camp Floyd. By many, <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Spencer</persName>, at the time of the shooting, was considered insane, made so by the terrible blow he had received from the Sergeant's musket. In fact this was the ground upon which he was acquitted when tried for murder many years later.<ref target="n20">*</ref> Another murder was that of Alexander Carpenter by Thomas H. Ferguson, which has already been mentioned. All three killings occurred at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. Another notable homicide that took place there about the same time was the shooting of Messrs. Brewer and Johnson. This twain were gamblers and desperadoes. They were shot, it is said, at the same instant, while walking home one night together. Who their slayer or slayers were was never known. Other murders occurred in various parts of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> during this time of terror.</p>

<p>An interesting event of the summer of 1859 was the visit to our Territory of Horace Greeley, founder and editor of the New York Tribune. The great journalist was on his way to the Pacific coast, having taken his own advice and "come west," not to "grow up with the country," but to see what growth the western country had attained. He reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> on Sunday evening, July 10th, by overland mail stage from the frontier. On the evening of Saturday, the 16th, a reception and supper were given in his honor,&#8212;the former at the Council House, the latter at the Globe Restaurant,&#8212;by the Deseret Typographical and Press Association. Speeches were made by Mr. Greeley and by Messrs. <persName key="Hyde, Orson">Orson Hyde</persName>, <persName key="Taylor, John">John Taylor</persName>, <persName key="Clements, Gilbert">Gilbert Clements</persName> and <persName key="Banks, John">John Banks</persName>. Ballo's brass band and Foster

<note xml:id="n20">*The assault upon <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Spencer</persName> by <persName key="Pike, Ralph">Pike</persName> occurred in Rush Valley, March 22, 1859. It was both brutal and unprovoked. <persName key="Pike, Ralph">Pike</persName>, attended by a military escort, had come to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> to answer before the District Court to an indictment for the assault, when <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Spencer</persName>, entirely alone, walked up to him on East Temple Street, inquired his name and shot him in the presence of three of his comrades. <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Spencer</persName> then fled, and though hotly pursued, escaped.</note>

<pb n="724" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.725"/>

and Olsen's serenade band discoursed delightful music on the occasion, and a poem composed by John Lyon, entitled "Welcome to Greeley," was read by James McKnight. Mr. Greeley's address to the printers occupied about half an hour. In his plain and peculiar style he referred to the progress the world had made during his recollection ; remarked how extraordinary had been the increase of facilities for the spread of knowledge through the press and by means of the electric telegraph, and stated that he looked forward to a day when still greater improvements would be made&#8212;when the daily newspaper, printed from continuous rolls, cut and folded by steam, would be thrown off ready for distribution at a rate far exceeding that of the rapid eight and ten cylinder presses then in use; and when the telegraph would connect, through one grand electric cur-rent, continent with continent and island with island, till every corner of the earth should be illumined with telegraphic communication. Of course Mr. Greeley, during his stay, did not omit calling on President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, with whom he had several long and interesting interviews.</p>

<p>In addition to the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>, the pioneer journal, <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> had at this time a paper called the <hi rend="italic">Valley Tan</hi>. It was the first Gentile print published in the Territory, and lent vigorous influence to the Federal Judges and General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> in their antagonism to the Mormon leaders and to Governor Cumming. The first number of the <hi rend="italic">Valley Tan</hi>&#8212;a four-page weekly&#8212;was published November 5th, 1858. It was edited by Kirk Anderson, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, though it originated at Camp Floyd. The next paper established was <hi rend="italic">The Mountaineer</hi>, which made its appearance on the 27th of August, 1859. Its editors and proprietors were James Ferguson, Seth M. Blair and Hosea Stout. It was an ably conducted journal and opposed the <hi rend="italic">Valley Tan</hi>.</p>

<p>On August 1st of this year recurred the biennial election of delegate to Congress. Dr. John M. Bernhisel had represented <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> in that capacity since the organization of the Territory. He now retired and Hon. William H. Hooper was chosen delegate.</p>

<pb n="725" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.726"/>

<p>The "Pony Express," to carry dispatches between the Missouri River and the Pacific coast, was inaugurated in the spring of 1860. The first express from the west reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> on the 7th of April, having left Sacramento on the night of the 3rd. The first from the east, which left St. Joseph, Missouri, on the evening of April 3rd, arrived here on the evening of the 9th. This brought <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> within six days' communication with the frontier, and within seven days of the nation's capital; a result which our citizens, who were then accustomed to receiving news three months after date, duly appreciated. Said the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>: "Although a telegraph is very desirable, we feel well satisfied with this achievement for the present."</p>

<p>The first dispatches dropped by the Pony Express at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> contained the news of the intended introduction in the United States Senate of "a bill amendatory of the act organizing the Territory of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>." This bill, it was said, proposed that the seat of government be removed from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> to Carson Valley, and that the name of the Territory be changed from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> to Nevada. According to the Washington correspondent of the St. Louis <hi rend="italic">Republican</hi>, the Committee on Territories, who were expected to report the bill, hoped by this policy to pass the political power of the Territory from Salt Lake to Carson Valley&#8212;from the hands of the Mormons to those of the Gentiles. The removal of the seat of government to Carson Valley, in connection with the rich mines lately discovered there, it was thought would attract a large Gentile population to that locality. This, however, was the last that was heard of the bill for an act to obliterate <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</p>

<p>Other news of a still more stirring nature was brought by the Pony Express. The air was now filled with rumors of war. Events in the east had been hastening to a crisis; the plot for secession had ripened and borne fruit, and the great internecine struggle that was to temporarily split the nation and shake the whole earth with its thunder, was just about to begin. The direct result upon <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> of the opening of the conflict was the withdrawal of the Federal troops from the Territory.</p>

<pb n="726" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.727"/>

<p>As early as March, 1860, General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> had left Camp Floyd for Washington, D. C. He had never visited <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> since passing through it with the army in June, 1858. Consequently he and <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> never met. After his departure, Colonel Philip St. George Cooke became the post commander. By his order, early in February, 1861, Camp Floyd changed its name to Fort Crittenden. Secretary Floyd, for whom the post was originally named, had fallen from his allegiance and was now considered a traitor to his country. In May, 1860, most of the troops at Camp Floyd had left, pursuant to orders, for Arizona and New Mexico, and in July, 1861, the residue took up their march for the east, to participate in the war for the Union.</p>

<p>Prior to the abandonment of Camp Floyd vast stores of provisions and army supplies of all kinds were offered for sale by the military authorities and purchased by local merchants and other citizens. The sacrifice in price was enormous, and many far-sighted buyers made their fortunes. It is estimated that four million dollars worth of goods were disposed of for $100,000. This did not include arms and ammunition, great quantites of which, instead of being transported back to the States, were destroyed. Among the heaviest purchasers was President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, whose agent and business manager, Colonel <persName key="Clawson, H. B.">H. B. Clawson</persName>, visited the Fort for that purpose. Walker Brothers also bought extensively, as did other <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> merchants.</p>

<p>Some of the more prominent officers accepted an invitation from Colonel Clawson, who was President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s son-in-law, to visit the ex-Governor prior to their departure from the Territory. Among those who paid their respects to the Mormon leader were Colonel Cooke, Colonel Alexander, Captain Marcy and Quartermaster Crossman. All were very pleasant, the animosities of the past evidently having evaporated. These officers presented to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> the flag-staff from which the stars and stripes had floated over Camp Floyd. This interesting relic stood for many years on the brow of the hill near the White House, the President's early <choice><orig>resi-

<pb n="727" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1892.728"/>

dence</orig><reg>residence</reg></choice>, where it continued to bear aloft the national banner. Whatever General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName> had thought, it is evident that Colonel Cooke and his brother officers did not, at this time, deem the Mormons disloyal. The presentation of such a gift at such a time speaks volumes to the contrary. And what of General <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>, who had denounced the Saints as "rebels?" Himself a rebel now, wearing the grey instead of the blue, commanding a Confederate in lieu of a Union army, his star of life, with the star of his glory, was soon to set in a sea of blood on the fatal field of Shiloh.</p>

-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>