<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.nyt.18600807">
    <teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
	    <titleStmt>
		<title level="m" type="main">Affairs in Utah</title>
		<title level="m" type="sub">The New Judges&#8212;The Mountain Meadows Massacre></title>
		<author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
		<idno>mmm.news.nyt.18600807</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

	   <notesStmt>
		<note type="summary"></note>
	   </notesStmt>

	   <sourceDesc>
		<bibl>
		    <title level="j">New York Times</title>
		    <title level="a" type="main">Affairs in Utah</title>
		    <title level="a" type="sub">The New Judges&#8212;The Mountain Meadows Massacre</title>
		    <author></author>
		    <publisher></publisher>
		    <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		    <date when="1860-08-07">August 7, 1860</date>
		</bibl>
	    </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
	<textClass>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
	        <term>newspaper</term>
	    </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
		<term>^%culpability%</term>
	    </keywords>
	    <keywords scheme="original" n="sympathy">
		<term>^%sympathy%</term>
	    </keywords>
	</textClass>
   </profileDesc>

   <revisionDesc>
  	<change when="2011-08-02"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept Highlighting and Encoding Enrichment</change>
  	<change when="2011-07-26"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Validation</change>
  	<change when="2009-10-01"><name>Kelsey F. Harris</name> Initial Encoding</change>
	<change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>


<body>

<div1 type="newspaper">
    
    <pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.nyt.18600807.001"/>

<head type="main">AFFAIRS IN UTAH.</head>

<head type="sub">The New Judges&#8212;The Mountain Meadows Massacre&#8212;Merine Sheep&#8212;The Crops&#8212;
  Brigham Young.</head>

<head>From Our Own Correspondent.</head>

<dateline>Great Salt Lake City, Friday, July 13, 1860.</dateline>

<p>The last express brought news of the appointment 
of Judge <persName key="Kinney, John F.">KINNEY</persName> as Chief Justice of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>,
and of <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">ALEXANDER WILSON</persName> as Associate Justice. Of
course, the majority of the community here would
vastly prefer to have their Judges, and indeed all
their public officers, chosen from the inhabitants of
<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, and a little rather from the Mormon
portion thereof. As there seems, however, no chance
of such an arrangement, the next wish is that persons 
may be appointed who have no Anti-Mormon-
prejudices, but who evince a disposition to pursue a
conciliatory course, and do not manifest any particular
desire to get <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName>, or other high Mormon dignitaries 
into trouble. Consequently, the appointment of
<persName key="Kinney, John F.">KINNEY</persName> and <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">WILSON</persName> is looked on with satisfaction,
and as an evidence that the Administration, having
tried force with the Mormons and virtually failed, is
now fully determined to try what can be done by
purely civil means. The antecedents of both these
men are of such a nature that the Mormons think
there will be some chance of fair trials and an impartial 
administration of the law, which none of the
Mormons imagine was possible under the regime of
<persName key="Eckels, Delana R.">ECKLES</persName>, <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">CRADLEBAUGH</persName> and <persName key="Sinclair, Charles">SINCLAIR</persName>. People in the
States, perhaps, cannot fully realize the utter detestation 
and contempt in which the two Judges first
named are held by the majority of the <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> population.</p>

 <p>I believe that both Judge <persName key="Kinney, John F.">KINNEY</persName> and <persName key="Wilson, Alexander">WILSON</persName> are
firm in their conviction that they can hold United
States Courts in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this Territory</placeName> without calling bayonets 
to their aid ; that a tolerable degree of justice
can be meted out to Jew and Gentile by United
States Judges of the proper stamp ; and that the Mormons, 
like a <placeName type="state" key="California Territory">California</placeName> horse which is utterly intractable 
in certain hands, can actually be made something
of by men who know how to handle them to advantage. 
Whether or not these convictions are well
founded, time must prove. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation"><seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">It has been currently reported
in this city that the Mormon President
and other high dignitaries have frequently expressed
their wishes for, and offered to exert their influence
to effect, a thorough and impartial judicial investigation 
of the Mountain Meadows massacre, when an
unbiased Court can be held. If this is the case the
appointments referred to may produce good. Certain 
it is, that that fearful tragedy should be inquired
into, and the responsibility thereof placed upon the
right shoulders.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The last Eastern mail arrived on Wednesday night,
about ten and a half days from <placeName type="settlement" key="St. Joseph's, MO">St. Joseph</placeName>'s, nearly
four days within its usual time. The <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> mail,
which is a week over due, has not yet come to hand.
Nothing is known here of the condition of affairs near
<geogName type="valley" key="Canon Valley">Canon Valley</geogName>, as the express from the West starts
from <geogName type="valley" key="Ruby Valley">Ruby Valley</geogName>. The last express that came through
from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> accompanied the mail from <geogName type="valley" key="Carson Valley">Carson
Valley</geogName> to <geogName type="valley" key="Ruby Valley">Ruby Valley</geogName>. As the sixty troops from <orgName type="military" key="Camp Floyd">Camp
Floyd</orgName>, or a portion of them, went West some time
ago with the mail, it is supposed that the mail is
either coming this way slowly, escorted by the soldiers, 
or that the troubles with the Indians between
<geogName type="valley" key="Ruby Valley">Ruby</geogName> and <geogName type="valley" key="Carson Valley">Carson</geogName> still maintain a serious aspect. The
Indians immediately around <geogName type="valley" key="Ruby Valley">Ruby</geogName> are still very hostile 
and exhibit no disposition to make peace.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The Mormon newspapers have been very sarcastic
regarding the sending of Col. <persName key="Howe, Charles W.">HOWE</persName> with two hundred 
dragoons to <orgName type="military" key="Fort Hall">Fort Hall</orgName>, where there is no war,
no mail and little emigration, and at the same time
sending but sixty infantry on the central route, where
there is a mail, an express, and where serious difficulties 
with the Indians call for settlement.</seg></p>

<p>Emigrants for <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> are continually passing
through our city. Some go by the northern route,
and some by the central. Among the emigrants who
lately passed here was Mr. <persName key="McCommons">McCOMMONS</persName>, of <placeName type="state" key="Wisconsin">Wisconsin</placeName>, 
with, about three acore Merino sheep, which he
was conveying in Wagons to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>. As some
of his horses were worn down, he found himself compelled 
to exchange a few of his sheep in this city for
fresh horses. About a dozen, mostly bucks, were
bought at from $125 to $150 each ; lambs dropped on
the plains brought $50 each. When one of the bucks
was shorn his fleece weighed fourteen pounds. Fleeces
of ordinary sheep in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this Territory</placeName> weigh three or
four pounds each. The Merino bucks were bought to
cross with the common breed.</p>

<p><persName key="San Pitch">SAN PITCH</persName>, an lndian chief, with about a hundred
followers, made his appearance at <placeName type="settlement" key="Brigham City, UT">Brigham City</placeName> on
the 29th ult., and said that Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">FORNEY</persName> had sent to
him to come there aim receive presents. When told
that no presents had been deposited there, <persName key="San Pitch">SAN PITCH</persName>
became sulky, and went off. This is not the first
time <persName key="Forney, Jacob">FORNEY</persName> has been charged with forgetting his
promises, either to the red or the white man.</p>

<p>It is stated that Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">FORNEY</persName> and Sub-Agent ROGERS
recently found themselves passengers us the same
mail-coach for the States, and that the Doctor got out
at Bridger, and preferred staying another week to going 
to the States in the same vehicle with <persName key="Rogers, William">ROGERS</persName>
The reasons for their conduct are not given, out may
be inferred.</p>

<p>Late papers tell us of a great drouth in the Western
States. It is remarkable that in this valley the present 
season we have had more frequent rains than
usual. Just at present we are in the midst of the hay
harvest. Rye and barley are being cut, and early
wheat is about ready. In <placeName type="county" key="Utah County, UT">Utah County</placeName> I am told
teat the crops are excellent.</p>

<p>Speculators are busy calculating the chances of
supplying <placeName type="county" key="Carson County, UT">Carson</placeName> with bread from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>. Cash,
it is expected, will soon buy wheat for about a dollar
pet bushel, flour tor $3 50 per hundred. The cost of
freight to <placeName type="county" key="Carson County, UT">Carson</placeName> is reckoned at nine or ten cents per
pound, which, it is thought, will enable <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>
merchants to sell at <placeName type="county" key="Carson County, UT">Carson</placeName> as cheaply as <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>
merchants can afford to.</p>

<p>On Sunday <persName key="Young, Brigham">BRIGHAM</persName> preached twice in the Bowery.
A fair sprinkling of emigrants attended. In the
morning the drift of his discourse was that Jesus
Christ was but a man, though he was, perhaps, a trifle
better than most of us. In the afternoon he told the
people they could not make any sacrifices. He said
that the word was anomalous, and but another mode
of expressing the act of <q>"rendering to God the things
that are God's."</q></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>