<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.ct.18730518">
    <teiHeader>
	<fileDesc>
	    <titleStmt>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mountain-Life</title>
		<title level="m" type="sub"></title>
		<author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
	        <idno>mmm.news.ct.18730518</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

	    <notesStmt>
		<note type="summary"></note>
	    </notesStmt>

	    <sourceDesc>
		<bibl>
		    <title level="j">Chicago Tribune</title>
		    <title level="a" type="main">Mountain-Life</title>
	            <author></author>
		    <publisher></publisher>
		    <pubPlace>Chicago, IL</pubPlace>
		    <date when="1873-05-18">May 18, 1873</date>
		</bibl>
	    </sourceDesc>

	</fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

	<profileDesc>
	    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>newspaper</term>
		</keywords>
		<keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
		    <term></term>
		</keywords>
		<keywords scheme="original" n="action">
		    <term></term>
		</keywords>
	    </textClass>
	</profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
	<change when="2011-07-28"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name>Encoding Enhancement and Concept Highlighting</change>
	<change when="2010-04-27"><name>Kelsey F. Harris</name>Initial Encoding</change>
	<change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name>Model Encoding</change>
    </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text>


<body>

<div1 type="newspaper">

    <pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.ct.18730518.001"/>

<head>MOUNTAIN-LIFE.</head>

<head type="sub">Mirage&#8212;Luggernal Alley&#8212;Brown's Hole&#8212;Material Prosperity.<lb/>

<milestone unit="section" rend="horbar"/>

Trout-Fishing&#8212;Indian Fight at Pierre's Hole&#8212;And Indian Fort.<lb/>

<milestone unit="section" rend="horbar"/>

Uncle Jack Robinson&#8212;Col. O'Hara&#8212;Young Indian Braves and Squaws.<lb/>

<milestone unit="section" rend="horbar"/>

Utes Informed of Modoc Battles by Mormons&#8212;New Breed of Coach-Dogs.</head>

<head>From our Correspondent.</head>

<dateline>SMITH'S FORK, Wyo. Tex., May 13, 1873.</dateline>

<p>While out on the plateau to-day, I could not
help being stuck with the appearance of</p>
</div1>
<div1>
  <head type="sub">THE MIRAGE</head>

<p>which spread over the whole plain near the base
of the hills.  It was as if an immense lake
stretched out between the point where I was
and the black hills beyond, showing the shadows
below of rock and ravine; and, had I not
known the whole to be a desert-waste, with no
water near, I could have almost sworn that I was
near the sea-shore.  Even the sails of vessels
appeared at different points, and an immense
stone bridge seemed to span one of the narrowest 
places.  What a wonderful illusion this is,
and how many men have been led on by
it to certain destruction!  When weary,
thirsty, and worn out, a beautiful lake
has appeared in the distance, and the
coveted water could be seen sparkling in the 
sun's rays.  It seemed to the famishing traveler
to be near at hand, and a few minutes' brisk
traveling would bring him to it.  But, as he approached,
the seeming water receded, and always 
kept way off beyond his reach.  Instead of 
getting nearer the precious fluid, he was going 
father and farther out on the burning plains,
until at last, utterly worn out, he has laid himself
down and died from thirst, which is said to
be the most terrible of all deaths.  The mirage is
caused by heated air which lies near the surface
of the ground, and which seems to have the
power of reflecting the ray of the sun.  Some of 
these illusions are wonderfully beautiful, and
render the sterile plains as gorgeous in appearance
as the most splendid dreams of enchantment.</p>

  <p>Some time ago, while traveling, I met a lady
who inquired of me if I had ever been in.</p>

</div1>
  <div1>
  <head type="sub">LUGGERNAL ALLEY.</head>

<p>which is described in Theodore Winthrop's book
called <q>"John Brent,"</q> and which is supposed to 
be somewhere in the <geogName type="mountain" key="Rocky Mountains">Rocky Mountains</geogName>.  From
the description, I imagine Winthrop wished to
locate it in the <geogName type="mountain" key="Uinta Mountains">Uintah Range</geogName>,&#8212;for, being, as he
supposes himself, at <orgName type="military" key="Fort Bridger">Fort Bridger</orgName>, he says:</p>

  <q><p>"How far is Luggernal Alley from Fort
Bridger?"</p></q>

  <p><q>"Fifty miles or so to the south and east.  I
almost fancy I recognize it in the slight notch in
the line of the blue sierra on the horizon."</q></p>

  <p>This would carry it directly into the range of
Uintahs.  But what Winthrop was trying to
describe was undoubtedly </p>

</div1>
<div1>     
<head type="sub">BROWN'S HOLE,</head>

<p>which is 100 miles south of cast from <orgName type="military" key="Fort Bridger">Fort
Bridger</orgName>, and is indeed a remarkable place.  Wonderful
stories are told of the strange things to
be seen in this locality, and it is a favorite 
wintering-place for men who own herds of horses 
and cattle; <geogName type="waterway" key="Green River">Green River</geogName> running through its
whole extent, and it being shut in by high,
rocky walls, which shield it from the winter
storms and keep off the cold.  Here is what
Winthrop says of it: <q>“A pavement of slippery,
sheeny rock; great beds of loose 
stones; barricades of mighty boulders,
where a cliff had fallen an <unclear></unclear>
ago, before the days of the road-maker race;
crevices where an unwary foot might catch;
wide rifts where a shaky horse might fall, or a
timid horseman drag him down.  The blue sky
was overhead, the red sun upon the castellated 
walls a thousand feet above us, the purpling 
<unclear> </unclear>opened before.  An arroyo, the channel 
of a dry torrent, followed the pass.  It has
made its way as water does, not straightway,
but by that potent feminine method of passing
under the frowning front of an obstacle, and
leaving the dull rock staring there, while the 
wild creature it would have held is gliding away
down the valley."</q></p>

<p>I imagine Brown's Hole would be somewhat at
a loss to discover its own identity were this description 
read to it; but novel-writers must be 
allowed some latitude, and plenty has been taken
in this instance.  However, this hole is a mighty 
gorge, and the dividing land between two 
streams in it, though but a few feet wide, rises
steep and abrupt for nearly a thousand feet.</p>

<p>All through the mountain-region there seems
to be a steady advancement in the way of material
prosperity, and the</p>

</div1>
<div1>
<head type="sub">WAVE OF IMMIGRANTS</head>

<p>is gradually reaching out toward the high
grounds.  Ten years ago, no one dreamed of the
number of people who now occupy the new
Territories, and then years hence this number
may be more than doubled.  Great herds of 
cattle and sheep occupy the ground which was
once used by the buffalo and sheep, and every
twelvemonth their number is very considerably
increased.  There is one fact connected with</p>
</div1>
<div1>
<head type="sub">THE MOUTAIN-GRASSES</head>

<p>which I never knew until a few days ago.  It is
this: The grasses do not die down, as they do
in the Eastern States; but the sap runs down in 
autumn, as it does in a tree and leaves the stalk 
dry and sere.  This is excellent grazing during 
the winter-months, and, as spring approaches,
the sap runs up; and the grass again becomes 
green and handsome.</p>

<p>It is now the season for</p>
</div1>
<div1>
<head type="sub">TROUT-FISHING</head>

<p>and for a lazy man, or more property a man who
is fond of his ease, I know of nothing more
pleasant than his spot.  The smell of the willows
and sage-brush, the faint odor of the smoke 
from the Indian cannies, or wigwams, near the
stream, lull senses, and everything appears 
peaceful.  The read-throated robins, the yellow-
breasted meadow-larks, the flat-headed ducks,
and the reddish-brown-plumaged falcon-hawks
are enjoying themselves in bush and tree, and
all seem gladdened by the merry rippling of the
bright stream, as it dances along over the pebbles
by the velvet greensward.  Stretched at full
length of the grass, with the fly from one's fishing-
line daintily moving down the wrinkled 
waters, with here and there the black back of a 
trout visible way down in the dark depths&#8212;
can anything be more charming than this?  I 
fancy not; and all the wines of France or dugs
of India never threw so fairly a mantle over the
soil.  Wild rose-bushes rise on every hand, fresh
from their winter’s sleep, and almost ready to
adorn themselves with all their matchless loveliness.
Earth has no pleasure equal to trout-fishing
in the atmosphere which is perfumed
with rose-leaves!  Ha! here comes Oliver, and
I&#8212;land a two-pound trout neatly on the green!</p>

<p>After accomplishing this feat, I stroll off, and 
soon come to the lodge of an old trapper, and
he tells me about the</p>

    </div1>
    <div1>
<head type="sub">BATTLE OF PIERRE'S HOLE.</head>

<p>which was fought on Pierre's Creek, a branch of
Snake River, on the 17th of July, 1882.  In its
details it is not unlike the fights which have 
lately taken place against the Modocs.  It appears
that a party belonging to the Rocky Mountain
Fur Company was quietly wending its way
through the valley which is known as Pierre's
Hole, when they suddenly discovered a party of
Indians coming down the mountain-side, who
proved to be Blackfeet.  A parley ensued, when a
half-breed, belonging to the Fur Company, shot
a Blackfoot warrior dead in his tracks, or, rather,
and Indian did so at his bidding.  The Blackfeet
immediately retreated to a swamp, where, near
a beaver dam, they constructed a rude fortress.
The white men, sent to their friends, who were
in the lower part of the valley, and soon a considerable 
force of trappers, hunters, and friendly
Indians was gathered under the leadership of
Capt. William Sublette, Robert Campbell, and
Mr. Sinclair.  They advanced toward the position
of the Indians, which was in
a dense thicket of cottonwood trees and bushes.
In crawling in on their hands and knees, Capt.
Sublette was in the shoulder, and Mr. Sinclair 
was shot through the body.  The trappers,
however, closed in promptly, and soon the
Blackfoot fort was completely surrounded.  The
fighting continued all day, and at might the Indians
retreated, leaving their dead behind them,
and a large amount of peltries, blankets, and<cb n="2" />
savage finery, which was of great value to the
captors.  Ten Blackfeet were found dead in the
fort, and the survivors afterwards admitted
that they had lost twenty-six warriors
in the battle.  Five white men, seven friendly
Indians, and one half-breed were killed, and
about twenty wounded.  The Indians who assisted
the whites on this occasion were the <unclear></unclear>
Perces, who have always been friendly, and a
small party of Flatheads.</p>

<p>This was the great battle of the mountain-
region, and it became famous.  For years afterward, 
men recounted their prowess on this occasion
with the greatest zest, and all who participated
were looked upon as heroes.  It was indeed
almost creditable affair to the whites, and had a 
salutary effect upon the red-skins.  The Blackfeet
became more better than ever in their
hatred toward the whites, which bitterness they
retain, it would seem, in all its intensity to the
present day.  The man who gave me these facts
participated in the battle, and his name is</p>
    </div1>
  <div1>

<head type="sub">JOHN ROBERTSON.&#8212;</head>

<p>familiarly known as Uncle Jack Robertson,&#8212;one
of the oldest mountaineers now living, and esteemed
far and wide as an honorable and kind-
hearted man.  Jack has <q>"had a heap of rough
times,"</q> and, according to Walpolistia, it may be
said of him <q>"that he has as many lives as a
cat,&#8212;nay, even as many as one Plutarch is said 
to have had."</q></p>

<p>Jack owns a herd of cattle, and his lodge is
always open to the people of the frontier, who
avail themselves of his hospitality, and eat up
what he has.  Still, this does not interfere with 
his equanimity, and he enjoys himself as well as
if he were the verlest nabob in the land.  So
far as I know, he is the only one
living who belonged to Gen. Ashley's
party of trappers, who came to this region over
forty years ago.  Many anecdotes are told of
him, and he enters into the spirit of all games
and parties with as much zest as he did forty
years ago.  Last winter he attended the balls
given by the mountaineers, and danced as merrily
as the best of them.  The old man is a great 
favorite wherever he goes, as he is ever ready
to do a kindness for any one; and the aid he
rendered the California immigrants, years ago,
will always reflect credit upon his name.  When 
their teams were broken down, he supplied
animals of his own, and helped them along for
days and days, and would not receive any pay 
for his services.</p>

<p>Lately I came across some lines written by
my old friend.</p>
</div1>
    <div1>
<head type="sub">THEODORE O'HARA.</head>

<p>upon the occasion of the removal of the remains 
of the Kentucky volunteers who fell at Buena
Vista, from the soil of Mexico to the cemetery 
at Frankfort, where, on a high bluff overlooking 
the Kentucky River, their ashes are enshrined 
beneath marble monuments shaped like tents. 
This poem is unquestionably one of the finest 
ever written in the English language.  It commences 
with these lines:</p>

<lg type="poem">

   <l>The muffled drum's sad roll has best</l>
    <l>The soldier's last tattoo;</l>
   <l>No more of Life's parade shall meet</l>
    <l>The brave and fallen few.</l>
   <l>On Fame's eternal camping-ground</l>
    <l>Their silent tents are spread,</l>
   <l>And Glory guards, with solemn round,</l>
    <l>The bivouac of the dead.</l></lg>

<p>Col. O'Hara belonged first to the Kentucky
volunteers; was afterwards an Assistant-Quartermaster,
with the rank of captain; and was
made a brevet Major for gallant and meritorious
conduct in the battles of Contreras and Churubusco,
in Mexico.  He served until the close of
the war, when he returned to civil life, and afterwards
took part in the invasion of Cuba by Opez,
and was severely wounded at Cardenas, in 1851.
In March, 1855, he became a Captain in the 
Second Regiment of United States Cavalry,
and served as such until Dec. 1, 1856,
when resigned, being at that time in
Texas, doing duty on the frontier.  Subsequently 
he edited the Mobile register, and when
the Rebellion broke out, joined the Confederate 
cause, where he gained the rank of Colonel.
The last time I was near him was at the siege of 
Atlanta, GA., while he was serving under the
Confederate flag, and I following the glorious
old stars and stripes.  Col. O'Hara died in Barbour
County, Ala, on the 7th of June, 1867.  He
was a man of ardent temperament, true and
kind to his friends, and possessed of decided 
talents.  He was wayward, and could not brook
the control so necessary in military discipline; 
but, with all this, was a gallant gentleman
and a brave soldier.  At evening, after a long
day's march, no man could be more companionable
and pleasant than he, as he had a fund of
anecdote at his command, which was always
ready to be drawn upon for the benefit of his
friends.  It is not too much to say that he was
one of the finest writers the South has produced.</p>

<p>The weather in the mountains does not appear 
to get settled; as it is in the East, so it is
here,&#8212;threatening all the time, with occasional 
gusts of wind and flurries of snow.</p>
</div1>
      <div1>
<head type="sub">THE INDIANS</head>

<p>are appearing in the forests some distance from
their reservations, but peacefully inclined, as
far as known, though all of them seem well informed 
in regard to the sad tragedies which have
been enacted in the California Lava-Beds.  The 
young men would like to go to war, in order to
show their prowess;&#8212;for, like all young men,
they think a great deal of themselves,
and are anxious to bring home something
which will make them look like heroes
in the eyes of the young squaws.  
The young Indian women say to their sweethearts, 
<q>"How can I know anything about your
bravery, and skill in a hunter?  You have 
brought in no scalps of horses, and the number
of elk and deer killed by you amounts to
nothing.  In case I marry you, how are you to
support me? I am willing to do my share; but
I wish to wed a warrior who has made a name
for himself, and one who occupies an honorable
place among the great men of the nation."</q></p>

<p>Here then is the</p>

        </div1>
        <div1>
<head type="sub">REASON FOR MANY A RAID</head>

<p>against the whites, or the red neighbors of the
Indians:  It is, that the young men may occupy
an honorable place in the councils of the nation,
and prove to the female portion of the community
that they, too, have scalped a foeman.
It matters very little to whom the scalp belonged,
whether to an old or young man or woman,
or to a helpless infant, for every scalp 
counts.  No Indian can be considered a warrior
until he can show a scalp taken by himself.</p>

<p>I learn from the Agent of the Uintah Utes
that</p>
</div1>
          <div1>
<head type="sub">THE MORMONS WERE DETERMINED</head>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">these Indians should not remain in ignorance of
what was going on in the <placeName type="county" key="Modoc County, California">Modoc country</placeName>, and
one of the Mormon Bishops wrote a letter to one
of the Indian Chiefs, giving an account of what
had occurred in the Lava-Beds.  This is a strange
proceeding, and it is difficult to account 
for it.  Did this white man intend
to make the <orgName type="tribe" key="Ute">Utes</orgName> dissatisfied, or
was it merely the work of an idle
brain?  It would hardly be fair to suppose this
Mormon Bishop wishes to incite the Utes to
massacre the people of the settlements along
the line of the <orgName type="railroad" key="Pacific Railroad">Pacific Railroad</orgName>; but what was 
his object, if this was not it?  <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">We know the
Mormons were guilty of the Mountain Meadow
massacre</seg>,&#8212;one of the most cold-blooded that
ever occurred in our country; and, if they could
do this, are they any too good to endeavor to kill
off the inhabitants of our infant settlements?</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The disguise of white men as Indians</seg> reminds 
me of a story told of a livery-stable-keeper in
<placeName type="settlement" key="Omaha, NE">Omaha</placeName> who owned a fine lot of</p>

</div1>
<div1>

<head type="sub">COACH-DOGS</head>

<p>These dogs are white with black spots all over
them, and are noted for their docile, not to say
cowardly, dispositions.  The dogs belonging to 
the livery-stable-keeper were beset on all occasions
by the other dogs in the streets, and, as
they were meek in spirit, were as
easily overcome as a lot of sheep.
The livery-stable-man stood this as long as he
could, when, one day, he found a large white
bull-dog, and it immediately occurred to him
what to do.  He brought that dog, took him to 
his stable, and there kept him until he got
thoroughly acquainted with the coach-dogs.
The bull-dog was then sent to the barber's shop,
and black spots were neatly printed or dyed
all over him, so that he looked like a 
veritable coach-dog, with a somewhat
short nose and elongated lower jaw.  The next
time the carriage was sent out, this model coach-dog
went along, and the street dogs "went for
him," thinking they would have their usual sport
and victory; but in this they were mistaken;
the bull-dog waded in, and the way the hair,
guitar-strings, and sausage-meat flew was a caution. 
Since that time, the coach-dogs have 
been let alone.</p><closer><signed>ALGEBRA.</signed></closer>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>