<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The City of the Saints</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                <author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.wa.burton.1862</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m">The City of the Saints</title>
                    <author><forename>Richard</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Burton</surname></author>
                    <publisher>Harper &amp; Brothers</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
                    <extent>322-343</extent>
                    <date when="1862">1862</date>
		    <note type="source">Richard F. Burton. <hi rend="italic">The City of the Saints</hi>. New York, NY: Harper &amp; Brothers, 1862. 322-43.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>western_americana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-02-10"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2009"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
<text>
<body>

<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="322" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.322"/>

<!--

<figure xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.322.figure">
<p>THE DEAD SEA.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

-->

<head>CHAPTER VII.</head>

<p><hi rend="center">Third Week at Great Salt Lake City.&#8212;Excursions.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="smallcaps">GOVERNOR <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">CUMMING</persName></hi> had asked me to accompany Madam and himself to the shores of the lake, with an ulterior view to Lathing and picnicking.</p>

<p>One fine morning, at 10 A.M., duly provided with the <hi rend="italic">n&#233;cessaire</hi> and a thermometer&#8212;which duly snapped in two before immersion&#8212;we set out down the west road, crossed the rickety two laned bridge that spans the holy stream, and debouched upon a mirage-haunted and singularly ugly plain. Wherever below the line of debordement of the lake's spring freshet, it is a mere desert; where raised, however, the land is cultivable, from the Wasach Mountains to Spring Point, at the north of the Oquirrh, giving about eighty square miles of fertile land. The soil, as near the lake generally, is a thin layer of saline humus, ovenspreading gravel and pebbles. The vegetation is scattered artemisia, rose-bushes, the <hi rend="italic">Euphorbia tuberosa</hi> and other varieties of milk-weed, the greasewood, salicornias, and several saisolaceae. Thera are numerous salt deposits, all wet and miry in the rainy season; and the animals that meet the sight are the coyote, the badger, and the hideous Phrynosoma. A few blue cranes and sage-chickens, which are eatable till October, were seen; and during winter the wild-fowl are found in large flocks, and the sweet-water streams are stocked with diminutive fish. In contrast with the bald and shaven aspect of the plain, rose behind us the massive forms of

<pb n="323" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.323"/>

the Wasach Mountains, robed in forests, mist-crowned, and showing a single streak of white, which entitles them to the poetical boast of eternal snow&#8212;snow apparently never being respectable without eternity.</p>

<p>After fifteen miles of good road we came to the Point o' the Mountain&#8212;the head of the Oquirrh, also called West Mountain&#8212;where pyramidal buttes bound the southern extremity of the lake. Their horizontal lines are cleanly cut by the action of water, and fall in steps toward the plain. Any appearance of regularity in the works of Nature is always pleasing&#8212;firstly, because it contrasts with her infinite diversty; and, secondly, because it. displays her grandeur by suggesting comparison with the minor works of mankind. Ranches and corrals, grass and cattle, now began to appear, and the entrance of a large cave was pointed out to me in the base of the buttes. We drove on, and presently emerged upon the shores of this "dead and desert"&#8212;this "still and solitary" sea. It has not antiquity enough to have become the scene of fabulous history; the early Canadian <hi rend="italic">voyageurs</hi>, however, did their best to ennoble it, and recounted to wondering strangers its fearful submarine noises, its dark and sudden storms. and the terrible maelstrom in its centre, which, funnel-like, de scended into the bowels of the earth. I believe that age is its only want; with <hi rend="italic">quasi</hi>-lifeless waters, a balance of evaporation and supply&#8212;ever a mystery to the ignorant&#8212;and a horned frog. the Dead Sea of the New World has claims to preternaturalism at least equal to those of its sister feature, the volcano of depression, in the Old Hemisphere.</p>

<p>The first aspect of Mare Mortuum was by no means unprepossessing. As we stood upon the ledge, at whose foot lies the selvage of sand and salt that bounds the wave, we seemed to look upon the sea of the Cyclades. The sky was light and clear, the water of a deep lapis-lazuli blue, flecked here and there with the smallest of white horses&#8212;tiny billows, urged by the warm soft wind; and the feeble tumble of the surf upon the miniature sands reminded me, with the first surveyor, "of scenes far, far away, where mightier billows pay their ceaseless tribute to the strand." In front of us, and bounding the extreme northwest" lay Antelope or Church Island, rising in a bold central ridge. This rock forms the western horizon to those looking from the city, and its delicate pink&#8212;the effect of a ruddy carpet woven with myriads of small flowers&#8212;blushing in the light of the setting sun, is ever an interesting and beautiful object Nearer, it has a brown garb, almost without a tinge of green, except in rare, scattered spots; its benches, broken by gashes and gullies, rocks and ravines, are counterparts to those on the main land; and its form and tintage, softened by the damp overhanging air, and contrasting with the light blue sky and the dark ultramarine streak of sea at its base, add greatly to the picturesqueness of the view. The foreground

<pb n="324" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.324"/>

is a strip of sand, yellow where it can be seen, incrusted with flakes of salt like the icing of a plum-cake, and bearing marks of submergence in the season of the spring freshets. At the water's edge is a broken black line of a peculiar drift, which stands boldly out from the snowy whiteness around. Where my sketch was taken I looked as through a doorway, whose staples were two detached masses of stone. On the right rose an irregular heap of conglomerate and sandstone, attached to the ledge behind, and leaning forward as if about to fall. On the left, the "Black Rock," which can be seen as a dot from the city, a heap of flint conglomerate, imbedded in slaty, burnt, and altered clay, formed the terminating bluff to a neck of light sand and dark stone.</p>

<p>Before proceeding to our picnic, I will briefly resume the history and geography of this Mare Mortuum. The Baron de la Homan, the French governor of Placentia, in Newfoundland, about 1690, heard from Indians of a Great Salt Water, which he caused to disembogue through a huge river into the South Sea or Pacific Ocean. Like the Lake Tanganyika, in Central Africa, it was arrayed in the garb of fable, 300 leagues of length, 30 of breadth, with "100 towns about it," like Mr. Cooley's highly imaginative "Zanganica," and navigated in large boats by the say-age Mozeemleks, who much remind one of the old semi-mythical "Mono-moezi." Doubtless many a trapper and obscure trader has since that time visited it; a name or two has been found upon the adjacent rocks, but those were braves who, to speak metaphorically, lived before the age of Agamemnon. In 1845, Colonel Fr&#234;mont, then engaged with his second expedition, made a partial flying survey, which, in 1849-50, was scientifically completed by Captain Howard Stansbury.</p>

<p>In geologic ages the lake occupied the space between the Sierra Madre on the east, and the ranges of Goose Creek and Humboldt River on the west. The length is roughly computed at 500 miles from north to south, the breadth from 350 to 500, and the area at 175,000 square miles. The waters have declined into the lowest part of the basin by the gradual upheaval of the land, in places showing thirteen successive steps or benches. A freshet of a few yards would submerge many miles of flat shore, and a rise of 650 feet would in these days convert all but the highest peaks of the surrounding eminences into islands and islets, the kanyons into straits, creeks, and sea-arms, and the bluffs into slightly elevated shores. Popular opinion asserts that the process of desiccation is going on at the rate of about half a mile in ten years. But the limits of beach and drift line laid down by Captain Stansbury are still well defined, and the shrinking of the volume may be ranked with its "sinking"&#8212;like the sink of the Humboldt and other rivers&#8212;an empirical explanation, by which the mountaineer removes the difficulty of believing that evaporation can drain off the sup-plies of so many rivers.</p>

<pb n="325" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.325"/>

<p>The lake, which is about the size of the African Chad, occupies the northeastern corner of Utah Territory, and lies to the north-west of the Great Salt Lake Valley, which is forty miles long by about twelve in breadth. The major axis of the irregular parallelogram is sixty to seventy miles in length from north to south, by thirty to thirty-five from east to west. Its altitude has been laid down at 4200 feet above, while the Dead Sea of Palestine is 1300 feet below sea level. The principal influents, beginning from the north, are the Bear River, the Weber River. and the Jordan. They supply the balance of evaporation, which from water is greater, and from high lands is usually lea, than the rain. The western side is a perfect desert&#8212;a salt and arid waste of clay and sand, with the consistence of mortar when wet, which can not boast of a single stream; even the springs are sometimes separated by "jornadas" of seventy miles. When the rivers are in flood, the lake, it is said, rises to a maximum of four feet, overflowing large tracts of level saline plain, winding between the broken walls of rock which surround it on all sides. Near its shores the atmosphere is reeking, bluish, and hazy, from the effects of active evap oration, and forms a decided change from the purity and transparency of the air elsewhere. Surveyors have observed that it is a labor to use telescopes for geoditic purposes, and that astronomical observations are very imperfect. The quantity of vapor is less, and evaporation has less tension and density from the surface of salt than of fresh water; here, however, the operation is assisted by sunheat sufficient to produce an aeriform state, and by a wind brisk enough to prevent the vapor accumulating over the surface.</p>

<p>The water of this remarkable feature, which so curiously reproduces the marvels of Judea, contains nearly one quarter of solid matter, or about six times and a half more than the average solid constituents of sea-water, which may be laid down roughly at three and a half per cent. of its weight, or about half an ounce to the pound.<ref target="n01">*</ref> The Dead Sea is its sole known superior. The specific

<note xml:id="n01">* "One hundred parts by weight were," says Dr. Gale, "evaporated to dryness in a water-bath below the boiling-point, and then heated to about 300&#176; of the thermometer, and retained at that heat till the mass ceased to lose any weight. It gave solid contents 22&#8226;422(?), and consisted of

<figure xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.325.figure">
<p></p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

</note>

<pb n="326" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.326"/>

gravity is 1&#8226;170, distilled water being 1&#8226;000; the North Atlantic, between latitude 25&#179; N. and longitude 52&#179; W. (G.), 1&#8226;020; and the Dead Sea, at 60&#179; Fahrenheit, from 1&#8226;22742 to 1&#8226;130. The vulgar estimate of its saltness is exaggerated. I have heard at Salt Lake City of one bucket of saline matter being produced by the evap. oration of three; and that meat can be salted, and corned beef converted into junk, alter twelve or fourteen hours in the natural unevaporated brine. It is used without preparation by the citizens, who have not adopted the precautions recommended by Dr. Gale.<ref target="n03">*</ref> It is collected by boys, shoveled into carts at the points of the beach where the winds dash up the waves—forming a regular wind tide—and is sold in retail at half a cent per pound, or two shillings per hundred pounds. The original basin of geological ages was, doubtless, as the shells have proved, fresh water. The saline substances are brought down by rain, which washes the soil and percolates through the rocky ledges, and by the rivers, which are generally estimated to contain from ten to one hundred grains of salt per gallon, <ref target="n04">&#8224;</ref> and here probably more, owing to the abundance of soda. The evaporation is, of course, nearly pure, containing but very minute traces of salts.</p>

<p>It has been generally stated that the water is fatal to organic life. The fish brought down the rivers perish at once in the con-centrated brine; but, according to the people, there is a univalve, like a periwinkle, found at certain seasons within the influence of its saline waves; and I observed, floating near the margin, delicate moss-like algae. Governor Cumming mentioned his having seen a leaf; of a few inches in length, lined with a web, which shelters a vermicular animal, of reddish color, and about the length of the last joint of the little finger. Near the shore, also, <choice><orig>muci-

<note xml:id="n02">The strongest natural brine in the United States, according to Professor Beek, is that of the Syracuse Saline, New York, which contains 17.35 per cent of chloride of sodium.</note>

<note xml:id="n03">* "The salt water" (it is elsewhere called "one of the purest and most concentrated brines known in the world") "yields about 20 per cent. of pure common salt, and about 2 per cent. of foreign salts; most of the objectionable parts of which are the chloride of lime and the chloride of magnesia, both of which, being very deliquescent, attract moisture from the damp atmosphere, which has the effect to moist-en and partially dissolve the common salt, and then, when the mass is exposed to dry air or heat, or both, a hard crust is formed. I believe I have found a remedy for the caking, which is cheap and easily used. It consists in sprinkling over the salt obtained by the evaporation of the water, and heaped up in a bin or box containing a porous bottom of blankets or other like material, a cold solution of the salt as it is concentrated from the lake till crystals begin to be deposited. This concentrated brine, while it will dissolve none of the common salt, will dissolve all the chlorides of calcium and magnesium, and carry them down through the porous bottom, and thus leave the salt purer and better than any now found in our markets. For persons who are obliged to prepare temporarily the salt, as travelers passing through the country, the water of the lake, without concentration, may he used for washing out the deliquescent chlorides, sprinkling the heap of salt by a watering-pit at intervals of two or three hours during a single day, and allowing it to drain and dry at night, and be spread to the sun an hour or two the following morning."</note>

<note xml:id="n04">&#8224; "The Physical Geography of the Sea" (by Captain Maury), chap. ix., § 502, quoted from "Youmans' Chemistry."</note>

<pb n="327" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.327"/>

laginous</orig><reg>mucilaginous</reg></choice> matter, white, pink, and rusty, like macerated moss, ad. bores to the rocky bed, and lies in coagulated spots upon the sand. We may fairly doubt the travelers' assertion that this Dead Sea contains no living thing; whereas neither animalculae nor vestige of animal matter were, according to Lieutenant. Lynch, detected by a powerful microscope in the waters of the Asphaltite Lake.</p>

<p>The Great Salt Lake is studded with an archipelago of islands, which would greatly add to its charms were their size commensurate with its diminutive limits. These, beginning from the north, are,</p>

<p>1. Dolphin Island, so called from its shape, a knoll of rock and shoal near the northwestern end, surrounded by about three feet of water.</p>

<p>2. Gunnison's Island, a large rock and small outlier, southeast of the former, and surrounded with water from nine to twelve feet deep.</p>

<p>3. Hat Island, southeast of Gunnison's, the smallest of the isles, with a reef sunk about seven feet: it was probably part of the following, and is separated from it by a narrow channel nowhere more than six feet in depth.</p>

<p>4. Carrington Island, so named from the Mormon surveyor, a circular mass with a central peak : the water is from three to six feet deep on every side except the western and southwestern, which are shoals and shallows. It contains no springs, but is rich in plants and flowers, as the sego, also spelled sigo, seacoe, and segose (<hi rend="italic">Calochortus luteus</hi>, an onion-like bull) or tuber about the size of a walnut, more nutritious than palatable, much eaten as a table vegetable by the early Mormons and the root-digging Indians, and even now by white men when half starved), a <hi rend="italic">cleome</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">malvastrum</hi>, a new species of <hi rend="italic">malacothrix</hi>, and several others.</p>

<p>5. Stansbury Island, the second largest in the lake, an ovate mass, with a high central ridge, dome-shaped above, and rising 3000 feet, twenty-seven miles in circumference, and about twelve in length. During the dry season it is formed into a peninsula by a sand-bank connecting it with the lake's western shore. Thus antelopes, deer, and coyotes pass over to browse upon the plants and to attack the young of the ducks, geese, plover, gulls, and pelicans, that make their homes upon the cliffs: it is also used for grazing purposes. The principal plants are a <hi rend="italic">comandra</hi>, and sundry new species of <hi rend="italic">heuchera</hi>, <hi rend="italic">perityle</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">stenactis</hi>. Fossils and shells are found in scatters.</p>

<p>6. Antelope, also called Church Island, because the stock of the Saints is generally kept there. Lying to the east and northeast of the preceding, and in shape an irregular and protracted conoid, it is the largest of the islands, sixteen miles long by six of extreme width, with a western ridge and an eastern line of broken peaks, which attain a maximum of 3000 feet above the lake and

<pb n="328" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.328"/>

7200 above sea level. It lies twenty miles to the northwest of the city, and the narrow passage between it and the opposite plain is fordable. This island is surrounded on the north by a tufa bed twelve feet deep; eastward by six feet of water; southeast and south by shoals; and westward by a deposit of black mud: the deepest sounding in the lake, thirty-five feet, is found between it and Stansbury island. Off the northwestern coast is a rock, called, after its principal peculiarity, Egg Island: in the eastern cliff there is said to be a cave, described to resemble the Blue Grotto at Capri, which has been partially explored. Formerly there was a small pinnace on the "Big Shallow;" it has either been wrecked or broken up for fuel.<ref target="n05">*</ref> Antelope Island contains arid ravines and a few green valleys, besides a spring of pure water, and, being safe from Indians, it is much esteemed as a grazing-place.</p>

<p>7. Fr&#234;mont Island, so named by Captain Stansbury from the first explorer, who called it, after the rude dissipation of a dream of " tangled wilderness of trees and shrubbery, teeming with game of every description that the neighboring region afforded," "Disappointment Island." The Mormons have preferred "Castle Island," suggested by its mural and turreted peak, that rises above the higher levels. It lies north and northeast from Antelope Island, parallel with the mouth of the Weber River, and south of Promontory Point, the bluff termination of a rocky tongue which separates Bear-River Bay front the body of the lake. Its shape is a semilune, fifteen miles in circumference, abounding in plants, especially the Indian onion, but destitute of wood and water. Here, on the summit, Captain Fr&#234;mont lost the "brass cover to the object-end of his spy-glass"—disdain not, gentle reader, these little reminiscences — and Captain Stansbury failed to find the relic.</p>

<p>I was surprised by the want of freshness and atmospheric elasticity in the neighborhood of the lake: the lips were salted as by sea air, but there the similarity ended. We prepared for bathing by unhitching the mules upon the usual picnicking place, a patch of soft white sand between the raised shore of the lake and the water brink. The bank supplies a plentiful stream of water, potable, though somewhat brackish, bitter, and sulphurous: it shows its effects, however, in a clump of plants, wild roses, and the euphorbia of many names, silk-plant, <hi rend="italic">vache &#224; lait, capote de sacarte</hi>,
and milk-plant The familiar magpie prevented the solitude of the scene being too impressive. Here was also a vestige of humanity, a kind of "lean-to" of dry stone wall, with the bank for a back-bone: you might have ridden over it without knowing that it belonged to Mrs. Smith of Vermont, now departed, unless <choice><orig>warn-

<note xml:id="n05">* In the "Revue des Deux-Mondes" (April, 1861) we are told that, "Pendant l'&#223;t&#223; un petit bateau &#224; vapeur fait un service r&#223;gulier sur to Lac Sal&#223;" Fresh proof, if it he required, how difficult, or rather how impassible, it is for any amount of talent or ingenuity in a reviewer to supply the want of natal eye-seeing information. The "Lac Sal&#223;" is not yet come.</note>

<pb n="329" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.329"/>

ed</orig><reg>warned</reg></choice> off by the sudden appearance of what your superior sagacity would have discovered to be a chimney.</p>

<p>The bathing-place is behind the Black Rock. The approach is first over the fine soft white sand, like that of the sea-shore, but shell-less, soppy where it receives the spring-water, and almost a quicksand near the lake. The foot crunches through caked and crusty salt-flakes, here white, there dark green, there dun-colored ilke <hi rend="italic">bois de vache</hi>, and every where the reverse of aromatic, and sinks deep into the everlastingly wet sand below. This leads to the neck of broken, riven stone pavement, whose head is the Black Rock. As the lake is neared, the basalt-like surface becomes red and rusty, the points are diamonded by sparkling spiculae, and in the hollows and crevices where the waters have dried to salt ii gathers in the form of icy. lumps. A dreadful shock then awaits the olfactory nerves. The black mud of peculiar drift before al luded to proves to be an aceldama of insects: banks a full fool high, composed of the <hi rend="italic">larv&#230;</hi>, <hi rend="italic">exuvi&#230;</hi>, and mortal coils of myriad: of worms, musquetoes, gnats, and gallinippers, east up by the waves, and lining the little bay, as they ferment and fester in the burning sun, or pickle and preserve in the thick brine.<ref target="n06">*</ref> Escaping from this mass of fetor. I reached the farther end of the promontory where the Black Rock stood decorously between the bath ing-place and the picnic ground, and in a pleasant frame of curi osity descended into the new Dead Sea.</p>

<p>I had heard strange accounts of its buoyancy. It was said It support a bather as if he were sitting in an arm-chair, and to float him like an unfresh egg. My experience differs in this point from that of others. There was no difficulty in swimming, not indeed in sinking. After sundry immersions of the head, in order to feel if it really stang and removed the skin, like a mustard plaster&#8212;as described&#8212;emboldened by the detection of so much hyperbole, I proceeded to duck under with open eyes, and smart-ed "for my pains." The sensation did not come on suddenly; at first there was a sneaking twinge, then a bold succession of twinges, and lastly a steady, honest burning like what follows a pinch of snuff in the eyes. There was no fresh water at hand; so. scrambling upon the rock, 1 sat there for half an hour, presenting to Nature the ludicrous spectacle of a man weeping flowing tears. A second experiment upon its taste was equally satisfactory; I can easily believe, with Captain Stansbury, that a man overboard has little chance against asphyxiation; <hi rend="italic">vox faucibus h&#230;sit</hi> was the least that could be said concerning its effects upon my masticators. Those who try such experiments may be warned that a jug filled at the fresh spring is necessary in more ways than one. The hair on emersion is powdered like the plastered

<note xml:id="n06">*According to Mr. T. R. Peale (quoted by Captain Stansbury. Appendix C). "More than ?As of the mass is composed of the larvae and exuvixe of the <hi rend="italic">Chironomus</hi>, or some species of musqueto, probably undescribed."</note>

<pb n="330" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.330"/>

locks of the knights of flamingo-plush and bell-hanging shoulder-knots, and there is a clammy stickiness, which is exceedingly unpleasant. Salt, moreover, may be scraped from the skin-imag-inative bathers have compared themselves to Lot's wife&#8212;and the Ethiop, now prosaically termed "nigger," comes out after a bath bleached, whitewashed, and with changed epidermis.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the <hi rend="italic">fumet</hi> from the kitchen of that <hi rend="italic">genius loci</hi> whom I daurna name, we dined with excellent appetite. While the mules were being hitched to, I found an opportunity of another survey from below the Black Rock: this look-out station is sometimes ascended by those gifted with less than the normal modicum of common sense. The lands immediately about the lake are flat, rising almost imperceptibly to the base of abrupt hills, which are broken in places by soft and sandy barriers, irreclaimable for agriculture, but here and there fit for grazing; where springs exist, they burst out at too low a level for irrigation. The meridional range of the Oquirrh, at whose northern point we were standing, divides the Great Salt Lake Valley from its western neighbor Toxic or Tuilla, which in sound curiously resembles the Arabic Taw&#237;lch&#8212;the Long Valley. It runs like most of these formations from north to south: it is divided by a transverse ridge declining westward, and not unaptly called Traverse Mountain, from Rush Valley, which again is similarly separated from Cedar Valley. From the point where we stood, the only way to Tooele settlement is round the north point of West Mountain, a bold headland, rugged with rocks and trees. Westward of Tooele Valley, and separated by a sister range to the Oquirrh, lies Spring Valley, so called because it boasts a sweet fountain, and south of this "Skull Valley"&#8212;an ominous name, but the evil omen was to the bison.</p>

<p>Bidding a long farewell to that inland briny sea, which apparently has no business there, we turned our faces eastward as the sun was declining. The view had memorable beauties. From the blue and purple clouds, gorgeously edged with celestial fire, shot up a fan of penciled and colored light, extending half way to the zenith, while in the south and southeast lightnings played among the darker mist-masses, which backed the golden and emerald bench-lands of the farther valley. The splendid sunset gave a reflex of its loveliness to the alkaline and arternisia barrens before us. Opposite, the Wasach, vast and voluminous, the storehouse of storms, and of the hundred streams that cool the thirsty earth, rose in stern and gloomy grandeur, which even the last smile of day failed to soften, over the subject plain. Northward, to a considerable distance, the lake-lands lay uninterrupted save by an occasional bench and a distant swell, resembling the upper convexity of a thunder-cloud. As we advanced, the city became dimly discernible beyond Jordan, built on ground gently rising away from the lake, and strongly nestling under its protecting

<pb n="331" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.331"/>

mountains. A little to its northeast, a thin white vapor, like the spray of a spouting whale, showed the direction of the Hot. Springs: as time wore on it rolled away, condensed by the cooling air, like the smoke of a locomotive before the evening breeze. Then the prominent features of the city came into view, the buildings separated themselves from their neighbors by patches and shades of several green, the streets opened out their regular rows and formal lines; once more we rolled over Jordan's rickety bridge, and found ourselves again in the Holy City of the Far West.</p>

<p>The ultimate destination of the Judiciary whom I had accompanied was Carson Valley, in the Sierra Nevada, a distance of some hundreds of miles through a wild country where "lifting of hair" is by no means uncommon. The judge, though not a sucking diplomat, had greenly relied upon bona verba at Washington for transportation, escort, and other necessaries which would be easily procurable at Camp Floyd. It was soon found advisable to apply to the military authorities at the cantonment. The coach, as I have said, had ceased to run beyond <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>. In May, 1858, a contract had been made with Major <persName key="Chorpenning, George">George Chorpenning</persName> to transport mails and passengers&#8212;the litre being $120&#8212;from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> to <placeName type="settlement" key="California">California</placeName>, he receiving $130,000. This lasted till September, 1859, when the drivers, complaining that the road-agents charged with paying them for eighteen months had expended the "rocks" in the hells of <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, notably evinced their race's power of self-government by seizing and selling off by auction wagons and similar movable property. On the 20th of March, 1860, it came into the hands of the proprietors of the Eastern line, Messrs. Russell and Co., who ran a mail-wagon first to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, then to Camp Floyd, and lastly, on the 1st of June, finding their expenditure excessive, packed the mails on mule.<ref target="n07">*</ref> Single travelers were sometimes thus pushed through, starting on the Wednesdays, once a fortnight; for a party like ours such a proceeding would have been impossible. Consequently, the judge and I set out for Camp Floyd to see what could be done by "Uncle Sam" and his "eagles."</p>

<p>Mr. Gilbert&#8212;of the firm of Gilbert, Gerrish, and Co., general (Gentile) merchants&#8212;offered us seats in his trotting wagon, drawn by a fine tall pair of iron-gray mules, that cost $500 the twain, and were christened Julia and Sally, after, I believe, the fair daughters of the officer who had lately commanded the district. With a fine clear day and a breeze which veiled us with dust-hangings&#8212;the highway must be a sea of mud in wet weather&#8212;we set out along the county road, leading from the southeastern angle of the Holy City. Our route lay over the strip of alluvium that separates the Wasach Mountains from the waters of Jordan: it is cut by a multitude of streamlets rising from the kanyons; the <choice><orig>prin-

<note xml:id="n07">* They carry 50 to 60 Ike; and the schedule time to <placeName type="settlement" key="Placerville, CA">Placerville</placeName> is sixteen days.</note>

<pb n="332" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.332"/>

cipal</orig><reg>principal</reg></choice> are Mill Creek, Big Cotton-wood, Little Cotton-wood, Dry Cotton-wood, and Willow Crock. The names are translated from the Indians, and we saw from the road traces of the aborigines, who were sweeping crickets and grass-seed into their large conical baskets&#8212;among these ragged gleaners we looked in vain for a Ruth. Near Big Cotton-wood, where there is a settlement distant seven miles from the city, an English woman came across the fields and complained that she had been frightened by four Indian braves who had been riding by to bring in a stolen horse. The waters of the kanyons are exceedingly cool, sweet, and clear, and suggested frequent reference to a superior kind of tap which had been stored away within the trap. In proportion as we left the city, the sterility of the River Valley increased; cultivation was unseen except upon the margins of the streams, and the look of the land was "real mean." In front of us lay the denticulated bench bounding the southern end of the valley.</p>

<p>After twenty miles from the city we reached a ranch on rising ground, near the water-gate of the Jordan. It was built at an expense of $17,000, and was called the Utah Brewery. Despite, however, the plenty of hop and barley, the speculation proved a failure, and the house had become a kind of mail-station. Between it and the river were a number of little rush-girt "eyes"&#8212;round pools, some hot, others cold&#8212;and said to be unfathomable; that is to say, from twenty to thirty fathoms deep. They related that a dragoon, slipping with his charger into one of them, found a watery grave, where a drier death might have been expected. At the ranch we rested for an hour, but called in vain for food. From the Utah Brewery, which is about half way, drivers reckon twenty-two miles to Camp Floyd, making a total of forty-two to forty-three miles between the head-quarters of the saint and the sinner, and we therefore looked forward to a "banian day."</p>

<p>About noon we hitched to and proceeded to ascend Traverse Mountain, a ridge-like spur of the Wasach, running east and west. It separates the Valley of the Northern or Great Salt Lake from the basin of the Utah, or Sweetwater Lake, to the southward, and is broken through by the waters of Jordan. The young river&#8212;called Piya Ogwap, or the Big Water, by the Shoshonees&#8212;here rushes in a foaming shallow stream, that can barely float a dug-out, over a rocky, pebbly bed, in the sole of a deep but short kanyon, which winds its way through the cross range. The descent is about 100 feet in two miles, after which the course serpentines, the banks fall, and the current becomes gentle.</p>

<p>As we toiled up the Dug-way, the graded incline that runs along the shoulder of the mountain, we saw a fine back view of the Happy Valley through an atmosphere clear as that of the English littoral before rain. Advancing higher, we met, face to face, an ambulance full of uniform <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to the Holy City, drawn by four neat mules, and accompanied by strikers&#8212;military <choice><orig>serv-

<pb n="333" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.333"/>

ants</orig><reg>servants</reg></choice>. We drew up, the judge was readily recognized, and I was introduced to Captains <persName key="Heth, Henry">Heth</persName>, Clarke, and Gibson, and to Lieutenant Robinson. They began with an act of charity, supplying ham sandwiches to half-starved men, and 1 afterward spent pleasant evenings with them at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>, and became Captain <persName key="Heth, Henry">Heth</persName>'s guest at Camp Floyd. Their kindness and hospitality lasted to the end of my stay. After the usual "liquoring up," they pointed to Ash Hollow, the depths below, where the Mormons had intended to make a new Thermopylae. Promising to meet them again, we then shook hands and resumed our road.</p>

<p>The steep descent on the counterslope of Traverse Mountain disclosed to us the first sight of Utah Lake, which is to its sister what Carmel is to Lebanon. It was a soft and sunny, a placid and beautiful landscape, highly refreshing after the aria lands on the other side. A panorama of lake, plain, and river lay before us. On the east, south, and west were rugged walls and peaks of mountain and hill; and northward a broad grassy slope rose to the divide between the valleys of the Fresh and of the Salt Lake. From afar the binding of plain round the basin appeared so narrow that the mountains seemed to dip their feet into the quiet reservoir; and beyond the southern point the lone peak of lofty Nebo stood, to adopt the Koranic comparison, like one of the pins which listen down the plains of earth. A nearer approach discovers a broad belt of meadow, rich alluvial soil, in parts marshy, and in others arable, wheat and root-crop flourishing in the bottom, and bunch-grass upon the acclivities. The breadth is greater to the west and south of the lake than in other parts. It is cut by many a poplar-fringed stream that issues from the tremendous gorges around&#8212;the American Fork, the Timpanogos<ref target="n08">*</ref> or Provo River, and the Spanish Fork. On the near side, beyond the winding Jordan, lay little Lehi, whose houses were half hid by black trees; and eastward of the Utah Water, dimly visible, was Provo City, on a plain watered by four creeks. Such were the environs of the Sea of Tiberias.</p>

<p>The Utah Lake, another Judean analogue, derives its supplies from the western versant of the Wasach. It is in shape an irregular triangle, the southern arm forming a very acute angle. The extreme length is thirty miles, and the greatest breadth Is fifteen. It owes its sweetness, which, however, is by no means remarkable, to its northern drainage, the Piya Ogwap, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Utah Outlet, <hi rend="italic">alias</hi> Jordan River. Near the shores the water soon deepens to fifteen feet; the bottom is said to be smooth, uniform, and very profound in places; but probably it has never been sounded. The bed,

<note xml:id="n08">* From <hi rend="italic">Timpa</hi>, a rock, and <hi rend="italic">ogwabe</hi>, contracted to <hi rend="italic">oge</hi>, a river, in the Yuta dialect. In English maps published as late as seven years ago, "Timpanogos" is applied to the Grunt Salt Lake: <hi rend="italic">Provo</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Provaux</hi> is the name of a Canadian trapper and trader, who in past times defeated with eighty men a thousand Indians, and was killed at the moment of victory. The Mormons call the City <hi rend="italic">Provo</hi>, and Gentiles prefer as a "rile" <hi rend="italic">Timpamogus</hi>.</note>

<pb n="334" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.334"/>

where it shows, is pebbly; a white, chalky incrustation covers the shallower bottom; shells, especially the fresh-water clam, are numerous upon the watery margin; the Baggy "Deseret weed" in the tulares is ten feet high,<ref target="n09">*</ref> and thicket is dense in places where rock does not occupy the soil. The western side is arid for want of influents; there is a "lone tree," a solitary cottonwood, conspicuous amid the grazing-ground of bunch-grass, sage, and grease-wood, and the only inhabitants, excepting a single ranch&#8212;Evan's&#8212;are, apparently, the Phrynosoma and the lizard, the raven and the jackass-rabbit. The Utah Lake freezes in December, January, and February. At these months the Jordan rolls down floes of ice, but it is seldom to be traversed on foot, In the flood sea-son it rises two, and the wind tide extends to about three feet. It is still full of fish, which in former times were carried off in barrels. The white trout weigh thirty pounds. There are many kinds of mountain trout averaging three pounds, while salmon trout, suckers, and mudfish; are uncommonly large and plentiful; water-snakes and "horsechair fish" are also found.</p>

<p>After descending the steep incline we forded the Jordan, at that point 100 feet broad, and deep to the wagon-hubs. The current was not too swift to prevent the growth of weeds. The water was of sulphur color, the effect of chalk, and the taste was brackish, but not unpleasant; cattle are said to like it. The fording was followed by a long ascent, the divide between Utah Valley and its western neighbor Cedar Valley. About half way between the Brewery and the Camp is a station, held by a Shropshire Mormon, whose only name, as far as I could discover, was Joe Dug-out, so called, lice the Watertons de Waterton, from the style of his habitation. He had married a young woman, who deterred him from giving her a sister&#8212;every Oriental language has a word to express what in English, which lacks the thing, is rudely translated "a rival wife"&#8212;by threatening to have his cars cut of by the "horifficers." Joe, however, seemed quite resigned to the pains and penalties of monogamy, and what was more to our purpose, had a good brew of porter and Lager-bier.</p>

<p>Having passed on the way a road that branches off to the old camp, which was deserted for want of water, we sighted front afar the new cantonment. It lies in a circular basin, surrounded by irregular hills of various height, still wooded with black cedar, where not easily felled, and clustering upon the banks of Cedar Creek, a rivulet which presently sinks in a black puddly mud. For a more thoroughly detestable spot one must repair to Gharra, or some similar purgatorial place in Lower Sindh. The winter is long and rigorous, the summer hot and uncomfortable, the alkaline water curdles soap, and the dust-storms remind one of the

<note xml:id="n09">*Tulare Is a marsh, of bulrush (<hi rend="italic">Scirpus lacustris</hi>), which is found extending over immense tracts of river valley in Western America. "Tooly" water, as it is pronounced, is that which is flavored or tainted by it.</note>

<pb n="335" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.335"/>

Punjaub. I lost no time in suggesting, to <hi rend="italic">my compagnon de voyage</hi>, Lieutenant Dana, as a return for his kindness in supplying me with a "Bayonet Exercise," and other papers, our old campaigning habit of banging wet canvas before every adit, and received the well-merited thanks of Madam. The hardest part of these hardships is that they are wholly purposeless. Every adobe brick in the place has been estimated to have cost a cent, as at Aden each cut stone was counted a rupee; and the purchase of lumber has enriched the enemy. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">In 1858 the Peace Commissioners sent by the supreme government conceded to the Mormons a point which saved the Saints. The army was not to be "located" within forty miles of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>; thus the pretty sites about Utah Lake were banned to them, and the Mormons, it is said, "jockeyed" them out of the rich and fertile Cache Valley, eighty miles north of the head-quarters.</seg></p>

<p>A broken wall surrounds this horrid hole. Julia and Sally carried us in with unflagging vigor. We passed through <placeName type="settlement" key="Fairfield, UT">Fairfield, less euphoniously termed Frogtown</placeName>, the bazar of the cantonment on the other side of the creek. During the days when Camp Floyd contained its full complement of camp followers&#8212;5000 souls&#8212;now reduced to 100 or 200 men, it must have been a delectable spot, teeming with gamblers and blacklegs, grog-house-keepers and prostitutes: the revolver and the bowie-knife had nightly work to do there, and the moral Saints were fond of likening <placeName type="settlement" key="Fairfield, UT">Frogtown</placeName> to certain Cities of the Plains. Of late years it has become more respectable, and now it contains some good stores.</p>

<p>We removed from the wagon the mail-bags containing letters for the camp, and made ourselves at home with the hospitable Gilbert. On the next day, after "morning glory" and breakfast, we called upon the officer commanding the department, Colonel <persName key="Cooke, Philip St. George Cooke">P. St. G. Cooke</persName>, of the 2d Dragoons, and upon the commandant of the cantonment, Lieutenant Colonel <persName key="Smith, C. F.">C. F. Smith</persName>. They introduced us to the greater part of the officers, and, though living in camp fashion, did not fall to take in the strangers after the ancient, not the modern, acceptation of the term. It is a sensible pleasure, which every military man has remarked, to exchange the common run of civilian for soldier society in the United States. The reveill&#233; in the morning speaks of discipline; the guard-mounting has a wholesome military sound; there is a habit of 'tention and of saluting which suggests some subordination; the orderlies say "Sir," not Sirree nor Sirree-bob. The stiffness and ungeniality of professionals, who are all running a race for wealth or fame, give way in a service of seniority, and where men become brothers, to the frankness which belongs to the trade of arms The Kshatriya, or fighting caste, in the States is distinctly marked. The officers, both of the navy and the army, are, for the most part, Southerners, and are separated by their position

<pb n="336" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.336"/>

from general society. The civilian, as was the ease in England twenty years ago, dislikes the uniform. His principal boasts are, that he pays his fighting servants well, and that he&#8212;a militiaman&#8212;is far superior to the regular. A company of Cadets, called the Chicago Zouaves, during the summer of 1860, made a sensation throughout the land. The newspaper writers spoke of them in terms far higher than have been lavished upon the flower of the French army; even the military professionals were obliged to join in the cry. As a republican, the citizen looks upon a soldier as a drone. "I hate those cormorants," said to me an American diplomat, who, <hi rend="italic">par parenth&#232;se</hi>, had made a fortune by the law, as he entered a Viennese caf&#233;. <hi rend="italic">L'arte della guerra presto s' impara</hi> is his motto, and he evinces his love of the civilian element by giving away a considerable percentage of commissions in the army to those whose political influence enables them to dispense with the preparation of West Point.</p>

<p>I am here tempted to a few words concerning the cheap defense and the chief pride of the United States, viz., her irregular army. The opposite table shows the forces of the militia to be three millions, while the regular army does not number 19,000. The institution is, therefore, a kind of public, a writing, speaking, voting body, which makes itself heard and felt; while the existence of the regulars is almost ignored. To hint aught against the militia in the United States is sure seriously to "rile up" your civil audience, and Elijah Pogram will perhaps let you know that you can not know what you are talking about. The outspoken Britisher, despite his title and his rank as a general officer, had a "squeak" for his commission when, in the beginning of the volunteer mania, he spoke of the new levies as a useless body of men: it is on the same principle in the United States. Thus also the liberal candidate declares to his electors his "firm belief that, with all our enormous expenditure, the country had not felt itself se-cure, and straightway a noble arm of defense, springing unbought from the patriotism of the people, had crept into existence, form. ing a better shield for our national liberties than all that we had been able to buy with our mounds of sold." (Cheers.) The civilian in the United States boasts of his military institutions, his West Point and his regular army, and never fails to inform a stranger that it is better paid than any force in Europe. On the other hand, he prides himself upon, as he is probably identified with, the militia.</p>

<p>That writing, speaking, and voting have borne fruit in favor of the militia, may be read in the history of the Americo-Mexican War. The fame of the irregulars penetrated to Calcutta and China: it was stopped only by the Orient sun. But who ever heard of the regulars? The "newspaper heroes" were almost all militiamen, rangers, and other guerrillas: "keeping an editor in pay" is now a standing sarcasm. The sages of the Revolution initiated a <choice><orig>yeo-

<pb n="337" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.337"/>

<figure xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.337.figure">
<p>MILITIA FORCE OF THE UNITED STATES. General Abstract of the Militia Force of the United States, according to the latest Returns recieved at the Office of the Adjutant General.</p>
<figDesc></figDesc>
</figure>

manry</orig><reg>yeomanry</reg></choice> second to none in the world: they had, however, among them crowds of frontiersmen accustomed to deal with the hear and the Indian, not with the antelope and the deer. The Texan Rangers in later times were a first-rate body of men for irregular purposes, not to be confounded with the militia, yet always put forward as a proof how superior to the "sweepings of cities," as the regular army was once called in the Senate, are the irregulars, who "never fire a random shot, never draw trigger till their aim is sure," and are "here to-night and to-morrow arc fifty miles off." But the true modern militia is pronounced by the best authorities

<pb n="338" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.338"/>

&#8212;indeed, by all who hold it no economy to be ill served, for any but purely defensive purposes, a humbug, which costs in campaigns more blood and gold&#8212;neglect of business is perhaps the chief item of the expenditure&#8212;than a standing army would. As a "Garde Nationale" it is quite efficient. When called out for distant service, as in the Mexican War, every <hi rend="italic">pekin</hi> fault becomes apparent. Personally the men suffer severely from unaccustomed hardship and exposure; in dangerous climates they die like sheep; half are in hospital, and the other half must nurse them: Nature soon becomes stronger than martial law; under the fatigue of the march they will throw away their rations and military necessaries rather than take the trouble to carry them: improvident and wasteful, their convoys are timid and unmanageable. Mentally they are in many cases men ignoring the common restraints of society, profoundly impressed with insubordination, which displays equality, which has to learn all the wholesome duty of obedience, and which begins with as much respect for discipline as for the campaigns of Frederick the Great. If inclined to retire, they can stay at home and obtain double or treble the wages: not a few are driven to service by that enthusiasm which, as Sir Charles Napier well remarked, readily makes men run away. Their various defects make organization painfully slow. In camp they amuse themselves with drawing rations, target practice, asking silly questions, electing officers, holding meetings, issuing orders, disobeying orders, "cussing and discussing:" the sentinels will sit down to a quiet euchre after planting their bayonets in the ground, and to all attempts at dislodging them the reply will be, "You go to&#8212;&#8212;, Cap.! I'm as good a man as you." In the field, like all raw levies, they are apt to be alarmed by any thing unaccustomed, as the sound of musketry from the rear, or a threatened flank attack: they can not reserve their fire; they aim wildly, to the peril of friend and foe, and they have been accused of unmilitary cruelties, such as scalping and flaying men, shooting and killing squaws and children. And they never fail, after the fashion of such men, to claim that they have done all the fighting.<ref target="n10">*</ref></p>

<p>Such is, I believe, the United States militia at the beginning of a campaign. After a reasonable time, say a year, which kills off the weak and sickly, and rubs out the brawler and the mutineer; when men have learned to distinguish the difference between the often Dutch courage of a bowie-knife squabble and the moral fortitude that stands firm in presence of famine or a night attack, then they become regulars. The American&#8212;by which I understand a man whose father is born in the United States&#8212;is a first-rate soldier, distinguished by his superior intelligence from his compeers in other lands; but he rarely takes to soldiering. There are not more than five of these men per company, the rest being

<note xml:id="n10">* These remarks were penned in 1860; I see no reason to alter them in 1861.</note>

<pb n="339" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.339"/>

all Germans and Irishmen. The percentage in the navy is greater, yet it is still inconsiderable. The Mexican "War, as History writes it, is the triumph of the militia, whom old "Rough and Ready" led to conquest as to a "manifest destiny."<ref target="n11">*</ref> On the other hand, the old and distinguished officer who succeeded General Taylor has occasionally, it is said, given utterance to opinions concerning the irregulars which contrast strongly with those generally attributed to him.</p>

<p>At Camp Floyd I found feeling running high against the Mormons. "They hate us, and we hate them," said an intelligent officer; consequently, every statement here, as in the city, must be received with many grains of salt. At Camp Floyd one hears the worst version of every fact, which, as usual hereabouts, has its many distinct facets. <seg type="Context" subtype="WesternViolence">These anti-Mormons declare that ten murders per annum during the last twelve years have been committed without punishment in New Zion, whereas <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> averages 18-33.</seg> They attribute the phenomenon to the impossibility of obtaining testimony, and the undue whitewashing action of juries, which the Mormons declare to be "punctual and hard-working in sustaining the dignity of the law," and praise for their "unparalleled habits of industry and sobriety, order, and respect to just rights." Whatever objection I made was always answered by the deception of appearances, and the assertion that whenever a stranger enters <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>, one or two plausible Mormons are told off to amuse and hoodwink him. Similarly the Mormons charge the Christians with violent injustice. On a late occasion, the mayor of <placeName type="settlement" key="Springville, UT">Springville</placeName>, Mr. <persName key="Macdonald, H. F.">H. F. Macdonald</persName>, and the bishop were seized simply because they were Church dignitaries, on the occasion of a murder, and the former, after durance vile of months at Camp Floyd, made his escape and walks about a free man, swearing that he will not again be taken alive. <seg type="Context" subtype="GunnisonMurder">In 1858, Captain <persName key="Gunnison, J. W.">J. W. Gunnison</persName> and seven of his party were murdered near Nicollet on Sevier River, twenty-five miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Nephi City, UT">Nephi City</placeName>. The anti-Mormons declare that the deed was done under high counsel, by "white Indians," to prevent the exploration of a route to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, and the disclosures which were likely to be made.</seg> The Mormons point to their kind treatment of the previous expedition upon which the lamented officer was engaged, to the friendliness of his book, to the circumstance that an Indian war was then raging, and that during the attack an equal number of Yuta Indians were killed. <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><persName key="Remy, M.">M. Remy</persName> distinctly refers the murder to the Pahvant Indians, some of whom had been recently shot by emigrants</seg> <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">to California</seg>.<ref target="n12">&#8224;</ref> <seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">The horrible "Mountain Meadow Massacre"<ref target="n13">&#8225;</ref> was,</seg>

<note xml:id="n11">* And it will be remembered, the Mexicans were not Austrians or Russians.</note>

<note xml:id="n12">&#8224; See Translation, vol. i., p. 463.</note>

<note xml:id="n13">&#8225; The following is the account of that affair, officially given, of course, by anti-Mormons: <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">On the 4th or 5th of September, 1857</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">a large emigrant train <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">proceeding to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">with horses, mules, and ox-wagons, conveying stores of clothing and valuables</seg></seg>, was suddenly attacked <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">near a spring at the west end of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadow Valley</geogName></seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">The Indians, directed by white men, cut off from water the travelers</seg>, who had fortified themselves behind the vehicles, which they&#8212;filled with earth, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">killed and wounded several</seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">When the attacked party, distressed by thirst and a galling fire, showed symptoms of surrender, several Mormons, among whom the leaders, <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> and Elder <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, are particularly mentioned, approached them with a white flag, and by soft words persuaded them that if they would give up their weapons they should be safely forwarded to Panther Creek and <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. The emigrants unwisely disarmed themselves, and flocked toward the spring.</seg> The work of murder and robbery began near a patch of scrub-oak brush, about one mile and a half from water.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Between 115 and 120 adults were slain.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Three emerged from the valley; of these, two were soon overtaken and killed, and the third was slaughtered at Muddy Creek, distant about fifty miles.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="SexualViolence">One of the Mormons&#8212;the name has been variously given&#8212;is accused of a truly detestable deed; a girl, sixteen years old, knelt to him, imploring mercy: he led her away into the thicket&#8212;and then cut her throat.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Seventeen children, aged from two months to seven years, were taken from the Indians by the whites, and were distributed among the several Mormon families in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, Fort Harmony, <placeName type="settlement" key="Santa Clara, UT">Santa Clara</placeName>, etc. Of these, sixteen were recovered, and the seventeenth was found in the April of 1858.</seg> <seg type="Reaction" subtype="FederalInvestigation">Mr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Jacob Forney</persName>, the late Superintendent of Indian Affairs, conducted the investigation on the part of the federal government; he reported that <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">white men joined in the murder and the robbery</seg></seg>.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Mormons of course deny, in toto, complicity with the Indians,</seg> and remark that many trains&#8212;for instance, to quote no others, the emigrants at Sublette's Cut-off, <placeName type="state" key="Oregon">Oregon</placeName>, in August, 1858&#8212;have similarly suffered, and that <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">they can not be responsible for the misfortunes which men who insult and ill-treat the natives bring upon themselves.</seg></seg></note>

<pb n="340" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.340"/>

<seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">according to the anti-Mormons, committed by the Saints to revenue the death of an esteemed apostle&#8212;Parley P. Pratt&#8212;who, in the spring of 1857, when traveling through <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, was knived by one <persName key="McLean, Hector">Hector M'Lean</persName>, whose <persName key="McLean Pratt, Eleanor ">wife</persName> ho had converted and taken unto himself. The Mormons deny that the massacre was committed by their number, and ask the Gentiles why, if such be the case, the murderers are not brought to justice? They look upon Mr. <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">P. P. Pratt</persName>'s proceeding&#8212;even in El Islam, the women of the infidels are, like their property, <hi rend="italic">halal</hi>, or lawful to those who win them&#8212;as perfectly justifiable.</seg><ref target="n14">*</ref> In February, 1859, occurred

<note xml:id="n14">* <seg type="Context" subtype="PrattMurder">The following is an extract from the "Millennial Star," July 25th, 1857. The article is headed "More of the Assassination:" "We publish the following extract from a letter written by two gentlemen to the editor of a <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> paper. The letter was dated Flint-Cherokee Nation, <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, May 17th, 1857, and says that after Elder <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> was arrested in the Indian country, "he was 'placed under a strong guard, and by a military escort conveyed in chains to the Supreme Court, <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>. The case being promptly investigated, and there being no evidence upon which a bill of indictment could he found, he was liberated on the 13th instant. Brother <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName>, being without arms, and without friends to protect him, and knowing that <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName> was thirsting for his blood, and that he had the aid of a mass of the corrupt, money-bought citizens of <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName>, endeavored to make his escape on horseback, unmolested; but every road and passway being under strict watch, he did not succeed in getting far till his path was discovered. <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName> and half a dozen other armed fiends pursued him; and Brother <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> being totally unarmed, they succeeded in killing him without being hurt. Two of the party in advance intercepted his road, and brought him to a halt, while <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName> and the others came up in the rear. <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName> discharged a six-shooter at him, but the balls took no effect: some passed through his clothes others lodged in his saddle. The parties now being in immediate contact, <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName> stabbed him (both being on horseback) with a heavy bowie-knife twice under the left arm. Brother <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> dropped from his horse, and <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName> dismounted and probed the fatal wounds still deeper; he then got a Derringer from one of his aids, and, as Brother <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> lay dying upon his back, shot him in the upper part of the breast, dropping the pistol by the side of the victim. The assassin then mounted his horse and fled. This occurred within a few steps of the residence of a farmer by the name of Wire. Two gentlemen, being at the house at the time, saw the whole affair, and have made oath to what they witnessed before a coroner's jury. Brother <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> survived the work of this assassin two hours and a half, and was enabled to tell those who came to his assistance who he was, that he had been murdered hy a fiend for doing his duty, and gave full instructions as to what course should he pursued in interring his body, and the disposition of the means and property connected with his person. His instructions were fully attended to by Elder <persName key="Higginson, George">Higginson</persName> and Mrs. <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName>, who reached the place of his assassination the same evening. Those who saw his last moments state that Brother <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> died without a murmur or a groan, and apparently without a pain, perfectly resigned to the will of Heaven. Brother <persName key="Pratt, Parley P.">Pratt</persName> told Elder <persName key="Higginson, George">Higginson</persName>, the morning after his arrest, that his enemies would kill him, and requested Elder Higginson to go through with this spring's emigration to Utah, and carry the news of his death to the Church and his family. This Elder <persName key="Higginson, George">Higginson</persName> will do, the Lord helping. After perpetrating this heaven-daring deed, <persName key="McLean, Hector">M'Lean</persName> returned to <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName> and made it known. After remaining in town several hours, and walking the streets with impunity, he was escorted bv a number of citizens of <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, AR">Van Buren</placeName> to the boat, and took his leave of tho place. <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSPersecution">Verily we had long thought that the bloodthirsty mobocrats of <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="Illinois">Illinois</placeName> were without a parallel in the world, but we now yield the palm to the Church-going citizens of <placeName type="settlement" key="Van Buren, UT">Van Buren</placeName>, for they have proven to the world that they are a den of murderers and assassins.</seg> <hi rend="smallcaps"><persName key="Higginson, George">George Higginson</persName></hi>.
<hi rend="smallcaps"><persName key="Crough, George">George Crough</persName></hi>."</seg></note>

<pb n="341" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.341"/>

sundry disturbances between the soldiers and citizens at Rush Valley, thirty-five miles west of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>, in which Mr. <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Howard Spencer</persName>, nephew to Mr. <persName key="Spencer, Daniel">Daniel Spencer</persName>, a squatter, while being removed from a government reservation by First Sergeant <persName key="Pike, Ralph">Ralph Pike</persName> of the 10th Infantry, raised a pitchfork, and received in return a broken head. Shortly afterward the sergeant, having been summoned to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>, was met in Main Street and shot down before all present. The anti-Mormons, of course, declare the deed to have been done by Mr. <persName key="Spencer, Howard">Spencer</persName>, and hold it, under the circumstances&#8212;execution of duty and summons of justice&#8212;an unpardonable outrage; and the officers assert that they could hardly prevent their men arming and personally revenging the foul murder of a comrade, who was loved as an excellent soldier and an honest man.<ref target="n15">*</ref> The Mormons assert that the "shooting" was done by an unknown hand; that the sergeant had used unnecessary violence against a youth, who, single-handed and surrounded by soldiers, had raised a pitchfork to defend his head, and that the provocation thus received converted the case from murder to one of justifiable homicide. In the month of June before my arrival, a Lieutenant <persName key="Saunders, ">Saunders</persName> and Assistant Surgeon <persName key="Convey, Edward N.">Covey</persName> had tied to a cart's tail and severely flogged Mr. <persName key="Hennefer, ">Hennefer</persName>, a Mormon. The opposition party assert that they recognized in him the man who two years before had acted as a spy upon them when sitting in Messrs. <persName key="Livingston, ">Livingston</persName>'s store, and, when ordered to "make tracks," had returned with half a dozen others, and had shot Dr. <persName key="Covey, Edward N.">Covey</persName> in the breast.  The Mormons represent Mr. <choice><orig>Hen-

<note xml:id="n15">* On this occasion. Cedar Fort, a neighboring settlement, with cultivation, and a few huts, near Camp Floyd, was attacked at night by camp-followers (soldiers); a single calf was killed (the whole place was burned to the ground), and the damages speedily rose from a dozen to $10,000, claimed from Congress (which did not half repay the injury done).</note>

<pb n="342" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.342"/>

nefer</orig><reg><persName key="Hennefer, ">Hennefer</persName></reg></choice> to be a peaceful citizen, and quiet, unoffending man, thus brutally outraged by tyrannical servants of government, and, moreover, prove for him an <hi rend="italic">alibi</hi> from the original cause of quarrel. I have given but a few instances: all are equally contradictory, and <hi rend="italic">tantas componere lites quis audet</hi>?</p>

<p>Strongly disclaiming the idea that the officers who discussed with me the subject at Camp Floyd had any tendency to exaggeration or to set down aught in malice, and quite conscious, as they never failed to remark, that a stranger is allowed to see only the <hi rend="italic">beau c&#244;l&#233;</hi> of the New Faith, I can not but think that their views are greatly warped by causes external to it. This is to be expected. Who, after the massacre of Cawnpore, would have admitted into his mind a shadow of excuse for Nana Sahib? Among so many, however blinded and fanatic, and <seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">however fond of polygamy</seg>&#8212;this is ever the first reproach&#8212;there must be some good men. Yet from the "chief impostor" to the last "acolyte," all are represented to be a gang of miscreants. The Mormons are far more tolerant; they have praise for those Gentiles, even federal officers, who have abstained from injuring them. They speak well of Lieutenant Colonel <persName key="Steptoe, E. J.">E. J. Steptoe</persName>, 9th Regiment of Infantry, and the officers of his force;<ref target="n16">*</ref> of General Wilson, afterward the Navy Agent at <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>; and of the present commandant, Colonel <persName key="Cook, Philip St. George">Cooke</persName>. They have nothing to say against Judge <persName key="Reed, ">Reed</persName>, or Mr. <persName key="Kinney, John J.">John J. Kinney</persName>, the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court; and when Judge <persName key="Shaver, Leonidas">Leonidas Shaver</persName> died in 1855, they put the papers in mourning, and buried the Gentile in their cemetery. They do not abuse even their merchant rivals. Mr. <persName key="Kimball, J. B.">J. B. Kimball</persName>, to mention no other, is generally praised and trusted. But when they find it necessary or advisable to take away a man's character, they can do it, "and no mistake." At the same time, their tolerance and discipline are, to say the least, remarkable. Judge <persName key="Brocckus, ">Brocckus</persName>,<ref target="n17">&#8224;</ref> to quote but one, would run the risk of being torn to pieces in almost any fanatical meeting in Europe.</p>

<p>At Camp Floyd I was introduced to Colonel <persName key="Crossman, G. H.">G. H. Crossman</persName>, Department Quarter-master General, and Major <persName key="Montgomery, ">Montgomery</persName> of the same department; to Dr. <persName key="Porter, ">Porter</persName>, who was uncommonly and unnecessarily shy upon the subject of a "sick certificate;" and to Lieutenant <persName key="Dudley, N. A. M.">N. A. M. Dudley</persName>, when we passed many a merry time over "simpkin." It is hardly necessary to say that the judge, having no authority to demand, did not obtain cither escort or carriage. Colonel <persName key="Cook, Philip St. George">Cooke</persName> frankly told him that he had neither men nor conveyance at liberty, and even if they were that he could not exceed orders. The Secretary of "War is ready to "be down" upon such offenses, and in the United States Army <choice><orig>prob-

<note xml:id="n16">* Mr. <persName key="Hyde, ">Hyde</persName> (chap, vi.) gives the official document in which these officers petitioned President <persName key="Pierce, Franklin">Pierce</persName> to reappoint Mr. <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> as Governor and Superintendent of Indian Affairs in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah Territory</placeName>, and it speaks volumes in praise of the much-abused Saints.</note> <note xml:id="n17">&#8224; Chap. vi.</note>

<pb n="343" xml:id="mmm.wa.burton.1862.343"/>

ably</orig><reg>probably</reg></choice> more officers throw up the service from distress for leave than in the English army. It was clear that we must travel without the dignities, so we inspected an ambulance and a four-mule team, for which the Hungarian refugee, its owner, asked $1000&#8212;but little beyond its worth. After an exceedingly satisfactory day in a private sense, I passed the evening at Captain <persName key="Gove, Jesse">Gove</persName>'s, and watched with astonishment the game of <placeName type="settlement" key="Boston, MA">Boston</placeName>. Invented by the French prisoners in the islands of the American Liverpool, and abounding in "grand misery," "little misery," and other appropriate terms, it combines all the difficulties of whist, &#233;cart&#233;, piquet, brag, and cribbage, and seems to possess the same attractions which beam upon the mind of the advanced algebraic scholar. Fortunately there was on abundance of good commissariat whisky and excellent tobacco, whose attractions were greater than that of <placeName type="settlement" key="Boston, MA">Boston</placeName>. On the morrow, a gloomy morning, with cold blasts and spatters of rain from the southwest, and the tameness of the snowbirds&#8212;which here represent

<quote><hi rend="center">"Cock Robin and Jenny Wren, 
God Almighty's cock and hen"&#8212;</hi></quote>

warned us that the fine season was breaking: up, and that we had no time to lose. So, inspanning Julia and Sally, we set out, and after six hours reached once more the City of the Saints.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>