<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.doc.price.1867">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">General Ingalls's Inspection Report: Price Report from Salt Lake and Fort Mojave W. R. Express</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"/>
                <author><forename>George</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Price</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.doc.price.1867</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in
                    Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all
                        rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as
                        allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires
                        express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                        publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary"/>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="a">Salt Lake and Fort Mojave W. R. Express, Camp 31, Fort Mojave, Arizona Territory, Wednesday, June 22, 1864</title>
                    <title level="m">General Ingalls's Inspection Report. Letter from the Secretary of War, in answer to a resolution of the House of February 27, transmitting report of General Ingalls's inspection made in 1866</title>
                    <title level="s">US House. 39th Cong., 2d sess. House Exec. Doc. 111</title>
                    <author><forename>George</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Price</surname></author>
                    <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                    <extent>20-25</extent>
                    <date when="1864">1867</date>
                    <note type="source">George F. Price. “Salt Lake and Fort Mojave W. R. Express, Camp 31, Fort Mojave, Arizona Territory, Wednesday, June 22, 1864,” in Rufus Ingalls. <hi rend="italic">General Ingalls's Inspection Report. Letter from the Secretary of War, in answer to a resolution of the House of February 27, transmitting report of General Ingalls's inspection made in 1866</hi>. US House. 39th Cong., 2d sess. Washington, DC: GPO, 1867. House Exec. Doc. 111. 20-25.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>government_document</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="culpability">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="action">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-06-14"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enrichment and
                Concept Highlighting</change>
            <change when="2011-05-12"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Validation</change>
            <change when="2010-01-19"><name>Kelsey F. Harris</name> Initial Encoding</change>
            <change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>

        <body>

            <div1 type="doc">

                <pb n="20" xml:id="mmm.doc.price.1867.020"/>
                
                <head>SALT LAKE AND FORT MOJAVE W. R. EXPRESS,</head>

                <head type="sub">CAMP 31, FORT MOJAVE, ARIZONA TERRITORY</head>
                <dateline>Wednesday, June 22, 1864.</dateline>

                <p>SIR: I have the honor to submit herewith preliminary report of this expedition to
                    this camp; a full and complete map of my route, together with a complete history
                    of the expedition, will be furnished as soon as practicable after my arrival at
                        <orgName type="military" key="Camp Douglas">Camp Douglas</orgName>. It is
                    intended to furnish in this preliminary report sufficient information to enable
                    the general commanding district of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory"
                        >Utah</placeName> to determine how far the expedition was successful, to
                    what extent it succeeded in accomplishing his wishes, and whether a route from
                    the <geogName type="waterway" key="Colorado River">Colorado river</geogName> to
                        <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake
                        City</placeName> can be made superior to the present route from <placeName
                        type="settlement" key="Carson City, NV">Carson City</placeName> to Salt
                    Lake, or equal to it.</p>

                <p>In obedience to the letter of instructions of May 7, 1864, from headquarters
                    district of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, 1
                    left <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> on the morning of the 9th
                    May, 1864, with Lieutenant <persName key="Conrad">Conrad</persName> and
                    sixty-one non-commissioned officers and men, four six-mule teams, and sixty-four
                    government horses. I arrived at <orgName type="military" key="Fort Crittenden"
                        >Fort Crittenden</orgName> on the 11th May, from which point I was
                    instructed to commence operations. <pb n="21" xml:id="mmm.doc.price.1867.021"/>
                    I have determined to move the column and teams by the San Bernardino road,
                    sending out small parties to my west to explore the country. Upon arrival at
                        <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy creek</geogName> the
                    wisdom of this measure was apparent for had I attempted to haul my teams on any
                    one of the routes run by my side scouts I would have been destitute of horses
                    and means of transportation long before arrival at <geogName type="valley"
                        key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. I moved the column by
                    easy marches to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain
                        Meadows</geogName>, a distance of 302 1/4 miles, in sixteen days, having
                    good water and grass along the route, with as fine a road as I ever travelled
                    over. To this point six of my horses had become unserviceable and were run in
                    the herd. Two of my teams gave evidence of failing and I commenced feeding them
                    from my private grain; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">at this point I
                        also erected a monument in memory of the victims of the Mountain Meadow
                        massacre</seg>, which fact was at that time communicated to you in an
                    official letter. From <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain
                        Meadow</geogName> to <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy
                        creek</geogName> my stock failed rapidly. I employed every means in my power
                    to keep it up, making short drives, working at the teams whenever a pull was
                    required, and keeping a working party ahead to improve the road. The distance
                    was ninety-eight miles, and I occupied nine days in travelling it, besides
                    resting at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain
                        Meadows</geogName> for two days, and then did not get two of the teams into
                    camp at <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy creek</geogName> until
                    three days after making the camp; was compelled to pack the loads in and give
                    the mules empty wagons, which they could scarcely haul. Leaving the <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Virgin River">Rio Virgin</geogName> for <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy creek</geogName>, have to rise a
                    large hill, one mile long; at that point was compelled to pack outfit on horses,
                    then place all mules to wagons, and sixty men with ropes in addition, to get
                    them on top of the hill. It was not so much the condition of the route which
                    broke down my means of transportation, as it was the fact of having old and
                    worn-out mules, who commenced failing on a road which was equal to a turnpike. I
                    made camp 24, on <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy
                        creek</geogName>, June 3, 1864, having succeeded in getting all my stock in
                    excepting one mule; one horse died, and one horse strayed. Total distance from
                        <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>, 396 miles, 6 furlongs, and
                    21 rods. My side scouts from <orgName type="military" key="Fort Crittenden">Fort
                        Crittenden</orgName> to <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy
                        creek</geogName> are as follows: One from <orgName type="military"
                        key="Fort Crittenden">Fort Crittenden</orgName> to <geogName type="valley"
                        key="Round Valley">Round valley</geogName>, via <geogName type="valley"
                        key="Tontic Valley">Tontic valley</geogName>, <geogName type="waterway"
                        key="Oak Creek">Oak creek</geogName>, and <geogName type="waterway"
                        key="Sevier River">Sevier river</geogName>, 101 miles. One from Radford's to
                        <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>,
                    via Deseret settlement, Sevier river, Sevier lake, sink of Bear and Black Rock
                    Springs; distance, l56 miles. No wagons accompanied either of these scouts.
                    Neither could wagons have accompanied them, the mutes being across heavy sand,
                    rank growth of sage brush, no grass, and but little water on routes, and it at
                    long intervals. The third and most important side scout started from <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Corn Creek">Corn creek</geogName>, south of Fillmore,
                    taking with it one six-mule team, the best one I had, with twenty days' rations.
                    This scout, after almost superhuman exertions, succeeded in making New Mines
                    west of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver
                        City</placeName>, and passing down to Black mountains were forced to come in
                    my route to San Bernardino road at <geogName type="valley"
                        key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>; distance travelled, 350
                    miles. All of these scouts reported barren, desolate country, and no chance to
                    run a natural wagon road where there could be found wood, water, and grass. A
                    care-fully prepared map of each of these side scouts has been made, together
                    with complete daily journal, which will be submitted with final report. 13v
                    means of these Scouts I was possessed with much valuable information, and
                    succeeded in running a complete line from <orgName type="military"
                        key="Fort Crittenden">Fort Crittenden</orgName> to Clover and Meadow
                    valleys, to within a distance of seventy miles of <geogName type="waterway"
                        key="Muddy Creek">Muddy creek</geogName>, and at one point on the side
                    scout, living 115 miles west of <placeName type="settlement"
                        key="Beaver City, UT">Beaver City</placeName>. The last-named scout joined
                    me at <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy creek</geogName> on 5th
                    June. having occupied twenty days, with team and horses much jaded. It thus
                    became evident to me that I could not continue the expedition with all of my
                    teams and horses, and accordingly left Sergeant Gass with fifteen men at Muddy,
                    having in charge two wagons, nineteen horses, and eleven mules, together with
                    all of outfit. not absolutely necessary for me to have, and by reducing rations
                    of those who were to accompany me, was enabled to leave him rations for thirty
                    days. He was instructed to run lines from <pb n="22"
                        xml:id="mmm.doc.price.1867.022"/> Muddy to Clover valley, as soon as horses
                    were rested enough to do so. and to await at that point (Muddy) orders from me.
                    None of the horses or mules left behind were in condition to cross to the Vegas;
                    in fact, could not have them drove across the desert loose.</p>

                <p>I left Muddy on Tuesday evening, June 7, 1864, with forty-five men, forty-seven
                    horses, and ten teams, having only provisions and water barrels on them. The men
                    were reduced to one blanket, and their saddle-bags, each containing one shirt,
                    one pair of drawers, and one pair of socks, Mr. <persName key="Conrad"
                        >Conrad</persName> and self doing the same, leaving all our mess kid,
                    bedding, &amp;c, at :Muddy; succeeded in crossing the desert without much
                    trouble, and found at Vegas plenty of excellent water and grass. Had to leave at
                    that place two horses, which could not have proceeded any further. After resting
                    there until evening of the 9th of June, resumed march from Las Vegas for El
                    Dorado canon; distance, forty-four miles. Travelled to Musquit springs that
                    night, when halted until daybreak, using the spring water, which was very bad.
                    Next day (l0th) resumed march; After travelling up grade eighteen miles, halted
                    at grass; mules and horses much exhausted. Gave horses three quarts of water
                    each, and men had one quart each issued to them. Wagons and troops then
                    separated, former taking road, latter taking trail. We made water in maintains.
                    which stood in pot-holes in the rocks, and was only rain-water; about dark
                    horses were crazy for water, and had the men been compelled to travel five miles
                    further some of them would have gone crazy. On this route four horses gave out
                    and had to be shot. Next morning went down into El Dorado canon, and made camp
                    27; water enough standing in canon for stock, but no grass; teams came in some
                    two or three hours afterwards; mules scarcely able to stand in the harness. I
                    remained in canon until next day in the afternoon, when resumed march for
                    Mojave; arrived at Lewis springs with many of the horses exhausted; men nearly
                    all walking. Upon arrival at springs could not obtain water enough for the
                    stock. Horses arrived there at about reveille; team mules did not get in until
                    middle of afternoon, and then only brought in one wagon. It became evident to me
                    that I would be compelled to leave them. Had taken precaution to send party from
                    El Dorado canon to Mojave by river trail, and knew that fresh mules would come
                    out in a few days. Left Sergeant Gordon and nine men at Lewis springs with the
                    teams; also left with them about all the provisions I had; also left with him
                    two horses who could not travel any further. Six additional horses were shot or
                    left on route from El Dorado canon to Lewis springs, making a total of twelve
                    horses shot or left at water and grass since leaving Muddy. I then started from
                    Lewis springs for Rock springs, with twenty-five horses, all told, and upon
                    arrival there found no water for stock; drove then out to Government Hole, where
                    they obtained enough to quench thirst; found a stray cow and shot her for meat;
                    next day resumed march for Piute creek, and from <geogName type="waterway"
                        key="Piute Creek">Piute creek</geogName> arrived here on the 16th instant,
                    completely worn out and exhausted, half the men bare-footed, horses scarcely
                    able to walk, not because they were poor from flesh, but because the route from
                    Vegas here affords but little grass and water, and where the grass is there is
                    no water, and where water is found there is no grass. I was very thankful that I
                    had suceeded in getting here. At Piute creek met six fresh mules going out to
                    meet my wagons, taking also some provisions to the men. From Fillmore to
                        <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> the
                    route makes a circle into the east, and I ran three observation lines as
                    follows: one from <geogName type="waterway" key="Coon Creek">Coon
                        creek</geogName> to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver City, UT"
                        >Beaver City</placeName>, one from <geogName type="waterway"
                        key="Coon Creek">Coon creek</geogName> to Parowan, and one from <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Coon Creek">Coon creek</geogName> to <placeName
                        type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. None of these
                    are practicable for want of water and grass; the streams starting out from the
                    mountains do not run down more than from one to six miles, excepting <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Beaver Creek">Beaver creek</geogName>. I found the maps
                    extant of the country through which I travelled very incorrect; no reliance
                    whatever can he placed upon the maps for any portion south of <placeName
                        type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>. From the distance
                    from <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> to El Dorado canon, 488
                    mules, and from <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> to Fort Mojave,
                        <pb n="23" xml:id="mmm.doc.price.1867.023"/> 585 miles 4 furlongs and 19
                    rods. The route can be shortened from El Dorado canon probably twenty-five or
                    thirty miles, and from Fort Mojave at least sixty miles, which will be done on
                    return trip. On Thursday (21) despatched an express for Muddy, with orders to
                    Sergeant Gass to resume line of march for <persName key="Forney, Jacob"
                        >Forney</persName>. I cannot obtain any fresh teams or horses at this post;
                    there are but few animals here and they are in but little better condition than
                    my own.</p>

                <p>The condition of my stock may be stated as follows : Left at Muddy, June 7, 1864,
                    nineteen horses and eleven mules, worn out and unserviceable; left at Las Vegas,
                    June 9, 1864, two horses, unserviceable; shot on route to Rock springs ten
                    horses; left at Rock springs two horses; left at Lewis springs twelve mules and
                    ten horses. Total rendered unserviceable on route, including mule and horse died
                    before reaching Muddy and one horse strayed, twenty-four mules and forty-five
                    horses. My team mules were driven in yesterday; the stock I have here will not
                    be in condition to resume travel for at least one month, and I doubt my ability
                    to return much of it to <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>; plenty
                    of provisions can be obtained here, but I do not purpose taking full supply when
                    starting, only enough to supply to <geogName type="valley"
                        key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadow</geogName>, intending that teams will
                    meet me from <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> at or near that
                    point. You will be advised fully of my plan of operation in time to meet me at
                    Mountain Meadow, should I so adopt.</p>

                <p>I repeat that the condition of my stock was not caused so much by the character
                    of the road as it is from the fact that the team mules were old, worn out, and
                    almost unserviceable at the start for a march of such magnitude; the delay of
                    the teams also delayed the troop, keeping it in poor range much longer than it
                    would have been had the teams been serviceable. You will remember that at
                        <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> I remarked that not less
                    than fifteen of my horses were totally unfit for this expedition. I made the
                    same remark to the general commanding, and was told that he could not do better
                    for me. This I believe, and am satisfied I had as good an outfit as could be at
                    that time furnished. Yet the fact cannot be denied that the outfit was entirely
                    inadequate to the wants of the expedition; as a natural result, the route proved
                    severe upon both men and animals, and both frequently suffered intensely from
                    want of water and also from fatigue, incident to misfortune of getting through
                    with broken down teams. As soon as the teams commenced failing I issued private
                    grain belonging to Mr. <persName key="Conrad">Conrad</persName> and self,
                    amounting to eight hundred pounds.</p>

                <p>As regards the route I have fully made up my mind as follows: while I will not
                    yet say that road cannot be opened west of present travelled route until I learn
                    result of line run from Muddy to Clover valley, am decided that no nearer,
                    better, or more practicable road can be run than the present one from <persName
                        key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName> to Las Vegas; and having travelled
                    from <placeName type="settlement" key="Carson City, NV">Carson City</placeName>
                    to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>
                    over the mail road, state without any hesitation that the route I have travelled
                    to mouth of El Dorado canon is superior in every respect to it, and that the
                    total length of route need not exceed 150 miles. There is no occasion to run the
                    southern terminus of road below El Dorado canon. Steamboats can navigate the
                    river as easily to the canon, or a point eight miles above it, as they can and
                    do to La Pax, two hundred miles south of Mojave.</p>

                <p>I will locate the southern terminus of road either at mouth of El Dorado canon or
                    at a landing eight miles above, running from thence to <placeName
                        type="settlement" key="Las Vegas, NV">Las Vegas</placeName>, to <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Muddy River">Muddy</geogName>, <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Virgin River">Virgin river</geogName>, <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Clara River">Clara river</geogName>, <geogName
                        type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, <placeName
                        type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>, <placeName
                        type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, <placeName
                        type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, west side of
                        <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> Lake to
                        <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake
                        City</placeName>. Nature of road as follows : From El Dorado canon, 44 miles
                    desert, to Las Vegas, where find most excellent water and grass; from Las Vegas
                    to Muddy, 47 miles desert, where find good water and abundance of grass; from
                    Muddy to Virgin, 20 miles, good road; on Virgin to <placeName type="settlement"
                        key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, down, 32 miles sandy road, heavy
                    hauling; from <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>
                    down to Clara river: good road; from Clara river to <geogName type="valley"
                        key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, heavy room; from
                        <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>
                    to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake
                        City</placeName>, 302 1/4, a turnpike road, supplied with wood, water, and
                    grass; longest drive on it without water is 27 miles. Best <pb n="24"
                        xml:id="mmm.doc.price.1867.024"/> time to start freight trains from El
                    Dorado canon, on or about 20th of April, as follows: A train of one hundred
                    government wagons, divided into five parts, each part two days in advance of
                    rear, each twenty wagons to have two grain and water wagons along, and every
                    wagon to have water barrel holding twenty-five gallons. Feed grain to <geogName
                        type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>; any how
                    haul water to <geogName type="waterway" key="Muddy Creek">Muddy
                    creek</geogName>. From these two points load grain and water wagons from other
                    teams, and the through trip can be made in twenty-six to twenty-eight days easy.
                    So well satisfied am I of this fact, would be willing to take charge of such a
                    train and stake my commission on bringing it through without loss of an animal,
                    except from natural causes, provided that at the start the outfit was of a. No.
                    1. quality. To start out any other kind of stock would simply result in delays
                    and losses, and also injure the reputation of the route. It is useless to run a
                    road from the canon at Fort Mojave. It would make nearly one hundred miles
                    additional land carriage, over a country poorly supplied with water and
                    grass.</p>

                <p>The <geogName type="waterway" key="Colorado River">Colorado river</geogName> can
                    be navigated to El Dorado canon with greater ease than the <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Sacramento River">Sacramento river</geogName> can be
                    navigated from Knight's Landing to Red Bluff, using the same kind of boats as
                    are employed on the upper <geogName type="waterway" key="Sacramento River"
                        >Sacramento river</geogName>. There are no obstructions in the <geogName
                        type="waterway" key="Colorado River">Colorado river</geogName>, excepting
                    the casual shifting of sand bars which is peculiar to the Missouri, Mississippi,
                    and Sacramento rivers. No appropriations of public money are necessary to
                    improve the navigation of the river. Rich mines are located along it from a
                    point 70 miles south of La Paz to the mouth of the Virgin. The country is
                    rapidly filling up with an energetic people, and private enterprises can easily
                    do all that is required, and receive handsome profit from any outlay thus
                    made.</p>

                <p>The so-termed Colorado Steam Navigation Company runs one heavy, good-for-nothing
                    boat to La Paz, which town property is mostly owned by that arrangement. Instead
                    of placing good boats on the river, the company act as though it wished to
                    retard the opening of the country, and it is my decided opinion that this
                    company is seeking to obtain from the government a large appropriation for the
                    ostensible purpose of improving the navigation.</p>

                <p>Steamboat brought a load of freight to this post on the 20th of May last, and
                    said would return immediately. Mr. Hardy has over three hundred tons of freight
                    lying at La Paz awaiting transportation from this model company; and when it is
                    a notorious fact that the river is as easily navigated from La Paz to El Dorado
                    cannon as it is from Fort Yuma, to La Paz, no reasonable excuse can be offered
                    for such conduct on the part of a company professing a great desire to open the
                    river and supply the wants of a region rapidly developing in great mineral
                    wealth. All the steamers they could place on the river could run down every trip
                    loaded to utmost capacity with rock from the many ledges, and receive four cents
                    per pound for freighting it.</p>

                <p>A steam company could make fortune upon fortune at the business of freighting
                    rock down the river. It is scarcely a year since the mines were di-covered in
                    this section of <placeName type="state" key="Arizona">Arizona</placeName>, and
                    now there are over one hundred thousand persons interested in them. Many of
                    these ledges rival in richness the Comstock and Could &amp; Curry, of Nevada
                    Territory, and it is my belief that ledges will be discovered all the way from
                    here to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake
                        City</placeName>, in the mountains of <placeName type="state" key="Colorado"
                        >Colorardo</placeName>, the Virgin and the Sevier rivers. The importance of
                    opening the navigation of the <geogName type="waterway" key="Colorado River"
                        >Colorado river</geogName> and establishing good wagon-road communication
                    from head of navigation to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT"
                        >Salt Lake City</placeName> cannot be urged too strongly or impressed too
                    firmly upon the minds of those in authority, who have the power within their
                    hands of prosecuting such a work to a successful termination.</p>

                <p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">I passed through numerous bands of Indians
                        from Mountain Meadow to this point, and had no trouble with them; on the
                        contrary, found them the most inveterate beggars I ever met. In conversation
                        with Indians at Muddy they charged the Mormons with the Mountain Meadow
                        massacre, naming <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> and
                            <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName> as two of the
                        principal leaders in that affair</seg>.</p>

                <pb n="25" xml:id="mmm.doc.price.1867.025"/>

                <p>I have now communicated about all I deem worthy of note at the present time. The
                    daily journal of the expedition will, when finished, embody every detail
                    occurring from day to day, which, together with the map of routes, will afford
                    complete information, and will. I trust, meet the approval of the general
                    commanding, and I desire you to assure him that no effort has been spared on my
                    part to make the expedition successful and to accomplish his wishes in regard to
                    it. Whatever of hardships and suffering the expedition may have endured amounts
                    to nothing, if success, in his judgment, has been accomplished by it. The health
                    of the command is excellent.</p>

                <closer><signed>Very respectfully, your obedient servant.<lb/> <persName
                            key="Price, George F.">GEORGE F. PRICE</persName>,<lb/> <hi rend="italic">Captin 2d California Cavalry, Commanding Expedition.</hi><lb/> Captin M. G.
                    Lewis,<lb/> <hi rend="italic">Assistant Adjutant General. District of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</hi><lb/></signed>
                    HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF <placeName type="state" key="California"
                        >CALIFORNIA</placeName>,<lb/> <hi rend="italic"><placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="California">Cal.</placeName>, September</hi> 5, 1866.<lb/>
                    Official:<lb/> <persName key="Drum, R. C.">R. C. DRUM</persName>,<lb/> <hi rend="italic">Assistant Adjutant General</hi> H. Ex. Doc. 111 3</closer>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
