<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">History of Utah, Volume II</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename>Orson</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Whitney</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.uh.whitney.1893</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Reaction!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m">History of Utah, Volume 2</title>
                    <author><forename>Orson</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Whitney</surname></author>
                    <publisher>George Q. Cannon &amp; Sons Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Salt Lake City, UT</pubPlace>
                    <extent>781-829</extent>
                    <date when="1893">1893</date>
                    <note type="source">Orson F. Whitney. <hi rend="italic">History of Utah. Vol. 2.</hi> Salt Lake City, UT: George Q. Cannon &amp; Sons Co., 1892. 781-829.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>utah_history</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-07-12"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
            <change when="2009"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>

<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="781" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.781"/>

<head>CHAPTER XXVIII.</head>

<head>1874-1875. </head>

<p><hi rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">THE MOUNTAIN MEADOWS MASSACRE INVESTIGATED&#8212;INDICTMENTS PRESENTED BY THE GRAND&#8212;JURY COLONEL DAME AND JOHN D. LEE ARRESTED&#8212;THE BATES CONTEMPT CASE&#8212;THE LEE TRIAL&#8212;KLINGENSMITH, A PRINCIPAL IN THE MASSACRE, TURNS STATE'S EVIDENCE&#8212;HIS VERSION OF THE TRAGEDY&#8212;TWENTY OTHER WITNESSES EXAMINED&#8212;THE JURY DISAGREE&#8212;WHY THE TRIAL PROVED A FAILURE.</hi></hi></p> 

<p>AN EVENT of importance during the decade of the seventies 
was the trial, conviction and execution of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John Doyle Lee</persName>, a leading spirit in the Mountain Meadows massacre. A full and accurate account of this awful affair, in the previous volume, renders unnecessary another recital. If the details given at the trial convey but a partial impression of all the circumstances connected with the tragedy, it must be borne in mind that all testimony deemed irrelevant to the special issue in court&#8212;the guilt or innocence of the indicted parties&#8212;was excluded, while the author of this work was unrestricted in his field of research, and had the advantage of writing at a period subsequent to the trial, when the facts were more easily obtained.</p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">It was in the autumn of 1874 that public interest in the Mountain Meadows massacre was reawakened by a movement on the part of prosecuting officers in the Second Judicial District, within which the deed was committed. That movement was to ascertain the identity and whereabouts of witnesses, so that an investigation might be made and a prosecution of implicated persons be instituted.</seg> It was known that <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>,<ref target="n01">*</ref> one of the chief participants in the massacre, and an apostate from the Mormon 

<note xml:id="n01">*He is also referred to as <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingon Smith</persName>, or <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">P. K. Smith</persName>, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Bishop Smith</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Mr. Smith</persName>. The indictment designates him as <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip K. Smith</persName>.</note>

<pb n="782" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.782"/> 

Church, was in <placeName type="county" key="San Bernardino County, CA">San Bernardino County</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, and that he was anxious to secure immunity from punishment for his complicity in the crime, by turning state's evidence.<ref target="n02">*</ref> The probability, however, that his testimony would be more or less unreliable, and therefore subject to impeachment, because of his ardent desire to exculpate himself and gratify a feeling of hatred and revenge toward some of his former friends and associates, deterred the Government representatives from proceeding without seeking further direct proof in addition to the corroborative evidence available.</p>

<p>Though there was a plenitude of rumors as to persons who knew the internal history of the massacre, a degree of difficulty was encountered in determining who were actually in possession of that knowledge. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">This may have been partly owing to the obligation of secrecy placed upon all who were at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> on the fatal day;</seg><ref target="n03">&#8224;</ref> but the greatest impediment in the way of obtaining the requisite information was the action of the officers themselves, in shaping their course, as Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> had formerly done, for a crusade against the Mormon Church and its leaders. They thereby forced the members of that organization to stand aloof and refrain from extending the aid which otherwise would have been willingly given. It was vain to say to them that only guilty persons would be pursued. They knew better. The memory of the conspiracy of the <persName key="McKean, James B.">McKean</persName> clique against the Church leaders, which had been overthrown by the United States Supreme Court, was yet fresh in their minds. <persName key="McKean, James B.">McKean</persName> was still in office; a prosecution of the case by <persName key="Baskin, R. N.">Baskin</persName> was prospective; while <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName>, Judge in the Second Judicial District, with U. S. Attorney <persName key="Carey, Joseph M.">Carey</persName> and U. S. Marshal <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> were ardent followers of the Chief Justice in his anti-Mormon mission. Had the officers 

<note xml:id="n02">* The eagerness of <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> to do this was shown when, on April 10th, 1871, he made a sworn statement before the county clerk of <placeName type="county" key="Lincoln County, NV">Lincoln County</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Nevada">Nevada</placeName>, purporting to give a full account of the massacre and the causes which led to it. His story is at variance on several material points with that told by other and trustworthy witnesses, and with his own testimony on the witness stand. His evident purpose was to shield himself by shifting a large share of his own responsibility to the shoulders of others. </note>

<note xml:id="n03">&#8224;See the detailed account of the massacre in Volume I., pages 692 to 709.</note> 

<pb n="783" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.783"/>  

started out upon the legitimate course which was adopted when a change occurred in the office of District Attorney of ferreting out and pursuing the actual criminals, the people would have rendered them greater assistance, and their efforts would have been attended with earlier and probably better success. The unwisdom of the method adopted as to one of the most culpable actors in the tragedy&#8212;<persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>&#8212;would have been seen. But the prosecution, in an unreasonable desire to elicit proof of a condition which never existed, surrounded itself with difficulties not easily surmounted.</p>

<p>Enough witnesses were found, however, to make a presentment of the case before the Grand Jury. This jury&#8212;the first to be empaneled under the Poland law&#8212;was summoned for the opening of the Second District Court, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, on the 7th of September, 1874. The panel was not completed until the 9th. Of the fifteen members, ten were Gentiles, four Mormons, and one an apostate from the Mormon Church. The unanimity of twelve was necessary for the finding of an indictment. During the session of the jury, which ended on September 25th, twenty-eight bills were presented to the Court for crimes against United States and Territorial statutes'. One of these was an indictment charging <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName>, <persName key="Adair, George Jr.">George Adair, Jr.</persName>, <persName key="Wilden, Elliott">Eliot
Wilden</persName>, <persName key="Jukes, Samuel">Samuel Jukes</persName>, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip K. Smith</persName><ref target="n04">*</ref> and <persName key="Stewart, William C.">William C. Stewart</persName> with participation in the Mountain Meadows massacre. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><persName key="Smith, John">John Smith</persName> and fifty other unknown persons were the alleged victims of the crime</seg>, which was stated to have occurred on <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">September 16th, 1857</seg>.<ref target="n05">&#8224;</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n04">* <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>. </note>

<note xml:id="n05">&#8224; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">September llth was the actual date of the massacre</seg>. The first indictment upon which <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> were arraigned charged the murder of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><persName key="Wilson, James">James Wilson</persName> and fifty others</seg>, at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows Valley</geogName>. This was quashed on July 20th, 1875, on motion of <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>'s attorney, for the reason that it did not allege that the crime was committed within the jurisdiction of the Court. District Attorney <persName key="Carey, Joseph M.">Carey</persName> immediately presented another indictment, found at the same time as the previous one&#8212;September 24th, 1874&#8212;which did not contain this defect, and which he carried in his pocket for just such an emergency. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">This second indictment alleged a combination or conspiracy of the defendants to kill <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the emigrants</seg></seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">"<persName key="Smith, John">John Smith</persName> and fifty others,"</seg> and upon this the case went to trial.</note>

<pb n="784" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.784"/> 

<p>This indictment was returned into court on the 24th of September. About the beginning of October Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, was arrested and lodged in the Penitentiary.<ref target="n06">*</ref> Warrants for the apprehension of the others were placed simultaneously in the hands of U. S. Deputy Marshal <persName key="Stokes, William">William Stokes</persName>, with instructions from Marshal <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was wanted first, if possible. <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> was of the opinion that the arrest would be a dangerous proceeding, as he did not believe that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> would be taken alive; but he wished his deputy to do his best to make the capture.</p>

<p>On the 28th of October <persName key="Stokes, William">Stokes</persName> started for Lee's Crossing, on the 
Colorado River, <placeName type="state" key="Arizona">Arizona</placeName>, where he expected to find the object of his 
search. Next day he received information at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was at <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, <placeName type="county" key="Washington County, UT">Washington County</placeName>, and the officer arranged to attempt an arrest there, but soon ascertained that he was several days too late.</p>

<p>On November 7th, <persName key="Stokes, William">Stokes</persName> again started from <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, and learning that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was at <placeName type="county" key="Panguitch County, UT">Panguitch</placeName>, then in <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron</placeName>, but now in <placeName type="county" key="Garfield County, UT">Garfield County</placeName>, went there with a posse consisting of <persName key="Winn, Thomas">Thomas Winn</persName>, <persName key="LaFevre, Thomas">Thomas
LaFevre</persName>, <persName key="Rodgers, Samuel G.">Samuel G. Rodgers</persName>, <persName key="Evans, David">David Evans</persName> and <persName key="Fish, Franklin R.">Franklin R. Fish</persName>. Next morning, Sunday the 8th, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s house was surrounded and searched, but he was not in the building. By the movements of 
some of the family, however, the attention of the officer was attracted to a log pen, used as a chicken house, and in this, partly covered with straw, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was found, disarmed, and taken into custody.&#8224; There was talk of his sons making an effort to rescue him, but it was seen that a movement of that kind meant certain 
death to the prisoner, and probably to others, so that the idea, if 

<note xml:id="n06">* President <persName key="Grant, Ulysses S.">Grant</persName>, as stated, visited the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> Penitentiary on October 4th, 1875. Looking down from the walls into the prison enclosure, his attention was directed to Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> as one of the parties indicted for the Mountain Meadows massacre. The President gazed intently upon him and then remarked: "That is not the face of a murderer." </note>

<note xml:id="n07">&#8224; Mr. <persName key="Stokes, William">Stokes</persName> says that at the moment he discovered <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> he was himself covered by two guns in the hands of some of the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> family. He had the accused at a disadvantage, however, with a loaded pistol close to his head, and he surrendered quietly.</note> 

<pb n="785" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.785"/>  

entertained, was soon abandoned. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was taken to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, his wife <persName key="Lee, Rachel">Rachel</persName> accompanying him. They arrived there on November 10th, and the prisoner was placed in Fort Cameron for safe keeping.</p>

<p>Of those indicted, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> were the only ones arrested in 1874. When the spring term of court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> came on, it was anticipated that they would be placed on trial; but on the evening of 
April 2nd Messrs. <persName key="Sutherland, Jabez">Sutherland</persName> and <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName>, of counsel for the prisoners, received at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> this telegram from Assistant District Attorney <persName key="Whedon, D. P.">D. P. Whedon</persName>, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>: "Cannot bring on those trials this term." 
Next morning, however, Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> was removed from the Penitentiary by Marshal <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName>, and hurried off to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, and on the 5th his attorneys started for the same place to secure as early a date 
as possible for the trial. It was expected, and so announced in the newspapers, that all the defendants not arrested would voluntarily appear in court and request a hearing of the case.<ref target="n08">*</ref></p> 

<p>In conformity with an order of court, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, on April 
6th, was brought to plead to the indictment, and to its reading responded "Not Guilty." Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> was called for arraignment on the 7th, but when the U. S. Deputy Marshal, <persName key="Pratt, Arthur">Arthur Pratt</persName>, looked for him in the jail he was not there. A flurry of excitement followed, and at the request of Marshal <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> the court issued an order to Sheriff <persName key="Hunt, ">Hunt</persName>, of <placeName type="county" key="Beaver County, UT">Beaver County</placeName>, to show 
cause why he had released the prisoner. Mr. <persName key="Hunt, ">Hunt</persName> proved to the 
court that <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> had never been in his custody, and in fact had been 
practically set free by the U. S. Marshal. During this attempt to punish the Sheriff for the shortcomings of the Marshal, <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> was quietly eating his breakfast at the prisoner's boarding house 
opposite the jail, to which he returned after finishing his meal, and was found on the deputy's next appearance there. Though left without a guard, he had no intention of escaping or evading trial.</p> 

<p>Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>'s attorneys made strenuous efforts to have his case 

<note xml:id="n08">* This course would probably have been pursued at that time, had it not been for the dilatory methods of the prosecution, which promised to keep the accused in prison, without trial, for an indefinite period.</note> 

<pb n="786" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.786"/> 

heard, but the prosecuting officers refused, and on April 14th he was returned to the Penitentiary. On this date <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>'s attorneys made a similar attempt in his behalf, but were unable to accomplish 
their purpose. The officers for the Government alleged that they had not yet procured all the necessary witnesses, one of the desired parties being <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, who, it was said, could not be found. It 
was also stated that the officials had no funds to pay jurors, officers or witnesses. For these reasons the cases were continued till the next term of court. Five days after the postponement <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had 
an epileptic fit, as a result of his rapidly declining health, caused by the change from an active outdoor life to close confinement in the Fort Cameron prison.<ref target="n09">*</ref></p> 

<p>It was finally determined that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s trial should take place in July, and on the 12th of that month the Second District court room at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> was crowded with spectators. The Territorial newspapers 'and leading journals East and West had special representatives present, in anticipation of developments of an unusually interesting and sensational character. An incident on this occasion illustrates the bearing of Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> toward attorneys engaged on that side of a case to which his own predilections were opposed. Ex-District Attorney <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName> was one of the counsel for <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>. Several months prior to the date given, he had been communicated with by some of the parties jointly indicted with them, but not arrested, and had been requested to proffer to the court security for their appearance for trial. He had done this, when to his astonishment he was sharply reprimanded by the Judge. In vain the attorney apologized and protested that, in delivering the message and making the tender 

<note xml:id="n09">* On May 31st, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was removed from Fort Cameron to the <placeName type="county" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver County</placeName> jail, to curtail expenses. On July 28th, a search of his cell resulted in the discovery of a saw file, butcher knife, hatchet, twenty feet of rope, and other articles to aid in an escape. In order to guard against any attempt to break jail, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was placed in irons and all visitors refused admission. His wife <persName key="Lee, Emma">Emma</persName> called to see him, but the jailer, <persName key="Thompson, William">William Thompson</persName>, required her to leave the building. The jailer asserted that she made a savage assault upon him with a rock.</note>

<pb n="787" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.787"/>  

of bail, as requested, he had no knowledge of impropriety or intention of disrespect to the court. Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> suspended him from practicing as an attorney in the Second District, and issued an order for him to show cause why the disbarment should not be permanent.<ref target="n10">*</ref> To this the attorney had filed an answer disclaiming any thought or design of contempt or disrespect for the court or Judge.</p> 

<p>All this had occurred, as stated, several months prior to the 12th of July. On that day Mr. <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName> solicited the indulgence of the court while he read an affidavit, but the Judge stopped him abruptly with the remark, "Mr. <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName>, you are not authorized to appear in this court until you are permitted to do so." To this the response was, "I beg your honor's pardon. I did not think of that." Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> sharply rejoined, "I think you ought to have known it." A few moments later he relentingly informed Mr. <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName> that he could read the affidavit. This, however, the attorney declined to do. Nothing further in the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> case, or the <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName> affair, was done on that or the succeeding day, but on the 14th Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> delivered himself of an address, strongly censuring Mr. <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName> for his "very improper application" in behalf of "alleged criminals fleeing from justice," an application which he (the Judge) "supposed no sane man would make,"&#8212;but stating that in view of the old age of the defendant, the fact that this was "his first offense in this court," and his "sworn disclaimer of any and all improper motives," etc., the court, in spite of the "very great provocation," would "lean to the side of mildest mercy" and not disbar the defendant, though a fine of fifty dollars would be entered up against him. It is understood that the fine imposed by Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> remained unpaid, and that Mr. <persName key="Bates, George C.">Bates</persName> entertained such contempt for His Honor that he refused to take any steps toward his own reinstatement.</p> 

<p>On the 14th of July the town of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> was thrown into <choice><orig>com-

<note xml:id="n10">* The unusual and uncalled for severity of Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> in this matter doubtless had its effect in causing the unarrested defendants to change their design of coming into court, as it gave them to understand that the Judge was specially hostile before learning the testimony of the witnesses, and that his attitude would prejudicially affect their interests. </note>

<pb n="788" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.788"/> 

motion</orig><reg>commotion</reg></choice> by the report that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> had decided to make a full statement of what he knew concerning the Mountain Meadows massacre, and these tidings were at once flashed to every part of the Union. Mr. <persName key="Bishop, William W.">W. W. Bishop</persName>, one of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s attorneys, being interviewed by a representative of the <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Enterprise</hi> in relation to the matter, made the following statement: </p>

<p>On coming here some days ago we found ourselves in a peculiar position as regards this trial. We found that scarcely any of the witnesses we had summoned were here; some could not be found, others would not come. We found that a feeling of general disapprobation existed in regard to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and the course he had taken; that everyone we asked in regard to him gave us the one reply, 'If he is guilty let him suffer, we have no desire to interfere;' that so strong is the general belief that he is a guilty, bloodstained man, that but very few seem to desire aught else but that he shall be punished. We find that the prosecution have now in this city and on the way here an array of witnesses and a mass of testimony which are overwhelming, and, though we have not been idle by any means, we have failed in this respect. There seems to be a fixed determination on the part of all&#8212;even those who professed to be <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s friends at one time to let him be sacrificed that justice might be appeased and the clamor of the people stilled forever. Even I, myself, who not long since was met by everyone with the greatest of courtesy and hospitality, have almost been frozen in the last few days by the way parties would meet me and merely say "Good day," and pass on, as if they did not wish to be conspicuously impolite, but could not afford to be seen talking with me upon the street. We find every avenue to a fair trial barred, our client deserted and alone, without even the means to pay us for our labors, neither Mr. <persName key="Hoge, E. D.">Hoge</persName><ref target="n11">*</ref> nor myself having received a cent; but we will not go back on him. * * * You can probably understand some of the difficulties we have to encounter in the matter. Things have taken such a shape that the only hope I can see for my client is in taking advantage of the means of escape which the government holds out to him and turn state's evidence. I have been talking with him seriously and have advised this step. Then the whole truth will come out, the mystery will be unraveled, and the stain that has blackened <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s reputation for more than seventeen years will be effaced.<ref target="n12">&#8224;</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n11">* <persName key="Hoge, E. D.">E. D. Hoge</persName>, Esq. of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> was one of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s counsel at this time.</note> 

<note xml:id="n12">&#8224; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> actually made a statement concerning the massacre at this time. But in the "Life and Confessions of John D. Lee," published after his death by Attorney <persName key="Bishop, William W.">Bishop</persName>, the latter makes no reference to it. He practically denies that such a statement was made, by asserting that all of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s confession "was written by him while in prison, and after the jury had returned its verdict of guilty." He also says that "he refused to confess at an early day, and save his own life by placing the guilt where it of right belonged." The truth is that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement was rejected by the prosecution because it was not sufficiently far-reaching to implicate leading Mormons who were innocent of any complicity in or knowledge of the crime, but whom rabid anti-Mormon Federal officials were eager to proceed against.</note>

<pb n="789" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.789"/>  

<p>On the 17th it was given out that the prosecuting officers were "very undecided whether they will accept <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement, which is now completed, thinking he is not telling the whole truth." A member of the legal fraternity, who was also acting at that time as a special newspaper correspondent, was permitted by the attorneys for the defense to read what <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had prepared, and stated its effect as 
follows: "The testimony of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, as well as of other important witnesses will entirely refute all charges which have been made against <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and the leaders of the Mormon Church in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>."<ref target="n13">*</ref> Attorney <persName key="Baskin, Robert N.">Baskin</persName> arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> on the evening of the 18th, to conduct the case for the Government.<ref target="n14">&#8224;</ref> On the morning of the 19th came the announcement: "The prosecution will not accept <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement, as they expect to prove, by the witnesses already here, some of whom are said to have participated in the massacre, more than he confesses." <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> had arrived at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> three days before, and had had an interview with the prosecutor. His offer to turn state's evidence had been accepted. When U. S. Deputy Marshal <persName key="Cross, ">Cross</persName> found him in southern <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, he expressed to the officer his willingness to come and testify. He was nominally under arrest, but was really present as a witness and 
not as a defendant.</p> 

<p>In court, the attorneys for the defense entered pleas of abatement, etc., which were overruled. As stated, one indictment was quashed because of a defect, but another and more perfectly framed accusation, found by the same grand jury, was forthwith substituted.<ref target="n15">&#8225;</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n13">* <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s first statement was never entirely given to the public, though a few short extracts were permitted to be used by the newspapers. All of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s manuscript passed into the possession of his attorney, <persName key="Bishop, William W.">W. W. Bishop</persName>, who was strongly antagonistic to the Mormons generally, and to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> in particular.</note> 

<note xml:id="n14">&#8224; "I was leading counsel in the case," <persName key="Baskin, Robert N.">Baskin</persName> subsequently informed a Senate committee in <placeName type="state" key="Washington, D. C.">Washington</placeName>.</note>

<note xml:id="n15">&#8225; A movement, somewhat out of the usual order, was made by the defense, who entered before a justice of the peace complaints against some of the more conspicuous witnesses, charging them with complicity in the massacre and other high crimes. Warrants were issued for persons thus accused, but Marshal <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> directed his deputies to prevent, by armed force if necessary, the service of these processes. The attempt to arrest implicated witnesses was abandoned, and the excitement caused by the proceeding subsided.</note>

<pb n="790" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.790"/> 

<p>Both sides being ready, <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was placed on trial. It was 
the 22nd of July, 1875. The attorneys for Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> urged that 
the case against their client be heard at the same time, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s 
counsel wanted <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> also tried, but the prosecution refused 
to consent to either proposition. For the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> case there had been 
summoned one hundred and seven witnesses in behalf of the Government. The defense had but few. The following jurors were 
sworn to try the issue: <persName key="Wade, Josephus">Josephus Wade</persName>,<persName key="Hiester, L. C."> L. C. Hiester</persName>, <persName key="Price, Paul">Paul Price</persName>, <persName key="Brewer, John">John Brewer</persName>, <persName key="Rogers, David">David Rogers</persName>, <persName key="Duffin, Isaac">Isaac Duffin</persName>, <persName key="Jarvis, Geroge F.">George F. Jarvis</persName>, <persName key="Robinson, James C.">James C. Robinson</persName>, <persName key="Daley, Milton">Milton Daley</persName>, <persName key="Dunkin, John C.">John C. Dunkin</persName>, <persName key="Knight, James">James Knight</persName> and <persName key="Perkins, Ute">Ute Perkins</persName>. The first four were Gentiles, and the remaining eight Mormons.</p> 

<p>District Attorney <persName key="Carey, William C.">Carey</persName> made a lengthy opening speech, stating 
that the Government expected to prove that <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeIndian"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">the emigrants who were massacred were, upon their arrival at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, refused supplies and "worse treated than they had been treated by the wild Indians; "<ref target="n16">*</ref> that "the barns and granaries were full to overflowing," but all through the settlements on the journey south they could obtain no grain, except thirty bushels of corn from an Indian at Corn Creek, and a small quantity purchased from a man who was subsequently cut off the Church for selling it; that when they were resting at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, previous to starting across the desert,</seg> </seg>

<note xml:id="n16">* The statement has been frequently published that the emigrants had to camp "over Jordan"&#8212;on the bank opposite the principal portion of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>&#8212;because of a feeling of hostility towards them. They did not camp on the Jordan at all, but on Mill Creek, which then ran through the city, on a vacant piece of land now bounded on the north by Eighth South Street and on the east by Fifth West Street. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">There was no restriction on the sale of supplies to them; but as the harvest was not fully gathered, it being the early part of August, and prices for grain were high in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, the emigrants refrained from making large purchases of this commodity, for the reason that they believed they could get it cheaper farther along on their journey, in the settlements of southern <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</seg></note> 

<pb n="791" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.791"/>

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">they were attacked by a large force of Indians, gathered there by <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, the Indian agent; that when the savages were repulsed messengers were sent to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> asking the whites to render assistance in carrying out the <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">previously arranged plan of destroying <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the entire emigrant company</seg></seg></seg>; that a military order was issued, and a body of militia sent to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, ostensibly to bury massacred emigrants; that on arrival it was found too hazardous an undertaking to attack the camp of the emigrants, therefore <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">the latter were decoyed out by a flag of truce and induced to surrender their arms, under a promise of protection; that as they were marching along, at a given signal they were assailed by the combined force of militia and Indians, and murdered</seg></seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">only seventeen children, all under eight years of age, being spared</seg>; that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">the bodies of the slaughtered emigrants were stripped by Indians and left unburied, to be preyed on by wild beasts</seg>; that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">on the field of murder <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> directed affairs and afterwards took possession of the emigrants' property, <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">reporting the whole transaction to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, who told him not to talk about it</seg>, and ordered the property given to the Church;</seg> that the commander of the whole southern country, from <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName> to <placeName type="state" key="Arizona">Arizona</placeName>, was <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>; that under him <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName> commanded the <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName> militia, and next to him <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName> were over the forces called out to do the bloody work; that by the perfect enforcement of a military order for the massacre, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">not a single emigrant escaped, though some of them succeeded in getting away from the scene of the butchery and were not overtaken by their murderers for several days</seg>.</p> 

<p>The taking of testimony then began, the first witness being <persName key="Keyes, Robert">Robert Keyes</persName>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">He stated that he was returning from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> and passed through <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> on the 2nd of October, 1857; he there saw the nude forms of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">sixty or seventy men, women and children, who had been shot or otherwise killed</seg>, and whose bodies had been torn by the wolves.</seg> The next witness, <persName key="Bennett, Ashael">Ashael Bennett</persName>, testified that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">in December of the same year he saw many of the skeletons, which had been torn out of their shallow graves by the wolves.</seg></p> 

<pb n="792" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.792"/> 

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith">At this point in the trial a <hi rend="italic">nolle prosegui</hi> was entered in the case of <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>, and he was sworn as a witness. His story was as follows. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Some days before the emigrants reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName> he heard that the people had been forbidden to trade with them. On their arrival at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar</placeName> a Mr. <persName key="Jackson, Samuel, Sr.">Jackson</persName> sold them some wheat.</seg><ref target="n17">*</ref> <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">Several of them went swearing about town and created a disturbance, and were taken before <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName> and fined. The emigrants continued on their way and witness heard "hard rumors" about their conduct.</seg> At the regular meeting of the local presidency and high council, on the Sunday preceding the arrival of the emigrants, the matter of their attitude toward the settlers and Indians came up. <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Witness</persName> was then acting in the capacity of Bishop of Cedar Ward. He, with <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">I. C. Haight</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">J. M. Higbee</persName>, <persName key="Morrill, Laban">Laban Morrill</persName>, <persName key="Allen, Ira">Ira Allen</persName>, <persName key="Willis, Wesley">Wesley Willis</persName> and others attended this meeting. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">A proposition to permit the emigrants to be destroyed was strongly opposed by a number of those present.</seg> <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> said that he was among those averse to it. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">At that time the destruction was intended by Indians, and not by 
whites.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The question was, what would the consequence be if the whites permitted such a thing to take place.</seg> The next day, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, <persName key="White, Joel W.">Joel W. White</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> again met and talked the matter over. Witness said that he again expressed himself in favor of allowing the emigrants to pass through unmolested, and <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> said to him, "You may go with Mr. <persName key="White, Joel">White</persName> over to <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Painter Creek, [Pinto]</placeName>. He will tell the people there." <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">The purpose was to pacify the Indians so that the emigrants could get through.</seg> <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Witness</persName> and <persName key="White, Joel">White</persName> went as directed, passing <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">the emigrant company at Iron Springs, en route to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName></seg>. On their way they met <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, who inquired, "Where are you going?" to which <persName key="White, Joel">White</persName> responded, "We are going to see that these people get through unmolested." <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> said, "I have something to say in that matter, and will see to it," and passed on toward <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar</placeName>.<ref target="n18">&#8224;</ref> On their return </seg>

<note xml:id="n17">* When on the witness stand Mr. <persName key="Jackson, Samuel, Sr.">Jackson</persName> denied the truth of this statement.</note> 

<note xml:id="n18">&#8224; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> denied that this incident ever occurred, and said that he was with the Indians at the time it was alleged to have taken place. He, however, admits being in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName> during this absence of <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, and says: <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">"<persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> said he had sent <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and others over towards <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Pinto</placeName>, and around there, to stir up the Indians and force them to attack the emigrants." The testimony of all the witnesses acquainted with this transaction, as well as the events which occurred at the time, prove <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement of the errand of <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and his associate to be incorrect.</seg></note> 

<pb n="793" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.793"/>  

<seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith">from <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Painter Creek</placeName> they met <persName key="Allen, Ira">Ira Allen</persName>, about four miles from where they passed <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> the day before, and he informed them that when the emigrants got to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> their doom was sealed, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">for <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D.Lee</persName> had orders from headquarters at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName></seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">to gather Indians, go around below and destroy the company.</seg> <persName key="Allen, Ira">Allen</persName> also had orders to go to <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Painter Creek</placeName> and undo what <persName key="White, Joel">White</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> had done.</seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> stated that he and <persName key="White, Joel">White</persName> then went home. About three days afterwards <persName key="McFarlane, Dan">Dan McFarlane</persName> came to him from <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, saying that he had received word from <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> that "they hadn't got along as they anticipated."<ref target="n19">*</ref> <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> had communicated with Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, said the witness, and had received orders that, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">to finish the massacre, they were to "decoy them out</seg>, and to <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">spare nothing</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">but small children that could not tell the tale</seg>." At the direction of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, witness went down town, where he met Major <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName>, who said, "You are ordered out, armed and </seg>

<note xml:id="n19">* In making this statement, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> omitted all mention of the proceedings of an entire week. During that time councils were held at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> and <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, at which it was determined that the emigrants should be protected from molestation. A few persons suggested that, as the emigrants had declared themselves as enemies, they should be intercepted and treated as such; and in the <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar</placeName> councils there were some, notably <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, who advocated an immediate attack upon the camp. A proposition prevailed that a courier be sent to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, with dispatches detailing the provocation to hostilities that had been given, noting the Indian desire for revenge, and asking his advice in regard to the situation. Lieutenant Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">I. C. Haight</persName> wrote and forwarded these dispatches by <persName key="Haslam, James H.">James H. Haslam</persName>. He also sent word to <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> to pacify the Indians and keep the emigrants from harm till further orders. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">When this message reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Pinto</placeName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and the Indians had gone to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, and before it was received there the first attack had been made.</seg></seg> (See Vol. I., p. 701.) <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">The witness also failed to relate how two of the emigrants, who had broken through the Indian lines under cover of darkness and were going to the settlements for assistance, were met in the cedars by a party commanded by himself. "Both the emigrants were killed, one of them falling, it is said, by <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>'s own hand.'</seg> (Vol. I., p. 704.)</note> 

<pb n="794" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.794"/>  

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">equipped as the law directs, to go to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain Meadows</geogName>." He, with a number of others, obeyed and went as militia, arriving at <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName>'s ranch, three miles from the eimgrants' camp, in the night. There was militia from <placeName type="county" key="Washington County, UT">Washington County</placeName>, as well as <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName>, there under orders. The men began to find out that all the emigrants were not killed, as had been represented. Then there was a consultation between <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, <persName key="Hopkins, Charles">Hopkins</persName>, <persName key="Allen, Ira">Allen</persName>, <persName key="Wiley, Robert">Wiley</persName>, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and a few others who were called aside by <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, about the instructions that had come through <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, from Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>.<ref target="n20">*</ref> <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> stated that tie emigrants were strongly fortified, and Major <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> replied that they must be got out in any way possible.<ref target="n21">&#8224;</ref> Everything was given into <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s hands to carry out; so he formed the militia, numbering forty or fifty men, into a hollow square, and addressed them on the work that they were expected to perform. <ref target="n22">&#8225;</ref> There was some murmuring among the men, who asked among themselves what they could do, and the conclusion was that </seg>

<note xml:id="n20">* <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in his second confession, alleges that <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> said: "<persName key="Haight, Isaac C>">Haight</persName> has counseled with Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, or has had orders from him to get all of the emigrants out of the way. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">None who are old enough to talk are to be spared</seg>."</seg></note> 

<note xml:id="n21">&#8224; <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">It is also asserted by <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in his published confession, that <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> handed him a written order from Lieutenant-Colonel <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, in which he, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, and those with him were directed to decoy the emigrants out of their stronghold and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">kill all that could talk</seg>. He says these were "the orders of our military superir, that we were hound to obey."</seg></seg></note> 

<note xml:id="n22">&#8225; <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">This was on the morning of the fateful day of the massacre&#8212;<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">Friday, September llth</seg>. "There is no doubt that until he [<persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>] reached <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> the fatal order for the massacre had not been received. When he arrived he conferred with the leaders, and then for the first time was there talk as to the plan of attack. He brought encouragement and strength to those, if any there were who were bent upon destroying the company&#8212;which had been his own plan in all the councils held at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar</placeName> and he undoubtedly gave the impression that the superior officer of the militia had given orders to that effect. <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, who as major of battalion was in command of militia on the ground, was of equal rank with <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, though much younger in years. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was also major, but at this time devoted himself more especially to the Indian forces. It was <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, however, who seemed to have the direction of affairs, and it is not unlikely that <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, by his ardor and represetations he was the latest arrival from <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar</placeName> had more influence in the subsequent coucils than anyone else."</seg> (Vol. I., p. 705.)</note> 

<pb n="795" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.795"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">they could not help themselves, but must obey orders as soldiers. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">They then marched out, as commanded, and waited while a flag of truce was sent to the emigrant camp. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had a long conference with <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a man from the camp after which the emigrants came out, the children, wounded persons and arms being in the baggage wagons; the women walking next, and the men last. The men marched alongside of the militia, in single or double file, and the women and wagons were a short distnce ahead</seg>. They had gone two hundred yards or more when the order was given to "Halt!" This was immediately followed by the command "Fire!"</seg></seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> went on to testify that he was in the militia
ranks at the time when the order to halt and fire was given. "Every man fired as far as I know. I fired once," said he. He was about twenty feet from the nearet emigrant.</seg></seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">In response to an inqiry by the defendant's counsel, "You first shot over his head, I presume?" the witness responded, "I didn't think I did. I would not swear that I hit him or not. I might have hit him."</seg></seg></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Question:</hi> "Didn't you make an effort to hit him?"</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer:</hi> "Of coure I did; obeying orders to the fullest capacity."</p>

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The witness proceeded with his narrative, saying that he thought there were about fifty men among the emigrants. He further said that<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors"> <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> directed him to take charge of the children. One of these was wounded severely, and subsequently died. The witness did as he was commanded, and collected seventeen children, whom he afterwards distributed with families in <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName> and other places.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">By instruction of <persName key="Haight, Issac C.">Haight</persName>, he also took charge of some of the property of the emigrants which the Indians had not carried off. He did not take it, however, in the capacity of Bishop, but only to store it, awaiting orders. This property was afterwards disposed of at auction.</seg> It was aranged that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> should report the whole transaction, as directed by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, to Governor
<persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> informed the witness, in the following October, that he 

<pb n="796" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.796"/> 

had done so.<ref target="n23">*</ref> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">After this, the witness, with <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> and <persName key="Hopkins, Charles">Charles Hopkins</persName>, had called upon the Governor [<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>] and the latter directed <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, as Indian agent and interpreter, to take charge of the property left by the emigrants.</seg> Nothing was said at that time of the circumstances of the massacre; as <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">the Governor remarked that he did not wish to hear it talked of.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">At the time of the massacre "the hills were full of Indians" who took part in the butchery.</seg></seg></seg></p> 

<p>In response to a question by Mr. <persName key="Bakin, Robert N.">Baskin</persName>: "Do you know whether any of those orders that led to that massacre emanated from <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, and if so state what it was?" <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> said: "No, sir; not that I know of."</p> 

<p><seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The witness admitted that he received and kept a span of mules and two wagons which had belonged to the emigrants.</seg> He had resigned the office of Bishop of Cedar Ward in 1858 or 1859, and moved away shortly afterward. About 1870 he heard that he had been cut off from the Mormon Church. Before he became a resident of <placeName type="state" key="Nevada">Nevada</placeName> he had only stated the facts regarding the massacre to one man&#8212;<persName key="Dalton, Charles">Charles Dalton</persName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s son-in-law. He had not conversed on the subject with <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>, nor did he, when <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> said that he would rather <persName key="Buchanan, James">Buchanan</persName> should hear of all the men in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> being killed than give his consent to the killing of women and children, reply, <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">"If you break out that way around the mouth, we will have to take care of you."</seg> During the consultations at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> he had not raised his voice against the proposed slaughter because he "had no authority to do so." He denied, however, having advocated the commission of the deed.</seg></seg></p> 

<p>Such was the statement of the witness <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>. In it the 
inconsistency which usually marks efforts of criminals to shield themselves at the expense of others is glaringly manifest. Here was 

<note xml:id="n23">* <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Whether or not <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> acted under <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>'s advice in reporting to the Governor, it is certain that he did not relate the facts of the case. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">He placed the blame entirely upon the Indians, without intimating that any white man was connected with the crime. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">He explained the presence of the surviving children in the settlements by saying that the Indians had sold them to the whites.</seg></seg></seg></note> 

<pb n="797" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.797"/>  

an individual who, because he "had no authority," was too much overawed to raise his voice in protest against the perpetration of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a soul-sickening slaughter, not only of men, but of women and children</seg>. Yet his obscurity did not preclude his presence in convocations of the most influential men at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and again in the councils of the leading spirits at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>; nor did it prevent him from being among the foremost spokesmen on each occasion. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">His prominence was such that he was given charge of
the surviving children, apportioning them among the people</seg>, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">he also gathered into his possession that portion of the emigrants' baggage which had not been carried off by the savages</seg>. In an ecclesiastical capacity, the majority of the men who composed the  body of militia at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> were under his supervision, and he had heard among them murmurings of dissatisfaction which only required a word of encouragement from him to break forth in such volume as to change the entire situation. His whole course showed that he was fully <hi rend="italic">en rapport</hi> with the murderous scheme, if indeed he was not its chief promoter.<ref target="n24">*</ref> Careful examination of the deplorable event <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">at Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg> makes it clear that if any man within reach of the law officers ought to have been prosecuted with <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, that man was <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>.<ref target="n25">&#8224;</ref></p> 

<p><persName key="White, Joel">Joel W. White</persName> was the fourth witness. He had been brought to 
<placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> by the notorious <persName key="Hickman, Bill">Bill Hickman</persName>, who had been made a special U. S. Deputy Marshal. <persName key="White, Joel">White</persName> testified that he and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> had taken the message to <persName key="Robinson, Richard">Richard Robinson</persName>, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Painter Creek</placeName>, to 

<note xml:id="n24">* <persName key="Pearce, James">James Pearce</persName>, a witness who resided in <placeName type="county" key="Washington County, UT">Washington County</placeName>, testified that he regarded <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> as "one of the officers, as he seemed to have a good deal to say about it frequently;" that "he was the biggest chief there."</note> 

<note xml:id="n25">&#8224; <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">Statements such as those made by <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and others have been the basis of charging the massacre to men "high in authority" among the Mormons, yet the highest officials which these accounts, in their broadest scope, can be made to implicate are <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> and <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, Colonel and Lieutenant-Colonel of the <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName> militia, and the former is only included by hearsay testimony. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says that he received written instructions from <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and heard the latter say that his orders were from Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> an assertion which the latter denied.</seg></note>

<pb n="798" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.798"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">pacify the Indians. He related the incident of meeting <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> the same 
as <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, but did not remember seeing <persName key="Allen, Ira">Ira Allen</persName> on the return trip. After he had been home several days he was called out as a militia-man by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">I. C. Haight</persName>, and ordered to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> with a baggage wagon. He was there two days before the massacre, camped a short distance from, and out of sight of the emigrants. According to his testimony, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> were the most prominent men in the movements at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>.<ref target="n2">*</ref> The witness related the circumstances of the killing, as previously given, 
but said that he took no part therein, as he had no gun.</seg></p> 

<p>Mrs. <persName key="Hoag, Annie Elizabeth">Annie Elizabeth Hoag</persName>, <persName key="Willis, Thomas T.">Thomas T. Willis</persName>, <persName key="Willis, John H.">John H. Willis</persName>, 
<persName key="Mathews, William">William Mathews</persName>, <persName key="Young, William">William Young</persName>, <persName key="Pollock, Samuel">Samuel Pollock</persName>, <persName key="Sherratt, John">John Sherratt</persName>, 
<persName key="Bradshaw, John Wl.">John W. Bradshaw</persName>, <persName key="Kershaw, Robert">Robert Kershaw</persName>, <persName key="Mathews, E. C.">E. C. Mathews</persName>, <persName key="Pearce, James">James Pearce</persName>, 
<persName key="Thomopson, E. W.">E. W. Thompson</persName>, <persName key="McFarlane, John M.">John M. McFarlane</persName>, <persName key="King, Frank">Frank King</persName>, <persName key="Riddle, Isaac">Isaac Riddle</persName> and 
<persName key="Roberts, William">William Roberts</persName> were examined as witnesses and the prosecution 
rested.<ref target="n27">&#8224;</ref> No information beyond that given in the published account of the massacre (Volume I) was elicited.</p>

<p>The statement of what the defense expected to prove was made 

<note xml:id="n26">* This statement was corroborated by the other witnesses who were on the ground, with the exception of <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>.</note>

<note xml:id="n27">&#8224; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><persName key="Pollock, Samuel">Samuel Pollock</persName> stated that he overlooked the proceedings of the massacre from nearly a mile distant.<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"> He estimated that from four to five hundred Indians, beside the whites, were engaged in the work.</seg></seg></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">After it was all over he went down to the place and helped bury the dead, whom he thought <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">numbered about one hundred</seg>. The ground was so hard that it was impossible to dig it, so the burying party put most of the bodies in a wash or gully, and the others in some depressions in the ground, and covered them with about four feet of dirt.</seg> 

<seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar"><persName key="Kershaw, Robert">Robert Kershaw</persName> testified that <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName> preached at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> that the people were not to sell <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrant company</seg> grain, as they might need it for themselves, because of the approach of <persName key="Johnston, Albert Sidney">Johnston</persName>'s army.</seg> He also said that a man named <persName key="Morgan, John">John Morgan</persName> was cut off the Church by Bishop <persName key="Farnsworth, P. T.">P. T. Farnsworth</persName>, two weeks after the emigrant company passed through, for trading a cheese to them. Bishop <persName key="Farnsworth, P. T.">Farnsworth</persName> testified that <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName> made no reference to the emigrants, as he was not aware, when in <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, of their presence in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, but advised the people not to feed grain to their animals or to sell it for that purpose, as they were likely to need it. He also stated that <persName key="Morgan, John">John Morgan</persName> was never cut off the Church, or dealt with in any way, for trading with the emigrants; on the contrary, when he left <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, Bishop <persName key="Farnsworth, P. T.">Farnsworth</persName> gave him a recommend of full fellowship and good standing in the Church.</seg></note> 

<pb n="799" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.799"/>  

on July 29th, by Attorney <persName key="Spicer, Wells">Wells Spicer</persName>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">He said that <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">the emigrants, by their own misconduct in poisoning cattle and springs of water</seg>, so 
enraged the Indians that from Corn Creek down runners were sent out, gathering help from the various tribes, till<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"> at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName></seg> the savages numbered four or five hundred warriors, who there attacked the company</seg></seg>; that <seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">on the route thither the whites sold the emigrants supplies and treated them well</seg>; <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> held no military or Church office, but was merely a farmer to the Indians;<ref target="n28">*</ref> that on the ground he tried to protect the emigrants, and wept when the massacre was proposed; that <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName> formed the plot to kill the emigrants, and that what was done by the other white men there was through obedience to the military authority of the three persons named, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">from fear of death at the hands of the Indians if the small force of militia present did not join in the attack on the emigrants</seg>.</seg></p> 

<p><persName key="Pollock, Samuel">Samuel Pollock</persName> and <persName key="Young, William">William Young</persName>, who had been witnesses for the prosecution, were called by the defense, but nothing new was elicited.</p> 

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS"><persName key="Smith, Jesse N.">Jesse N. Smith</persName> stated that at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> he sold the emigrants flour and salt, and urged them to purchase more, but they did not desire to do so. He traveled in company with <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName> and others to <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, and knew that no instructions were given not to trade with the emigrants; but the people were advised not to feed their grain to animals or to sell it for that purpose, as they would probably need all that they had.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">A few days after the company of emigrants passed <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, the witness heard that they had been attacked by Indians, and was sent by Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> to ascertain if it was true. He went as far as <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Pinto</placeName>, where the rumor was verified, and returned and reported to Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">This was on Friday, September llth, and he afterwards learned that it was the day of the massacre.</seg></p> 

<note xml:id="n28">* <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, according to his own statement, was at the time of the massacre Probate Judge of <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName>, and "president of civil and local affairs" in the <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName> district (which included <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>) but had no control in Church matters.</note> 

<pb n="800" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.800"/> 

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS"><persName key="Smith, Silas S.">Silas S. Smith</persName> corroborated the testimony of the previous
witness in regard to <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>'s instructions,</seg> and stated that 
he (the witness) was sent by Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>; <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">with a small body of men, to relieve Duke's company of emigrants when they were attacked by Indians, and that he did so.</seg><ref target="n29">*</ref> <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">This was immediately succeeding the report made to Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> by <persName key="Smith, Jesse N.">Jesse N. Smith</persName>. <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">The witness saw the dead ox left at Corn Creek by the Fancher company, and heard one of the party inquire whether the Indians would eat it.</seg></seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison"><persName key="Hoops, Elisha">Elisha Hoops</persName> testified as to the poisoning of the ox left at Corn Creek. He saw a German doctor with the Fancher company make three incisions in the animal, and pour the contents of a vial therein. Some Indians came up soon afterward and the ox was sold to them for two buckskins. They flayed it, but he did not think at the time that they intended to eat the flesh. He also gave evidence of that company of emigrants leaving small bags of poison in the springs. A boy named <persName key="Robinson, ">Robinson</persName> drank the water from one spring, and died from the effects. The Indians afterwards told witness that some of their number met their death in the same way and from the same cause.</seg></p> 

<p><persName key="Farnsworth, P. T.">Philo T. Farnsworth</persName>, <persName key="Hamilton, John, Sr.">John Hamilton, Sr.</persName>, <persName key="Hamilton, John, Jr.">John Hamilton, Jr.</persName>, <persName key="Robinson, Richard">Richard Robinson</persName>, <persName key="Jackson, Samuel, Sr.">Samuel Jackson, Sr.</persName>, and <persName key="McFarlane, John M.">John M. McFarlane</persName> gave their testimony, which was merely corroborative of the statements of the others, no additional facts of importance being brought out.<ref target="n30">&#8224;</ref></p> 

<p>The defense offered in evidence the affidavits of Presidents <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName>, who were in too feeble health to attend court, but the prosecution objected, and Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName> refused to permit their introduction.<ref target="n31">&#8225;</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n29">* See page 693, Vol. I.</note> 

<note xml:id="n30">&#8224; <persName key="Robinson, Richard">Richard Robinson</persName> was Indian overseer at <placeName type="settlement" key="Pinto, UT">Pinto</placeName>, and denied ever receiving the letter or message which <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and <persName key="White, Joel">White</persName> claimed to have carried. Several days after the alleged date of the delivery by these witnesses, he received, by another messenger, a letter from <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> for <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, and forwarded it to the latter at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>.</note> 

<note xml:id="n31">&#8225; These affidavits were used by the prosecution at the second trial, in September, 1876.</note> 

<pb n="801" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.801"/>  

<p>The jury then listened to the arguments of the attorneys. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The speech of Mr. <persName key="Baskin, Robert N.">Baskin</persName> was a bitter attack upon the Mormon people, whom he alleged to be responsible for the delay in taking up the Mountain Meadows massacre, because "Mormons would not punish Mormons for such crimes."</seg><ref target="n32">*</ref> He declared that Mormons "gave up all manhood, all individuality when they entered the Endowment House." He gave the jurors to understand that the Government did not anticipate conviction, and charged a failure in that respect to the religion of the majority. </p>

<p>The case was submitted on the 5th of August, and on the afternoon of the 7th the jurors were discharged, having failed to agree upon a verdict. They had stood nine for acquittal and three for conviction.</p> 

<p>So closed the first trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>. Its failure was due to the fact that the prosecution of the case was improperly conducted. Instead of an action to punish the guilty, it was an effort on the part 
of the U. S. District Attorney and his coadjutors to bring within the shadow of an awful crime the leading authorities of the Mormon Church.<ref target="n33">&#8224;</ref> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">In the vain attempt to accomplish this object they had deliberately released a self-confessed assassin, one of the chief promoters and participators in the terrible tragedy.</seg> There is little doubt that the status of this latter-day Barrabas, as an apostate 

<note xml:id="n32">* <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> at his second trial was convicted of murder in the first degree by a jury composed entirely of Mormons.</note> 

<note xml:id="n33">&#8224; The <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi>, the mouthpiece of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> anti-Mormonism, openly avowed the purpose of the prosecution in the following comment upon <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s first confession, the one rejected by the District Attorney and his associates: "The prosecuting officers, in dealing with this great crime, were less desirous to convict and punish the prisoner than to get at the long concealed facts of that case. The impression that there was 'some person (or persons) high in the estimation of the people' at the bottom of the affair had grown to be a settled conviction; and as <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had been a subordinate actor in the massacre it was thought that the ends of justice would be attained by releasing this man if he was honest in his avowed resolution to tell it all." <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">When the second trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> came on in 1876, the <hi rend="italic">Tribune</hi> said: "There was this peculiarity in the trial of last year&#8212;the conviction of the prisoner was not so much an object with the prosecution as the procurement of such testimony as would fix the crime of this wholesale assassination upon men higher up in the Church."</seg></note>

<pb n="802" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.802"/> 

Mormon, full of bitterness and rancor against his former brethren, secured, for him, quite as much as his highly-colored testimony, immunity from punishment. His harrowing tale of blood, though it* purchased his own safety, utterly failed to fasten guilt upon the foreordained victims of anti-Mormon malice.</p> 

</div1>
<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="803" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.803"/>  

<head>CHAPTER XXIX.</head> 

<head>1875-1877.</head> 

<head>JOHN D. LEE'S SECOND TRIAL&#8212;A CHANGE IN THE OFFICES OF U. S. DISTRICT ATTORNEY AND MARSHAL&#8212;SUMNER HOWARD'S SENSIBLE SPEECH "I HAVE NOT COME TO TRY BRIGHAM YOUNG AND THE MORMON CHURCH, BUT JOHN D. LEE"&#8212;THE FACTS CONCERNING THE MOUNTAIN MEADOWS MASSACRE DETAILED BY EYE-WITNESSES&#8212;AFFIDAVITS OF PRESIDENTS BRIGHAM YOUNG AND GEORGE A. SMITH&#8212;OTHER DOCUMENTARY EVIDENCE LEE'S CONFESSIONS&#8212;HE IS CONVICTED OF MURDER IN THE FIRST DEGREE&#8212;JUDGE BOREMAN'S UNWARRANTABLE ASSAULT UPON THE MORMON LEADERS&#8212;LEE'S EXECUTION AT MOUNTAIN MEADOWS.</head> 

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">IMMEDIATELY after the close of the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> trial the prisoner was taken to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> and lodged in the Penitentiary. Continued efforts were made for the apprehension of the other persons indicted. On September 12th of this year&#8212;1875&#8212;the houses of <persName key="Macfarlane, John">John Macfarlane</persName> and <persName key="Branch, W. H.">W. H. Branch</persName>, at St. George, were searched by deputy marshals for <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> and <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, but they were not found. <persName key="Adair, George, Jr.">George Adair, Jr.</persName>, was arrested near <placeName type="settlement" key="Richfield, UT">Richfield</placeName> on the 1st of November, and placed in jail at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>.</seg><ref target="n34">*</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n34">* <seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">About this time a petition dated at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, Sept. 1st, and signed by a considerable number of Gentiles, was received by Governor <persName key="Emery, George W.">Emery</persName>. It asked that he use his influence to prevent the removal of any troops from Fort Cameron, (one company of them had been ordered elsewhere,) and among the reasons for this request alleged that the late trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was considered as persecution of the Mormon people and an attempt to overthrow the Mormon Church, and that were it not for the presence of the military at this post, such feelings and hatred as were every day manifest would culminate in overt acts of rebellion against the civil authorities representing the national government, and the courts would be powerless to execute the laws.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">Said the petitioners: "The Indians are cajoled and baptized into the Mormon Church and told that they are 'battle-axes of the Lord,' many of them were encamped about this place during the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, and on several occasions inquired when the Mormons and 'Mericats' were going to war. The very fact that we cannot understand all the Indian movements, concurring with other events, such as the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, makes our suspicion all the stronger, and indeed so as to appeal to those in authority to have their actions closely and persistently watched by the government. A large number of Navajoes were recently prevented from crossing the Colorado River by the Indian agents. Over three hundred Utes and Piutes were recently baptized into the Mormon Church. * * * At the present time several Mormon missionaries are preaching to the Indians in Arizona."</seg> 

It is perhaps needless to say that most of the foregoing statements were malicious falsehoods. <seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">When Governor <persName key="Emery, George W.">Emery</persName> applied in the following May for two companies of troops for <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, the <hi rend="italic">Square-Dealer</hi>, a non-Mormon paper published there, made this comment: "It is not our purpose to quarrel with the Governor on the soldier proposition. They are a moneyed institution, and the Lord knows we are not going to object to an increase of that article. When Cameron had four full companies of soldiers the citizens of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> had money, and the newspaper business was a flourishing one. If anybody imagines we are opposed to seeing good times again, they have mistaken us&#8212;that's all. Send on your soldiers, Governor <persName key="Emery, George W.">Emery</persName>, only Cameron will take four companies instead of two."</seg></note> 

<pb n="804" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.804"/> 

<p>The <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> cases were passed at the September term of court, owing to "lack of funds" for the expenses of the prosecution. The Grand Jury, in December, made a report which stated that a searching investigation revealed the fact that, while little or nothing had been paid out, the Marshal's books, by false entries, represented unpaid accounts as settled; and that out of $13,200 allowed for the expenses of the court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, only about eight thousand dollars had been in any way accounted for. General <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> explained that the $13,200 had not been intended for the Second District Court expenses alone, but for the whole <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Territory</placeName>, and he maintained that it had been properly expended. A letter from the U. S. Attorney-General, <persName key="Pierrepont, Edwards">Edwards Pierrepont</persName>, however, stated that the amount was "to defray the expenses of the United States court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver City</placeName>." <ref target="n35">*</ref> <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> was removed from office early in the following February, and Colonel <persName key="Nelson, William">William Nelson</persName>, who had been editor of the <placeName type="settlement" key="La Crosse, WI">La Crosse</placeName> Republican Leader, was appointed his successor, assuming the duties of the position on the 15th of March.<ref target="n36">&#8224;</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n35">* The crookedness in the Marshal's office was exposed in the Second District by U. S. Deputy Marshal <persName key="Cross, Jerome B.">Jerome B. Cross</persName>, and in the Third District by U. S. Deputy Marshal <persName key="Pratt, Arthur">Arthur Pratt</persName>. There was no imputation of dishonesty as to General <persName key="Maxwell, George R.">Maxwell</persName> himself. The accusations were against some whom he employed in his office, and who, it was alleged, took advantage of his loose manner of conducting business.</note> 

<note xml:id="n36">&#8224; On March 14th, the day of Colonel <persName key="Nelson, William">Nelson</persName>'s arrival at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, seven of the most hardened convicts in the Penitentiary made an assault on the Warden, Captain <persName key="Burgher, Mathew B.">Bergher</persName>, whom they mortally wounded. They then succeeded in making their escape, but were afterwards retaken. On a subsequent occasion the murderers of Captain <persName key="Burgher, Mathew B.">Bergher</persName> succeeded in breaking from the prison and eluding all efforts for their recapture.</note> 

<pb n="805" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.805"/>

<p>The Mountain Meadows case was again called up in court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> on the 8th of May, 1876, but was postponed till the September term. The defendants under arrest <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Adair, George W., Jr.">Adair</persName> were released on bail, in the respective sums of twenty, fifteen and ten thousand dollars. One more was added to the list of those in custody, by the arrest, at St. George on August 28th, of <persName key="Wilden, Elliott">Elliott Wilden</persName>.</p> 

<p>The second trial of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> began before Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName>, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, on September 14th of that year. There had been a change in the office of U. S. District Attorney by this time and <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Sumner Howard</persName> now filled the position; <persName key="Denny, Presley">Presley Denny</persName> was associated with him as assistant. The attorneys for the defendant were <persName key="Foster, J. C.">J. C. Foster</persName>, <persName key="Spicer, Wells">Wells Spicer</persName> and <persName key="Bishop, William W.">W. W. Bishop</persName>. Of the witnesses placed on the stand,<persName key="White, Joel"> Joel W. White</persName> was the only one who had testified at the former trial. <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> was at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, but was seldom seen and avoided conversation or inquiry. He is said to have looked dejected and worn. When the case was concluded he departed for his new home at <placeName type="settlement" key="Ehrenberg, AZ">Ehrenberg, Arizona</placeName>. He never again returned to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</p> 

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">In the opening statement of the case Mr. <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName> made the sensible observation that he had not come to try <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and the Mormon Church, but to proceed against <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> for his personal actions. The Government, he said, proposed to prove that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, without any authority or advice from any council or officer, but in direct opposition to the feelings and wishes of the leaders of the Mormon Church,<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"> had gone to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain Meadows</geogName> and assumed command of the Indians, whom he induced to attack the emigrants</seg>, in which movement he was repulsed; that he sent word to various settlements for assistance, to some saying that the emigrants were all killed and needed to be buried, to others that they required protection and to still others that an attack on the company had been

<pb n="806" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.806"/> 

made by the Indians, and it needed men to draw them off: that these men went in good faith to perform a humane act; that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">arranged the scheme to draw the emigrants out of their camp and have them fired upon by Indians and some of the whites</seg>; that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">killed at least four of them himself</seg>, and that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">he took a part of property for his own use</seg></seg>.</p> 

<p>Mr. Bishop's statement for the defense was mainly denunciat of the character of the evidence about to be introduced. He claimed that the part <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> took in the massacre was under compulsion, and that other parties were the instigators and were responsible for the crime.</p> 

<p>For the Government, Mr. <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName> presented the following documents, which were admitted in evidence.<ref target="n37">*</ref></p> 

<p>TERRITORY OF UTAH,	SS
BEAVER COUNTY,</p>  

<p>IN THE SECOND JUDICIAL DISTRICT COURT. THE PEOPLE, ETC., VS. JOHN D. LEE, WILLIAM H. DAME. ISAAC C. HAIGHT <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, INDICTMENT FOR MURDER, SEPTEMBER 16th. 1857. </p>

<p><hi rend="center">AFFIDAVIT OF BRIGHAM YOUNG.</hi></p> 

<p>Questions to be propounded to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> on his examination as witness in the case of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> and others, on trial at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver City</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, this 30th day of July, 1875, and the said answers of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> to the interrogatories hereto appended were reduced to writing, and were given after the said <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> had been duly sworn to testify to the truth in the above entitled cause, and are as follows:</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">First</hi>.&#8212;State your age, and the present condition of your health, and whether in your present condition you could travel to attend in person at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, the court now there? If not, state why?</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;To the first interrogatory he says: I am in my seventy-fifth year.  It would be a great risk, both to my health and life for me to travel to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> at this time. I am, and have been for some time, an invalid.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Second</hi>.&#8212;What offices, either ecclesiastical, civil or military, did you hold in year 1857?</p>

<note xml:id="n37">* The first two had been offered by the counsel for the defense at the first trial, but the Court then ruled them out. When they were presented on this occasion, Mr. <persName key="Biship, William W.">Bishop</persName> said to the Court: "In the former trial we came near being placed in jail for offering the same papers."</note> 

<pb n="807" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.807"/> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;I was the Governor of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this Territory</placeName>, and ex-officio Superintendent of Indian affairs, and the President of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, during the year 1857.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Third</hi>.&#8212;State the condition of affairs between <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory of Utah</placeName> and the Federal Government in the summer and fall of 1857 ?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">In May or June, 1857, the United States mails for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> were stopped by the Government, and all communication by mail was cut off; an army of the United States was en route for <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, with the ostensible design of destroying the Latter-day Saints, according to the reports that reached us from the East.</seg></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi>.&#8212;Were there any United States judges here during the summer and fall of 1857?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;To the best of my recollection there was no United States Judge here in the latter part of 1857.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Fifth</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">State what you know about trains of emigrants passing through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> to the West, and particularly about a company <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">en route for <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>, passing through this city in the summer or fall of 1857?</seg></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">As usual, emigrant trains were passing through our Territory for the West. I heard it rumored that <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">a company from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">en route to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>, had passed through the city.</seg></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Sixth</hi>.&#8212;Was this <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">Arkansas company</seg> of emigrants ordered away from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> by yourself or anyone in authority under you?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;No, not that I know of. I never heard of any such thing, and certainly no such order was given by the acting Governor.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Seventh</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Was any counsel or instruction given by any person to the citizens of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> not to sell grain, or trade with the emigrant trains passing through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> at that time?</seg> If so what were those instructions and that counsel?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Yes, counsel and advice was given to the citizens not to sell grain to the emigrants to feed their stock, but let them have sufficient for themselves if they were out. <seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">The simple reason for this was that for several years our crops had been short, and the prospect was at that time that we might have trouble with the United States army, then en route for this place; and we wanted to preserve the grain for food.</seg> The citizens of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> were counseled not to feed grain even to their own stock. No person was ever punished or called in question for furnishing supplies to the emigrants, within my knowledge.</seg></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Eighth</hi>.&#8212;When did you first hear of the attack and destruction of <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> company</seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in September, 1857</seg>?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;I did not learn anything of the attack or destruction of <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg> company until sometime after it had occurred, then only by a floating rumor.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Ninth</hi>.&#8212;Did <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> report to you at any time after this massacre what had been done at that massacre, and if so what did you reply to him in reference thereto?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">Within some two or three months after the massacre he called at my office and had much to say with regard to the Indians, their being stirred up to anger and threatening the settlements of the whites, and then commenced giving an account of the

<pb n="808" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.808"/> 

massacre.</seg> I told him to stop, as from what I had already learned by rumor I did not wish my feelings harrowed up with a recital of the details.<ref target="n38">*</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n38">* <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> says, in his published confession, "When I arrived in the city I went to the President's house and gave to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> a full, detailed statement of the whole affair, from first to last only I took rather more on myself than I had done." What <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> actually told Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> was in accord with the agreement made by the leaders of the massacre on the field, when they feared Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> would report the whole truth. In the private journal of <persName key="Woodruff, Wilford">Wilford Woodruff</persName>, under date of September 29th, 1857, it is noted that <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> called on the Governor, and in the presence of Mr. <persName key="Woodruff, Wilford">Woodruff</persName> related "an awful tale of blood. <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">He told how a company of emigrants, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">numbering about one hundred and fifty men, women and children</seg>, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">had poisoned beef for the Indians, and springs of water</seg>, and been guilty of other wrongs, till <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">the Indians became enraged, surrounded them on the prairie, and fought them five or six days until <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">all the white men, about sixty in number, were killed</seg></seg>.</seg></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">Then the savages rushed upon the emigrants' corral and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">killed the women and children</seg>, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">except about ten of the latter, whom they sold to the whites</seg>.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> said that when he found it out, he took some men and went and buried the bodies, which had been stripped and left on the ground."</seg> <persName key="Young, John W.">John W. Young</persName>, who was then  messenger boy in the Governor's office, says he was in the room and heard <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> tell this story. Judge <persName key="Farr, Aaron F.">Aaron F. Farr</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Ogden, UT">Ogden</placeName>, testified as follows on this point: "I was personally acquainted with <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, having known him when a boy in <placeName type="settlement" key="Nauvoo, IL">Nauvoo</placeName>. In the fall of 1857 he came to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> from his home in <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName>, shortly after the massacre, to report to <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> how it occurred. On the same day that he reported to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> in the morning, he came to my residence on West Temple Street, opposite Bishop <persName key="Hunter, Edward">Hunter</persName>'s place, in the afternoon, and in a conversation with me, lasting about an hour and a half, detailed every particular of the horrible occurrence. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">He placed the whole blame of the massacre on the Indians.</seg> He stated that he and his associates had done all in their power to protect the emigrants, but were totally helpless in their object. He seemed very earnest while he was telling me this story, and at intervals wept bitterly. I asked him if he had informed President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> of these particulars, and he answered me that he had seen President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> that same morning, and had related to him the circumstances as he had told them to me." President <persName key="Woodruff, Wilford">Woodruff</persName> says that when, in 1870, Apostle <persName key="Snow, Erastus">Erastus Snow</persName> stated to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> that there was strong evidence that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was personally implicated in the massacre, President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> was very much surprised, and declared that if it was true, <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> had lied to him. He had the matter investigated, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was cut off the Church. <persName key="Haight, Isaac C>">Isaac C. Haight</persName> was also cut off for not preventing the crime. Apostle <persName key="Snow, Erastus">Erastus Snow</persName> says he began to learn the facts, little by little, in 1861 to 1863, and, when, by 1870, he had become fully satisfied that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had taken a direct hand with the Indians, he communicated the facts to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, who expressed astonishment and wondered how and why the truth had been so long concealed from him. He ordered an investigation, which was made by <persName key="Snow, Erastus">Erastus Snow</persName> and Bishop <persName key="Roundy, L. W.">L. W. Roundy</persName>, of Kanarra, and which resulted in the excommunication of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, with an order that he should never again be admitted to the Church. <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> was also expelled for failing, as his superior officer in the Church, to restrain <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, or to take prompt action against him.</note> 

<pb n="809" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.809"/>  

<p><hi rend="italic">Tenth</hi>:&#8212;Did <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName> call at your office with <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> at the time of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> making his report, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">did you at that time order <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Smith</persName> to turn over the stock to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName></seg>, and <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">order them not to talk about the massacre</seg>? </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;No, he did not call with <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, and I have no recollection of his ever speaking to me or I to him concerning the massacre, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">or anything pertaining to the property</seg>.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Eleventh</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Did you ever give any directions concerning the property taken from the emigrants at the Mountain Meadows massacre, or know anything as to its disposition?</seg></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;No. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">I never gave any directions concerning the property taken from the company of emigrants at the Mountain Meadows massacre, nor did 1 know anything of that property or its disposal; and I do not to this day, except from public rumor.</seg></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Twelfth</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">Why did you not, as Governor of Utah Territory, institute proceedings forthwith to investigate that massacre and bring the guilty authors to justice?</seg></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;<seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">Because another Governor had been appointed by the President of the United States, and was then on the way here to take my place, and I did not know how soon he might arrive, and because the United States judges were not in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. Soon after Governor <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Cumming</persName> arrived, I asked him to take Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, who belonged to the southern district, with him, and I would accompany them with sufficient aid to investigate the matter and bring the offenders to justice.</seg><ref target="n39">*</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n39">* In a letter written to Secretary <persName key="Belknap, William W.">Belknap</persName>, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName>, under date of May 21, 1872, President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> said: "<seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">In 1858, when <persName key="Cumming, Alfred">Alfred Cumming</persName> was Governor of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah Territory</placeName>, I pledged myself to lend him and the court every assistance in my power, in men and means, to thoroughly investigate the Mountain Meadows massacre, and bring if possible, the guilty parties to justice. That offer I have made again and again, and although it has not yet been accepted, I have neither doubt nor fear that the perpetrators of that tragedy will meet their just reward.</seg> <seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">But sending an armed force is not the means of furthering the ends of justice, although it may serve an excellent purpose in exciting popular clamor against the Mormons. In 1859, Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> employed a military force to attempt the arrest of those alleged criminals.</seg> He engaged in all about four hundred men, some of whom were civilians, reputed gamblers, thieves and other camp followers, who were doubtless intended for jurors (as his associate Judge <persName key="Eckels, D. R.">Eccles</persName>, had just done in another district); but these accomplished absolutely nothing further than plundering hen roosts and rendering themselves obnoxious to the citizens on their line of march. Had Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName>, instead of peremptorily dismissing his grand jury and calling for that military posse, allowed the investigation into the Mountain Meadows massacre to proceed, I have the authority of Mr. <persName key="Wilson, ">Wilson</persName>, U. S. Prosecuting Attorney, for saying the investigation was proceeding satisfactorily; and I firmly believe, if the county sheriffs, whose legal duty it was to make arrests, had been lawfully directed to serve the processes, that they would have performed their duty and the accused would have been brought to trial. Instead of honoring the law, Judge <persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Cradlebaugh</persName> took a course to screen offenders, who could easily hide from such a posse under the justification of avoiding a trial by court martial. It is now fourteen years since the tragedy was enacted, and the courts have never tried to prosecute the accused; although some of the judges, like Judge <persName key="Hawley, ">Hawley</persName>, have used every opportunity to charge the crime upon prominent men in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and influence public opinion against our community."</note> 

<pb n="810" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.810"/> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Thirteenth</hi>.&#8212;Did you, about the 10th of September, 1857, receive a communication from <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, or any other person of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, concerning a company of emigrants called the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> company? </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;I did receive a communication from <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> or <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, who was then a farmer for the Indians.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Fourteenth</hi>.&#8212;Have you that communication?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;I have not. I have made diligent search for it but cannot find it.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Fifteenth</hi>.&#8212;Did you answer that communication?</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;I did, to <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, who was then acting President at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName>.</p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Sixteenth</hi>.&#8212;Will you state the substance of your letter to him?</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Answer</hi>.&#8212;Yes. It was to let this company of emigrants, and all companies of emigrants, pass through the country unmolested, and to allay the angry feelings of the Indians as much as possible.<ref target="n41">*</ref></p>

<p><hi rend="right">(Signed), BRIGHAM YOUNG.</hi></p> 

<p>Subscribed and sworn to before me this 30th day of July, A. D. 1875.</p> 

<p><hi rend="right">WILLIAM CLAYTON, Notary Public.</hi></p> 

<note xml:id="n40">* This letter, which was subsequently found, was dated at the "President's Office, <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Great Salt Lake City</placeName>, September 10, 1857," and reads as follows: "Elder <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>. Dear Brother: Your note of the 7th inst. is to hand. Capt. <persName key="Van Vliet, Stewart">Van Vliet</persName>, Acting Commissary, is here, having come in advance of the army to procure necessaries for them. We do not expect that any part of the army will be able to reach here this fall. There is only about 850 men coming. They are now at or near Laramie. A few of their freight trains are this side of that place, the advance of which are now on Green River. They will not be able to come much, if any further on account of their poor stock. They cannot get here this season without we help them. So you see that the Lord has answered our prayers, and again averted the blow designed for our heads. In regard to the emigration trains passing through our settlements, we must not interfere with them until they are first notified to keep away. You must not meddle with them. The Indians we expect will do as they please, but you should try to preserve good feelings with them. There are no other trains going south that I know of. If those who are there will leave, let them go in peace. While we should be on the alert, on hand, and always ready, we should also possess ourselves in patience; preserving ourselves and property, ever remembering that God rules. He has overruled for our deliverance thus once again, and he will always do so if we live our religion and be united in our faith and good works. All is well with us. May the Lord bless you and all the Saints forever. Your brother in the gospel of Christ.

"BRIGHAM YOUNG," </note> 

<pb n="811" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.811"/>  

<p>AFFIDAVIT OF GEORGE A. SMITH</p>

<p>TERRITORY OF UTAH, ss.
<placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> County,</p>

<p>IN THE SECOND JUDICIAL DISTRICT COURT OF THE TERRITORY OF UTAH. THE PEOPLE, ETC., vs. JOHN D. LEE, WILLIAM H. DAME, ISAAC C. HAIGHT, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. INDICTMENT FOR MURDER COMMITTED SEPTEMBER 16. 1857.</p> 

<p><persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName> having been first duly sworn, deposes and says: That he is aged fifty-eight years; that he is now and has been for several months suffering from a severe and dangerous illness of the head and lungs, and that to attend the court at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, in the present condition of his health, would in all probability end his life.<ref target="n41">*</ref> Deponent further saith that he had no military command during the year 1857, nor any other official position, except that of one of the Twelve Apostles of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.</p> 

<p>Deponent further saith that he never, in the year 1857, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> or elsewhere, attended a council where <persName key="Dame, William H.">William H. Dame</persName>, <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> or others were present, to discuss any measures for attacking or in any manner injuring an emigrant train <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg> or any other place, which is alleged to have been destroyed <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in September, 1857</seg>. Deponent further saith that he never heard or knew anything of a train of emigrants, which he learned afterwards, by rumor, was from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>, until he met said emigrant train at Corn Creek on his way north to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, on or about the 25th day of August, 1857. Deponent further saith that he encamped with <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>, <persName key="Farnsworth, P. T.">Philo T. Farnsworth</persName>, <persName key="Smith, Silas S.">Silas S. Smith</persName> and <persName key="Hoops, Elisha">Elisha Hoops</persName>, and there for the first time he learned of the existence of said emigrant train and <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">their intended journey to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>. Deponent further saith that, having been absent from <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> for a year previous, he returned in the summer of 1857 and went south to visit his family at <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, and to look after some property he had there, and also visit his friends and for no other purpose; and that on leaving <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> he had no knowledge whatever of the existence of said emigrant train, nor did he acquire any until as before stated.</p> 

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">Deponent further saith that, as an Elder in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, he preached several times on his way south, and also on his return, and tried to impress upon the minds of the people the necessity of great care as to their grain crops, as all crops had been short for several years previous to 1857, and many of the people were reduced to actual want, and were suffering for the necessaries of life. Deponent further saith that he advised the people to furnish all emigrant companies passing through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> with what they might actually need for bread stuff, for the support of themselves and families while passing through the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, and also advised the people not to feed their grain to their own stock, nor to sell it to the emigrants for that purpose.</seg></p>

<p>Deponent further saith that he never heard or knew of any attack upon the said emigrant train until some time after his return to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, and that while near Fort Bridger [now in <placeName type="state" key="Wyoming">Wyoming</placeName>] <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">he heard for the first time that the Indians had massacred an emigrant company <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>.</seg></p> 

<note xml:id="n41">* He died September 1st, 1875.</note> 

<pb n="812" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.812"/> 

<p>Deponent further saith that he never, at any time, either before or after that massacre, was accessory thereto; that he never, directly or indirectly, aided, abetted or assisted in its perpetration, or had any knowledge thereof, except by hearsay; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">that he never knew anything of the distribution of the property taken there, except by hearsay as aforesaid</seg>. Deponent further saith that all charges and statements as pertaining to him, contrary to the foregoing, are false and untrue. </p>

<p><hi rend="right">(Signed), GEORGE A. SMITH.</hi></p> 

<p>Subscribed and sworn to before me this 30th day of July, A. D. 1875.</p> 

<p><hi rend="right">WILLIAM CLAYTON, Notary Public.</hi></p> 

<p>The proclamation of Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, dated at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, September 15th, 1857, declaring <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> under martial law, was placed in evidence, as was also President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s report as Superintendent of Indian Affairs to Indian Commissioner <persName key="Denver, James W.">James W. Denver</persName>, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently"><seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">This report was under date of September 12th, and relates to financial affairs, except complaints that travelers and emigrants had brought on trouble from the Indians by shooting them whenever they made themselves visible: "a practice," Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> went on to say, "utterly abhorrent to all good people, yet, I regret to say, one that has been indulged in to a great extent by travelers to and from the Eastern States and <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>; hence the Indians regard all white men alike as their enemies, and kill and plunder whenever they can do so with impunity; and often the innocent suffer for the deeds of the guilty."</seg></seg> The Governor recommended an effort to induce travelers to "omit their infamous practice of shooting them [the Indians] down whenever they happen to see one;" that "the Government should make more liberal appropriations to be expended in presents," as it was "far cheaper to feed the Indians than to fight them;" and that the troops be kept away. Next in the order of evidence came the following:</p>

<p><hi rend="center">LETTER OF JOHN D. LEE TO BRIGHAM YOUNG.</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="right">HARMONY, WASHINGTON COUNTY, U. T.,</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="right">November 20th, 1857.</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">To His Excellency Governor B. Young, ex-officio and Superintendent of Indian 

Affairs,</hi></p> 

<p>DEAR SIR:&#8212;My report under date of May llth, 1857, relative to the Indians over whom I have charge as farmer, showed a friendly relation between them and the whites, which 

<pb n="813" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.813"/>  

doubtless would have continued to increase had not the white man been the first aggressor, as was the case with Captain <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName>'s company of emigrants <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">passing through to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg> about the middle of September last, on Corn Creek, fifteen miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore City</placeName>, <placeName type="county" key="Millard County, UT">Millard County</placeName>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">The company there poisoned the meat of an ox, which they gave the Pah Vant Indians to eat, causing four of them to die immediately, besides poisoning a number more. The company also poisoned the water where they encamped, killing the cattle of the settlers.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">This unguarded policy, planned in wickedness by this company, raised the ire of the Indians, which soon spread to the southern tribes, firing them up with revenge till blood was in their path; and as the breach, according to their tradition, was a national one, consequently any portion of the nation was liable to alone for that offense.</seg></seg></p> 

<p>About the 22nd of September, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Captain <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName> and company</seg> fell victims to their wrath, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">near <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">their cattle and horses were shot down in every direction, their wagons and property mostly committed to the flames</seg>.<ref target="n42">*</ref> Had they been the only ones that suffered we would have less cause of complaint; but the following company of nearly the same size had many of their men shot down near <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver City</placeName>, and had it not been for the interposition of the citizens of that place the whole company would have been massacred by the enraged Pah Vants. From this place they were protected by military force, by order of Col. <persName key="Dame, William H.">W. H. Dame</persName>, through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, besides providing the company with interpreters to help to the Los Vegas. On the Muddy, some three to five hundred Indians attacked the company, while traveling, and drove off several hundred head of cattle, telling the company that if they fired a single gun they would kill every soul. The interpreters tried to regain the stock, or a portion of them, by presents, but in vain; the Indians told them to mind their own business, or their lives would not be safe. Since that occurrence no company has been able to pass without some of our interpreters to talk and explain matters to the Indians. Friendly feelings yet remain between the natives and settlers, and I have no hesitancy in saying that it will increase so long as we treat them kindly, and deal honestly toward them. I have been blessed in my labors the last year. Much grain has been raised for the Indians. I herewith furnish you the account of:</p> 

<p><persName key="Dame, William H.">W. H. Dame</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, for cattle, wagons, etc., furnished for 
the benefit of the Chief Owanup (ss.); for two yoke of 
oxen $100 each, one wagon and chains, $75, total,. . . . . . . . $275.00</p> 

<p>Two cows, $30 each, for labor $80,. . . . . . . . . .  140.00</p> 

<p>TOTAL, . . . . . . . . . . $415.00 </p>

<note xml:id="n42">*The nature of this report harmonizes with a statement made by <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> in his confession, where he says that after <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils"><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">the dead bodies of the emigrants had been searched by himself and three others</seg></seg>: "<persName key="Higbee, James M.">Higbee</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>, as well as myself, made speeches, and <seg type="Reaction" subtype="Silence">ordered the people to keep the matter a secret from the entire world. Not to tell their wives, or their most intimate friends, and we pledged ourselves to keep everything relating to the affair a secret through life. We also took the most binding oaths to stand by each other</seg>, and <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">to always insist that the massacre was committed by Indians alone</seg>."</note> 

<pb n="814" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.814"/> 

<p><persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">P. K. Smith</persName>, <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName>, for two yoke of cattle, $100</p>

<p>each, and No. 2 Weekses band, 8200.00</p> 

<p>One cow, $35, do. one wagon, $80 ., $115.00</p>

<p>TOTAL, *$315.00</p> 

<p><persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>'s account, for the benefit of Talse Gobbeth (Tutse 
Gabits) band, <placeName type="settlement" key="Santa Clara, UT">Santa Clara</placeName>, <placeName type="county" key="Washington County, UT">Washington County</placeName>, (ss.), two</p> 

<p>yoke of cattle, $100 each, do. one wagon, two chains, $100,. . $300.00</p> 
 
<p>Two cows, $35, total, 70.00</p>

<p>TOTAL, $370.00</p> 

<p><persName key="Barney, Henry">Henry Barney</persName>'s account for the benefit of Tenquitches' band,</p> 

<p><placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT">Harmony</placeName>, (ss.), for two yoke cattle, $100 $200.00</p> 

<p>do. one wagon, $100, do. one plow, $40, total, 140.00</p> 

<p>do. four cows at $35, each, total, 140.00</p> 

<p>For labor in helping to secure crops, 40.00</p> 

<p>TOTAL $520.00 </p>

<p>For my services for the last six months and lor provisions, clothing, </p>

<p>etc., $600.00 </p>

<p>SUM TOTAL, $2,220.00 </p>

<p>From the above report you will see that the wants of the natives have increased commensurate with their experience and practice in the art of agriculture.<ref target="n43">*</ref></p> 

<p>With sentiments of high consideration, I am your humble servant,</p> 

<p><hi rend="right">JOHN D. LEE, Farmer to Pah Ute Indians.</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="right">To Gov. B. Young, ex-ojficio and Sup't of Indian Affairs.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="center">ABSTRACT FROM REPORT OF BRIGHAM YOUNG.</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="center">OFFICE OF SUP'T OF INDIAN AFFAIRS,</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="right">G. S. L. CITY, U. T., January 6th, 1858.</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Hon. James W. Denver, Commissioner of Indian Affairs, Washington City, D. C.,</hi></p> 

<p>SIR:&#8212;<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">On or about the middle of last September</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">a company of emigrants</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">traveling by the southern route to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>, <seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">poisoned the meat of an ox that died, and gave it to</seg> 

<note xml:id="n43">* <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Says John D. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> in his confession: "I forwarded that letter, and thought I had managed the affair nicely. I put in the expense account of $2,220, just to show off." He also adds, "I never gave the Indians one of the articles named in the letter. No one of the men mentioned had ever furnished such articles to the Indians, but I did it this way for safety."</seg> </note>

<pb n="815" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.815"/>  

<seg type="Encounter" subtype="Poison">the Indians to eat, causing the immediate death of four of their tribe, and poisoning several others. This company also poisoned the water where they were encamped. This occurred at Corn Creek, fifteen miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore City</placeName>.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">This conduct so enraged the Indians that they immediately took measures for revenge.</seg></seg> I quote from a letter written to me by <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, farmer to the Indians in <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron</placeName> and <placeName type="county" key="Washington County">Washington counties</placeName>: "<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">About the 22nd of September</seg> Captain <persName key="Fancher, Alexander">Fancher</persName> &amp; Co., fell victims to the Indians' wrath <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">near <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg>. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">Their cattle and horses were shot down in every direction, their wagons and property mostly committed to the flames.</seg>" <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">Lamentable as this case truly is, it is only the natural consequence of that fatal policy which treats the Indians like the wolves or other ferocious beasts. I have vainly remonstrated for years, with travelers, against pursuing so suicidal a policy, and repeatedly advised the government of its fatal tendency. It is not always upon the heads of the individuals who commit such crimes that such condign punishment is visited, but more frequently the next company that follow in their fatal path become the unsuspecting victims, though preadventure perfectly innocent.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="GunnisonMurder">Of this character was the massacre of Captain <persName key="Gunnison, John W.">Gunnison</persName> and party in 1853. He was friendly and unsuspecting, but the emigrant company that immediately preceeded him had committed a most flagrant act of injustice and murder upon the Indians, escaped unscathed, causing the savage feeling and vengeance which they had so wantonly provoked to be poured out upon the head of the lamented <persName key="Gunnison, John W.">Gunnison</persName>.</seg> Owing to these causes, the Indians upon the main traveled roads leading from this Territory to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> have become quite hostile, so that it has become quite impossible for a company of emigrants to pass in safety. The citizens of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName> have frequently compromised their own safety and other peaceful relations, by interfering in behalf of travelers; nor can they be expected to be otherwise than hostile, so long as the traveling community persist in the practice of indiscriminately shooting and poisoning them, as above set forth. In all other parts of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, except along the north and south routes to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, as above mentioned, the Indians are quiet and peaceful; it is owing to the disturbed state of our Indian affairs that the accounts of this quarter have been so considerably augumented. It has always been my policy to conciliate the native tribes by making them presents, and treating them kindly, considering it much more economical to feed and clothe them than to fight them. I have the satisfaction of knowing that this policy has been most eminently successful and advantageous, not only to the settlements but to the government as well as to the emigrants and travelers. But the most uniform judicious and humane course will sometimes fail in holding ignorant, wild and revengeful Indians by the wrist, to be indiscriminately murdered. We trust, henceforward, such scenes may not be re-enacted, and the existing bad feelings among the native tribes may become extinguished by a uniform, consistent, humane and conciliatory course of superior acts, by those who profess superior attainments.</p> 

<p>Respectfully, I have the honor to remain, your obedient servant, </p>

<p>BRIGHAM YOUNG,</p> 

<p>Gov. and Sup't of Indian Affairs, U. T.</p> 

<p>Certified as correct by James Jack, Notary Public of Utah Territory, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, August 15th, 1876.</p> 

<pb n="816" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.816"/> 

<p><hi rend="center">CIRCULAR BY BRIGHAM YOUNG AND DANIEL H. WELLS.</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="right">GREAT SALT LAKE CITY, September 14th, 1857.</hi></p> 

<p><hi rend="italic">Colonel Win. H. Dame, <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName>, Iron County</hi>:</p> 

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">Herewith you will receive the Governor's proclamation declaring martial law.</seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">You will probably not be called out this fall but are requested to continue to make ready for a big fight another year. The plan of operations is supposed to be about this: In case the United States government should send out an overpowering force, we intend to desolate <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, and conceal our families, stock, and all of our effects in the fastnesses of the mountains, where they will be safe, while the men waylay our enemies, attack them from ambush, stampede their animals, take their supply trains, cut off detachments, and parlies sent to the canyons for wood, or on other service, to lay waste everything that will burn houses, fences, trees, fields and grass so that they cannot find a particle of anything that will be of use to them, not even sticks to make a fire to cook their supplies. To waste our enemies and lose none, that will be our mode of warfare. Thus you see the necessity of preparing. First secure places in the mountains where they cannot find us, or if they do where they cannot approach in force, and then prepare for our families, building some cabins, caching flour and grain. Flour should be ground in the latter part of the winter, or early in the spring, to keep. Sow grain in your fields as early as possible this fall, so the harvest of another year may come off before they have time to get here. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">Conciliate the Indians and make them our fast friends.</seg></seg></p>

<p>In regard to letting the people pass or repass, or travel through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">this Territory</placeName>, this applies to all strangers and suspected persons. Yourself and Brother <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName>, in your district, are authorized to give such permits; examine all such persons before giving to them permits to pass. Keep things perfectly quiet, and let all things be done peacefully, but with firmness, and let there be no excitement. L<seg type="Context" subtype="LDSReformation">et the people be united in their feelings and faith, as well as works, and keep alive the spirit of the reformation</seg>; and what we said in regard to saving the grain and provisions we say again. Let there be no waste. Save life always when it is possible. We do not wish to shed a drop of blood if it can be avoided. This course will give us great influence abroad.</p> 

<p>[Signed], BRIGHAM YOUNG,</p> 

<p>DANIEL H. WELLS.<ref target="n44">*</ref></p> 

<p>Certified to under seal by James Jack, Notary Public, August 16th, 1876.</p> 

<note xml:id="n44">*<persName key="Bishop, William W.">W. W. Bishop</persName>, in his Life of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, says of this document: "The circular bears date two days before the massacre is charged to have been committed, and the supposition is that it had been delivered to <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> at the time he issued his orders for the massacre." While the indictment "charged" the crime on September 16th, Attorney Bishop well knew, when he wrote the foregoing sentence, that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">the crime was proved to have been committed on September llth&#8212;three days prior to the date of the circular, and four days before Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>'s proclamation, which was issued on the 15th.</seg> He further says: "Next, take the proclamation declaring martial law in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, and put these facts together, and no fair-minded person can deny that the massacre was the result." His logic is that the effect was produced before its cause existed. As <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>'s letter of inquiry about the emigrants at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName> was received and answered on the 10th and by the utmost haste it took the special pony express until the evening of the 13th to reach <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName> several days before the circular and proclamation were issued, it is not unlikely that it inspired in the letter to <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> the expression, particularly applicable to the existing conditions in <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName> "Save life always when it is possible. We do not wish to shed a drop of blood if it can be avoided," and also the authorization of <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> and <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> to issue permits to travelers passing through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>. </note>

<pb n="817" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.817"/>  

<p>Now came the examination of witnesses for the Government. General <persName key="Wells, Daniel H.">Daniel H. Wells</persName> was the first one called. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">His testimony was to the effect that in 1857 <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was farmer to the Indians and was popular with them</seg>; he had previously held the office of major in the militia.</p> 

<p><persName key="Morrill, Laban">Laban Morrill</persName> who was present at a council held at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName> on the Sunday previous to the massacre, stated that the proceedings of the meeting had begun when he entered. <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">There was considerable excitement among those in attendance, and upon inquiring the reason, Mr. <persName key="Morrill, Laban">Morrill</persName> was informed of the offensive course of the emigrants in threatening that they would return and "destroy every d&#8212;d Mormon." The hostile attitude of the emigrants caused much feeling as there was already an army coming on the north against the people.</seg> A proposition was made, supported by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Philip Klingensmith</persName>, that the emigrants be treated as a hostile force, arid that they be attacked and destroyed or captured. Mr. <persName key="Morrill, Laban">Morrill</persName> opposed this in several speeches, and demanded to know what authority they had for such a step, and whether they had a letter from Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>. The reply was that they had no word from <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, but were proceeding on their own authority. <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> thought it would be best to kill the emigrants, but <persName key="Morrill, Laban">Morrill</persName> would not consent. "<persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>," he says, "was the hardest man I had to contend with there." The witness proposed, as a settlement of the matter, that a message be sent to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, inquiring what to do, and that no hostile course be pursued until the messenger returned. This was unanimously agreed to. 

<pb n="818" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.818"/> 

Word was sent to <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, who was not at the council, to have the Indians kept back, and not interfere with the emigrants, while another dispatch was forwarded by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> to the Governor. This letter was sent with <persName key="Haslam, James H.">James H. Haslam</persName>, and witness went to his home at Fort Johnson feeling that all was well. On Friday, the llth, about fourty-eight hours before <persName key="Haslam, James">Haslam</persName> returned, <persName key="Morrill, Laban">Morrill</persName> was called by business to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, and before leaving there "learnt that the job had been done; that is, that the destruction of the emigrants had taken place." When <persName key="Haslam, James">Haslam</persName> came, witness asked <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> about the Governor's answer, and <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> replied. "President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> sent word to let the emigrants pass on in peace."</p>

<p><persName key="Haslam, James H.">James H. Haslam</persName> was then sworn as a witness. He testified that on the evening of Monday, September 7th, 1857, he started for <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, having been directed by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Isaac C. Haight</persName> to take a message to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, with all speed. At the same time an order which the witness read, was issued by <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> to <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>, to keep the Indians in check till the messenger returned from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>. The message which <persName key="Haslam, James">Haslam</persName> bore was addressed to "<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, Governor of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah Territory</placeName>." The witness was permitted to read it before it was sealed up. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">It stated that the Indians had got the emigrants corraled <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">at Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg></seg>, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> wanted to know what should be done. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was at that time Major of what was called the Post,<ref target="n45">*</ref> and also Indian agent or farmer. When <persName key="Haslam, James">Haslam</persName> reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> he procured a note from Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> requesting the Bishops on his route to furnish him horses, which they did. He reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> on the morning of Thursday, September 10th, and handed the message to Governor <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> who told him to get a little sleep and return at 1 p. m. that day. The Governor asked him if he could stand the trip back. The reply was yes, and President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> handed him a letter to <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, in an unsealed envelope, saying, "Go with all speed. Spare no horse flesh. The emigrants must not be meddled with, if it takes all <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron</placeName> 

<note xml:id="n45">* This was a post built at Cedar City as a protection from hostile Indians.</note> 

<pb n="819" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.819"/>  

<placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">County</placeName> to prevent it. They must go free and unmolested."<ref target="n46">*</ref> <persName key="Haslma, James">Haslam</persName> hastened back to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, arriving there on Sunday morning, September 13th. He met <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> in the street and handed him the letter. When he read it <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> exclaimed, "Too late! Too late!" and cried like a child. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">That was the first that witness knew of the massacre. On his way to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> he had found the Indians very mad, and they told him they would kill the emigrants before he got back.</seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The testimony of <persName key="White, Joel">Joel W. White</persName> did not differ from that given by him at the former trial. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">He was followed by <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Samuel Knight</persName> and <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">Samuel McMurdy</persName>, who drove the teams in which the wounded emigrants, children and guns were placed after tbe company surrendered. Knight and <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> acted under the direction of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>. <persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> was on the first wagon and <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName> on the second, with <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> walking between. <persName key="Knight, Samuel">Knight</persName> testified that when the halt was made and the Indians rushed on to the train, he saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> club a woman to death. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><persName key="McMurdy, Samuel">McMurdy</persName> said that he saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, at the moment of attack, in the act of shooting a woman; also saw him shoot with his pistol two or three of the wounded who were in the wagon.</seg><ref target="n47">&#8224;</ref> <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The Indians, who came out of ambush, did the principal part of the killing.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">Both witnesses, when they were first called out, understood that it was to rescue the emigrants from the Indians.</seg></seg></seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Johnson, Nephi">Nephi Johnson</persName> testified that he was present <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName></seg>, where "<persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> seemed to be engineering the whole thing." <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">At the time of the killing, witness was after his horse about three hundred yards up the hill. He saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> fire, and a woman fall. The Indians rushed in and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> helped them to pull the wounded out of the wagons. Before the shooting, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had told the militia that the emigrants were to be killed</seg> and a good many</seg> 

<note xml:id="n46">*This testimony, with the greater part of the evidence of <persName key="Haslma, James">Haslam</persName>, is omitted in Bishop's "Life of <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>."</note> 

<note xml:id="n47">&#8224; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, in his confession says: "I did not kill anyone there."</note> 

<pb n="820" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.820"/> 

<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">of the men objected, but did not dare say anything to those in command. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had full control on the field. <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> did not reach <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> till next morning.<ref target="n48">*</ref> The matter was talked over, and it was agreed to keep still about the affair. <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> was one of those who gave this advice.</seg></p> 

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">Testimony was also elicited from <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Jacob Hamblin</persName>, who, the next spring, counted and buried <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">one hundred and twenty</seg> skeletons that had been torn up by wild animals. He returned to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> a few days after the massacre, and saw the dead bodies lying around.</seg> On his way down he met <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> at <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, en route to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> had heard of the affair from the Indians, and asked <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> about it. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The latter said that the Indians compelled him to lead the attack. He did not want to do so, and when he cried, the Indians called him "Yah Guts," or "Cry Baby."</seg> <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> also said that he sent word to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar</placeName> of what had occurred, and received a message saying that he was not to disturb the emigrants&#8212;then came another order that they were to be used up. Witness was not told who this order was from. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> told <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">that there were white men in the massacre; that they did not know what they were going for till they got there; and that some would not act and some would. He named <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> as a participator.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> also said to him that an Indian chief brought him two young girls and asked what should be done with them. The Indian shot one and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> killed the other.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">When the Indian agent, Dr. <persName key="Forney, Jacob">Forney</persName>, came for the surviving children, <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> gathered up seventeen&#8212;all that he could find&#8212;and delivered </seg>

<note xml:id="n48">* <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> states that <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> and <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> came in the morning and had a quarrel. He also says: "Col. <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> was silent for some time. He looked all over the field, and was quite pale, and looked uneasy and frightened. I thought then that he was just finding out the difference between giving and executing orders for wholesale killing. He spoke to <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, and said: 'I must report this matter to the authorities.' 'How will you report it?' said <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>. <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> said, 'I will report it just as it is.' 'Yes, I suppose so, and implicate yourself with the rest?' 'No,' said <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>, 'I will not implicate myself, for I had nothing to do with it.' <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> then said, 'That will not do, for you know a d&#8212;d sight better. You ordered it done.'" <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> adds, "Col. <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> was much excited. He choked up, and would have gone away, but he knew <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> was a man of determination and would not stand any foolishness." <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> adds that he interposed to stop the quarrel.</seg></note>

<pb n="821" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.821"/>  

<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">them to him.</seg> Mr. <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob">Hamblin</persName> also stated that he afterwards told President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> and Apostle <persName key="Smith, George A.">George A. Smith</persName> what <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had related to him, and President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> said that when they could get a court of justice the matter should be ferreted out. This was the first opportunity the witness had had to tell it in a court of justice. </p>

<p><persName key="Johnson, Nephi">Nephi Johnson</persName> was recalled and stated that under orders of Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> he piloted <persName key="Dukes, William C.">Duke</persName>'s company, which followed the massacred emigrants, safely though the country. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">At <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony,  UT">Harmony</placeName> <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> asked him to take the company into the mountains in the Santa Clara and he would follow with the Indians and kill them.</seg> Witness said that he would not do it; that he was sent to see the company through the country, and he would do that or die.</p>

<p>With this witness the prosecution rested. The other side introduced no evidence. The attorneys for the defense assumed the position that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> only obeyed the orders of his superiors, and Mr. <persName key="Bishop, William W.">Bishop</persName> declared that "the Mormon Church had resolved to sacrifice <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, discarding him as of no further use, and leaving him to a fate consequent on such evidence as had been introduced." In his closing address, District Attorney <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName> said that he had unanswerable evidence that the authorities of the Mormon Church knew nothing of the butchery till after it was committed, and then <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had knowingly misrepresented the facts to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, seeking to keep him in ignorance of the truth. The speaker stated that as Government attorney he had received all the assistance that any United States official could ask in any case; nothing had been kept back. It was not his intention to prosecute anyone innocently lured to <geogName type="valley" key="Mountian Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>.</p> 

<p>The case was given to the jury on the morning of September 20th, and after four hours' deliberation they brought in a verdict of guilty of murder in the first degree.<ref target="n49">*</ref> This result, upon the <choice><orig>testi- 

<note xml:id="n49">* All the jurors were Mormons. Their names were <persName key="Greenwood, William">Wm. Greenwood</persName>, <persName key="Page, John E.">John E. Page</persName>, <persName key="Farnsworth, A. M.">A. M. Farnsworth</persName>, <persName key="Barton, Stephen S.">Stephen S. Barton</persName>, <persName key="Carson, Valentine">Valentine Carson</persName>, <persName key="Randall, Alfred I.">Alfred I. Randall</persName>, <persName key="Montague, James G.">James G. Montague</persName>, <persName key="Goddwin, A. S.">A. S. Goodwin</persName>, <persName key="Elmer, Ira B.">Ira B. Elmer</persName>, <persName key="Correy, Andrew A.">Andrew A. Correy</persName>, <persName key="Adams, Chalres">Charles Adams</persName> and <persName key="Granger, William">Walter Granger</persName>:</note> 

<pb n="822" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.822"/> 

mony</orig><reg>testimony</reg></choice> which had been introduced, surprised no one. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> received the news gloomily. His attorneys were granted a stay of proceedings pending a motion for a new trial.</p>

<p>During the progress of the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> case&#8212;on September 14th&#8212;the indictments against Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName> and Messrs. <persName key="Adair, George Jr.">Adair</persName> and <persName key="Wilden, Elliott">Wilden</persName> I were, on motion of the District Attorney, quashed, as the evidence did not justify their prosecution.</p> 

<p>On the 7th of October a motion for a new trial in the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> 
case was argued and on the 10th overruled. The defendant was sentenced to suffer the death penalty. As the law gave him the choice of being hanged, beheaded or shot, he chose the latter method. The date set for the execution was January 26th, 1877. A large portion of Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob">Boreman</persName>'s speech at the time of passing judgment was an anti-Mormon tirade, utterly without justification by the evidence at either of the trials; in fact it contradicted the testimony and the statements of the Government attorney. Among other things he said:</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The evidence of both trials will be considered together, and according to the evidence at the former trial, the massacre seems to have been the result of a vast conspiracy, extending from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> to the bloody field, and the emigrants were plundered all along this line of travel. * * * Both trials, taken together, show that others, and some high in authority, inaugurated and decided upon the wholesale slaughter of the emigrants; that the slaughter took place nineteen years ago, and from that time down to the present term of court, <seg type="Reaction" subtype="StateInvestigation">there has been throughout the entire Territory, a persistent and determined opposition to an investigation of the massacre.</seg></seg></p>

<p>No such evidence as that referred to by the Judge was brought out at either trial, nor indeed, could it truthfully be given. Respecting some of <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName>'s assertions, the <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Enterprise</hi> said: "We have resided in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> much longer than Judge <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName>, and we have not witnessed the persistent opposition of which he speaks. * * We can prove, by witnesses whose testimony his honor will allow is entitled to due weight, that no such conspiracy [that alleged by the Judge to extend "from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> to the bloody field"] existed in <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver City</placeName> or <placeName type="county" key="Beaver County, UT">Beaver County</placeName>. We will prove that no such conspiracy, nor even a knowledge of the deed, 

<pb n="823" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.823"/>  

existed in <placeName type="county" key="Millard County, UT">Millard County</placeName>. We will prove the same by good witnesses in regard to <placeName type="county" key="Juab County, UT">Juab</placeName> and <placeName type="county" key="Salt Lake County">Salt Lake Counties</placeName>. We do not deny that such conspiracy existed in <placeName type="settlement" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName>; but its existence there does not prove, by a great deal, that it was to be found everywhere between <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> and <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>. If it was known in any other county besides <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron</placeName>, it was in <placeName type="county" key="Washington County">Washington County</placeName>, and that county only."</p> 

<p>The <placeName type="settlement" key="Ogden, UT">Ogden</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Junction</hi> had this to say of <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName>'s speech: "His business was merely to sentence <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>. But being angry because he could not try men in authority in the Mormon Church, he took this occasion of convicting them as far as his unwarrantable language could do so. To us his harangue from the bench was an insult to the people of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and an arraignment of unaccused persons which renders him unfit for the position that he occupies. To the great public it will appear as a disgraceful act in a public officer, and to the District Attorney as an attack on his veracity. When the prosecuting officer finds no case against persons whom rumor has accused, but whom the law has no ground for indictment, the Judge has no right even to insinuate anything against them, much less to condemn them in language only suited to a pothouse debate on some current report. But, then, what could be expected of <persName key="Boreman, Jacob S.">Boreman</persName>, the last lingering remnant of the McKean ring, the fag end of the defunct Methodist-Christian crusade."<ref target="n50">*</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n50">* The Methodist Church, through <hi rend="italic">Zion's Herald</hi>, its official organ, thus avowed its paternity of the anti-Mormon crusade: "We find <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> was not so far out of the way in declaring that the present judicial movement of the government against his system, and even against his own immaculate person, is due to the Methodists; Dr. <persName key="Newman, John P. ">Newman</persName>'s argument in the temple began the war. Our missionaries organized it by fortifying themselves on the field, and the camp meeting brethren gave it the last stroke before the arm of the state was raised to carry out its just decrees." The camp meetings referred to were held for one week, in June, 1871, by the Revs. Mr. <persName key="Inskip, John S.">Inskip</persName>, <persName key="Pierce, G. M.">G. M. Pierce</persName>, <persName key="Vincent, J. H.">J. H. Vincent</persName> and others. President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> invited all, and specially urged the young people, to attend them. He gave this notice at the tabernacles in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> and <placeName type="settlement" key="Ogden, UT">Ogden</placeName>, and published the invitation in the <hi rend="italic">Deseret News</hi>. One of the Methodist ministers, Rev. <persName key="Vincent, J. H.">J. H. Vincent</persName>, of <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName>, expressed a wish to President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> to address the Sabbath School children of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>. On Sunday, June 4th, about four thousand of these children, and nearly as many adults, assembled in the Large Tabernacle and listened attentively to Dr. <persName key="Vincent, J. H.">Vincent</persName>. The audiences at the camp meetings were large and orderly, and consisted chiefly of Latter-day Saints and their children. At the meeting on Sunday, June lltli, President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> was present. It was naturally expected that, aside from proper consideration for the many courtesies he had extended to them, he would at least receive the respectful treatment due to a stranger. On the contrary he was reviled at and abused, the ministers aiming their sermons directly at him. This insulting and un-Christian procedure was in strong contrast to the kindness and liberality which had been uniformly shown by the Mormon leader to the Methodist ministers.</note>

<pb n="824" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.824"/> 

<p>An appeal [was taken in the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> Case to the Supreme Court of the Territory, where it was argued on January 31st, 1877. The action of the lower court was affirmed on February 10, and on the 7th of March Judge Boreman fixed Friday, March 23, as the date for carrying lout the judgment of the court.<ref target="n51">*</ref> A move to obtain a reprieve was inaugurated, the basis of executive clemency being that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> should make a statement implicating the Mormon leaders; but this he could not do, the facts being plainly against such an allegation, so the matter was dropped.<ref target="n52">&#8224;</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n51">* <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was taken from the Penitentiary on March 4th, arriving at <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> on the 6th. He looked utterly broken down, and his health was poor. A son and son-in-law were present to meet him.</note> 

<note xml:id="n52">&#8224; The <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> and <placeName type="settlement" key="San Francisco, CA">San Francisco</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> published, two days prior to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s execution, an alleged confession said to have been made by him to U. S. Attorney <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName>. On the llth of the following April there was filed in the Department of Justice, at <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName>, an affidavit made by <persName key="Oilman, Edwin">Edwin Oilman</persName>, an ex-deputy U. S. Marshal, who alleged that in that confession vital parts implicating <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> were omitted, and charged that the U. S. Attorney had suppressed them. <persName key="Oilman, Edwin">Oilman</persName> said that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had made the statement on a promise that in return he should receive a reprieve, and eventually a full pardon. This promise was made, according to <persName key="Oilman, Edwin">Oilman</persName>, by the U. S. Attorney. <persName key="Oilman, Edwin">Oilman</persName>, according to his affidavit, was a go-between and made overtures to <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> for the confession, promising him immunity in consideration of the disclosure. He said that he had seen the confession, and it was at variance with that given to the public by the District Attorney. <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName> denied having made any change (the fact of the negotiations was not controverted); and subsequent developments vindicated him in this regard. The <placeName type="settlement" key="New York, NY">New York</placeName> <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> sent a correspondent&#8212;<persName key="Stillson, Jerome B.">Jerome B. Stillson</persName>&#8212;to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, and for a time continued to publish mendacious sensational reports about the Mormons preparing for war, etc., and urging the sending of an army to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. General <persName key="Smith, ">Smith</persName>, then in command at Fort Douglas, reported all quiet in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and General <persName key="Crook, George">Crook</persName>, who was sent out by the War Department, came and ascertained the falsity of the <hi rend="italic">Herald</hi> telegrams, reporting thereon in such forcible language that Stillson had to change his tactics. The correspondent then claimed that efforts were being made to assassinate him&#8212;by the Mormons, of course&#8212;and alleged that on the night of May 26th he was shot at, and that on the afternoon of May 31sl, while at his room in the Walker House, a stranger came in and attempted to stab him. In proof of this he showed an incision about an inch long in his vest and through two photographs, and an indented suspender buckle, with a slight abrasion of the skin on the left breast, such as might have been made with a pin. An official investigation exposed the fraud&#8212;the whole thing being a trick of Stillson's to create a sensation&#8212;and the Herald soon withdrew its correspondent.</note> 

<pb n="825" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.825"/>  

<p>Marshal <persName key="Nelson, William">Nelson</persName> refrained from giving to the public any intimation as to the place selected for the execution until after the event occurred. Two days before the date fixed by the court, and in time for the party to make the necessary trip of ninety miles over an uneven road, he communicated to the newspaper correspondents and citizens who were to be present the fact that it would take place at what is known as Monument Point, <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>. It is said that the Marshal and his coadjutors chose this spot in the hope that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, when brought face to face with death on the field where the awful crime for which he was to forfeit his life had been committed, would make a more complete and far-reaching confession than he had done. This may have been one of the reasons for the step, but doubtless another and equally powerful motive on the part of the Marshal was a desire for dramatic effect.<ref target="n53">*</ref></p> 

<note xml:id="n53">*The <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> Square-Dealer (non-Mormon), in its issue three days prior to the execution, had this to say of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s last confession, which the editor had had the privilege of perusing: "One particular statement he has adhered to from the first. He has at all times declared that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and the Church leaders had nothing to do with the massacre. His hopeful statement, made at the time of his arrest, and reiterated for several weeks, that he would place the saddle on the right horse, was found to refer solely to <persName key="Higbee, John M.">John M. Higbee</persName>, who <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> said succeeded him as major of the <placeName type="county" key="Iron County, UT">Iron County</placeName> militia, some time before the massacre. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement does not even reach Colonel <persName key="Dame, William H.">Dame</persName>. He knows nothing affecting anybody higher in the Church than <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> and <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName>. The value of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s statement accrues chiefly to the Church leaders, whom it exonerates completely. Standing on the eve of the execution, after a searching investigation which has been prolonged for two years, not a jot or tittle ot evidence has been elicited connecting the Mountain Meadows massacre with <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> or any leading Church official. Everything which <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingensmith</persName> and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> have told goes to prove that the conspiracy was hatched at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> has told nothing because he has nothing to tell. The country will be satisfied after the execution that he died with no secret in him affecting <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>. If he held such a fearful lodgment, Attorney <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName> would be in possession of it today and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s sentence commuted. A few facts warrant our statements: <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was tried by a Mormon jury, who, on the testimony of Mormon witnesses, brought in their verdict of murder in the first degree. Years ago <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> severed <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> from his Church, thus challenging the exposition of any orders, written or otherwise, which he may have held from him as the head of the Church. The conviction of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> by a Mormon jury and his silent execution will be a receipt for <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> for all time to come as against the massacre of the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrants." In view of this statement the reader is left to draw his own conclusions as to why <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>'s last confession, published after his death by his attorney, W. W. Bishop, is so worded as to cast reflections upon President <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName> in relation to the Mountain Meadows massacre.</note>

<pb n="826" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.826"/> 

<p>On the afternoon of Wednesday, March 21st, <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> was placed in a close carriage, and driven southward from <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>, a company of troops from Fort Cameron acting as guard. U. S. Marshal <persName key="Nelson, William">Nelson</persName>, U. S. Attorney <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName>, a few press representatives, and about twenty citizens made up the remainder of the party, which did not travel in a body lest particular attention should be attracted. All met at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName> on the morning of March 23rd.</p> 

<p>During the trip <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was sullen and silent. Rev. George <persName key="Stokes, William">Stokes</persName> of <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName> was present as his spiritual adviser, and sought to. draw him into a conversation. His efforts were vain until Friday morning, when <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> began talking about religion. The parson advanced some ideas which did not meet with the prisoner's approval, and a discussion ensued, drifting from one subject to another till the massacre was named. The talk upon this topic was between themselves. Mr. <persName key="Stokes, William">Stokes</persName> afterwards said that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> confessed to the killing of live persons, but did not state their age or sex. In conversation with others a few minutes later <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> stoutly denied having made such a confession, and protested his innocence of actual participation in the killing. He pointed out to the party various points of interest in connection with the massacre. His countenance betrayed no emotion, but wore the same stolid look that it had borne from the outset. He seemed to conduct himself with perfect coolness. This was probably in a degree attributable to the fact that almost up to his last moment he anticipated the interposition of the reprieve promised as a reward for his confession. But it never came.</p> 

<pb n="827" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.827"/>  

<p>The spot selected for the execution was about one hundred yards from Monument Point, and toward this place the members of the party in camp, began, about 9 a. m., to make their way. On eminences overlooking the ground soldiers were stationed, while a squad stood in line facing the monument. Three government wagons were drawn into a semi-circle, and a covering of blankets so arranged that the shooting party was hidden from view. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> sat some distance away, with the Marshal, quietly watching the preparations. He betrayed no fear of death. A coffin was brought and placed about twenty-five feet from the wagons, for him to sit upon. A slight trepidation was noticeable as he glanced at it, but this was only momentary.</p> 

<p>When the preparations were completed, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was called forward. He presented a bottle of "bitters" to those immediately around, some of whom responded to his invitation to take a last drink with him; then, leaning upon the arm of Parson <persName key="Stokes, William">Stokes</persName>, he approached the wagons. It was a strange sight to see this old man of sixty-five years walking calmly, and, to all outward appearance, unconcernedly to his doom. As he reached the coffin, he deliberately removed his overcoat and laid it down. He then handed his hat to Marshal <persName key="Nelson, William">Nelson</persName> and his muffler to District Attorney <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName>, and quietly took his seat on the end of the coffin, facing his executioners.</p> 

<p>The death warrant was read, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> listened attentively. At its conclusion Marshal <persName key="Nelson, William">Nelson</persName> spoke: "Mr. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, if you have anything to say before the order of the court is carried into effect, you may now do so."</p>

<p>"I wish to speak to that man," said <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, pointing to <persName key="Fennimore, James">James Fennamore</persName>, the photographer, who was fixing his camera to take a negative before the shooting. "Come over here," he said, beckoning with his hand.</p> 

<p>"In a second, Mr. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>," replied <persName key="Fennimore, James">Fennamore</persName>.</p> 

<p><persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> waited till the artist was ready, and proceeded: "I want to ask a favor of you. I want you to furnish my three wives each a copy of my photograph" meaning the one about to be 
 
<pb n="828" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.828"/> 

taken "send a copy of the same to <persName key="Lee, Rachel A.">Rachel A.</persName>, <persName key="Lee, Sarah C.">Sarah C.</persName>, and <persName key="Lee, Emma B.">Emma B.</persName>"</p> 

<p>Mr. <persName key="Howard, Sumner">Howard</persName> responded for Mr. <persName key="Fennimore, James">Fennamore</persName>, who was busy with his instrument, "He says he will do it, Mr. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>."</p> 

<p>The condemned man repeated the three names again, carefully, and said, "Please forward them you will doit?" To which the artist gave an affirmative reply. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> then arose, looked calmly at those around him, and began speaking:</p> 

<p>I have but little to say this morning. Of course I feel that I am upon the brink of eternity, and the solemnities of eternity should rest upon my mind at the present. I have made out, or endeavored to do so, a manuscript and an abridged history of my life. This is to be published. I have given my views and feelings with regard to all those things. I feel resigned to my fate. I feel as calm as a summer morning. I have done nothing intentionally wrong. My conscience is clear before God and man, and I am ready to meet my Redeemer and those that have gone before me behind the veil.</p> 

<p>I am not an infidel. I have not denied God or His mercy. I am a strong believer in those things. The most I regret is parting with my family. Many of them are unprotected, and they will be left fatherless. [He paused here two or three seconds.] When I speak of those little ones they touch a tender chord within me. [Here his voice faltered perceptibly.]</p> 

<p>I have done nothing designedly wrong in this affair. I used my utmost endeavors to save these people. I would have given worlds were they at my command, to have averted that calamity, but I could not do it. I am sacrificed to satisfy feelings I am used to gratify parties. But I am ready to die. I have no fear. Death has no terror. No particle of mercy have I asked of the court or officials, to spare my life. I do not fear death. I shall never go to a worse place than the one I am now in. I have said it to ray family, and I will say it today, that the government of the United States sacrifices their best friend. That is saying a great deal, but it is true it is so.</p> 

<p>I am a true believer in the gospel of Jesus Christ. I do not believe everything that is now practiced and taught by Brigham Young. I do not agree with him. I believe he is leading the people astray. But I believe in the gospel as it was taught in its purity by Joseph Smith, in former days. I have nay reasons for saying this. I studied to make this man's [Brigham Young's] will my pleasure, and did so for thirty years. See how and what I have come to this day. I have been sacrificed in a cowardly and dastardly manner. Evidence has been brought against "me which is as false as the hinges of hell. I am now singled out and sacrificed sacrifice a man that has waited upon him, that has wandered and endured in the days of adversity, true from the beginning! He has an influence over the people like a reptile, that draws its prey into the jaws of death. I cannot compare it to anything else.</p> 

<p>There are thousands of people in the Church, honorable, good-hearted, that I cherish in my heart. I regret to leave my family. They are near and dear to me. These are things to rouse my sympathy. I declare I did nothing wrong designedly in this unfortunate

<pb n="829" xml:id="mmm.uh.whitney.1893.829"/>  

affair. I did everything in my power to save all the emigrants; but I am one that must suffer. Having said this, I feel resigned. I ask the Lord my God to extend His mercy to me and receive my spirit.</p> 

<p>When <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> had ceased speaking the Marshal announced that the hour for execution had come. Mr. <persName key="Stokes, William">Stokes</persName> knelt on one side of the coffin <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> kneeling opposite and offered a fervent prayer. This being ended the Marshal tied a white handkerchief around the eyes of the doomed man, who requested that he be shot through the heart, so that his body would not be mangled.</p> 

<p>After the blindfolding, the Marshal went to tie his hands, when <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> said, "Don't do that. Please let my arms be free." The request was granted, and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, sitting erect upon the coffin, clasped his hands over his head and exclaimed, "Center my heart, boys!"</p> 

<p>In a few seconds the Marshal spoke: "Ready! Aim! Fire!'" A line of flame shot out from the wagons, and the ground at the rear of the coffin was torn up with bullets. The body of <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> poised for an instant and dropped heavily back upon the coffin; the arms fell down by the sides, and all was over. Death was instantaneous. One of the chief actors in the Mountain Meadows massacre had paid with his life the penalty of his crime.</p>

<p>The body was lifted into the coffin, which was slightly tilted up for a photograph to be taken of the corpse. It was then placed in a wagon and conveyed to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar, UT">Cedar City</placeName>. The officers and spectators returned to <placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">Beaver</placeName>. The body was forwarded to the <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> family at <placeName type="settlement" key="Panguitch, UT">Panguitch</placeName>, there to be consigned to its earthly tomb.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>