<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.wa.boyd.1891">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Recent Indian Wars</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                    <author><forename>James</forename> <forename type="middle">P.</forename> <surname>Boyd</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.wa.boyd.1891</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m" type="main">Recent Indian Wars, Under the Lead of Sitting Bull, and Other Chiefs; with a Full Account of The Messiah Craze, and Ghost Dances.</title>
                    <author><forename>James</forename> <forename type="middle">P.</forename> <surname>Boyd</surname></author>
                    <publisher>Publishers Union</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Philadelphia, PA</pubPlace>
                    <extent></extent>
                    <date when="1891">1891</date>
		    <note type="source">James P. Boyd. <hi rend="italic">Recent Indian Wars, Under the Lead of Sitting Bull, and Other Chiefs; with a Full Account of The Messiah Craze, and Ghost Dances.</hi>. Philadelphia, PA: Publishers Union, 1891.  73-78.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>western_americana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
	    <change when="2011-09-06"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enhancement</change>
            <change when="2010-08-02"><name>Rosie Hanneke</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="73" xml:id="mmm.wa.boyd.1891.089"/>

<head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>  

<head>THE AFFAIR OF MOUNTAIN MEADOW.</head>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsLDS">T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> Indians who lived in the great Utah
Basin or who used it as part of their 
tramping grounds, were of the Shoshone stock,
and embraced the Snake, Bannock and Ute
families. These families were again sub-divided
into tribes with various names, more or less 
fanciful. As a rule, they were not unfriendly to the
whites, though not disinclined to war under the
provocations which frequently arose. The 
Mormons had no trouble with them, because they
approached them as equals and without a desire
to force their civilization upon them. <seg type="Context" subtype="IndianRelationsUS">They had
great power over them, for the reason that they
stood up for them, when the United States
attempted to execute its authority among them.
It may be said that the Mormon influence over
them was bad, in so far as it represented 
antagonism to the Government.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="UtahWar">It is not our purpose to narrate how bitter
Mormon antagonism became in 1856, nor to 
discuss the wisdom of that costly and useless <choice><orig>inva-

<pb n="74" xml:id="mmm.wa.boyd.1891.090"/>

sion</orig><reg>invasion</reg></choice>
of their country by the Army of the United States, but this invasion produced the greatest excitement in all Mormondom. It fanned the flames of religious and political passion till they
broke out in various forms.</seg> In that year there
passed through <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a large emigrant train</seg>,
<seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">composed mostly of Arkansas families</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">on their
way to Southern <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>. These emigrants
encamped for several days at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> where their numbers were largely increased by Gentile
accessions, and by some Mormons who had become
dissatisfied with their religion.</p>

<p><seg type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">When the emigrant train started on, it was
denied supplies in the Mormon settlements</seg>, was
treated as an intrusive and dangerous mass, and
was denounced as the vanguard of such an 
eastern mob as might soon be expected to come for
the purpose of sacking the Mormon Zion. The
train moved rapidly, amid contumely and scant
food supply, but without thought of direct attack
on their lives. After crossing the Great Basin,
they stopped for rest <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName>, in
Southwestern <placeName type="state" key="Utah">Utah</placeName></seg>. While enjoying their rest
here, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">their camp was suddenly attacked by
Indians, who fired upon the emigrants as they
were seated around their fires cooking breakfast.
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Seven of their number fell in death at the first
volley</seg>, and sixteen were wounded. The rest

<pb n="75" xml:id="mmm.wa.boyd.1891.091"/>

were thrown into confusion, but quickly rallied,
and having placed their women and children
under shelter of the wagons, they were soon
returning the fire with deadly effect. The Indians
recoiled, and were held to their bloody work with
difficulty by their leaders, several of whom were
recognized as whites in disguise. They shot
down the cattle of the emigrants, and maintained
a desultory fire throughout the day and night.</seg></seg></p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">On the next day the Indians were reinforced,
and by whites in <choice><sic>diguise</sic><corr>disguise</corr></choice>, supposably Mormon
allies.</seg> The emigrants, meanwhile, were making
their position strong by chaining their wagons
together and banking earth against them. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="RescueAttempt">Two
of their number stole out of the valley and started
to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> for aid. They met three citizens
of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> on their way, and were attacked
by them. One of them was instantly killed and
the other wounded. The wounded man made his
way back to the emigrant camp, and his story
revealed the awful fact that whites as well as 
Indians were their antagonists.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">In this they were
confirmed by witnessing a manoeuvering party
on the divide of <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName>, composed of fully 250 men, one third of whom were whites. This
party decided that the position of the emigrants
was impregnable.</seg></seg></p>

<pb n="76" xml:id="mmm.wa.boyd.1891.092"/>

<p>But, surrounded as they were, escape was out 
of the question. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">Surrender must be a matter of
only a few days.  <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning">A council of Mormons had
been held and it was agreed that the emigrants
should be decoyed from their stronghold and 
exterminated.</seg> <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and <persName key="Bateman, William Lehi">Bateman</persName>, two Mormon
leaders, approached the camp with a flag of truce.
<persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> represented to the emigrants that the Indians
were very excited and bent on massacre, but that
he had gotten them to promise they would injure
no one who surrendered to the Mormons. 
Believing that the Mormons would protect them, the
surrender was made. The men were to march
out unarmed, each one with a Mormon by his
side, to make the Indians believe he was a captive.
The wagons, loaded with food, sick and wounded
were to go ahead. The women and children were
to follow. The procession passed over the divide
in <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Meadows</geogName> and down the slope beyond. A
Mormon leader, <persName key="Higbee, John M.">Higbee</persName>, is there with a company
of militia. His appearance is assuring, for his
company may prove a source of protection in case 
the Indians renew hostilities.  But in a 
twinkling his company wheels, and each member aims
for the emigrant nearest him. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">Flash go their
rifles in concert and down drop the victims of
their bullets. The Indians rush from their 
ambush and dash with yells upon the women.</seg> The

<pb n="77" xml:id="mmm.wa.boyd.1891.093"/>

horrid work goes on upon the right and left, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>
being present everywhere to see that the 
extermination is made complete. The rifle, the 
tomahawk, the bowie-knife, all do their devilish 
bidding, till there is no one left to tell the tale of a
massacre whose fiendishness is without parallel.
<seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">If it be said it was not inspired by white men,
and not participated in by them, the answer is, no 
Indian could be so hellishly malignant, however 
much he might be a tool and dupe.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">The men all
fell at the first fire. The wounded and the 
women were brained with tomahawks.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">Some 18
children, too young to babble as witnesses, were
taken and distributed among the Mormon 
families.</seg></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The property of the emigrants was divided,
one part went to the Indians, the other was sold
for the benefit of the Mormon Church.</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">The date
of the massacre was Sept. 11, 1857.</seg></p>

<p>For months and years this massacre gave 
occasion for discussion and investigation. <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">The
Mormon leaders charged it to the Indians, who had
been excited by the hostility of the whites.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Even
admitting that whites had participated in it
they too had been wronged. The Church, as a 
Church, had nothing to do with it. On the other
hand, it was contended that the whole thing was
actuated by the Church, and bore evidence of its
action. The facts never could be conclusively

<pb n="78" xml:id="mmm.wa.boyd.1891.094"/>

reached, for the Mormons had hushed the lips of
those who might have convicted them, with their
bullets.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">In 1859 Captain <persName key="Campbell, Reuben P.">Campbell</persName> passed through <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the
Meadows</geogName> and buried <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">the remains of 120 men,
women and children</seg>.</seg> The Mormons showered
honors upon <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and the other leaders in this
dastardly affair. Years afterwards they were
brought to trial. The first trial was a farce. The
second one was even a worse farce, in the respect
that the shrewder Mormons felt that <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> must be
sacrificed in order to save themselves. He was
found guilty of murder, and was shot to death on 
the scene of the massacre, where <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">he confessed to
having killed five of the emigrants with his own
hands</seg>. He died cursing the leaders who had 
deserted him, but professing faith in his religion.
He was not a victim to justice, but was as much
murdered by his accomplices as if they had fired
the last fatal volley.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>