<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">An Overland Journey from New York to San Francisco in the Summer of 1859</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                <author><forename>Horace</forename> <surname>Greeley</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.wa.greeley.1860</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m" type="main">An Overland Journey from New York to San Francisco in the Summer of 1859</title>
                    <author><forename>Horace</forename> <surname>Greeley</surname></author>
                    <publisher>C. M. Saxton, Barker &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>H. H. Bancroft &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                    <extent>182-189; 219-229; 245-257; 258-274</extent>
                    <date when="1860">1860</date>
                    <note type="source">Horace Greeley. <hi rend="italic">An Overland Journey from New York to San Francisco in the Summer of 1859.</hi> New York: C. M. Saxton, Barker &amp; Company, 1860. 182-89, 219-29, 245-57, 258-74.
                    </note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>western_americana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-02-10"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enrichment</change>
            <change when="2010-07-14"><name>Rosie Hanneke</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>

        </revisionDesc>

      
    </teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="182" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.191"/>

<head>XVII</head>

<head type="sub">LARAMIE TO SOUTH PASS.</head>

<opener><dateline><hi rend="smallcaps">SOUTH PASS</hi>, Rocky Mountains, <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 5, 1859.</dateline></opener>

<!-- Need to double Check, this section does not appear relevant:

<p><hi rend="smallcaps">I exhausted</hi> all the possibilities of obtaining a lodging
in Laramie before applying to the commander of 
the post; but no one else could (or would) afford me a
shelter on any terms; so I made a virtue of necessity,
and applied to Captain <persName key="Clarke, Newman S.">Clark</persName>, who at once assigned me
a room&#8212;there being few troops there at present&#8212;and
for the five days I remained there I slept between a
floor and a roof, after five weeks' experience of the more
primitive methods of keeping cold and storm at bay.
I was treated with more than hospitality&#8212;with generous
kindness&#8212;by Captain <persName key="Clarke, Newman S.">Clark</persName>, Lieutenants <persName key="Hascall, Herbert A.">Hascall</persName>
and <persName key="Follett, Frederick M.">Follett</persName>, and Dr. Johns&#8212;and yet the long tarry
became at length irksome, because I had already lost
too much time, and was most anxious to be moving
westward. Finally, the mail-stage from the East hove
in sight on the morning of June 30, but halted just
across Laramie River all day, repairing coach; and it
was eight, p.m., when it started&#8212;I alone perched on
the summit of its seventeen mail-bags as passenger&#8212;
he who had thus far filled that exalted post kindly 
giving way for me, and agreeing to take instead the slower
wagon that was to follow next morning. We forded
the swollen Laramie two miles above the fort, in the last
vestige of twilight&#8212;had the usual trouble with mules

<pb n="183" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.192"/>

turning about in mid-stream, tangling up the team, and
threatening to upset the wagon&#8212;but overcame it after
a while, got safely out, drove on fifteen miles to Warm
Spring&#8212;a fountain which throws out half water enough
for a grist-mill, all which is drank up by the thirsty
sands through which it takes its course, before it can
reach the Platte, only three or four miles distant. We
camped here till daylight, then lost two hours in 
hunting up our mules, which had been simply tied in pairs,
and allowed to go at large in quest of the scanty grass
of that region. They were found at last, and we went
on our way rejoicing.</p>

<p>I shall not weary my readers with a journal of our
travels for the last four days. Hitherto, since I left
civilized <placeName type="state" key="Kansas">Kansas</placeName>, I had traversed routes either newly
opened, or scarcely known to the mass of readers; but
from Laramie I have followed the regular California
and Oregon Overland Trail, already many times 
described, and by this time familiar to hundreds of 
thousands. Suffice it that, for over two hundred miles from
Laramie, it traverses a region substantially described
in my notes of my journey from the buffalo-range to
Denver, and from <placeName type="settlement" key="Denver, CO">Denver</placeName> to Laramie; a region, for the
most part, rainless in summer and autumn, yet on whose
soil of more or less sandy clay, lacking support from
ridges of underlying rock, has been more seamed, and
gouged, and gullied, and washed away, by the action
of floods and streams than any other on earth&#8212;a region
of bluffs and buttes, and deep ravines, and intervales,
and shallow alkaline lakelets, now mainly dried up, and
streams running milky, even when low, with the clay

<pb n="184" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.193"/>

gullied from their banks, and sent off to render the 
Missouri a river of mud, and to fertilize the bottoms of the
lower Mississippi. Occasionally, but not so frequently
as south of Laramie, the clay-hills, hardened into rock
by some alchemy of nature, present the perpendicular
fronts and ruinous-castle aspects already described&#8212;in
a few instances, the scanty creeks which make their
way from the mountains to the North Platte, or the
Sweetwater run through narrow ca&#241;ons of such rock;
but usually each creek has washed out for itself a wide
valley, and the bluffs or buttes, where they exist, are
distant many miles on one side if not on both. In a
few places, the mountains are so near that their thinly-
scattered, stunted, scraggy yellow-pines are plainly
seen&#8212;are even close beside us; but usually the 
prospect is composed of rolling prairie very scantily grassed
and often thickly covered for miles on miles by the
everlasting sage-bush of this desolate region. This is
not an anomaly, as might be supposed&#8212;the stem lives
for years, perhaps centuries, though the shoots and
leaves die* every autumn. Another shrub, less 
common, but which often thickly covers hundreds of acres,
is the grease-wood&#8212;a low, prickly bush, growing in
bunches, like the sage-bush, and looking like a bad imi-
tation of the English privet. Besides these two 
miserable shrubs, the dry land, other than the mountains,
for hundreds of miles, produces a very little burnt-up
grass in patches, and a good many ill-favored weeds of
<note type="footnote">* I guess this is a mistake; further observation induces me to believe
that the sagebush is an evergreen.</note>

<pb n="185" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.194"/>

no known or presumed value. Of wood, the Platte
and its more easterly tributaries have, at intervals, a
shred of the eternal cotton-wood of the plains, much of
it the more scrubby and worthless species known as
bitter cotton-wood, with a very little of the equally
worthless box-elder&#8212;and that is all. But, one hundred
and forty miles this side of Laramie, we leave the Platte,
which here comes from the south, and strike nearly
forty miles across a barren "divide" to its tributary,
the Sweetwater, which we find just by Independence
Rock, quite a landmark in this desolate region, with
several low mountains of almost naked rock around it,
having barely soil enough in their crevices to support a
few dwarfish pines. Five miles above this is the Devil's
Gate&#8212;a passage of the Sweetwater, through a 
perpendicular ca&#241;on, some twenty-five feet wide, and said to
be six hundred feet high&#8212;a passage which must have
been cut while the rock was still clay. Here a large
party of Mormons were caught by the snows, while on
their way to Salt Lake, some years since, and compelled
to encamp for the winter, so scantily provided that
more than a hundred of them died of hunger and 
hardship before spring. Many more must have fallen 
victims had not a supply-train from Salt Lake reached
them early in the season. And here is a fountain of
cold water&#8212;the first that I had seen for more than a
hundred miles, though there is another on the long
stretch from the Platte to the Sweetwater, which is said
to be good, but a drove of cattle were making quite too
free with it when we passed. Here the weary crowds
of emigrants to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> were to gather yesterday for

<pb n="186" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.195"/>

a celebration of the "glorious fourth," and I was warmly
invited to stop and participate, and I now heartily wish
I had, since I find that all our haste was in vain.</p>

<p>It was midnight of the 3d, when we reached the mail-
route station known as the Three-Crossings, from the
fact that so many fordings of the Sweetwater (here 
considerably larger than at its mouth, forty miles or more
below) have to be made within the next mile. We had
been delayed two hours by the breaking away of our
two lead-mules, in crossing a deep water-course after
dark&#8212;or rather by the fruitless efforts of our conductor
to recover them. I had been made sick by the bad
water I had drank from the brooks we crossed during
the hot day, and rose in a not very patriotic, certainly
not a joyful mood, unable to eat, but ready to move on.
We started a little after sunrise; and, at the very first
crossing, one of our lead-mules turned about and ran
into his mate, whom he threw down and tangled so
that he could not get up; and in a minute another
mule was down, and the two in imminent danger of
drowning. They were soon liberated from the harness,
and got up, and we went out; but just then an 
emigrant on the bank espied a carpet-bag in the water&#8212;
mine, of course&#8212;and fished it out. An examination
was then had, and showed that my trunk was missing&#8212;
the boot of the stage having been opened the night
before, on our arrival at the station, and culpably left
unfastened. We made a hasty search for the estray,
but without success, and, after an hour's delay, our 
conductor drove off; leaving my trunk still in the bottom
of Sweetwater, which is said to be ten feet deep just

<pb n="187" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.196"/>

below our ford. I would rather have sunk a thousand
dollars there. Efforts were directed to be made to fish
it out; but my hope of ever seeing it again is a faint
one. We forded Sweetwater six times yesterday after
that, without a single mishap; but I have hardly yet
become reconciled to the loss of my trunk, and, on the
whole, my fourth of July was not a happy one.</p>

<p>Our road left a southerly bend of Sweetwater after
dinner, and took its way over the hills, so as not to
strike the stream again till after dark, at a point three
miles from where I now write. We passed, on a high
divide some miles before we were crossing of the 
Sweetwater, a low swamp or meadow known as "Ice Springs,"
from the fact that ice may be obtained here at any time
by digging down some two or three feet into the frosty
earth. We met several wagon-loads of come-outers
from Mormonism on their way to the states in the course
of the afternoon ; likewise, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">the children</seg> of <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas">the <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName>
people killed</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">two years since</seg></seg>, in what is known as the
mountain-meadows-massacre. We are now nearly at
the summit of the route, with snowy mountains near us
in several directions, and one large snow-bank by the
side of a creek we crossed ten miles back. Yet our
yesterday's road was no rougher, while it was decidedly
better, than that of any former day this side of Laramie,
as may be judged from the fact that, with a late start,
we made sixty miles with one (six mule) team to our
heavy-laden wagon. The grass is better for the last
twenty miles than on any twenty miles previously; and
the swift streams that frequently cross our way are cold
and sweet. But, unlike the Platte, the Sweetwater has

<pb n="188" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.197"/>

scarcely a tree or bush growing on its banks; but up
the little stream on which I am writing, on a box in the
mail company's station-tent, there is glorious water,
some grass, and more wood than I have seen so close
together since I emerged from the gold diggings on 
Vasquer's Fork, five hundred miles away. A snow-bank,
forty rods long and several feet deep, lies just across the
brook; the wind blows cold at night; and we had a
rain-squall&#8212;just rain enough to lay the dust&#8212;yesterday
afternoon.  The mail-agent whom we met here has
orders not to run into Salt Lake ahead of time; so he
keeps us over here to-day, and will then take six days
to reach Salt Lake, which we might reach in four. I am
but a passenger, and must study patience.</p>

<p>A word on the Salt Lake mail. Of the seventeen
bags on which I have ridden for the last four days and
better, at least sixteen are filled with large bound books,
mainly Patent Office Reports, I judge&#8212;but all of them
undoubtedly works ordered printed at the public cost&#8212;
<hi rend="italic">your</hi> cost, reader!&#8212;by 
Congress, and now on their way
to certain favored Mormons, franked (by proxy) " Pub.
Doc. <hi rend="italic">Free</hi>, J. M. Bernhisel, M. C." I do not blame
Mr. B. for clutching his share of this public plunder,
and distributing it so as to increase his own popularity
and importance; but I do protest against this business
of printing books by wholesale at the cost of the whole
people for free distribution to a part only. It is every
way wrong and pernicious. Of the one hundred and
ninety thousand dollars per annum paid for carrying the
Salt Lake mail, nine-tenths is absorbed in the cost of
carrying these franked documents to people who 
<choice><orig>contrib-

<pb n="189" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.198"/>

ute</orig><reg>contribute</reg></choice> little or 
nothing to the support of the government
in any way. Is this fair? Each Patent Office Report
will have cost the treasury four or five dollars by the
time it reaches its destination, and will not be valued by
the receiver at twenty-five cents. Why should this 
business go on? Why not " reform it altogether?" Let
Congress print whatever documents are needed for its
own information, and leavethe people to choose and
buy for themselves. I have spent four days and five
nights in close contact with the sharp edges of Mr ^
Bernhisel's " Pub. Doc."&#8212;have done my very utmost to
I make them present a smooth, or at least endurable 
surface; and I am sure there is no slumber to be extracted
therefrom unless by reading them&#8212;a desperate resort,
which no rational person would recommend. For all
practical purposes, they might as well&#8212;now that the
printer has been paid for them&#8212;be where I heartily wish
they were&#8212;in the bottom of the sea.</p>                
            
</div1> 

<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="219" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.228"/>
                
<head>XXII.</head>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">The Mormons and Mormonism</hi>.</head>
<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Salt Lake City</hi>, <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 18, 1859.</head>

<p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">ince</hi> my interview with Brigham Young, I have
enjoyed opportunities for studying the Mormons in their
social or festive and in their devotional assemblies. Of
private social intercourse&#8212;that is, intercourse between
family and family&#8212;I judge that there is comparatively
little here; between Mormons and Gentiles or strangers,
of course still less. Their religious services (in the 
tabernacle) are much like those that may be shared or 
witnessed in the churches of most of our popular sects; the
music rather better than you will hear in an average
worshiping assemblage in the states ; the prayers 
pertinent and full of unction ; the sermons adapted to tastes
or needs different from mine. They seemed to me
rambling, dogmatic, and ill-digested; in fact, 
Elder Orson Pratt, who preached last Sunday morning, prefaced
his harangue by a statement that he had been hard at
work on his farm throughout the week, and labored
under consequent physical exhaustion. Elder John
Taylor (I believe he is one of the Twelve ; at all events
he is a high dignitary in the church, and a man of 
decided natural ability) spoke likewise in the afternoon
with little or no premeditation. Now, I believe that
every preacher should be also a worker; I like to see
one mowing or pitching hay in his shirt-sleeves; and I
            
<pb n="220" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.229"/>
                
hear with edification an unlettered but devout and 
earnest evangelist who, having worked a part of the week
for the subsistence of his family, devotes the rest of it to
preaching the gospel to small school-house or wayside
gatherings of hearers, simply for the good of their souls.
Let him only be sure to talk good sense, and I will
excuse some bad grammar. But when a preacher is to
address a congregation of one to three thousand persons,
like that which assembles twice each sabbath in the
Salt Lake City Tabernacle, I insist that a due regard for
the economy of time requires that he should prepare
himself, by study and refiection, if not by writing, to
speak directly to the point. This mortal life is too short
and precious to be wasted in listening to rambling,
loose-jointed harangues, or even to those which severally
consume an hour in the utterance, when they might be
boiled down and clarified until they were brought within
the compass of half an hour each. A thousand half-
hours, Reverend Sir! have you ever pondered their
value? Suppose your time to be worth ten times that
of an average hearer; still, to take an extra half-hour
from a thousand hearers in order to save yourself ten or
fifteen hours' labor in the due and careful preparation
of a sermon, is a scandalous waste, which I see not how
to justify. Be entreated to repent and amend!</p>

<p>The two discourses to which I listened were each 
intensely and exclusively Mormon. That is, they assumed
that the Mormons were God's peculiar, chosen, beloved
people, and that all the rest of mankind are out of the
ark of safety and floundering in heathen darkness. I
am not edified by this sort of preaching. It reminds

<pb n="221" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.230"/>

me forcibly of the Pharisee's prayer: "Lord, I thank
thee that I am not as other men are&#8212;unjust, 
extortioners," etc. I do not think good men delight in this
assumption of an exclusive patent for the grace of God;
and I am quite sure it is not well adapted to the 
transformation of bad men into good. It is too well calculated
to puff up its disciples with self-conceit and spiritual
pride. That Jesus Christ is about to re-appear on the
earth in all the pomp and splendor of a mighty 
conqueror&#8212;that he will then proceed to take vengeance on his
enemies (mankind in general, whether heathen or 
nominally Christians) and to glorify his elect (the Latter-Day
Saints or Mormons) were treated by the Tabernacle
preachers as propositions too self-evident to need 
demonstration. Having thus chastised his enemies and 
"gathered his elect from the four winds of heaven," the
Saviour is to reign over them here on earth for a 
thousand years; at the end of which period, they are together
to be transferred to heaven. Of course, I had heard the
like of this before; but it always seems to me a very
gross and wooden perversion of the magnificent 
imagery whereby the Bible foreshadows a great spiritual
transformation. The spirit of the Mormon religion 
appears to me Judaic rather than Christian; and I am
well assured that Heber O. Kimball, one of the great
lights of the church, once said in conversation with a
Gentile&#8212;"I <hi rend="italic">do</hi> pray for my enemies : I pray that they
may all go to hell." Neither from the pulpit nor 
elsewhere have I heard from a Mormon one spontaneous,
hearty recognition of the essential brotherhood of the
human race&#8212;one generous prayer for the enlightenment

<pb n="222" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.231"/>

and salvation of all mankind. On the other hand, I
have been distinctly given to understand that my 
interlocutors expect to sit on thrones and to bear rule over
multitudes in the approaching kingdom of God. In
fact, one sincere, devout man has to-day assigned that
to me as a reason for polygamy; he wants to qualify
himself, by ruling a large and diversified family here,
for bearing rule over his principality in the "new earth,"
that he knows to be at hand. I think he might far 
better devote a few years to pondering Christ's saying to
this effect, "He who would be least in the kingdom of
heaven, the same shall be greatest."</p>

<p>I was undeceived with regard to the Book of 
Mormon. I had understood that it is now virtually 
discarded, or at least neglected, by the church in its 
services and ministrations. But Elder Pratt gave us a
synopsis of its contents, and treated it throughout as of
equal authority and importance with the Old and New
Testaments. He did not read from it, however, but
from Malachi, and quoted text after text from the 
prophets, which he cited as predictions of the writing and
discovery of this book.</p>

<p>The congregation consisted, at either service of some
fifteen hundred to two thousand persons&#8212;more in the
morning than the afternoon. A large majority of them
(not including the elders and chief men, of whom a
dozen or so were present) were evidently of European
birth; I think a majority of the males were past the
meridian of life. All gave earnest heed to the exercises
throughout; in fact, I have seldom seen a more devout
and intent assemblage. I had been told that the 
<choice><orig>Mor-

<pb n="223" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.232"/>

mons</orig><reg>Mormons</reg></choice>
 were remarkably ignorant, superstitious, and
brutalized; but the aspect of these congregations did
not sustain that assertion. Very few rural 
congregations would exhibit more heads evincing decided ability;
and I doubt whether any assemblage, so largely 
European in its composition, would make a better 
appearance. Not that Europeans are less intellectual or
comely than Americans ; but our emigrants are mainly
of the poorer classes; and poverty, privation, and 
rugged toil, plow hard, forbidding lines in the human 
countenance elsewhere than in Utah. Brigham Young was
not present at either service.</p>

<p>Do I regard the great body of these Mormons as
knaves and hypocrites? Assuredly not. I do not 
believe there was ever a religion whereof the great mass
of the adherents were not honest and sincere. 
Hypocrites and knaves there are in all sects; it is quite 
possible that some of the magnates of the Mormon Church
regard this so-called religion (with all others) as a 
contrivance for the enslavement and fleecing of the many,
and the aggrandizement of the few; but I cannot believe
that a sect, so considerable and so vigorous as the 
Mormon, was ever founded in conscious imposture, or built
up on any other basis than that of earnest conviction.
If the projector, and two or three of his chief 
confederates are knaves, the great body of their followers were
dupes.</p>

<p>Nor do I accept the current Gentile presumption, that
the Mormons are an organized banditti&#8212;a horde of 
robbers and assassins. Thieves and murderers mainly
haunt the purlieus of great cities, or hide in caverns

<pb n="224" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.233"/>

and forests adjacent to the great routes of travel. But
when the Mormon leaders decided to set up their Zion
in these parched mountain vales and ca&#241;ons, the said
valleys were utterly secluded and remote from all 
Gentile approach&#8212;away from any mail-route or channel of
emigration. That the Mormons wished to escape 
Gentile control, scrutiny, jurisprudence, is evident; that
they meant to abuse their inaccessibility, to the 
detriment and plunder of wayfarers, is not credible.</p>

-->

<p>Do I, then, discredit the tales of Mormon outrages
and crime&#8212;of <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">the murder of the Parrishes</seg>, the Mountain Meadow massacre, etc. etc.&#8212;<seg type="Source" subtype="PublicMind">wherewith the general ear has recently been shocked?</seg> No, I do not. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">Some of these may have been fabricated by Gentile malice&#8212;others are doubtless exaggerated&#8212;but there is some basis of truth for the current Gentile conviction that
the Mormons have robbed, maimed, and even killed
persons in this territory, under circumstances which
should subject the perpetrators to condign punishment,
but that Mormon witnesses, grand jurors, petit jurors,
and magistrates determinedly screen the guilty.</seg> I
deeply regret the necessity of believing this; but the
facts are incontestable. That <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a large party of emigrants &#8212;not less than eighty</seg>&#8212;<seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route">from <placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg> to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>,
were foully massacred <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain Meadows</geogName></seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in
September, 1857</seg>, <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">more immediately by Indians, but under the
direct inspiration and direction of the Mormon settlers
in that vicinity</seg>&#8212;to whom, and not to the savages, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">the emigrants had surrendered, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Battle">after a siege</seg>, on the strength
of assurances that their lives at least should be spared</seg>&#8212;
is established by evidence that cannot (I think) be 
<choice><orig>in-

<pb n="225" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.234"/>

validated</orig><reg>invalidated</reg></choice>
&#8212;the evidence of conscience-smitten partakers
in the crime, both Indian and ex-Mormon</seg>, and of 
<seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">children of the slaughtered emigrants, who were spared as too young to be dangerous even as witnesses, and of
whom the great majority have been sent down to the
states as unable to give testimony; <seg type="Source" subtype="Children">but two boys are retained here as witnesses, who distinctly remember
that <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">their parents surrendered to white men, and that <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">these white men at best did not attempt to prevent their perfidious massacre.</seg></seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">These children, moreover, were
all found in the possession of Mormons&#8212;not one of
them in the hands of Indians; and, though the 
Mormons say they ransomed them from the hands of Indians,
the children deny it, saying that they never lived with,
nor were in the keeping of savages; and the Indians
bear concurrent testimony.</seg></seg></seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">So in the Parrish case:</seg> the
family had been Mormons, but had apostatized&#8212;and
undertook to return to the states; they were warned
that they would be killed if they persisted in that 
resolution; they did persist, and were killed. Of course,
nobody will ever be convicted of their murder; but
those who warned them of the fate on which they were
rushing know why they were killed, and could discover,
if they would, who killed them.</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">The vital fact in the case is just this: The great mass
of these people, as a body, mean to be honest, just, and
humane; but they are, before and above all things else,
Latter-Day Saints, or Mormons. They devoutly believe
that they are God's peculiar and especial people, doing
His work, up-building His kingdom, and basking in the
sunshine of His peculiar favor. Whoever obstructs or

<pb n="226" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.235"/>
                
impedes them in this work, then, is God's enemy, who
must be made to get out of the way of the establishment
of Christ's kingdom on earth&#8212;made to do so by lawful
and peaceful means if possible, but by any means that
may ultimately be found necessary.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">The Parrisheswere apostates; had they been allowed to pursue their journey to the states, they would have met many Saints
coming, up the road, whose minds they would have
troubled if not poisoned; and they would have told
stories after reaching their destination which would have
deepened the general prejudice against the Saints; so
the up-building and well-being of Christ's kingdom 
required that they should die.</seg> <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">The <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName> emigrants</seg> slaughtered <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain-Meadows</geogName></seg>, had in some way
abused the Saints, or interposed obstacles to the progress
of God's work, and they were consequently given over
to destruction.</seg> Far be it from me to hint that one-fifth,
one-tenth, one-twentieth, of the Mormons ever bore any
part in these bloody deeds, or even know to this day
that they were perpetrated. The great body of the
Saints undoubtingly believe all the current imputations
of Mormon homicide and outrage to be abominable
calumnies. Many of the highest dignitaries of the
church may be included in this number. But there are
men in the church who know that they are <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
calumnies&#8212;who know that Gentiles and apostates have been
killed for the church's and for Christ's sake, and who
firmly believe that they <hi rend="italic">ought</hi> to have been. I grieve
to say it, but I hold these more consistent and logical
Mormons than their innocent and unsuspicious brethren.
For if I were a Latter-Day Saint, undoubtingly 
<choice><orig>believ-

<pb n="227" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.236"/>

ing</orig><reg>believing</reg></choice>
 all opposers of the Mormon Church to be God's
enemies, obnoxious to His wrath and curse, and 
powerfully obstructing the rescue of souls from eternal 
perdition and torture, I should be strongly impelled to help
put those opposers of God's purposes out of the way of
sending any more immortal souls to everlasting fire. I
should feel it my duty so to act, as a lover of God and
man. And I confidently predict that not one Mormon
who has killed a Gentile or apostate under a like view
of his duty will ever be fairly convicted in this territory.
No jury can be drawn here, unless in flagrant defiance
of territorial laws, which is not mainly composed of
Mormons; and no such jury will convict a Mormon of
crime for any act done in behalf of God's kingdom&#8212;
that is, of the Mormon church.</p>

<p>I ask, then, the advocates of "popular sovereignty"
in the territories to say what they propose to do in the
premises. How do they intend to adapt their principle
to the existing state of facts? They have superseded
<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, with a full knowledge that at least
nine-tenths of the people of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory"> Utah</placeName> earnestly desired his
retention as governor. They have sent hither a batch
of judges, who would like to earn their salaries; but
the Mormon legislature devotes its sessions principally
to the work of crippling and fettering these judges, so
that they shall remain here as mere dummies or be
driven into resignation. Their juries are all drawn for
them by Mormon officials, under regulations which 
virtually exclude all but Mormons from each panel; it is
a violation of all the laws of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> to cite in argument
before any judge or jury here the decisions of any
      
<pb n="228" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.237"/>
                
court&#8212;even the supreme court of the United States&#8212;
but the courts of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>; so that even the <persName key="Scott, Dred">Dred Scott</persName>
decision could not lawfully be cited here in a fugitive
slave case; in short, the federal judiciary, the federal
executive, and the federal army, as now existing in
<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, are three transparent shams&#8212;three egregious
farces; they are costing the treasury very large sums to
no purpose; and the sooner the governor, marshal,
judges, etc., resign, and the army is withdrawn, the 
better for all but a handful of contractors. "Popular
sovereignty" has such full swing here that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham
Young</persName> carries <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory"> the territory</placeName> in his breeches' pocket 
without a shadow of opposition; he governs without 
responsibility to either law or public opinion; for there is no
real power here but that of "the church," and he is
practically the church. The church is rich, and is 
hourly increasing in wealth; the church settles all civil
controversies which elsewhere cause lawsuits; the
church spends little or nothing, yet rules everything;
while the federal government, though spending two or
three millions per annum here, and keeping up a fussy
parade of authority, is powerless and despised. If,
then, we are to have "popular sovereignty" in the 
territories, let us have it pure and without shams. Let
<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> be reappointed governor; withdraw the 
present federal office-holders and army; open shorter and
better roads to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> through the country north of
Bridger; and notify the emigrants that, if they choose
to pass through <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, they will do so at their own risk. Let the Mormons have the territory to themselves&#8212;it is worth very little to others, but reduce its area by

<pb n="229" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.238"/>
                
cutting off Carson Valley on the one side, and making
a Rocky Mountain territory on the other, and then let
them go on their way rejoicing. I believe this is not
only by far the cheapest but the safest and best mode
of dealing with the difficulties already developed and
daily developing here, unless the notion of "popular
sovereignty" in the territories is to be utterly exploded
and given up. "Popular Sovereignty" in a territory
is a contradiction in terms; but "popular sovereignty"
in a territory backed by a thousand sharp federal 
bayonets and a battery of flying artillery, is too monstrous a
futility, too transparent a swindle, to be much longer
upheld or tolerated.</p>

</div1>

<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="245" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.254"/>    



<head>XXIV. THE ARMY IN UTAH.</head>

<head><hi rend="smallcaps">Camp Floyd</hi>, Utah, <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 21, 1869.</head>      

<!-- The following Section is not Directly Relevant to Mountain Meadows:

<p>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amp</hi> F<hi rend="smallcaps">loyd</hi>, 
forty miles south of Salt Lake City, is
located on the west side of a dry valley, perhaps ten
miles wide by thirty miles long, separated by high hills
from Lake Utah, some fifteen to twenty miles distant on
the north-east. This valley would be fertile were it not
doomed to sterility by drouth. A small stream takes its
rise in copious springs at the foot of the western hills
just north of the camp, but is soon drank up by the
thirsty plain. Water in this stream, and wood (low
cedar) on the adjacent hills, probably dictated the 
selection of this site for a camp; though I believe a desire,
if not a secret compact, to locate the troops as far as
possible from the Mormon settlements, had an influence
in the premises. No Mormons live in this valley nor
within sight of it; though all the roads leading from
Salt Lake City, as well as from Provo and the other
settlements around Lake Utah, are within a day's march
and may be said to be commanded by the camp. The
soil is easily pulverized when dry, and keeps the entire
area enveloped, during summer, in a dense cloud of
dust, visible for miles in every direction. I saw it when
eight miles away, as I came down from Salt Lake City
yesterday. We passed few houses on the way; but a
distillery and a brewery were among them. We crossed

<pb n="246" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.255"/>

the Jordan by fording, at a point seven or eight miles
from the Lake, and twenty-five to thirty from Salt Lake
City. The stream is here swift and strong, but hardly
thirty inches deep, and not more than thirty yards
wide. We passed within sight of Provo, but several
miles from it. We passed one spring on the route, and
two or three brooks running from the high-steep 
mountains on the east. The drouth was intense, and seemed
habitual in summer; there was no cultivation nor 
industry of any sort on our road, save within twenty miles of
Salt Lake City.</p>

<p>The camp is formed of low and neat adobe houses,
generally small. I presume there are three or four 
hundred of them&#8212;enough, at all events, to make six or
eight Kansas cities. "Frogtown" is a satellite, or 
suburb, whence grog and other luxuries (including 
execrable whisky at about ten dollars per gallon) are 
dispensed to thirsty soldiers who have not already drank
up more than their pay amounts to. The valley is
covered with sage-bush and grease-wood, as usual; but 
the camp has been freed from these, and is mainly level
as a house-floor. The adobes ware made on the spot by
Mexicans; the boards for roofs, finishing off, etc., 
supplied by Brigham Young and his son-in-law, from the
only ca&#241;on opening into Salt Lake Valley which abounds 
in timber (yellow-pine, I believe,) fit for sawing. The
territorial legislature&#8212;(which is another name for "the 
church") granted this ca&#241;on to Brigham, who runs three 
saw-mills therein, at a clear profit of one hundred dollars
or so per day. His profit on the lumber supplied to the
camp was probably over fifty thousand dollars. The

<pb n="247" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.256"/>
                
price was seventy dollars per thousand feet, delivered.
President Young assured me, with evident self-complacency,
that he did not need and would not accept a 
dollar of salary from "the church"&#8212;he considered himself
able to make all the money he needed by business, as
he had made the two hundred and fifty thousand dollars
worth of property he already possesses. With a 
legislature ever ready to grant him such perquisites as this
lumber ca&#241;on, I should think he might. The total cost
of this post to the government was about two hundred
thousand dollars.</p>

<p>The army in Utah has numbered three thousand five
hundred men&#8212;I believe its present strength is but about
three thousand. It is mainly concentrated in this camp,
though some small detachments are engaged in 
surveying or opening roads, guarding herds, etc., in different 
parts of the territory. I presume this is still the largest
regular force ever concentrated upon the soil of our 
country in time of peace. It consists of the 5th, 7th 
and 10th regiments of infantry, a battalion of light
artillery, and two or three companies of dragoons. I 
met, between Bridger and Ham's Fork, a considerable
force of dragoons going down.</p>

<p>Let us briefly consider the history and position of this
little army: </p>

<p>In the earlier half of 1857, it was concentrated in 
Kansas; late in that year, the several regiments 
composing it were severally put in march toward the Rocky
Mountains. The Mormons soon full learned that this
band was to be launched against them, and at once 
prepared to give it a warm reception; the army had no

<pb n="248" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.257"/>
                
information on the subject, save general report. 
Detained in Kansas to give effect to Governor Walker's
electioneering quackeries, it was at length sent on its
way at a season too late to allow it to reach Salt Lake
before winter. No commander was sent with it; 
General Harney was announced as its chief, but has not
even yet joined it. It was thus dispatched on a long
and difficult expedition, in detachments, without a chief,
without orders, without any clear idea of its object or
destination. Entering Utah thus as no army, but as a
number of separate, straggling detachments, neither of 
which was ordered to protect the supply-train, which 
followed one or two marches behind them, the soldiers
had the mortification to learn, about the first of 
October, that those supply-trains, without even an armed
corporal's guard in their vicinity, had been surprised
and burnt by a Mormon band, who thus in effect made 
war on the United States. Indignantly, but still 
without a leader and without definite orders, the army 
struggled on to Bridger, one hundred and thirteen miles from
Salt Lake, which the Mormons abandoned on its 
approach. Bridger is many thousand feet above the sea
level, and the ground was here so buried in snow that
its gaunt animals died by hundreds, and the residue
were unable to drag the baggage over the rivers and
steep mountains which still separated it from Salt Lake.
So the regiments halted, built huts to shelter themselves i
from the winter's inclemency, and lived through the 
snowy season as they might on a half allowance of
beef from their lean, gristly animals, without salt.</p>

<p>Spring at length came; the order to march, long

<pb n="249" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.258"/>

hoped and impatiently waited for, was given; they had
been promised a warm reception in the narrow defiles
of Echo Canon by Lieutenant-General Wells and his
Mormon host, and they eagerly courted that reception.
If General Wells were able, as he boasted, to send them
to the right about, they would have nothing to do but
to go. They had grown rusty from inaction, and stood
ready to be polished, even by so rough an implement as
General Wells. But news came that the whole affair
had been somehow arranged&#8212;that Colonel Kane, 
Brigham Young, and Governor Cumming had fixed matters
so that there would be no fighting&#8212;not even further
train-burning. Yet the Mormons lied from Salt Lake
City in anticipation of their entering it; they were
somehow, required to encamp as far from the Mormon
settlements as possible; and they have ever since been
treated by the federal executive as though they had
volunteered to come here in defiance of, rather than in
obedience to, that executive's own orders.</p>

<p>Whether truly or falsely, this army, probably without 
an individual exception, undoubtingly believes the 
Mormons as a body to be traitors to the Union and its 
government, inflexibly intent on establishing here a
power which shall be at first independent of, and 
ultimately dominant over, that of the United States. They
believe that the ostentatious, defiant refusal of Brigham
Young, in 1857, to surrender the territorial 
governorship, and his declaration that he would hold that post
until God Almighty should tell him to give it up, were
but the natural development of a polity which looks to
the subjugation of all earthly kingdoms, states, empires,
            
<pb n="250" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.259"/>
                
sovereignties, to a rule nominally theocratic, but 
practically autocratic, with Brigham Young or his designated
successor as despot. They hold that the instinct of self-
preservation, the spirit of that requirement of the 
Federal Constitution which enjoins that each state shall be
guaranteed a republican form of government, cry out
against such a despotism, and demand its overthrow.</p>

-->

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><seg type="Context" subtype="TerritorialAdministration">The army undoubtingly and universally believes that Mormonism is, at least on the part of the master spirits
of "the church," an organized, secret, treasonable 
conspiracy to extend the power, increase the wealth, and
gratify the lecherous appetites of those leaders, who are
using the forms and terms of religion to mask and shield
systematic adultery, perjury, counterfeiting, robbery,
treason, and even murder. It points to the <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">wholesale
massacre</seg> <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">at <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meados">Mountain-meadows</geogName></seg>, <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">the murder of the 
Parrishes</seg>, and a hundred more such, as instances of 
Mormon assassination for the good of the church, the 
chastisement of its enemies, or the aggrandizement of its
leading members&#8212;to the impossibility of bringing the 
perpetrators of these crimes to justice, to the territorial
laws of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> which empower Mormon functionaries to select the grand and petit jurors even for the United 
States courts, and impose qualifications which in effect 
secure the exclusion of all but Mormons from the jury-
box, and to the uniform refusal of those jurors to indict
or convict those who have committed crimes in the 
interest of Mormonism,* as proof positive that all <choice><orig>at-

<note type="footnote">* <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS"><persName key="Cradlebaugh, John">Judge Cradlebaugh</persName> asserts that on the list 
of jurors recently imposed on him for the investigation at <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>
<seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">of the Parrish and other murders</seg>, he knows there were not less
than <hi rend="italic">nine</hi> leading participants in 
those murders.</seg></note>

<pb n="251" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.260"/>

tempts</orig><reg>attempts</reg></choice>
 to punish Mormon criminals by Mormon jurors
and officers must ever prove abortive, and demands of
the federal government that it shall devise and put in
execution some remedy for this unbearable impunity to
crime.</seg> <seg type="Context" subtype="LDSApostates">It is uniformly believed in camp that not less than <hi rend="italic">seventy-five</hi> distinct instances of murder by Mormons because of apostacy, or some other form of 
hostility to "the church," or mainly for the sake of 
plunder, are known to the authorities here, and that there
is no shadow of hope that one of the perpetrators will
ever be brought to justice under the sway of Mormon
"popular sovereignty" as now established in this 
territory.</seg> The army, therefore, turns an anxious eye to
Washington, and strains its ear to hear what remedy is
to be applied.</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">Manifestly, the recent responses from that quarter
are not calculated to allay this anxiety. The official
rebuke recently and publicly given to the federal judges
here, for employing detachments of troops to arrest and
hold securely Mormons accused of capital crime, elicits
low mutterings of dissatisfaction from some, with a
grave silence on the part of many whom discipline
restrains from speaking. As the recent orders from
<placeName type="state" key="Washington, D. C.">Washington</placeName> are understood here, no employment of federal troops to arrest or secure persons charged with or even convicted of crime is allowed, except where the
civil power (intensely Mormon) shall have certified that
the execution of process is resisted by a force which it
cannot overcome by means of a civil <hi rend="italic">posse</hi>. How 
opposite this is to the orders given and obeyed in the
fugitive slave cases at <placeName type="settlement" key="Boston, MA">Boston</placeName>, etc., need hardly be 
indicated.</seg></p>
                              
<pb n="252" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.261"/>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">Very general, then, is the inquiry in the army, Why were we sent here? and why are we kept here? What
good can our remaining do? What mischief can it
prevent? A fettered, suspected, watched, distrusted
army&#8212;an army which must do nothing&#8212;must not even
be asked to do anything in any probable contingency&#8212;
what purpose does it subserve beyond enriching 
contractors and Mormon magnates at its own cost and that 
of the federal treasury? Every article eaten, drank, 
worn, or in any manner bought by the soldiers, costs
three to ten times its value in the states; part of this
extra cost falls on the treasury, the residue on the troops
individually. Their position here is an irksome one;
their comforts few; home, family, friends are far away.
If the policy now pursued is to prevail, they cannot be
needed in this territory. Why, then, are they kept
here? <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> will contract, and make moneyby contracting, to put down all resistance to this policy
at one-tenth the cost of keeping the army here: why,
then, not withdraw it?</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Reaction" subtype="MilitaryRetaliation">I have not so bad an opinion of the Mormons as that entertained by the army. While I consider the 
Mormon religion, so called, a delusion and a blight, I believe
many of its devoted adherents, including most of those
I have met, to be pure-minded, well-meaning people;
and <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">I do not believe that Mormons generally delight in plunder or murder, though the testimony in the 
Mountain-meadows, <seg type="Context" subtype="ParrishMurder">Parrish</seg>, and one or two other cases, is certainly staggering.</seg> But I concur entirely in the 
conviction of the army, that there is no use in its retention
here under existing orders and circumstances, and that
            
<pb n="253" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.262"/>

three or four companies of dragoons would answer every
purpose of this large and costly concentration of troops.
The army would cost less almost anywhere else, and
could not anywhere be less useful.</seg></p>

<p>A suspicion that it is kept here to answer private
pecuniary ends is widely entertained. It is known that
vast sums have been made out of its transportation by
favored contractors. Take a single instance already
quite notorious: twenty-two cents per pound is paid
for the transportation of all provisions, munitions, etc.,
from Leavenworth to this point. The great contractors
were allowed this for transporting this year's supply
of flour. By a little dexterous management at 
<placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, D. C.">Washington</placeName>, they were next allowed to furnish the flour here
&#8212;<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> flour&#8212;being paid their twenty-two cents per
pound for transportation, in addition to the prime cost
on the <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName>. As <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> has a better soil for growing
wheat than almost anything else, they had no difficulty
in sub-letting this contract at seven cents per pound 
net, making a clear profit of one hundred and seventy 
thousand dollars on the contract, without risking 
a dollar, or lifting a finger. Of course, I expect 
contractors to bargain for themselves, not for the 
government, but somebody is well paid for taking care of the
public's interest in such matters. Has he done his 
duty? </p>

<p>Again, pursuant to a recent order from <placeName type="state" key="Washington, D. C.">Washington</placeName>,
the Assistant Quartermaster-General here is now selling
by auction some two thousand mules&#8212;about two-thirds
of all the government owns in this territory. These
mules cost one hundred and seventy-five dollars each,
            
<pb n="254" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.263"/>
                
and are worth to-day one hundred and twenty-five to
one hundred and fifty dollars. I attended the sale for
an hour or so this forenoon; the range of prices was
from sixty to one hundred and fifteen dollars; the 
average of the seven hundred already sold about seventy-
five dollars. Had these mules been taken to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>,
and there properly advertised and sold, they would have
brought nearly cost; even at Leavenworth, they must
have sold for at least one hundred thousand dollars more
than here, where there is practically no demand and no
competition for such an immense herd; and, after every
Mormon, who can raise a hundred dollars or over, shall
have supplied himself with a span of mules for half
their value, one or two speculators will make as much as
they please, while the dead loss to the people will be at
least one hundred and fifty thousand dollars. Nobody 
here has recommended the sale of these mules; they
were being herded, under the care of detachments of the 
army, at no cost but for herdsmen, and they could have 
been kept through next winter, in secluded mountain
valleys, at a cost of about ten dollars per head; whereas 
the army can never move without purchasing an equal 
number; and they can neither be bought here nor
brought here for two hundred thousand dollars more 
than these animals are now fetching. <hi rend="italic">Somebody's</hi>
interest is subserved by this sale; but it is certainly not
that of the army nor of the people. The order is to sell
seven hundred wagon's as well; but these would not 
bring thirty dollars each, while they cost at least one 
hundred and thirty, and could not be replaced when
wanted even for that, while the army cannot move 

<pb n="255" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.264"/>
                
without them, and keeping them costs absolutely 
nothing. Who issues such orders as this, and for whose
benefit?</p> 

<p>Look at another feature of this transaction. There is
at this moment a large amount due to officers and 
soldiers of this army as pay, in sums of forty to five 
hundred dollars each. Many of those to whom this money
is due would very much like to take mules in part-
payment, either to use while here, to sell again, or to bear
them and their baggage to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, or back to the
<placeName type="state" key="Missiouri">Missouri</placeName>, on the approaching expiration of their terms of enlistment. In many instances, two soldiers would
doubtless club to buy a mule on which to pack their
blankets, etc., whenever their time is out. Hundreds
of mules would thus have been bought, and the 
proceeds of the sale considerably augmented, if the 
government, by its functionaries, had consented to receive its
own honest debts in payment. But no! on some 
ridiculous pretense of ill-blood between the pay and the
subsistence bureaux of the War department, this is
refused&#8212;it would be too much trouble to take 
certificates of soldiers' pay actually due in payment for these
mules; so the officers and soldiers must purchase of
speculators at double price, or go without, and the
mules be sold for far less than they would have brought,
if those who must have them had been enabled to bid
directly for them. Two or three speculators reap a
harvest here at the sore cost of the soldiers and the
treasury.</p>

<p>But it will be said that forage is dear in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>. It would suffice to answer that idle mules obtain, save in

<pb n="256" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.265"/>

winter, only grass growing on the public lands, which
may as well be eaten in part by government mules as
all by those of the Mormon squatters. But let us see
how it costs so much. There have recently been 
received here thirty thousand bushels of corn from the
states at a net cost, including transportation, of three 
hundred and forty thousand dollars, or over eleven 
dollars per bushel. No requisition was ever made for this
corn, which could have been bought here, delivered,
for two dollars per bushel, or sixty thousand dollars in
all. The dead loss to the treasury on this corn is two
hundred and eighty thousand dollars, even supposing
that the service required it at all. <hi rend="italic">Somebody</hi> makes a
good thing of wagoning this corn from the Missouri at
over ten dollars a bushel. Who believes that said 
somebody has not influential and thrifty connections inside
of the War department?</p>

<p>I will not pursue this exposition; Congress may.</p>

<p>Let me now give a sample of retrenchment in the 
public service in this quarter:</p>

<p>The mail from <placeName type="state" key="Missouri">Missouri</placeName> to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> has hitherto been carried weekly in good six-mule wagons; the 
contract time being twenty-two days. The importance of 
frequent and regular communication with head-quarters,
at least so long as a large army is retained here at a
heavy extra cost, and because of some presumed public
necessity is evident. Yet the new Postmaster-General
has cut down the mail-service on this important central
route from weekly to semi-monthly. But the 
contractors, who are obliged to run their stages weekly because
of their passenger business, and because they have to
                   
<pb n="257" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.266"/>
                
keep their stock and pay their men, whether they work
or play, find that they cannot carry the mail every
other week so cheaply as they can every week. For
instance, a mail from the states now often consists of
twelve to sixteen heavy sacks (most of them filled with
franked documents), weighing as many hundred pounds.
Double this, and no six-mule team would draw it at the
requisite pace, and no mail-wagon stand the jerks and
jolts of an unmade road. So they say, "please let us
carry the mail weekly, though you only pay us for car-
rying it semi-monthly." But no! this is strictly 
forbidden! The post-master at Salt Lake has express 
written orders to refuse it, and of course he at St. Joseph
also. And thus all this central region, embracing, at
least a dozen important military posts, and countless
Indian agencies, is reduced to a semi-monthly mail-
service, though the contractor would gladly make it weekly
at the same price!</p>

</div1>
          
<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="258" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.267"/>
                         
<head>XXV.</head>

<head><hi rend="smallcaps"><choice><sic>ROM</sic><corr>FROM</corr></choice> SALT LAKE TO CARSON VALLEY.</hi></head>

<head>P<hi rend="smallcaps">lacerville</hi>, Cal., <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 31, 1859.</head>

<p>There are two emigrant trails from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> to Carson Valley and the pass thence into <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>&#8212;
the older and more favored, starts north-west from the
Mormon Zion, passes north and west of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, crossing Weber and Bear Rivers near their mouths, with several small creeks, and gradually veering west and
south-west so as to strike the head springs of the 
Humboldt, which stream it follows more than three hundred
miles to its "sink," within a hundred miles of the 
eastern Base of the Sierra Nevada. The other route leaves
the Mormon capital in a south-westerly direction, touches
Lake Utah on the north, passes west of that Lake
through <placeName type="settlement" key="Provo, UT">Provo</placeName>, and thence southerly through <placeName type="settlement" key="Fillmore, UT">Fillmore</placeName>, the nominal capital of the territory, and so down by
Soyier River and Lake nearly to <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location">the southern boundary of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, whence it stretches west, nearly upon the southern rim of the Great Basin, on which are the "<geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">Mountain-Meadows</geogName>,"</seg> where <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a large emigrant party</seg>  from <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="StateAffiliationArkansas"><placeName type="state" key="Arkansas">Arkansas</placeName></seg> was so atrociously massacred <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in 1857</seg>.
Thence this trail turns north-west to hit the sink of 
Carson River. (I can get no tolerable map of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and the above may not be entirely correct, but is nearly so.) It will be seen that each of these routes must necessarily
be very circuitous, and that almost, if not quite half

<pb n="259" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.268"/>
                
<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the territory</placeName> lies between them.</p>

<!-- The Following Section is Not Directly Relevant to Mountain Meadows. (Note: The break falls in mid-paragraph, but a closing p tag was insterted after "the territory lies between them" in order for the file to be valid, despite the remainder of the actual paragraph falling within the commented out section):

 So, last year, Major <persName key="Chorpening, George">Chorpening</persName>, the contractor for carrying the <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>
and <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> Mail, resolved to seek a shorter route midway between them, which he partially succeeded in 
establishing. This route passes Camp Floyd, forty-three
miles south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName>, and thence strikes west
south-west through "the Desert," so called, which it
penetrates for one hundred and fifty miles or more;
thence turning north-west to reach and follow the 
original emigrant and mail-route down the Humboldt. Even
thus, it is somewhat shorter than any other traveled route
from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> to Carson Valley, but still very tortuous,
and at least one hundred and fifty miles longer than it
should be. Capt. <persName key="Simpson, James H.">Simpson</persName>, of the U. S. Topographical Corps, has recently made his way quite through the desert,
on a route which makes the distance only five hundred
and sixty-one miles from Camp Floyd to Carson Valley;
whereas it is six hundred and seventy by the present
mail-route, and further by any other. Capt. <persName key="Simpson, James H.">Simpson</persName> is now engaged in further surveys, whereby he hopes* to
shorten the distance from <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> to <placeName type="settlement" key="Genoa, UT">Genoa</placeName>, near
the head of Carson Valley, to about five hundred and 
fifty miles; and two of Major <persName key="Chorpening, George">Chorpening</persName>'s superintendents
are now examining the new portion of this route, 
intending to recommend a transfer of the mail to it should
they deem it practicable for wagons, and not hopelessly
destitute of grass and water. I trust they will find it

<note type="footnote">* These hopes have since been fully realized. The new direct central route is not only one hundred miles shorter, but is said to be better 
supplied with grass and water, than that I traveled.</note> 
           
<pb n="260" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.269"/>
                
passable; meantime, let me give some account of so
much of it as I have traveled, as I am not aware that
any is yet extant. </p>

<p>I left Camp Floyd in the mail-wagon from Salt Lake
City, on the morning of Thursday, July 21st, pursuing
a south-west course over a low mountain pass. 
Twenty miles on, we found a small brook making from the
mountains south of us across a thirsty plain, which, I 
presume, soon drank it up. The vegetation was the
same eternal sage-bush and grease-wood, which I am 
tired of mentioning, but which, together or separately, 
cover two-thirds of all the vast region between the 
Rocky Mountains and the Sierra Nevada. In places
the sage-bush, for miles in extent, is dead and withering,
seemingly parched up by the all-pervading drouth; the 
grease-wood is either hardier, or chooses its ground
more judiciously; for it is rarely found dead by acres. 
There is some bunch-grass on the sides of two or three
mountains, but very little of aught that can be relied 
on to sustain human or animal life. The mountains and 
plains seem to divide the ground very fairly between 
them&#8212;the soil of both being mainly a white clay;
while the former have that creased, gullied, washed-
away appearance, which I have repeatedly noticed.
Sometimes they are nearly perpendicular on one or
more sides, like the Buttes further east; but usually
they can be ascended on any side, and seem to rise
but one to three thousand feet above the plains at
their bases. These plains appear from a distance to be
level as so many tables; but, on attempting to cross
them in a wagon, you find them creased and scored by 

<pb n="261" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.270"/>
                
innumerable water-courses, now dry, but showing that,
in the wet season, water is most abundant here. In
most instances, a gradual slope of a mile or two 
intervenes between the foot of a mountain and the adjacent
plain or valley; this slope is apt to be intensely dry,
sterile, and covered with dead or dying sage-bush. I
judge these slopes to be composed of the rocky, 
gravelly material of the mountains, from which the lighter
clay has been washed out and carried off. They often
seem to be composed almost wholly of small bits of
rock. The valleys or plains are from five to fifteen
miles across, though they seem, in the clear, dry 
atmosphere of Utah, not half so much. These plains have
an imperceptible slope to some point near their 
respective centers, where a wider water-course runs toward
some adjacent valley; in some cases, a marsh or naked
space near the center indicates that the surplus water
from the surrounding monntains forms here in winter
and spring a petty, shallow lake, which the hot suns 
soon evaporate or the thirsty soil absorbs. The 
mountains are thinly belted or dotted with low, scrubby 
cedar, seldom ten feet high, and often nearly as far across
the green top formed by three or four stalks or stems
starting from a common root. The mountains seem to
have no particular, or rather no general direction; some
of the valleys being nearly or quite surrounded by
them. Even in the wettest seasons, I cannot perceive
that this region sends of any surplus water to Salt Lake 
or any other general reservoir. Such is the face of the 
country for some two hundred miles directly south-west 
of Camp Floyd.</p>
                 
<pb n="262" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.271"/>
              
<p>We found a station, a change of horses, and something
that was called dinner, on the little stream I have 
already mentioned, and halted here, twenty miles or more
from Camp Floyd. In the afternoon, we came on, over
a higher, rockier mountain-pass and a far rougher road,
to the next station&#8212;Simpson's Spring, nearly fifty
miles from Camp Floyd&#8212;where we halted for the night.
I fear the hot suns of August will dry up this spring;
while there is no other fit to drink for a weary distance
south and west of this point.</p>

<p>The station-keeper here gave me an incident which
illustrates the character of the country. Some few days
previously to our arrival, he ascertained that his oxen,
eight in number, had gone off, two or three nights 
before, taking a southerly course; so he mounted a horse
and followed their trail. He rode upon it one hundred
miles without reaching water or overtaking the cattle,
which had lain down but once since they started, and
were still a day's journey ahead of him. If he continued
the pursuit his horse must die of thirst, and then he too
must perish; so he turned about and left his oxen to die
in the desert or be found and eaten by savages. There was
not a shadow of hope that he would ever see them again.</p>

<p>We had to drive the same team (mules of course} all
next day, making fifty miles; but we stopped to rest
and feed them at a sub-station, only twenty miles from
our starting-point. It was about the forlornest spot I
ever saw. Though at the foot of a low mountain, there
was no water near it; that which was given our mnles
had been carted in a barrel from Simpson's Spring,
aforesaid, and so must be for most of each year. An
           
<pb n="263" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.272"/>
                
attempt to sink a well at this point had thus far proved
a failure. The station-keeper here lives entirely alone
&#8212;that is, when the Indians will let him&#8212;seeing a 
friendly face but twice a week, when the mail-stage passes
one way or the other. He deeply regretted his lack of
books and newspapers; we could only give him one of
the latter. Why do not men who contract to run mails
through such desolate regions comprehend that their
own interest, if no nobler consideration, should impel 
them to supply their stations with good reading matter!
I am quite sure that one hundred dollars spent by Major
Chorpening in supplying two or three good journals to
each station on his route, and in providing for their 
interchange from station to station, would save him
more than one thousand dollars in keeping good men in
his service, and in imbuing them with contentment and
gratitude. So with other mail-routes through regions
like this.</p>

<p>We drove on that day thirty miles further, to Fish
Springs station, just before reaching which we passed
one of the salt wells which are characteristic of this
country, though not absolutely peculiar to it. This one
is about six or eight feet in diameter, and perhaps an
equal distance from the surface of the surrounding 
earth to that of the water, which has a whitish green
aspect, is intensely salt, and said to be unfathomable,
with a downward suction which a man could hardly or
not at all resist. I had no desire to try, badly as I
needed ablution.</p>

<p>Fish Springs form quite a large pool at the north end
of a low mountain range, and send of a copious stream
              
<pb n="264" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.273"/>
                
to be drank up in the course of three or four miles by 
the thirsty clay of the plain. The water is brackish,
and I think sulphurous, as that of a spring in the 
adjacent marsh near the station clearly is. There are many
fish in the pool and stream, and they are said to be 
good. I should have liked to verify the assertion; and 
if they bite a hundredth part so freely as the musketoes
do hereabout, it were an easy matter to afford the stage
passengers here a change from their usual rations of
pork, bread and coffee; which, when the flour, or the
pork, or the coffee, happens to be out, as it sometimes
is, renders the diet unsatisfactory, even to those who 
would seem to have been seasoned to the like by a 
passage across the plains and the Rocky Mountains. Fish
Springs are just fifty miles from living water on either
side, and the stages have to run at least ten miles out
of their course to strike them. There is some coarse
grass here.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 23<hi rend="italic">d</hi>.&#8212;
We traveled this forenoon over a plain
nearly surrounded by mountains. Said plain is very
level to the eye, but the rapid traveler's sense of feeling
contradicts this, for he finds it full of dry-water-courses,
which give him most uncomfortable jolts. Before noon,
we came to the spot, where the stage-mules are turned
out to feed and rest, by the side of a sink or depression
in the plain, which is covered with coarse grass and reeds 
or bulrushes. By digging in the side of this sink,
water has been easily obtained, but so sulphurous, and 
generally bad, as to be barely drinkable. Even the
mules, I noticed, practice great moderation in the use 
of it. At one, we harnessed up, and were soon rising

<pb n="265" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.274"/>
                
over a long mountain-pass, hardly less than ten miles 
from the level plain to its summit, where a light 
thunder-shower&#8212;that is, a light rain with heavy 
thunder&#8212;overtook us. We drove rapidly down its western 
declivity, and, a little after 5, <hi rend="smallcaps">p. m.</hi>, reached our next 
station in "Pleasant Valley," a broad ravine, which 
descends to the south-west. Here we found water&#8212;bright,
sweet, pure, sparkling, leaping water&#8212;the first water
fit to drink that we had reached in a hundred miles; if
Simpson's Spring ever dries up, the distance will then
be at least a hundred and twenty. We were now across
what is here technically known as "the desert"&#8212;that
is to say, we had crossed the north-east corner of it. I
believe it extends at least two hundred miles south from
this point, and is at least as far from east to west across
its center. If Uncle Sam should ever sell that tract for
one cent per acre, he will swindle the purchaser 
outrageously.</p>

<p>Let me endeavor, on quitting it, to give a clear idea
of this desert, and thus of about half the land inclosed
between the Rocky Mountains and the Sierra Nevada&#8212;
the other half being mainly covered by mountains and
the narrow ravines or ca&#241;ons which separate them.</p>

<p>The plains or valleys of Utah, then, have generally
a soil of white clay, sometimes rocky, at others streaked
by sand or gravel; but usually pure clay, save as it is
impregnated with some alkaline substance:&#8212;usually
sal&#1237;ratus; but in plae niter, in others, salt or sulphur.
Sometimes, but rarely, considerable areas of this alkali
in a nearly pure state are exposed on the surface; in
many places, it covers the beds of shallow, dried-up

<pb n="266" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.275"/>
                
lakes, and even streams, with a whitish incrustation;
but it is more generally diffused through the soil, and
thus impregnates the springs and streams. Irrigating
a piece of ground, strongly imbued with alkali, will
often bring an incrustation of it to the surface, after 
which no trouble from it is experienced in that place.
I think the greater proportion of these plains ar valleys
&#8212;which could easily be cleared of their grease-wood
and sage-bush and plowed&#8212;would produce large crops
of wheat, and of almost anything else, if they could be
irrigated. But that can never be, unless by Artesian
wells. But little rain falls in summer, and that little is
speedily evaporated from the hot earth, leaving the clay
as thirsty as ever. I fear it is mainly doomed to 
perpetual barrenness.</p>

<p>The mountains which divide these plains exude very
little water. Wherever a range is single&#8212;that is, with
a broad valley each side of it&#8212;it is apt to be not more
than one to three thousand feet high, and so to be early
denuded of snow; its springs are few and generally
feeble, and their waters are often dried up before 
trickling half way down the sides of the mountain which
gave them birth. If a spring is so copious, or so many
are speedily combined, as to form a considerable stream,
they may reach the plain; but only to be speedily
drank up by its scorched surface. Cultivation, 
therefore, save in a very few narrow spots, seems here 
impossible.</p>

<p>But wherever a chaos or jumble of mountains is 
presented&#8212;still more, where mountains rise behind 
mountains, range behind range, rank above rank, till the 
                
<pb n="267" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.276"/>
                
summits of the furthest that may be seen are flecked
with snow&#8212;there the case is altered. Springs are there
more abundant and more copious; the gradual melting 
of the snows swells the rivulets formed by the speedy
meeting of their waters; and thus considerable brooks 
are formed and poured down upon the subjacent plains,
as we observe in and around Salt Lake City, and north
and west of Lake Utah. Thus are formed Bear and
Weber Rivers; such, I believe, is the origin of the
Humboldt. But such instances are far too rare in Utah.
From the Jordan to the Humboldt is about three 
hundred and fifty miles by the route I traveled, and in all 
that distance the brooks and rills I crossed or saw, could
they be collected into one channel, would barely form a
decent mill-stream. I thence traveled down the south
side of the Humboldt for two hundred and twenty-five
miles, and in all that distance not more than two 
tributaries come in on that side, and their united currents 
would barely suffice to turn a grindstone. This 
desolation seems therefore irredeemable.</p>

<p>The mountains of central Utah are less hopeless than
the Plains. Contrary to my former impression, they
are fairly wooded; by which I mean that wood is 
procurable on them at almost any point. This wood is for
the most part cedar, six to ten feet high, and from a foot
downward in diameter near the ground. White pines
of like size, and of equally scrubby character, are quite
common in the western part of the mountains I 
traversed, and there is some balsam-fir in the deeper ca&#241;ons,
which attains a diameter of fifteen to twenty inches,
and a height of forty to sixty feet. Of this fir, several

<pb n="268" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.277"/>
                
of the mail-station cabins are constructed; in Ruby
Valley, they have one of red or Indian-pine; but they
are quite commonly built of stones and mud. One on
the Humboldt is built of dwarf-willow canes or wattles
&#8212;not one any where of cedar nor of the dwarfed white-
pine of this region. Neither could be made to answer.</p>

<p>But I must hurry on. At Pleasant Valley, we turned
north-west up a broad ravine, and thenceforth held that
general course to reach the Humboldt, instead of still
making west south-west directly toward Carsou Valley,
as it is proposed hereafter to do if that be found 
practicable. For the next one hundred and forty miles or
thereabouts, our trail led us mainly up one side of a
mountain range and down the other, thence across a
valley of some ten miles in width to the foot of another
chain, and so on. As the train naturally runs up the 
deepest ca&#241;ions and over the lowest passes, the ascent
and descent are rarely abrupt for any considerable 
distance, and we seldom lacked water; but our route was
the most devious imaginable&#8212;veering from north-east
on one hand to south on the other. Sometimes, two or
three hundred square miles were visible at a glance&#8212;
the mountain-sides half covered with cedar and pine,
with some dwarf-willows and rose-bushes often fringing
their slender rivulets; but not a tree other than 
evergreen in sight. There is a large, pine-leaved shrub or
small tree which a driver termed a mountain-mahogany
and a passenger called a red haw, growing sparingly
among the evergreens on some mountain slopes, which
seems about half way between a thorn-bush and an 
untrimmed apple-tree, but nothing else deciduous above 
   
<pb n="269" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.278"/>            

the size of the dwarf-willow. Even the sage-bush and
grease-wood appear to be evergreens. Grass is here not
abundant but unfailing, as it must be where water is
perennial and wood in fair supply. The plains or 
valleys remain as further east, save that they are smaller,
and, because of the less scanty supply of water, more
susceptible of improvement. At Shell Creek, forty-five
miles from Pleasant Valley, where we spent our next
night, there is a little garden&#8212;the first I had seen since
Camp Floyd&#8212;and at Ruby Valley, fifty miles or so 
further on, the government has a farm in crop, intended
for the benefit, and partly cultivated by the labor of the
neighboring Indians. The mail-station also has its 
garden, and is cutting an abundance of hay. From this
station, it is expected that the new cut-off, saving one
hundred miles or more in distance to Carson Valley,
will be made, so soon as those now scrutinizing it shall
have pronounced it practicable.</p>

<p>At Ruby, the stage usually stops for the night; but
we had been six days making rather less than three
hundred miles, and began to grow impatient. The
driver had his own reasons for pushing on, and did so,
over a road partly mountainous, rough and sideling;
but, starting at eight <hi rend="smallcaps">p. m.</hi>, we had reached the next
(Pine Valley) station, forty miles distant, before 
sunrise. Here we were detained three or four hours for
mules&#8212;those we should have taken being astray&#8212;but
at nine we started with a new driver, and were soon 
entangled in a pole-bridge over a deep, miry stream&#8212;a
drove of a thousand head of cattle (the first ever driven
over this road) having recently passed, and torn the frail
            
<pb n="270" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.279"/>
                
bridge to pieces. Our lead-mules went down in a pile,
but were got up and out and the wagon ran over, after
a delay of an hour. We soon rose from Pine Valley
by a long, irregular, generally moderate ascent, to a
mountain divide, from which our trail took abruptly
down the wildest and worst ca&#241;on I ever saw traversed
by a carriage. It is in places barely wide enough at
bottom for a wagon, and if two should meet here it is
scarcely possible that they should pass. The length of
this ca&#241;on is a mile and a half ; the descent hardly less
than two thousand feet ; the side of the road next to the
water-course often far lower than the other; the road-
bed is often made of sharp-edged fragments of broken
rock, hard enough to stand on, harder still to hold back
on. The heat in this ca&#241;on on a summer afternoon is
intense, the sun being able to enter it while the wind is 
not. Two or three glorious springs afford partial 
consolation to the weary, thirsty traveler. I am confident no
passenger ever rode down this rocky ladder; I trust
that none will until a better road is made here ; though
a good road in such a gulch is scarcely possible. Fifteen 
miles further, across a plain and a lower range of hills, I
brought our mail-wagon at last, about seven <hi rend="smallcaps">p. m.</hi> of its
seventh day from Salt Lake City, to</p>

<p><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="center">The Humboldt.</hi></hi></p>

<p>I am not going to describe the route down this river,
as it is the old emigrant-trail, repeatedly written about
already. I only wish to record my opinion, that the
Humboldt, all things considered, is the meanest river
of its length on earth. Rising in the Humbnldt 
<choice><orig>Moun-

<pb n="271" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.280"/>

tains</orig><reg>Mountains</reg></choice>, hardly one hundred and fifty miles west of Salt
Lake, it is at first a pure stream&#8212;or rather streams, for
there are two main branches&#8212;but is soon corrupted by
its alkaline surroundings, and its water, for at least the
lower half of its course, is about the most detestable I
ever tasted. I mainly chose to suffer thirst rather than
drink it. Though three hundred and fifty miles in
length, it is never more than a decent mill-stream; I
presume it is the only river of equal length that never
had even a canoe launched upon its bosom. Its narrow
bottom, or intervale, produces grass; but so coarse in
structure, and so alkaline by impregnation, that no 
sensible man would let his stock eat it, if there were any
alternative. Here, however, there is none. Cattle must
eat this, or die&#8212;many of them eat it, and die. One of
the most intelligent emigrants I conversed with on its
banks informed me that he had all the grass for his
stock mowed, as he had found by experience that his
cattle, if grazed upon it, pulled up much of their grass
by the roots, and these roots were far more alkaline
than the stalks. I believe no tree of any size grows on
this forlorn river from its forks to its mouth&#8212;I am sure
I saw none while traversing the lower half of its course.
Half a dozen specimens of a large, worthless shrub,
known as buffalo-bush or bull-berry, with a prevalent
fringe of willows about the proper size for a school-
ma'am's use, comprise the entire timber of this 
delectable stream, whose gad-flies, musketoes, gnats, etc., are
so countless and so blood-thirsty as to allow cattle so
unhappy as to be stationed on, or driven along this
river, no chance to eat or sleep. Many have died this

<pb n="272" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.281"/>
                
season of the bad water, that would have survived the
water, but for these execrable insects, by which the
atmosphere, at times, is darkened. It certainly is not
a pleasure to ride, night and day, along such a stream,
with the heat intense, the dust a constant cloud, and
the roads all gullied, and ground into chuck-holes; but
then, who would stay in such a region one moment
longer than he must?</p>

<p>I thought I had seen barrenness before&#8212;on the upper
course of the Republican&#8212;on the North Platte, Green
River, etc.&#8212;but I was green, if the regions washed by
by those streams were not. Here, on the Humboldt,
famine sits enthroned, and waves his scepter over a
dominion expressly made for him. On the above-
named rivers, I regarded cotton-wood with contempt;
here, a belt, even the narrowest fringe, of cotton-wood
would make a comparative Eden. The sage-bush and
grease-wood, which cover the high, parched plain on
either side of the river's bottom, seems thinly set, with
broad spaces of naked, shining, glaring, blinding clay
between them; the hills beyond, which bound the 
prospect, seem even more naked. Not a tree, and hardly
a shrub, anywhere relieves their sterility; not a brook,
save one small one, runs down between them to swell
the scanty waters of the river. As the only 
considerable stream in the Great Basin that pursues a general
east and west direction, the Humboldt may continue
for years to be traveled; but I am sure no one ever left
it without a sense of relief and thankfulness. There
can never be any considerable settlement here.</p>

<p>After a course, at first west by south, then north by

<pb n="273" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.282"/>
                
west, afterward south-west, and for the last fifty miles
due south, the river falls into Lake Humboldt, a fine 
sheet of clear water, perhaps fifteen miles in length and
forty in circumference. I tried to obtain an 
approximation to its depth, but could not; those who have
staid beside it longest assuring me that no boat had
ever floated upon its waters&#8212;a statement which the
destitution of wood in all this region renders credible.
I am satisfied, however, that this lake is being slowly
filled up from the gradual washing down, and washing
in, of the hills which approach it on the east and south,
and that time will make great changes in its 
configuration and the volume of its waters.</p>

<p>A stream, not so copious as the river, runs from the
lake on the south, and flows with a gentle, sluggish
current into a large <hi rend="italic">tul&#233;</hi> or reed-marsh, which has no 
outlet, and is said to be but moderately salt. The lake
water is accounted sweeter than that of the river.
Here the Humboldt is said to <hi rend="italic">sink</hi>, like the Carson,
Truckee and Walker, which issue from the Sierra 
Nevada, and run eastwardly into the adjacent desert; but I
suspect they are all drank up by evaporation and by
the thirsty sands which surround them. The 
Mississippi, if it ran across the Great Basin and kept clear of
mountains, would be threatened by a similar fate.</p>

<p>We reached the Sink at 6 1/2 <hi rend="smallcaps">p. m.</hi> on Thursday, the
29th&#8212;scarcely two days from Gravelly Ford, where
we struck the river, having in those two days traversed
some two hundred and twenty miles of very bad and
intensely hot, dusty road. At eight, we were ready to
pass "the Desert"&#8212;that is, the desolate plain which
            
<pb n="274" xml:id="mmm.wa.greeley.1860.283"/>
                
separates the Sink of the Humboldt from that of the
Carson. Bpt one of our fresh mules was sick and could
not be replaced, which made our first drive a tedious
one, and we contrived, by dexterous mismanagement,
to get stuck in a bayou or back-set of the Humboldt
Sink, where we for a while seemed likely to spend the
night. Our lead-mules, having been mired and thrown
down, would not pull; the sick wheeler could not. At
length, by putting one of the leaders in his place, we
made a start, and come through, finding the bottom
firm and the water not deep, a yard either way from
the place of our misadventure. By a little past 
midnight, we were at the half-way station, where a well of
decent brackish water has been dug, and which a drove
of four or five hundred mules reached about the time
we did. They stopped here to rest, however, while we
pushed on with a fresh team&#8212;for ten miles of the way,
over as heavy a drag of sand as I ever endured, 
whereas most of this desert is a hard, alkaline clay. By five
<hi rend="smallcaps">A. M.</hi>, after riding four days and the intervening nights
without rest, we drew up at the station near the sink of
the Carson.</p>
        
-->

</div1>
</body>          
</text>
</TEI>