<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.news.nyt.18750724">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Mountain Meadows</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"/>
                <author></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.news.nyt.18750724</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary"></note>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title level="j">New York Times</title>
                    <title level="a" type="main">MOUNTAIN MEADOWS.</title>
                    <title level="a" type="sub">THE STORY OF THE MORMON MASSACRE.</title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
                    <date when="1875-07-24">July 24, 1875</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>newspaper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords n="culpability" scheme="original">
                    <term> </term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords n="action" scheme="original">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-08-09"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding
                Enhancement</change>
            <change when="2011-04-25"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Concept
                Highlighting</change>
            <change when="2009-10-06"><name>Kelsey F. Harris</name> Initial Encoding</change>
            <change when="2006-03-02"><name>Laura Weakly</name> Model Encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text>

        <body>

            <div1 type="newspaper">
                
                <pb n="unknown" xml:id="mmm.news.nyt.18750724.001"/>

                <head type="main">MOUNTAIN MEADOWS.</head>
                <milestone unit="horbar"/>
                <head type="sub">THE STORY OF THE MORMON MASSACRE.</head>
                <head type="sub">TESTIMONY AT LEE'S TRIAL&#8212;OVERWHELMING EVIDENCE AGAINST
                    THE MORMONS&#8212;THE MASSACRE PLANNED BY THE CHURCH&#8212;LEE THE
                    LEADER OF THE INHUMAN BUTCHERY.</head>

                <p><placeName type="settlement" key="Beaver, UT">BEAVER</placeName>, <placeName
                        type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, July 23. &#8212; At
                    2 o’clock to-day, the first witness in the trial of <persName key="Lee, John D."
                        >John D. Lee</persName> and others was called. <persName key="Keyes, Robert"
                        >Robert Keyes</persName> came to <placeName type="state" key="Utah">Utah
                        Territory</placeName> Oct. 2, 1857, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"
                        >through <geogName type="valley" key="Mountain Meadows">the Mountain
                            Meadows</geogName></seg>; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath">
                        <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">saw two piles of bodies of women
                            and children piled promiscuously, about sixty to seventy, the children
                            from two months old to twelve years; the smaller ones were torn by
                            wolves and crows; some bodies were shot, some had their throats cut,
                            some were stabbed, and all were torn by wolves except one woman a little
                            way off, who appeared as if she were asleep; there was a bullet hole in
                            her left side; from appearances the bodies had been dead for fifteen
                            days; seven of us saw them; the pile of men’s bodies was further on; did
                            not go to see them; there was no clothing on the bodies except a sock on
                            the foot of one man; none had been scalped.</seg>
                    </seg></p>

                <p><persName key="Benuette, Ashel">Ashel Benuette</persName>, called: Was at <seg
                        type="Massacre" subtype="Location">the Meadows</seg> December, 1857; <seg
                        type="Massacre" subtype="Aftermath"><seg type="Massacre"
                            subtype="Casualties">saw bones there&#8212;a horrible sight of
                            skeletons of women and children, with curls and long tresses of hair
                            dried in blood; the children were from ten to twelve years of age; some
                            of the skulls had the flesh dried on them; the bodies had been covered
                            up, but wolves evidently dug them out</seg>.</seg></p>

                <p>
                    <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><persName
                            key="Klingensmith, Philip">Phillip Klingen Smith</persName> a defendant
                        of <placeName type="settlement" key="San Bernardino, CA">San
                            Bernardino</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="California"
                            >Cal.</placeName>, was called. The prosecution entered a <hi
                            rend="italic">nolle prosequi</hi> as to himself: lived in <placeName
                            type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName> in 1857
                        since 1852; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Location"><geogName type="valley"
                                key="Mountain Medaows">the Meadows</geogName> are forty-five miles
                            south of <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar
                                City</placeName>, on <placeName type="route" key="California Road"
                                >the California road</placeName></seg>; was at the massacre <seg
                            type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">in September, 1857</seg>: <seg
                            type="Encounter" subtype="TradeLDS">heard of emigrants coming; the
                            people were forbidden to trade with them; felt bad about it; saw a few
                            of them at <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar
                                City</placeName>; this was on Friday; some swore, and Higbee fined
                            them; they went on</seg>; heard rumors of trouble; <seg type="Massacre"
                            subtype="Planning">
                            <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">on Sunday it was the
                                custom to have meetings of the President and Council, the Bishops
                                and Council, and the High Council; I was a Bishop; the question as
                                to their destruction came up for discussion; <persName
                                    key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, <persName
                                    key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName>, <persName
                                    key="Morrill, Laban">Morrill</persName>, <persName
                                    key="Allen, Ira">Allen</persName>, <persName key="Willis, John"
                                    >Willis</persName>, <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip"
                                    >myself</persName>, and others, were there; some of the brethren
                                opposed destruction; I did; <persName key="Haight, Isaac C."
                                    >Haight</persName> jumped up and broke up the meeting; I asked
                                what would be the consequences of such an act; Haight then got mad;
                                the Indians were to destroy them on Monday; <persName
                                    key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName>, <persName
                                    key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName>, <persName key="White"
                                    >White</persName>, and I met and discussed the same subject
                                again; I opposed their destruction; <persName key="Haight, Isaac C."
                                    >Haight</persName> relented, and told <persName key="White"
                                    >White</persName> and me to go ahead and tell the people that
                                the emigrants should go through safely, we did so; on the road we
                                met <persName key="Lee, John D.">John Lee</persName>, and told him
                                where we were going; he replied that he had something to say about
                                that matter;</seg>
                        </seg> we passed the emigrants at <placeName type="settlement"
                            key="Iron Springs">Iron Springs, UT</placeName>; next morning we passed
                        them again as we came back; <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="WagonTrain">they
                            had twenty or thirty wagons and numbered altogether <seg type="Massacre"
                                subtype="Casualties">over 100 persons, old and middle-aged men and
                                women, youths, and children</seg></seg>; <seg type="Massacre"
                            subtype="Planning"><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">while
                                near home we met <persName key="Allen, Ira">Ira Allen</persName>, he
                                said that the doom of the emigrants was sealed, and that the die was
                                cast for their destruction; also that Lee had orders to take men out
                                and intercept the emigrants, and that <persName key="Allen, Ira"
                                    >Allen</persName> was to go on and counteract what we had
                                done;</seg> I went home. Three days afterward <persName
                                key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> sent for me, and said that
                            orders had come from the camp that they did not get along, and wanted
                            reinforcements; that he had been to <placeName type="settlement"
                                key="Parowan, UT">Parowan</placeName> and got further orders from
                                <persName key="Dame, William H.">Col. W. H. Dame</persName> to
                            finish the massacre, to decoy the emigrants out, and <seg
                                type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">spare only the small children
                                who could not tell the tale</seg>; I went off and met <persName
                                key="Allen, Ira">Allen</persName>, our first runner, and others;
                                <persName key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName> came out, and said
                            we were ordered out armed and equipped, so I went: <persName
                                key="Hopkins, Charles">Hopkins</persName>, <persName
                                key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName>, <persName
                                key="Willis, John">John Willis</persName>, and <persName
                                key="Purdy, Sam">Sam Purdy</persName>, went along; we had two
                            baggage-wagons with us; we got to <persName key="Hamblin, Jacob"
                                >Hamblin</persName>’s ranch in the night, three miles from the
                            emigrants. We there met <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> and
                            others from the general camp, where the largest number of men were. <seg
                                type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">We then found the emigrants were
                                not all killed.</seg>
                            <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> called me out for
                            consultation. He told me the situation. The emigrants, he said, were
                            strongly fortified. There was no chance of getting them out. <persName
                                key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName> gave orders to decoy them
                            out the best way we could. This was agreed to, and the command was given
                            to <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName> to carry out the
                            whole plan. They went to the camp; <persName key="Lee, John D."
                                >Lee</persName> placed all the soldiers in a hollow square and
                            addressed them. They were all white men, about fifty in all. The Indians
                            were in another camp; saw there <persName key="Slade, William Rufus"
                                >Slade</persName> and his son; <persName key="Pearce, Jim">Jim
                                Pearce</persName> and probably his sons, too, all those from
                                <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar</placeName>,
                            and <persName key="Stewart, Bill">Bill Stewart</persName>, <persName
                                key="Jacobs, Levin">Levin Jacobs</persName>; I think <persName
                                key="McFarlan, Dan">Dan McFarlan</persName> too; <persName
                                key="Slade, William Rufus">Slade</persName> and I were outraged, but
                            we said, <q>“What can we do? We can’t help ourselves;”</q> just then the
                            order to march was given, and we had to go; we were put in double file;
                                <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence"><persName
                                    key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName> had command of part of
                                the men; it was the <orgName type="tribe" key="Nauvoo">Nauvoo
                                    Legion</orgName>, organized from tens up to hundreds; <seg
                                    type="Massacre" subtype="Surrender">we marched in sight of the
                                    emigrants; either <persName key="Bateman, William Lehi"
                                        >Bateman</persName> or <persName key="Lee, John D."
                                        >Lee</persName> went out with a white flag. A man from the
                                    emigrants met them. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>
                                    and the man sat down on the grass and had a talk; don’t know
                                    what they talked about. <persName key="Lee, John D."
                                        >Lee</persName> went with the man into the entrenchments.
                                    After some hours they came out and the emigrants came up with
                                    the wounded in wagons ahead. The wounded were those hurt in the
                                    three days’ previous fight; said the Mormons and Indians could
                                    not oust the emigrants;</seg> next came the women and next the
                                men; as the emigrants came up the men halted, and the women on foot
                                with the children and wounded, went on ahead with <persName
                                    key="Lee, John D.">John D. Lee</persName>; the soldiers had to
                                be all ready to shoot at the word; when the word halt came the
                                soldiers fired; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">I fired
                                    once; don’t know if I killed the men; they were not all killed
                                    the first shot; saw the women afterward dead, with their throats
                                    cut; I saw as I came up to them, a man kill a young girl;</seg>
                                the men were marched in double file first, then thrown in single
                                file with soldiers alongside; heard the emigrants congratulating on
                                their safety from the Indians at last; <persName
                                    key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName> came and ordered my
                                squad to fire; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, like the
                                rest, had fire-arms;</seg>
                            <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">no emigrants escaped; saw
                                soldiers on horses to take on the wing those who ran; saw a man run;
                                saw <persName key="Stewart, Bill">Bill Stewart</persName>, on a
                                horse, go after one and kill him; saw one wounded man beg for his
                                life, but <persName key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName> cut his
                                throat; the man said, <q>“I would not do this to you, <persName
                                        key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName>;”</q> he knew
                                him;</seg>
                            <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">after I fired, was told to
                                gather up little children</seg></seg>; <seg type="Massacre"
                            subtype="Casualties">as I went I saw a large woman running toward the
                            men crying <q>“My husband, my husband!”</q> a soldier shot her in the
                            back and she fell dead. As I went on I found wagons, with wounded all
                            out on the ground, with their throats cut.</seg>
                        <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">I went on and found children, and
                            put them in a wagon and took them to Hablin’s house. I saw no more. The
                            soldiers had dispersed. Two of the children were wounded. One died at
                            Hamblin’s. I think I had to leave it there. Many of the soldiers were
                            from southern counties, and I did not know them. Next day, <persName
                                key="Klingensmith, Philip">I</persName>, <persName key="McCurdy"
                                >McCurdy</persName>, and <persName key="Willis, John"
                                >Willis</persName> took the children to <placeName type="settlement"
                                key="Cedar City, UT">Cedar City</placeName>, leaving one at
                                <geogName type="waterway" key="Pinto Creek">Pinto Creek</geogName>.
                            On the road we met a freight train of wagons. I went to old <persName
                                key="Hopkins">Mrs. Hopkins</persName> and told her we had children
                            with us. She bustled around and got places for them. I took one girl
                            baby home, and my wife suckled her. I afterward gave it to <persName
                                key="Birkbeck">Birkbeck</persName>, he having no children. The
                            children were well treated, I believe. Good places were obtained for
                            them.</seg></seg>
                </p>

                <p>
                    <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><seg type="Massacre"
                            subtype="Spoils">The question of allowing the statements of the
                            co-conspirators as to to the disposal of the emigrants property after
                            the massacre was here argued for an hour. The court held it
                            admissible.</seg> During the argument, <persName key="Sutherland, Jabez"
                            >Sutherland</persName>, for the defense, said it was an attempt to fix
                        the crime on some one else, <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>
                        being only the figurehead.</seg>
                </p>

                <p>
                    <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership"><persName key="Baskin, Robert N."
                            >A. Baskin</persName>, for the prosecution, replied he wanted but the
                        truth whoever it implicated; that <persName key="Sutherland, Jabez"
                            >Sutherland</persName> feared his real client would be reached,(decided
                        sensation, it being known that <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham
                            Young</persName> was meant.)</seg>
                </p>

                <p>
                    <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><persName
                            key="Klingensmith, Philip">Witness</persName> resumed: <seg
                            type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">After several days <persName
                                key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName></seg></seg>
                </p>
                <cb n="1"/>
                <p>
                    <seg type="Source" subtype="Attributed_Klingensmith"><seg type="Massacre"
                            subtype="Spoils">sent me to the <placeName type="settlement"
                                key="Iron Springs, UT">Iron Springs</placeName>, where the wagons,
                            cattle, and goods of the emigrants were, to get them and put them in the
                            tithing-house; I was to brand the cattle too; found there <persName
                                key="Gorie, John">John Gorie</persName> and <persName key="Hunter"
                                >Hunter</persName>, and <persName key="Allen, Ira">Allen</persName>;
                            I put the goods in the Church tithing-office cellar; left the wagons in
                            front of the tithing office; branded the cattle with the Church brand, a
                            cross; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was in the cellar
                            with me and saw the goods;</seg>
                        <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> and <persName
                            key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName> told me a council had been held
                        and <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> deputed to go to President
                            <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and report all
                        the facts of the massacre; <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> went,
                        and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">I followed to attend to conference
                            Oct. 6 at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
                                Lake City</placeName>; met <persName key="Lee, John D."
                                >Lee</persName> at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City"
                                >Salt Lake</placeName>; asked if he had reported to <persName
                                key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>; he said yes, every
                            particular; same day <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">I</persName>,
                                <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>, and <persName
                                key="Hopkins, Charles">Charley Hopkins</persName> called on
                                <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>; he there ,
                            in presence of them, said, <q>“You have charge of that property in the
                                tithing office, turn it over to <persName key="Lee, John D.">John D.
                                    Lee</persName>. What you know of this, say nothing of it; don’t
                                talk of it even among yourselves;</q> had to go to <placeName
                                type="settlement" key="Las Vegas, NV">Vegas</placeName> Lead Mines
                            to get more ore; while I was gone <persName key="Lee, John D."
                                >Lee</persName> took the property, had an auction, and sold it off;
                            so <persName key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> and <persName
                                key="Higbee, John H.">Higbee</persName> told me: <persName
                                key="Haight, Isaac C.">Haight</persName> sold part of the cattle to
                                <persName key="Hooper, William H.">Hooper</persName>, afterward
                            Congressional delegate, for boots and shoes;</seg>
                        <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">there were Indians at the
                            massacre; the hills were pretty full of them; they were disputed to kill
                            the women; <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">I saw an Indian cut
                                a boy’s throat</seg>; I heard of no effort to restrain the Indians;
                            three of them died from wounds received from the emigrants. The Indians
                            came back to <placeName type="settlement" key="Cedar City, UT"
                                >Cedar</placeName>, where they lived. Two of their chiefs’ names
                            were Bill and Tom. <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">I saw some of
                                the emigrants’ property in the possession of the Indians.</seg> I
                            saw <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> get dresses and jeans
                            from the tithing office out of the emigrants’ plunder.</seg>
                        <seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansLDSInfluence">I learned from <persName
                                key="Allen, Ira">Allen</persName> that <persName key="Lee, John D."
                                >Lee</persName> was the one to gather up the Indians to attack the
                            emigrants. I talked with <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>
                            about it afterward. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName> was
                            Indian agent at <placeName type="settlement" key="Harmony, UT"
                                >Harmony</placeName>, traded with the tribes, and issued goods and
                            rations from the Government to the Indians.</seg></seg>
                </p>

                <p>The court here adjourned.</p>

                <p>After to-day night sessions will be held.</p>

                <p>The court has warned the citizens not to speak to the jurors from the street, and
                    declares that such an offense will be punished.</p>

                <p>
                    <seg type="Source" subtype="PublicMind">During the time that <persName
                            key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingen Smith</persName> was testifying,
                        giving the horrible details of the massacre, the suspense was terribly
                        painful. <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>’s square, hard,
                        low-browed face and neck became fairly purple and black. His wives scarcely
                        breathed, straining forward to catch each syllable.</seg>
                </p>

                <p><seg type="Source" subtype="PublicMind">The excitement in town is intense.</seg>
                    It is understood that <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingen
                        Smith</persName>’s story, in all the material details, is the same as
                        <persName key="Lee, John D.">Lee</persName>’s suppressed confession as to
                    the massacre. <persName key="Klingensmith, Philip">Klingen Smith</persName>’s
                    reputation here is that of a man of truth. He could not be impeached save by
                    facts.</p>

            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
