<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.2.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1874">
     <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Great West and Pacific Coast</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"></title>
                    <author><forename>James</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Rusling</surname></author>
                <principal>Douglas Seefeldt</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mmm.wa.rusling.1874</idno>
                <authority>"Horrible Massacre of Emigrants!!" : The Mountain Meadows Massacre in Public Discourse</authority>
                <publisher>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</publisher>
                <distributor>
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2010</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2012 by University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln, all rights reserved. Redistribution or republication in any medium, except as allowed under the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law, requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the publisher, the University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project"></note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <bibl>
                    <title level="m" type="main">The Great West and Pacific Coast</title>
		            <title level="m" type="sub">Or, Fifteen Thousand Miles by Stage-Coach, Ambulance, Horse-back, Railroad, and Steamer&#8212;Across the Continent and Along the Pacific Slope&#8212;through the Rocky Mountains, down the Columbia River, over the Sierra Nevadas&#8212;among Indians, Mormons, Miners and Mexicans.</title>
		            <title level="m" type="sub">By Order of United States Government.</title>
		            <title level="m" type="sub">With a Map of Entire Route and Eight full-page Engravings.</title>
		            <title level="m" type="sub">Being Sketches of Men and Things from New York to St. Louis&#8212;in Missouri, Kansas, Nebraska, Colorado, Dakota, Wyoming, Utah, Montana, Idaho, Oregon, Washington, California, Arizona, Nevada, Mexico, and Central America.  With a Chapter of Advice to Emigrants and Settlers.</title>
                    <author><forename>James</forename> <forename type="middle">F.</forename> <surname>Rusling</surname></author>
                    <publisher>Sheldon &amp; Company</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Crocker &amp; Stickney</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>H. W. Kelly</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Bryan, Brand &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>St. Louis, Missouri</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>P. W. Garfield</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Cleveland, Ohio</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>M. M. Burnham</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Syracuse, New York</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>A. Roman &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>San Francisco, California</pubPlace>
                    <extent></extent>
                    <date when="1874">1874</date>
		    <note type="source">James F. Rusling. <hi rend="italic">Across America: or, The Great West and the Pacific Coast</hi>. New York: Sheldon &amp; Company, 1874. 182-198.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Originally published as: Across America; or, The Great West and the Pacific Coast</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
                    <term>western_americana</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-02-16"><name>Jaclyn Cruikshank Vogt</name> Encoding Enrichment</change>
             <change when="2010-07-15"><name>Rosie Hanneke</name> Initial Encoding
            </change>	           
        </revisionDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>

<text>
<body>
  
<div1 type="chapter">

<pb n="182" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.196"/>

<head>CHAPTER XI. MORMON OUTRAGES&#8212;POLYGAMY, ETC.</head>

<p>A<hi rend="smallcaps">S</hi> to the alleged outrages and wrongs by Mormons
against Gentiles, we found public opinion at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> much divided. The Mormons, as a class, of course,
all repudiated and denied them; while the Gentiles, as
a class, were equally earnest in affirming them. Before
arriving there, we were very skeptical on this subject;
but before leaving, and afterwards, heard so many ugly
stories, that we were compelled to believe somewhat in
them. It is a delicate subject to touch at all, and I
would fain avoid it; but no account of <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> would
be complete without some allusion thereto. Space would
fail me to speak of them at length; so that I shall 
content myself with recording only a case or two, and from
them the reader must judge for himself. The Mountain
Meadow massacre, and the <persName key="Brassfield">Brassfield</persName> murder, were old
stories; but just previous to our arrival, a party of 
Gentiles had been threatened with drowning in the Jordan,
and indeed, while we were there, the atrocious murder
of Dr. <persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName> occurred. The editor of the little
<hi rend="italic">Vidette</hi>, the plucky Gentile paper then at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>,
was one of the Gentiles above referred to, and his story
was that a band of masked men seized them on the street
one night, and taking them out to the Jordan tied them
hand and foot, and then gave them the option&#8212;either to
leave <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> in one week, or to be tossed in and drowned.

<pb n="183" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.197"/>

Their only offence was, that they had been too bitter
against Mormonism, and <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> they were informed
was "an unhealthy place" for such people. They all
agreed, we believe, to emigrate. But the <hi rend="italic">Vidette</hi> man,
on getting home, concluded such a promise under duress
was not very binding, and proceeded to strengthen his
conclusion by securing a guard from Camp Douglas.
Loaded down with revolvers, he went about his business
as usual in the day time, but at night kept within doors,
and so far had remained unmolested. The others, 
however, as a whole, thought it safer to keep their agreement,
and accordingly duly quitted <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>.</p>

<p>The murder of Dr. <persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName> (Oct. 22d), it must be admitted, was a cold-blooded atrocity, worthy only of
fanatics or savages. He had come to <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> originally, as Surgeon or Ass't-Surgeon of a regiment of 
volunteers, ordered there from <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName> during the war, to replace the Regulars sent east. When his regiment was
mustered out, he concluded to settle at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, and soon after "pre-empted" the quarter-section containing
the Hot Sulphur Springs. Associating a Dr. <persName key="Williamson">Williamson</persName>
with him, who had also been in the army, they put up a
bath-house and refreshment-saloon at the Springs, and by
liberal advertising were soon in a fair way to make some
money. Now, all at once,two Mormons living near 
suddenly discovered that the property belonged to them,
although they had never claimed it before, or regularly 
"pre-empted" it, or made any "permanent improvement" 
there, as required by our pre-emption laws. They
accordingly brought suit in ejectment against Messrs.
<persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName> and <persName key="Williamson">Williamson</persName>, in the U. S. District Court
there; but before the cause reached trial, became 
convinced there was nothing in their case, and concluded to
abandon it. Now, however, <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake City</placeName> itself

<pb n="184" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.198"/>

stepped in as plaintiff in the cause, and claimed the Springs
also as corporation property, by virtue of some old 
ordinance, though two or three miles beyond the city
limits. Immediately, without waiting for the Court,
Messrs. <persName key="Robinson, John King.">R.</persName> and <persName key="Williamson">W.</persName> were declared trespassers, and the
Mayor ordered the city police to eject them from
the premises, which was done one night by tearing down 
the buildings over their heads, and dragging them both
off bodily. This summary proceeding, no better than a
riot, naturally created much excitement among the 
Gentiles, and was still being talked of when we reached <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City">Salt Lake</placeName>. Meanwhile, Dr. <persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName> took it very coolly, and
moving into <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, opened an office for practice there, proposing to abide the judgment of the Court.
Shortly, however, before this could be reached, he was
roused up one night by a man at his door, with the
plausible story, that a friend down the street had broken
his leg and needed his immediate services, being already
in great agony. His wife, newly married, fearing 
treachery, begged him not to go. But the Doctor felt bound
by the vows of his profession, and while proceeding
forth upon this supposed errand of mercy and 
benevolence, he was waylaid on one of the most public streets,
knocked down, and shot through the head, three or four
times, as if his assassins meant to make sure work of
their victim. From the testimony of those awakened by
the shots and his loud outcries, it appeared there were
over a half a dozen of his assassins and their accessories
&#8212;some doing the bloody work, while others stood guard
on the adjacent corners&#8212;and yet not one of them was
arrested, though it was a bright moonlight night, and a
fresh fall of snow on the ground. The city police, when
sought, were all found collected at the Central Police
Station, as if purposely out of the way, and no serious or

<pb n="185" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.199"/>

concerted attempt was made to track the murderers.
His watch was untouched; his pockets, unrifled; there
was no evidence that he had a personal enemy; and the
almost universal conviction of the Gentiles then at Salt
Lake was, that he had fallen a victim to the Mormons, at
the bidding or instigation of the Church&#8212;they preferring
to end their action of ejectment thus summarily, rather
than abide "the law's delay," or its "glorious 
uncertainties." Subsequently, a leading Mormon, a son-in-law
of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s, admitted to me, indeed, that 
<persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName> had probably been "silenced" by some ignorant or bigoted brother; but repudiated, of course, all connection
of the Church therewith, or responsibility therefor.</p>

<p>The morning after the assassination, as the facts
got known, the Gentile population became greatly excited,
and for a day or two there was hot talk of a "Vigilance
Committee," etc. Happily, however, this last suggestion
was abandoned, or the Mormons would have 
exterminated them, as they outnumbered the Gentiles fully six to
one in the city, and immensely more than that outside
in the Territory. To pacify them, however, a coroner's
inquest was ordered, and, as the excitement grew, the
City Government came out ostentatiously with a reward of
$2,000, for the apprehension and conviction of the 
murderers. So intense was the feeling, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>
himself thought it wise to start a private subscription, and
raised $7,000 more among the Mormon merchants and
"tender-footed" Gentiles. The sturdier Gentiles, 
however, and many of the U. S. officials, refused to have any
thing to do with this; and one, at least, of the U. S.
Judges, when asked to sign it, unhesitatingly branded
the whole movement, as only "a cheat and swindle to
throw dust into the eyes of people East." It was, 
however, a shrewd dodge, worthy of such an old fox, and

<pb n="186" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.200"/>

<persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> inimediately telegraphed to Gen. <persName key="Sherman, William Techumseh">Sherman</persName>, at
<placeName type="settlement" key="St Louis, MO">St. Louis</placeName>, then commanding that Department, "We
have offered $9,000 reward for Dr. <persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName>'s murderers.
The church nothing to do with it!" No doubt,
when interrogated by tourists about such outrages and
wrongs hereafter, he will refer to that "9,000 reward,"
for many a day, with great unction, and extol his saints
to the skies accordingly. Of course, it was perfectly safe
to "subscribe" it; for it was never meant, that any
body should be caught. The coroner's inquest made a
show of sitting several days, but nothing came of their
labors. Some Gentiles, indeed, went so far as to retain
Ex-Gov. <persName key="Weller, John B.">Weller</persName>, of <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, who happened then to be at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, and he prosecuted the inquiry with
some vigor; but the verdict of the jury was, "Killed by
some person or persons unknown." The effect of it all
was, to deepen the sense of insecurity in the minds of all
Gentiles there, as to both person and property, and to
intensify the general feeling against Mormonism, which
we found everywhere throughout <placeName type="state" key="Colorado">Colorado</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Idaho">Idaho</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Oregon">Oregon</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Nevada">Nevada</placeName>, and the Pacific Coast generally. It became at once another wall of division, another root of 
bitterness, between Gentiles and Mormons throughout all that
region; and will be sure to be treasured up "as wrath
against a day of wrath," when that dark day comes. And
justice, against even Brighamdom, we may depend, will
not sleep forever.</p>

<p>Mrs. <persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName>, it should be added, subsequently returned to her friends in <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, and Dr. <persName key="Williamson">Williamson</persName>
left for the East, both abandoning their undoubted
property, after such convincing arguments. The City 
immediately leased the Springs and their appurtenances for
$2,000 per year; and thus this cruel assassination was

<pb n="187" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.201"/>

apparently a "paying" operation for the Saints, 
whatever may be its barbarism, or however others fared.</p>

<p>This case I have given somewhat in detail, because it
occurred under my own eye&#8212;so to speak&#8212;and I 
endeavored to sift its facts pretty thoroughly for myself. In
my Official Report on <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, attention was called to it; and
whatever else may be said or thought of it, one thing
seems clear, to wit, that such unlawful and wicked acts
are but <hi rend="italic">the logical fruit of the habitual teachings of the Mormon chiefs and leaders</hi>. Said <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> some time before, in one of his pulpit discourses, "Brethren, if any body comes here, and goes to interfere with our lands or women, my advice is to send 'em to hell across
lots." Said the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Salt Lake Telegraph</hi>, the chief Mormon paper there, one day in my hearing, "If a man comes here, and don't like our institutions, all he
has to do is to leave. If he stops here, and minds his own
business, he will get along well enough&#8212;nobody will
molest him. But if he goes to denouncing President
<persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, or interfering with our domestic relations, of course he will get into trouble mighty quick, you bet!" I thought that a fair statement of their position; but
failed to see wherein it differed from the hideous 
despotism down South, which we had just had to break as with
a rod of iron, and dash in pieces as a potter's vessel. He
indignantly denied, that Gentiles were ordinarily ill-
treated or tabooed; but his own statement, it seemed to
me, confessed away the whole case substantially of 
<hi rend="italic">Gentile vs. Mormon</hi>, involving as it does a thorough surrender of our cherished freedom of speech and of the press. 
This editor was a bluff and hearty Englishman, about
forty years of age, and was reported engaged to a 
daughter of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s, only about seventeen. The  current criticism of him was, that he really believed no more

<pb n="188" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.202"/>

in Mormonism, than the most incorrigible Gentile but
he had found the institution, or rather "destitution," (as
<persName key="Parker, Theodore">Theodore Parker</persName> called its "twin relic," and would much
more have branded it), to "pay," and so eulogized and
defended it.</p>

<p>Perhaps I can not do better, than relate just here a
rather remarkable conversation I had with a high 
judicial officer of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, on this and kindred subjects.
He had been there several years, was a man of ability and
character, and I give the conversation at length, because
it seemed trustworthy, and also because it will probably
answer a variety of questions the reader may want to ask.
It took place in his own chambers, while I was at <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt
Lake</placeName>; and as no injunction of secrecy was imposed, or
apparently desired, I see no objections to publishing it.
He said he had come to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> unprejudiced against the
Mormons, but at length had become convinced, however
reluctantly, that they had a secret organization&#8212;call it
"Thugs," "Danites," "Destroying Angels," or what you
will&#8212;whose sworn duty it was to "put out of the way"
any person, who became hostile or obnoxious to their
views or interests. For a long while after coming there,
he had refused to credit this; but at length was compelled
to, by the most indubitable evidence, to wit, his own
multiplied observations and experiences as a U. S. judge.
He continued:</p>

<p>"I can't help believing, sir that poor Dr. <persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName>
was killed in this way, and when <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>'s
hypocritical subscription-paper, for a reward for the
arrest of the assassins, was presented for my signature,
I indignantly spurned it. I told the committe in charge,
that it was only another of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName>'s tricks to throw
dust into the eyes of the people at Washington, and I
would have nothing to do with it."</p>

<pb n="189" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.203"/>

<p>"Do you think his murderers will ever be 
discovered?"</p>

<p>"Suppose they are, they will never be convicted.
No Mormon jury would convict a brother Mormon, in
such a case, even if indicted, as everybody knows here.
I know very well who murdered poor Brassheld some
time ago, and where the Church sent him abroad to keep
him out of the way. I suppose England would return
him, under our extradition laws, if requested. But
<hi rend="italic">cui bono</hi>? Our juries here are all summoned by the
Mormon sheriffs, and the jurors, of course, are either
Mormons, or dough-face Gentiles, worse than Mormons;
so that, it would be hopeless to expect a righteous
verdict."</p>

<p>"Then you really think, the accounts we get East of
outrages and crimes by Mormons, against Gentiles or
apostate Mormons, are, on the whole, true?"</p>

<p>"Why, yes, I am sorry to say, I fear so&#8212;the most
of them&#8212;as true as holy writ. But the half of them
never come to light. ‘Dead men tell no tales.' <seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">And
what do we know of the mysteries and miseries of their
barbarous polygamy?"</seg></p>

<p>"Do you think <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> has much to do with
such outrages?"</p>

<p><seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDS">"In some cases, yes, directly. In others, only indirectly, by his sermons and addresses. No doubt he 
advised, or at least suggested, the taking off of 
<persName key="Brassfield">Brassfield</persName> and Dr. <persName key="Robinson, John Kiing">Robinson</persName>, to save trouble and serve as examples. So, also, he was directly responsible for the
Mountain Meadow massacre, <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Dates">that occurred several years ago</seg>, when <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Casualties">a whole train of Gentile emigrants</seg>, <seg type="Emigrants" subtype="Route"><hi rend="italic">en route</hi>
to <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName></seg>, were murdered in cold blood, and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">their
property and <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Survivors">little children distributed around among
the Mormons</seg></seg>. <seg type="Blame" subtype="EmigrantBehavior">They had offended the Saints while

<pb n="190" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.204"/>

passing through <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName>, and this was their revenge.</seg>
<seg type="Blame" subtype="IndiansIndependently">This murder by wholesale they have always charged
upon the Indians</seg>; but <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Planning"><seg type="Blame" subtype="USGovernment">I myself have seen the secret
orders for their massacre, signed 'By order of President
<persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, <persName key="Wells, Daniel H.">D. H. Wells</persName>, Adj't.-Gen.' I was in <placeName type="settlement" key="Washington, DC">Washington</placeName> in the autumn of 1865, and was at the White-
House one day, when these orders were shown to <persName key="Johnson, Andrew">Andrew
Johnson</persName>. He took the tattered and discolored papers to
the window, scanned them closely for awhile, and when
he returned them said, with much feeling, it was "high
time something was done to <hi rend="italic">clean out</hi> such scoundrels."</seg></seg>
It was a generous impulse, while it lasted, and he meant
it, too. But subsequently, when I saw him again, in the
winter, he had become embroiled with Congress, and
dismissed the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> question with the curt remark, that
there was "practical polygamy in <placeName type="state" key="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</placeName> too, as
well as <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>." <seg type="Massacre" subtype="Spoils">The property of these Mountain
Meadow emigrants, I repeat, was divided up, and
distributed around among the Mormons. Some of their
furniture is in <placeName type="settlement" key="Salt Lake City, UT">Salt Lake</placeName> now, and can readily be 
identified. Many of their mules were sold by Capt. <persName key="H.">H.</persName>
&#8212;subsequently our delegate to Congress&#8212;to the U. S.
Quartermaster then here, and the proceeds shared by
himself, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Young</persName>, <persName key="Well, Daniel H.">Wells</persName>, and others.</seg> There is plenty of
evidence of all this, that I can put my finger on at any
time; but it would be ridiculous to submit it to a 
Mormon jury, with any hope of a conviction now. And so,
the case rests."</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">"I suppose, this also is why our anti-polygamy laws prove to be a failure?"</seg></p>

<p><seg type="Context" subtype="Polygamy">"Certainly, sir! It is an old adage, ‘Dog won't eat dog!' There didn't use to be much polygamy here. I
But as soon as Congress made it a misdemeanor and a
crime, <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> and his Bishops set to work to get as

<pb n="191" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.205"/>

many of their people into it as possible, so as to make the
enforcement of the new law difficult, if not well nigh
impracticable. They argued very shrewdly, ‘You can't
indict and try a whole people. Polygamy, indeed, used
to be only a matter of taste, and but little talked about;
but now it is constantly preached, as a civil and religious
duty, and all who can support more than one wife are
proceeding to take others. The women objected a good
deal, at first, and do still; but they were told, it was a
New Revelation, ‘thus saith the Lord,' and submission
would make them ‘Queens in Heaven' etc., and so they
yielded. What else could they do in these mountain 
fastnesses, with Gown and Sword both against them?"</seg></p>

<p>"Well, judge, you must have seen a good deal of
the 'peculiar institution.' What are its practical
workings?"</p>

<p>"Bad, and only bad&#8212;every way. It tends to make
the men petty despots and mere animals, of course, while
it degrades American women to the level of the Oriental
harem. Their husbands, so-called, already habitually
think and speak of them, as their 'women'&#8212;not <hi rend="italic">wives</hi>&#8212;as
you may have noticed, as a part of their goodly possessions,
somewhat more esteemed perhaps than their flocks and
herds, but not so much more either. Affection, 
sympathy, confidence&#8212;the finer instincts and feelings&#8212;all true
delicacy between husband and wife&#8212;are fast dying out,
and we have nothing half so good to show for them.
Sometimes, however, a first wife gets the bit into her
teeth, and then the others have to stand around, or leave.
<hi rend="italic">Per contra</hi>, sometimes the first wife herself gets ejected.
One of <persName key="Kimball, Heber C.">Heber Kimball</persName>'s sons married a second wife some
time ago, and soon after she persuaded his first wife&#8212;a
wife of many years, with several children&#8212;to vacate, by
three shots from a revolver, and then installed herself as

<pb n="192" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.206"/>

<hi rend="italic">first</hi> wife instead! No doubt, the Saints have many
a little "unpleasantness," like this, to mar their 
domestic felicity; but they hush them up, and keep quiet
about it."</p>

<p>"What about their polygamous children?"</p>

<p>"Why, they are inferior of course, in many ways, <hi rend="italic">ex
necessitate</hi>, as the fruits of such a practice always are,
and must be. Go to the City Cemetery, and you will
und it a perfect Golgotha of infant graves. If not feeble
and tainted already in constitution, they must speedily
become so; or else all History is false, and Science a
slander."</p>

<p>"And yet those we have seen on the road, and about
the streets here, seem bright and spry enough."</p>

<p>"No doubt. It is a good climate, and there has not
been time enough yet. But, then, have you considered the
whole foul brood of downward influences at work here, and
what must be the logical result in due season, by the very
nature of things? Why, with our population of a 
hundred thousand souls, we have not a <hi rend="italic">Free</hi> School yet in all
<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, and outside of this city scarcely a <hi rend="italic">School</hi>-House.
Here,we have a few Ward Schools; but the teachers are
inferior, and the rates of tuition, cost of books etc., so
high, that only the children of the better classes can
attend. <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> has a school of his own, in his
seraglio grounds, where his numerous progeny are taught
music, dancing, and some of the commoner branches; but
the great bulk of our rising generation here are growing
up in a state of ignorance and superstition so dense, as to
be absolutely inconceivable elsewhere. So, too, many of
the Saints have two or more sisters for wives, at the same
time. Others, again, marry their own blood-cousins, and
some even their own step-daughters. And instances
exist, where they have had mother and daughter for

<pb n="193" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.207"/>

wives, at the same time. Now, where all this is to end,
it seems to me, it is not difficult to predict, unless Nature
suspends her laws, and Evil becomes our Good."</p>

<p>"It is certainly very shocking, judge. But what do
you propose to <hi rend="italic">do</hi> about it?"</p>

<p>"Well, I would do something, or at at least <hi rend="italic">try</hi> to.
I have thought a good deal about it, since I got my eyes
open; and, first of all, I would have Congress authorize
and instruct the U. S. Marshal here to summon the jurors
for the U. S. Courts direct. By some strange oversight,
I suspect by Mormon intrigue (for they watch Congress
closely, and boast they control it on all <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> matters
usually), this was omitted in our Organic Act, and
consequently our jury-lists are now taken from the
county-lists, which are of course made up by Mormon
sheriffs. Therefore, all open and avowed Gentiles, who
have any back-bone in them, are left off, and we get
nobody in our U. S. jury-boxes even, except Mormons and
doughface Gentiles. Of course, such juries won't indict
or convict for polygamy, or any other offence worth 
mentioning, if a Mormon is to be mulcted for it. But if our 
jurors were summoned by our Marshal direct, out of the
whole body of <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">the Territory</placeName>, as they are everywhere else, I
believe, he could take good care to put only reliable
citizens on the lists, and thus give us juries that <hi rend="italic">would</hi>
indict and convict in all necessary or flagrant cases.<ref target="n01">*</ref></p>

<note xml:id="n01">* Senator <persName key="Wade, Benjamin F.">Wade</persName>'s Bill (1867) met the <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> Question somewhat
like this, and I suspect Judge &#8212; had a finger in it. So, Senator 
<persName key="Cragin, Aaron H.">Cragin</persName>'s Bill subsequently, and others since. The present 
imbroglio in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> hinges on this Jury Question, more than anything else,
and Congress ought to settle it speedily, on a just and right basis.
Judge <persName key="McKean, James B.">McKean</persName> may be in the wrong technically; but substantially,
he is fighting for truth and justice, and if he lacks the necessary
weapons, should be furnished them. This is what Senator 
<persName key="Frelinghuysen, Frederick Theodore">Frelinghuysen</persName>'s Bill, now pending, (1874) proposes well to do.</note>

<pb n="194" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.208"/>

<p>"But would the Saints meekly consent to be thus
overslaughed, and ignored?"</p>

<p>"Of course, not! The first verdict we got and attempted
to enforce, there would be a riot, or threatened riot, and
then we would have to fall back on the Military. The
<placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName> Militia, of course, could not be depended on; for it is
all officered and controlled by the creatures of the Church.
Therefore, we would have to call on the United States,
and it would be for Uncle Sam to decide at last. This,
of course, would necessitate an increase of troops here;
for, if the garrison were small, the Saints might make
trouble. But give us a couple of batteries, a regiment
of cavalry, and say two regiments of infantry, such as
<persName key="Sherman, William Tecumseh">Sherman</persName> ‘went marching through <placeName type="state" key="Georgia">Georgia</placeName>' with; and
Brighamdom can be made to obey the laws, the same as
Dixie, or be ground to powder."</p>

<p>"But, judge, will not the Pacific Railroad solve the
problem in a more excellent way&#8212;peaceably and quietly
&#8212;by bringing in such an influx of Gentiles, that 
Mormonism will be neutralized? This is what we all hope
East?"</p>

<p>"Perhaps so, if this ‘influx' is <hi rend="italic">big</hi> enough, and <hi rend="italic">good</hi>
enough. But, you see, the Saints claim to have pre-
empted about all the land here, that is worth anything,
and they won't sell or lease to Gentiles, unless the Church
says so. Besides, with the heavy immigration the 
Mormons are constantly receiving&#8212;about three thousand
this year, to next to nothing by the Gentiles, and their
naturally rapid increase, I fear they will keep greatly
ahead of all outsiders, who won't be likely to come and
stay long where they will be ostracised and outlawed. It
isn't natural, that they should. Won't it be the same, as
it was down South before the war, and has been ever
since? Northern brain and capital wouldn't go there,

<pb n="195" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.209"/>

and won't, because they believe in perfect freedom of
speech and of the press&#8212;absolute security of person and
property&#8212;and won't settle where these are wanting.
How then can we expect them to emigrate here, where
we have no true enjoyment of either? What sensible
man would come to <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, or bring his wife and children
here, when he could go just as well to <placeName type="state" key="Colorado">Colorado</placeName> or 
<placeName type="state" key="Montana">Montana</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="Oregon">Oregon</placeName> or <placeName type="state" key="California">California</placeName>, and escape the dismal 
drawbacks we have here? I admit I have great hopes of the `
Railroad, in time; and yet I confess, I fear, our <hi rend="italic">qu&#1237;stio
vexata</hi> here in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>, like its "twin" question down in
Dixie, will find its solution only in gunpowder, if it is
to find it soon. When nothing else will do, I have great
faith in the moral power of bayonets&#8212;especially, when
used on the right side."</p>

<p>"But, judge, is not <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> the main 
cohesive power; and when he dies, what then?"</p>

<p>"Well, when that happens they may split up, on the
question of his successor; but I suspect <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName> is too
shrewd and far-seeing for that. He already has <persName key="Young, Brigham, Jr.">Brigham
Young, Jr.</persName>, his smartest son, in training for the 
succession&#8212;sent him missionary to England, and now he is a
Brigadier-General in the Mormon Militia here&#8212;and the
probability is, a "Revelation" will designate him for the 
Presidency, if death don't come too suddenly. <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham</persName>
will undoubtedly keep the succession in his own family,
if he can; but he will not hesitate a moment to designate
some other person, if the seeming interests of the Church
require it. Of course, he is very illiterate; but he is a
very able and sagacious man, for all that&#8212;devoted to
Mormonism, and "dangerous" in every sense of that
word."</p>

<p>"Have you no fear of him, yourself, judge? You
speak your mind pretty plainly."</p>

<pb n="196" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.210"/>

<p>"No, I think not. He would hardly strike so high.
Besides he is reputed to be a coward, personally, and I
guess <hi rend="italic">that</hi> is so. <seg type="Blame" subtype="LDS_LDSLeadership">I have seen him charged with
complicity in the Mountain Meadow massacre, and his shirking
and cringing then was pitiful.</seg> No doubt, my life is
always in danger here, more or less, as would be that of
any other upright and fearless judge. Indeed, I have
good reason to know, that they cordially hate me. After
Dr. <persName key="Robinson, John King">Robinson</persName>'s assassination a friendly Mormon came to
me at night, and told me confidentially my turn would
come next. But I keep indoors after dark, or else go out
only in company, or when heavily armed, and am 
prepared to sacrifice my life, if need be, at any time. I have
lived too long in this world, to be much afraid of leaving
it; and I don't know as I could die better anyhow, than
in upholding and enforcing the laws of my country here
in <placeName type="state" key="Utah Territory">Utah</placeName>."</p>

<p>"Do your Courts ever meet with real opposition to
their ordinary courses of procedure?"</p>

<p>"Why, no&#8212;not formally; though I never have much
confidence in a verdict, where one of the parties is a
Gentile. Where plaintiif and defendant are both 
Mormons, our verdicts are usually righteous enough; though
these are liable to be overruled or set aside, by the High
Council of the Church&#8212;a body of irresponsible 
ecclesiastics, of course, unknown to the laws. This Council is
composed of <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName>, and a number of the chief
dignitaries of the Church, and is often appealed to by
"big" Mormons, when the civil courts have gone against
them."</p>

<p>"No! Really? But is not this mere rumor, judge?"</p>

<p>"No, indeed! I could cite several such cases, but
will only trouble you with one. Not long ago, down in
one of our Southern counties, a laboring man&#8212;a 
<choice><orig>Mor-

<pb n="197" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.211"/>

mon</orig><reg>Mormon</reg></choice>
&#8212;was working in a barn, for and with a Mormon
Bishop. In some way or other, they got into a quarrel,
which ended in a fight, and in the course of this the
Bishop hurt the poor fellow very badly. Among other
things, he struck him with a pitchfork, harpooning him
&#8212;so to speak&#8212;through the leg, so that the poor man
was laid up for months, and made a cripple indeed for
life. After his recovery, the outrage was so atrocious,
and the community so generally with him, he mustered
up courage enough to bring an action against the Bishop.
The cause was tried in the Probate or County Court,
where of course, all were Mormons. But the jurors,
being neighbors of the injured man and cognizant of all
the facts, resolved to do justice, and accordingly without
much delay returned a verdict for $3,500 damages. The
Bishop being rich, as the high dignitaries all are, appealed
the case to my court, where I, after a full hearing, of
course, affirmed the judgment of the court below, with
heavy costs.</p>

<p>"Well, now, I supposed this settled the case, as
there was no higher court here. But judge of my
astonishment, when some weeks after the plaintiff came
to me one day, and said the Bishop had further appealed
the case to the High Council of the Church, where they
had tried it over again, and awarded him only $1,000 
damages; and he wanted to know if this was right and
"good law" here? Of course, I could do nothing for
him myself, with the facts in that shape. But I referred
him to one of our Gentile lawyers here, and told him if
he would put the case in his hands, and have the facts
brought regularly before me, so that I could get hold of
the matter judicially, I would soon teach this "High
Council of the Church" a lesson, as to their rights and
duties, as against a United States Court, that they would

<pb n="198" xml:id="mmm.wa.rusling.1877.212"/>

be apt to remember for awhile. He thanked me, and
took my advice. But before the papers got regularly
before me, the Mormons somehow got wind of the matter,
and hastened to settle with the man. I believe they
gave him $2,000, or something like that, and I suppose
frightened him into silence. Now, to think once of
these insolent villains, presuming&#8212;without law and in
violation of law&#8212;to review and overrule the solemn
decision of a United States Court! I tell you, it made
my Quaker blood boil, when I heard of it.<ref target="n02">*</ref> I would
just like to have laid my hands on that "High Council
of the Church," in a case like that. I feel right sure, I
would have taught <persName key="Young, Brigham">Brigham Young</persName> and his lawless
associates a wholesome lesson, they wouldn't have 
forgotten very soon, if it had cost me my life to do it."</p>

<p>There was something grand and heroic&#8212;almost
sublime&#8212;about this man's talk at times, and I only
reproduce it here very faintly. He knew I was
seeking official facts, and doubtless unburdened his
whole soul to me. He had had unusual opportunities
for observation; he seemed to be well-informed; and
certainly was thoroughly honest. Further than this, I
cannot vouch for him, but report the conversation 
substantially as it occurred, from notes made the same 
evening. I must, however, do him the justice to add, that
his views in the main were everywhere corroborated by
almost all the Federal officers I met&#8212;both civil and 
military&#8212;as well as the vast majority of Gentile settlers,
throughout all that region. Such were the views of
Judge&#8212;; and subsequent events there, it must be 
confessed, have pretty well illustrated them.</p>

<note xml:id="n02">* He was originally from Pennsylvania.</note>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>