<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
<body>
<h2>Browse</h2>

<p>The Mountain Meadows Massacre digital archive “Browse by topic” function gives users the opportunity to move through the collection via editorially-identified narrative elements within the text. Once identified, each narrative element has been labeled according to its content or function within massacre reportage or editorial comments. Generally, these segments contain themes that represent recurring points of description or reaction to the massacre as reflected in public discourse. The consistent use of, transformation, or absence of these narrative elements over time can provide useful points of analysis for archive users.</p>

<p>
Seven topics have been selected; within each topic specific identifications of important narrative elements have been made and more detailed descriptions of these labels can be found on the relevant pages. 
</p>

<h3>The topics: </h3>

<blockquote>
<p>
<a href="browse/Source.html">Source of Information</a><br/>
Refers to a primary or secondary source that is identified. There may be multiple sources within each document.
</p>

<p>
<a href="browse/Context.html">Historical Context</a><br/>
The context for a document’s reportage or editorial comments about the massacre, context may be explicit or implied and can refer to political, cultural, and/or social forces. 
</p>

<p>
<a href="browse/Emigrants.html">Baker-Fancher Wagon Train</a><br/>
Any description of the wagon train, its members, their state affiliations, or their route.
</p>

<p>
<a href="browse/Encounters.html">Encounters</a><br/>
Specifically Baker-Fancher Wagon Train contact with Mormons or Native Americans; this theme includes references to poison, slanderous comments about Mormon women, and trade.
</p>

<p>
<a href="browse/Massacre.html">Mountain Meadows Massacre</a><br/>
Descriptions of the planning, dates, location, battle, casualties, and survivors of the massacre. 
</p>

<p>
<a href="browse/Reaction.html">Reactions to the Massacre</a><br/>
Generally editorial commentary or reports of public outcry, these segments may refer to calls for governmental or extra-governmental investigation or action. 
</p>

<p>
<a href="browse/Blame.html">Blame</a><br/>
In instances where blame for the massacre is explicitly assigned or inferred, the accused are noted, usually with their motivation if it is specified.
</p>
</blockquote>

</body>
</html>