<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <doc>
      <field name="id">mmm.news.sfh.18571027</field>
      <field name="itemCategory">newspaper</field>
      <field name="titleMain">Untitled [From the news published in another column…]</field>
      <field name="author"/>
      <field name="dateSearch">1857-10-27</field>
      <field name="dateDisp">October 27, 1857</field>
      <field name="place">San Francisco, CA</field>
      <field name="state">San Francisco, CA</field>
      <field name="source">San Francisco Herald</field>
      <field name="text"> 
        

            
                
                
                
                From the news published in another
                        column, there can be
                        no doubt of the complicity of the Mormons with the Indians, in all the outrages which have
                            of late been committed on the middle plains.
                    
                        
                            There is no longer any
                                safety for the emigrant—he is forced on one side to submit
                                to the extortions of the Mormon guides, and on the other, to the
                                exactions of the Indians, [and is] too happy to escape with life.
                                Both have united to fleece, rob and murder all those who fall into
                                their hands.
                        
                     We are very much afraid we have not heard the last of the massacres by
                    the Indians this year. Whatever trains may yet be in the way, will not escape
                    without attacks. 
                        It will be seen from the
                                [Power and
                                Warn] statements published in another column,
                            that 
                                there is little
                                    doubt that the Mormons had a knowledge beforehand of what the
                                    Indians were going to do—were in constant
                                    communication with them during the time that the hapless emigrant train
                                        was battling against the savage foe, by whom they were
                                        assaulted—that, though fully aware that men, women and children
                                        were being cruelly murdered, they neglected to render
                                    any assistance, and did not even go so far as to remonstrate,
                                    and that they openly rejoiced with the Indians in the successful
                                    accomplishment of their bloody work.
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            Indeed, according to the
                                statements of Messrs. Power, Warn
                                and Honea, 
                                    the Mormons cannot be
                                        separated from the Indians in all these terrible outrages.
                                        They were the prompters, if not actors in the dreadful
                                        scenes which have been enacted on the middle plains. How well
                                            they have succeeded in moulding the savages, with whom
                                            they dwell, for the accomplishment of whatever objects
                                            they may have in view, is sufficiently evidenced by the
                                            distinction they now make between Mormons and
                                            Americans.
                                
                                They have been
                                    taught to believe there are two races of white men in
                                    existence—Mormons and Indians, and that while the
                                    former are their fast friends, the latter are their dreaded and
                                    uncompromising foes. It is horrible to contemplate that white
                                    men should be engaged in stirring up and goading on
                                    blood-thirsty savages to the commission of deeds of atrocity and
                                    blood—to the
                                        massacre of defenseless women and children of their own race
                                        at least; but we are afraid it is but too
                                true.
                        
                    
                    The poisoning of a dead ox, for which the
                        Indians asked, is stated as the main cause of the massacre; but that poisoning may have been done by
                            the Mormons.
                    The swaggering course pursued by the
                        emigrants, and which no one will seek to justify, excited a thirst for
                    vengeance in their minds, and this may have been the plan they adopted to
                    gratify it, knowing the fearful vengeance it would bring down on the heads of
                    the emigrants, if the act could be fastened on them. Such a theory is by no
                    means improbable or far-fetched. The spirit by which the Mormons are actuated is
                    no longer a secret; and no act or proceeding of theirs, no matter how fiendish
                    or blood-thirsty, should excite astonishment. The people of Los Angeles, at a meeting recently
                        held, adopted a preamble and resolutions calling on the President of the United States to take
                        measures for the punishment of the authors of the recent wholesale butchery
                        on the plains; and also calling on the Governor of the State to enforce the
                        laws in San
                            Bernardino, pledging themselves to respond to the call of
                        the proper authorities, if necessary in enforcing obedience. Matters wear a
                        menacing aspect!

            
        
     </field>
   </doc>
</add>