<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <doc>
      <field name="id">mmm.wa.price.1877</field>
      <field name="itemCategory">western_americana</field>
      <field name="titleMain">The Two Americas</field>
      <field name="author">Rose Lambart Price</field>
      <field name="dateSearch">1877</field>
      <field name="dateDisp">1877</field>
      <field name="place">London, ENG</field>
      <field name="state">London, ENG</field>
      <field name="source">The Two Americas An Account of Sport and Travel. With Notes on Men and Manners in North and South America.</field>
      <field name="text"> 




  
CHAPTER X.

Lathrop—Merced—American Politicians—Tuolumne Grove—The Yo-Semite Valley—Garrote—Mammoth Grove of "Big Trees," Calaveras County—South Park Grove of "Big Trees"—Lake Tahoe—Fishing on Tahoe—Carson—Night ride on a "cow-catcher"—Visit to a silver mine—Gold—Earthquakes—Virginia City—Land of Mormon—Funeral of George A. Smith—The Tabernacle—A Mormon sermon—Sulphur Springs—The trowel-bayonet—The Great Salt Lake—Jackass rabbits.







I arrived there on Sunday September 5th, in time
to witness the funeral solemnities of one of Brigham
Young’s shining lights—Mr. George A. Smith; his First Councillor, Church historian, and President of
the Twelve Apostles. This Apostle became identified
with the Mormon Church in its very infancy, and
participated in its travels and trials from New York to Ohio, to Missouri, to Illinois, and finally to Utah. Most people in Utah suspected him of having been
the willing instrument that Brigham used in compassing the massacre of the emigrants at Mountain Meadows; and had Mr. Smith lived another year, he would in all probability have been indicted and tried for that fearful crime. The Tabernacle—a huge building, looking at a distance more like an enormous
inverted boat on a pedestal than anything else I can
think of—was crowded to suffocation. Over ten
thousand people were congregated within its walls,
and it would have been impossible to have had a
better opportunity for inspecting these strange beings.



I put up at a Mormon hotel, "The Townsend
House," and can strongly recommend it. The
proprietor, a Mormon, was extremely obliging, and
does all in his power to make his guests comfortable.
He took me to call on Brigham Young, and drove me about the city, showing and explaining the
various objects of interest. Just about this time the
excitement caused by the trial of Lee for his participation in the Mountain Meadow massacre was still
going on; and many of the atrocities perpetrated by
the Mormons were constantly being published in the
daily papers. There is not the slightest doubt but that the leaders of the Mormon Church encouraged



assassination in the most methodical and wholesale
manner; the confessions of some of their own
disciples who were actually engaged in these 
outrages showed that such atrocities actually did occur;
and to me it seems strange that the Government of the country did not, and do not, take some active
steps in avenging the victims.







Clintons station and hotel on the Great Salt Lake
is about a three hours’ ride from the town. The
country on each side of the line leading to it is flat,
and in some parts marshy. A few wet splashes,
which we passed through just before first coasting



the lake, were covered with wild duck; I also saw a 
few snipe, and should fancy the shooting there in
winter would be pretty good. The mosquitos on
this part of the line were fierce and bloodthirsty as
tigers, and quite took possession of the cars, driving
most of us who were not extra thick-skinned to take
refuge on the platform, where the current of air
prevented them effecting a lodgment. After passing
Black Rock we stopped at Clintons, nicely situated on
the Lake, and looking directly on Church and 
Antelope islands. On the former Brigham is accused of
having stowed away the plunder so fearfully obtained
by the massacre at Mountain Meadows. A small
steamboat for the use of excursionists lay at a pier
near the hotel, and a few bathing boxes were erected
for the use of visitors.





 </field>
   </doc>
</add>