<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <doc>
      <field name="id">mmm.news.nyt.18590727</field>
      <field name="itemCategory">newspaper</field>
      <field name="titleMain">From Utah</field>
      <field name="author"/>
      <field name="dateSearch">1859-07-27</field>
      <field name="dateDisp">July 27, 1859</field>
      <field name="place">New York, NY</field>
      <field name="state">New York, NY</field>
      <field name="source">New York Times</field>
      <field name="text">




    
    

FROM UTAH.



Departure of the Mountain Meadow Children—Reception of the Instructions to Federal Officials.

We have received files of the Deseret News and the Valley Tan to the 29 th June, The news from Salt Lake City is interesting. The official instructions to the Federal officers in the Territory, (published some weeks ago in the TIMES,) had been received with great glee by the Mormons The Deseret News (BRIGHAM's organ) prints Attornery General BLACK'S two letters in full, accompanied by the following editorial comment.

"Fully do we indorse the spirit of both letters. The Constitution and laws of the United States should be a bright, unblemished mirrow, to reflect the whole nation and discover their scabby spots.

ON that subject, so much talked of outside, on which so many comments have been made, and of which so little appears to be truly known—the 'Mountain Meadow Massacre,' as it is termed—we have heretofore said but little. We have published much of what others have had to say about it, good or bad, as it came. Connected with this, we now expect that Judges shall sacrifice the flesh for the little time required to investigate this whole matter, do their legitamate duty, and no more; that the public accuser shall be the same straightforward, independent officer he has heretofore shown himself to be; and that the accused be tried by their peers, and their witnesses secured from treacherous arrests!

Give us a full record, "the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth" and, as an honest journalist we will give a full and honest transcript to the world!

Hold up the mirrow! Hold it up in the bright, broad, daylight. But hold it where there are no bayonets to glitter and dazzel the Juror's eye."

The Children rescued from the Mountain Meadow Massacre, left Salt Lake City on the 28th June, in charge of Dr. FORNEY, for Fort Smith. They were eighteen in number, of ages ranging from 2 to 8 years. 

The Valley Tan says:

"The first arrangements contemplated their transportation to the States with ox teams, but Ge. JOHNSTON kindly and promptly responded to a request from Dr. FORNEY, and has formshed for their better accommodation three spring ambulances and one baggage wagon, with teams of six mules each.

The change in the mode of transportation will, we think, contribute greatly to the comfort of the children and those in charge of them; From the circumstances connected with their orphanage, they are perculiarly objects for sympathy, and we are pleased to see the efforts of Dr. FORNEY to make the road on which they travel in search of relatives or friends as smooth as possible.

They will travel with, and are under the protection of Capt. R. ANDERSON, Second Dragoons, who is en route to Fort Kearney with his command. Mrs. WORLEY, Mrs. NASH, and two other ladies have been engaged as matrons to attend to the wants of the little ones, and three men as accompany the party as camp assistants. The names of the children, so far as can be learned, are as follows:

John Calvin, Lewis and Mary Sorel. (thier father being held in rememberance as "Joe Sorel;") Ambrose Miram, and William Taggett; Frances Horn; Charles and Annie Francher; Besse and Lane Baker; Rebecca, Louisa and sarah Dunlap; Sarhronia or Mary and Ephraim W. Huff; Angeline and Apple (surname unknown;) and a little boy of whom there is no account, the people with whom he was found called him William. 

The children are supposed to have resided in the same neighborhood, and in Johnston County, Arkansas. These children have been in charge of Dr. FORNEY since last fall, and we know that he has given his interested and personal supervision in order that they may be property and comforably cared for. We learn, moreover, that Dr. FORNEY has obtained the guardianship of these children. There was a large amount of property in the possession of the party massacred at the Mountain Meadows, and the children have now an agent here, who will undoubtedly use his best endeavors to recover the property of which they have been despoiled."

The Valley Tan has passed into new hands: Secretary HARTNETT having given place to Mr. GEORGE ADAMS. HARTNETT attacks a correspondent of the San Franciso Bulletin for the assertion that the paper was coerced by himself and Gov. CUMMING. He not only repels this imputation, but indulges in the somewhat strong statement that the correspondent aforesaid "tells not the truth—that he utters falsehoods—that he is a liar." This, however, is simply the Utah manner. The new editor relieves Judge SINCLAIR of the onus of threatening to quarter troops in the city, to protect his court, and comes to the defence of His Honor as follows:

"We have been reliably informed that the accusation is grounded and that Judge SINCLAIR did not even intend to have court in May, as he was awaiting the arrival of Chief Justice ECKELS; which fact of itself is all sufficient to refute such an allegation as has been made, and show what credit can be at ached to the statements of the writer. If one portion of the testimony of a witness is invalidated, it is held that the testimony in general is worthless, so that writers should be careful in regard to all their statements."

The Mormon paper puffs Gen. WILSON, the United States District-Attorney. It declares that "he has the esteem and confidence of the citizens of this Territory."

The Army Paymaster was reported on his way to Utah with upwards of $400,000 in specle for the army, and about five hundred recruits. 

The saints were getting discouraged about their crops. The News says:

"From the reports that have been recieved, from nearly every country and settlement in the Territory within the last few days, the prospects of an abundant harvest this season are not generally very flattering, and in several locations the whear crop will be almost an entire failure. Comparatively speaking there was but little wheat sown last Fall, and much of what was put in was either killed by the severity of the Winter of injured by the old blasting winds of April and May to that extent that many fields, especially in the northern counties, are not worth harvesting, and in some instances, the owners are mowing them, there being more cheat than ther is wheat growing, and, consequently, the crop is not of any value only as feed for stock."



MORE ARMY JOBBING.
Correspondence of the New-York Times.
CAMP FLOYD, U.T., Wednesday, June 29, 1859. 

Deputy Quartermaster-General GEO. H. CROSSMAN has been ordered by the secretary of War to sell at Camp Floyd, U.T. on twnety days' notice, 3,00 mules, 500 wagons and 500 sets of (six-mule team harness. 

Mr. B. HALLIDAY, or HOLLIDAY, of St. Louis, I believe, was sent out there at Government expense, (for truth of which statement please refer to Quartermaster at Fort Leavenworth, commanding officer at Fort Kearney and Laramie, and to Col, G.H. CROSSMAN.) by order of the Secretary of War, and brought with him the money to buy the mules a considerable length of time before the order was issued for the sale of the mules. As no one in this territory possesses money enough to buy these mules except Mr. HOLLIDAY, and as it requires at least forty days to bring capitalists to Camp Floyd from Missouri of California, it is extremely probable that Mr. H, &amp; Co. will obtain these mules for about $50 per head, when the Government paid for them last year and year before an average of $175 per head; and if a movement of the army should occur, they must be bought back at any price. The Secretary does not leave animals enough in the Department to perform the ordinary garrlson and detached duty. All the mules which are to be sold are very fat and of a superior quality.

The General Commanders and Cho Quartermaster General deplore the great loss which will befall tae Government by these transactions, but the order of the Secretary of War its peremptory and final as far as they are concerned, and nothing remains as a remedy except an appeal to public opinion.




 </field>
   </doc>
</add>