<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <doc>
      <field name="id">mmm.news.nyt.18590427</field>
      <field name="itemCategory">newspaper</field>
      <field name="titleMain">News By Telegraph</field>
      <field name="author"/>
      <field name="dateSearch">1859-04-27</field>
      <field name="dateDisp">April 27, 1859</field>
      <field name="place">New York, NY</field>
      <field name="state">New York, NY</field>
      <field name="source">New York Times</field>
      <field name="text">

    
    


    

NEWS BY TELEGRAPH.

Arrival of the Overland California Mail.
IMPORTANT NEWS FROM UTAH—ALARMING CONDITION
OF AFFAIRS.

 St. Louis, Monday, April 25,

The Overland California mail of the 4th April
arrived to-day, having made the trip in twenty-one
days eight hours, the quickest trip yet.

Advices from Utah represent the affairs in that Territory
as worse than they have ever been, either before
or since the arrival of the Army there.  The ill feeling
had reached its culminating point, and the people
were on the eve of open hostilities.  Differences
also exist between Governor CUMMING and General
JOHNSTON touching their respective powers; and there
is likewise an open rupture between the Executive
and the Judiciary.  The Federal Courts find it impossible
to exercise their functions, the Grand Jury refusing
to find bills, and using every other means to
screen parties accused of murder and other crimes.
Judge CRADLEBAUGH had discharged the jury, and had
been compelled to discharge, also, all the prisoners
in custody.  On the occasion of the discharge
of the juries, the Judge charged the Mormons
with having obstructed the officers of the Court, suppressed
testimony, and refused to make provision for
the confinement and maintenance of the prisoners for
the confinement and maintenance of prisoners.  Owing
to the excited state of the popular feeling, a detachment
of one thousand troops had moved from
Camp Floyd, and encamped near Provo.  Governor
CUMMING had issued a proclamation, taking part with
the Mormon sentiment.  It is not stated whether he
had demanded the withdrawal of the troops from
Provo, but his actions had laid him open to the charge
of complicity with the Mormon theocracy.  Much bad
feeling also existed between the Mormon and United
States troops, though these of the latter, who are
stationed at Provo, had behaved with remarkable forbearance.
A collision, however between the two
parties, was considered imminent.

A series of letters published in the Salt Lake
Valley Tan, giving the proceedings of Judge CARDLEBOUGHCRADLEBAUGH'S
Court at Provo, explain to some extent th
difficulties and disturbances in the Territory.  The
misunderstanding between Governor CUMMING and
General JOHNSTON seems to have grown out of a refusal
of the latter to withdraw the troops from Provo,
which had been sent there under a requisition of the
Court to protect witnesses.  Judge CARDLEBOUGHCRADLEBAUGH passed
severe strictures on Governor CUMMING's proclamation,
which has not been received here, characterizing it
as informal, as evidently designed to exasperate the
people against the troops, to obstruct the course of
justice, and to excite insubordination in the army.
He also says that instead of the presence of the troops
tending to terrify the inhabitants and to intimidate
witnesses; the jurors and parties testifying in behalf
of the prosecution have been compelled to seek the
protection of the troops against the threats and intimidations
of the very inhabitants, said to be so terrified.

Judge CARDLEBAUGHCRADLEBAUGH, who was sitting merely as a committing magistrate, would go to Camp Floyd the
following week to continue the investigations; the
testimony elicited implicating several Bishops and
Presidents, civil authorities of the Territory, in
murders at various times, all of whom fled to escape
arrest.  Four Grand Jurors, discharged by CARDLEBAUGH,
had also fled.  Cedar City and several other
towns in the vicinity of the Mountain Meadows massacre
are almost depopulated.  It is also stated that the
Indians, about a thousand strong, headed by white
men had mustered in that neighborhood, who express
a determination to prevent the arrest of any one in
that rection.  Judge CARDLEBAUGHCRADLEBAUGH emphatically denies
that the Grand Jury protested against their discharge,
as stated by the Deseret News.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>