<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <doc>
      <field name="id">mmm.news.uv.18660728</field>
      <field name="itemCategory">newspaper</field>
      <field name="titleMain">The Mountain Meadow Massacre</field>
      <field name="author"/>
      <field name="dateSearch">1866-07-28</field>
      <field name="dateDisp">July 28, 1866</field>
      <field name="place">Camp Douglas, UT</field>
      <field name="state">Camp Douglas, UT</field>
      <field name="source">Union Vedette</field>
      <field name="text">








The Mountain Meadow Massacre.

In the letter of an occasional correspondent  Callville in yesterday's
Bulletin it was intimated that the Mormons were exciting the United States authorities to punish the Indians for the massacre known by the above name. The Mormons having their own troubles with the Indians are now accusing those collected in the neighborhood of Muddy
river of being the murderers, and in possession of the cattle and other plunder obtained by his crime.  It will be remembered that in 1857 a large train of emigrants from Arkansas were attacked at Mountain Meadow by a band of Indians or white men, and every adult, numbering 141 persons of both sexes, slain and a large quantity of stock, wagons, carriages, jewelry, clothing and other property carried off.  After the massacre, 18 children, from eight years of age down to eight months, were picked up amongst the bushes into which they had crawled for shelter. James Lynch, formerly Superintendent of the United States post at Camp Floyd, has informed us that he was instructed by the United States authorities to inquire
into this matter while stationed at the above post, and he had communications
with John De Lee, Hamlin, Bishop Smith and other Mormons, and they all acknowledged that the attack was made by Mormons, assisted by give Prute Indians.  John De Lee boasting that he was the leader of the attacking party.  They admit also to finding of the children and that there had been a consultation about them, one Mormon brute advocating their death on the ground that "they should destroy the nits while killing the lice."  More humane counsels, however, prevailed, and Hamlin took charge of 16 and John De Lee of 2.  These children were found by the United States authorities, in Santa Clara, in 1859, in miserable condition, and were given up to our informant. The eldest, a sharp, intelligent child 10 years old, named Mary Dunlap, remembered distinctly the occurrences of two years before, and pointed out to Mr. Lynch the man who had taken part in the massacre.  Mary Dunlap also testified to articles of dress and jewelry worn by John De Lee's wife and other persons as being part of the plunder which she recognized; also carriages and wagons which formed part of the train then in possession of the Mormons with whom she had been living.  Over 30 witnesses testified to facts proving the guilt of the Mormons in this matter before Judge Cradlebaugh and Eckell, Territorial Judges in Utah.

The children were subsequently removed to the States, and Mary Dunlap, the eldest survivor the catastrophe, is living in Kansas City, Missouri, and can, we are informed, substantiate the charges against the men who are now seeking to throw the blame on the Indians. Mr. Lynch left by this day's steamer for Guayquil, Republic of Equador; but if through the instruinentality of the Judges named above or any other parties, an attempt should be made to bring the real assassins to punishment, he will be found ready to proceed to any part of the United States to depose to the above and other facts which came to his knowledge while employed in the Government service at the time the first enquiry was made. —S. F. Bulletin.



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>