<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<add xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
     xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
   <doc>
      <field name="id">mmm.wa.inmancody.1898</field>
      <field name="itemCategory">western_americana</field>
      <field name="titleMain">The Great Salt Lake Trail</field>
      <field name="author">Henry Inman and  William F. Cody ["Buffalo Bill"]</field>
      <field name="dateSearch">1898</field>
      <field name="dateDisp">1898</field>
      <field name="place">Topeka, KS</field>
      <field name="state">Topeka, KS</field>
      <field name="source">The Great Salt Lake Trail</field>
      <field name="text"> 


 


CHAPTER VII

    Mountain Meadows Massacre—Indians Attack the Wagons—Lee Offers Protection—Ambushed by Lee—Lee Flies to the Mountains—Mormon Church Acquitted—Execution of John D. Lee—Temporary Toll-Bridges—Indian Raids on Cattle Ranches—Stuttering Brown—Graves Along the Trail


John D. Lee



The most terrible fate that ever befell a caravan
on the Old Trail was that known to history as the Mountain Meadows Massacre.

The story of this damnable, outrageous, and wholesale murder is as follows:—

In the spring of 1857 a
band of emigrants numbering one hundred and thirty-six, from
Missouri and Arkansas, set out for
Southern California. The party had about
six hundred head of cattle, thirty wagons, and thirty
horses and mules. At least thirty thousand dollars worth
of plunder was collected by the assassins after the
massacre.

Owing to the impending war between the United States
and the Mormons, the Saints had been ordered not to
furnish any emigrant trains with supplies.  In view of


    
this fact the leaders of the train found it difficult to get
provisions for the party after reaching the territory
occupied by that sect. The party reached Salt Lake
and camped about the end of July, but finding the 
Mormons in so unfriendly a mood, decided to break camp
and move on. Continuing their journey, they proceeded
to Beaver City, thence to Parowan, where they obtained a
scanty supply of provisions.

Arriving at Cedar City, they succeeded in purchasing
about fifty bushels of wheat, which was ground at a mill
belonging to John D. Lee, formerly commander of the
fort at Cedar, but then Indian agent, and in charge of
an Indian farm near Harmony.

About thirty miles to the southwest of Cedar are the
Mountain Meadows, which form the divide between
the waters of the Great Basin and those which flow into
the Colorado. At the south end of the Meadows, which 
are four to five miles in length and one in width, but here
run to a narrow point, is a large stream, the banks of
which are about ten feet in height. Close to this stream
the emigrants were encamped on the 5th of September,
almost midway between two ranges of low hills some four
hundred yards apart.

It was Saturday evening when the trains encamped at
Mountain Meadows. On the Sabbath they rested, and at
the usual hour one of them conducted divine service as
had been their custom throughout the journey.

At dawn on the following morning while the camp-fires
were being lighted, they were fired upon by Indians,
or white men disguised as savages, and more than twenty
were killed or wounded, their cattle having been driven
off by the assailants who had crept on them under cover
of darkness. The men now ran for their wagons, pushed
them together so as to form a corral, and dug out the
earth deep enough to sink them to the hubs; then in the


    
centre of the enclosure they made a rifle-pit large enough
to contain the entire company. Thereupon the attacking
party, which numbered from three to four hundred, 
withdrew to the hills, on the crest of which they built parapets,
whence they shot down all who showed themselves outside 
the intrenchment.

The emigrants were now in a state of siege, and had
little hope of escape as all the outlets of the valley were
guarded. Their ammunition was almost exhausted, many
of their number were wounded, and their sufferings from
thirst had become intolerable. Down in the ravine and
within a few yards of the corral was the stream of water,
but only after sundown could any of the precious liquid
be obtained, and then at great risk, for this point was
covered by the muskets of the Indians, who lurked all
night among the ravines waiting for their victims.

On the morning of the fifth day of the siege, a wagon
was seen approaching, accompanied by an escort of 
Mormon soldiers. When near the intrenchment the company
halted, and one of them, William Bateman by name, was
sent forward with a flag of truce. In answer to this 
signal a little girl, dressed in white, appeared in an open
space between the wagons. Half-way between the 
Mormons and the corral, Bateman was met by one of the 
emigrants named Hamilton, to whom he promised protection 
for his party on condition that their arms were surrendered,
assuring him that they would be conducted safely to Cedar
City. After a brief interview each returned to his 
comrades.

It was arranged that John D. Lee should conclude terms
with the emigrants, and he immediately went into their
camp. Bidding the men pile their arms into the wagon,
to avoid provoking the Indians, he placed in them the
wounded, the small children, and a little clothing.
While thus engaged, a man rode up with orders from


    
Major Higbee, an officer of the Mormon army, to hasten,
as the Indians threatened to renew the attack.

The emigrants were then hurried away, the men and
women following the wagons, the latter in front. All were
in single file, and on each side of them the militia were
drawn up two deep, with twenty paces between their lines.
Within two hundred yards of the camp, the men were
halted until the women approached a copse of scrub-oak,
about a mile distant, and near which, it appears, the
Indians were in ambush.

The men now resumed their march, the militia forming
in single file, each one walking by the side of an emigrant,
and carrying his musket on the left arm. As soon as the
women were close to the ambuscade, Higbee, who was in
charge of the detachment, gave a signal, which had 
evidently been prearranged, by saying to his command, "Do
your duty"; and the horrible butchery commenced. Most
of the men were shot down at the first fire. Three only
escaped from the valley; of these, two were quickly run
down and slaughtered; the third was slain at Muddy
Creek, some fifty miles distant.

The women and those of the children who were on foot
ran forward some two or three hundred yards, when they
were overtaken by Indians, among whom were some
Mormons in disguise. The women fell on their knees,
and with clasped hands sued in vain for mercy, clutching
the garments of their murderers. Children pleaded for
life, but the steady gaze of innocent childhood was met
by the demoniac grin of the savages, who brandished over 
them uplifted knives and tomahawks. Their skulls were
battered in, or their throats cut from ear to ear, and, while
still alive, the scalp was torn from their heads. Some of
the little ones met with a more merciful death, one, an
infant in arms, being shot through the head by the same
bullet that pierced its father's heart. Of the women


    
none were spared, and of the children only those who were
not more than seven years of age.

To two of Lee's wagoners was assigned the duty, so
called, of slaughtering the sick and wounded. Obeying
their instructions, they stopped their teams and 
despatched their unfortunate victims. Some were shot;
others had their throats cut.

The massacre was now completed, and after stripping
the bodies of all articles of value, Brother Lee and his
associates went to breakfast, returning after a hearty meal
to bury their dead.

It was a ghastly sight that met their eyes on their
return, and one that caused even the assassins to shudder
and turn pale. The bodies had been entirely denuded by
the Indians. Some of the corpses were horribly mangled
and nearly all of them scalped. The dead were piled in
heaps in a ravine near by and a little earth thrown over
them. This was washed off by the first rains, leaving the 
remains to be devoured by wolves and coyotes.

It was not until two years after the massacre that they
were decently interred, by a detachment of United States
troops sent for that purpose from Camp Floyd.

On arriving at Mountain Meadows, the soldiers found
skulls and bones scattered for the space of a mile around
the ravine, where they had been dragged by the wolves.
Nearly all of the bodies had been gnawed by those ghouls
of the desert, so that few could be recognized, as their 
dismembered skeletons were bleached by the sun. Many of
the skulls had been crushed by the butts of muskets, or
cloven with tomahawks; others were shattered by 
firearms discharged close to the head.

A few remnants of apparel, torn from the backs of
women and children as they ran from their merciless 
pursuers, still fluttered among the bushes, and near by were
masses of human hair, matted and trodden in the earth.



Over the last resting-place of the victims was erected
a cone-shaped cairn, twelve feet high. Against its 
northern base was a slab of rough granite with the following
inscription: "Here 120 men, women, and children were
massacred in cold blood, early in September, 1857. They
were from Arkansas." Surmounting the cairn was a cross
of cedar, inscribed with the words: "Vengeance is mine; I
will repay, saith the Lord."

The survivors of the awful slaughter were seventeen
children, from two months to seven years of age, who
were carried, on the evening of the massacre, by John D.
Lee and others to the house of Jacob Hamblin, and 
afterward placed in charge of Mormon families at various
points in the territory. All of them were recovered in
the summer of 1858, with the exception of one, who was
rescued a few months later, and though thinly clad, they
bore no marks of ill-usage. In 1859 they were conveyed
to Arkansas, the Congress of the United States having
appropriated ten thousand dollars for their rescue and
restoration to relatives.

Those concerned in the massacre had pledged
themselves by the most solemn oaths to stand by each other,
and ever to insist that the deed was done entirely by
Indians. For several months this was the accepted theory,
but when it became known that some of the children had
been spared, suspicion at once pointed elsewhere, for
among all the murders committed by the Utes, there was
not a single instance of their having shown any such
mercy. Moreover, it was ascertained that an armed party
of Mormons had left Cedar City, and had returned with
spoil, and that the savages complained of having been 
unfairly treated in the division of the booty.

It is claimed that when John D. Lee discovered that
the United States authorities suspected him as being the
principal actor in the awful tragedy, he left the valley of


    
the Great Salt Lake, and hid himself in one of the cañnons
of the Colorado,1 where he remained for years suffering
that terrible anxiety which comes to all fugitives from
justice, sooner or later, and which is said by those who
have experienced it to be absolutely unbearable.

In 1874, under the provisions of what is legally known
as the "Poland Bill," whereby the better administration of
justice was subserved, the Grand Jury was instructed to
investigate the Mountain Meadows Massacre, and find bills
of indictment against John D. Lee, William H. Dame,
Isaac C. Haight, and others. Warrants were issued for
their arrest, and after a vigorous search Lee and Dame
were captured, Lee having been discovered in a hog-pen
at a small settlement on the Sevier River.

On the 23d of July, 1875, the trial was begun, at
Beaver City, in Southern Utah. Much delay ensued,
however, by the absence of witnesses, and by the fact that
Lee had promised to make a full confession, and turn
state's evidence. His statement was not accepted by the
court, and the case was brought to trial on the 23d of
July, with the expected result, that the jury, eight of
whom were Mormons, failed to agree.

Lee was then tried a second time, and it was proved
that the Mormon Church had nothing to do with the
massacre ; that Lee, in fact, had acted in direct opposition

1 He took refuge in the Grand Cañon of the Colorado River; his hiding-place was three miles from any possible pass, and he kept a faithful 
adherent constantly on guard. When any one was seen approaching the
pass, Lee was immediately signalled and forthwith repaired to a cave,
where he remained until it was discovered whether the intruder was
friend or foe. If not a friend, he kept to his cave until the party had
left, then returned to his house. Lee followed this life for five or six
years, until he became so weary of dodging, and running from supposed
enemies, that he finally returned to Salt Lake City. I saw his cave and
house some years ago when, in company with General N. A. Miles and
others, I made a pleasure trip to the Grand Cañon. —W. F. Cody.



to the officers of the Church. It was shown that he was
a villain and a murderer of the deepest dye; that with
his own hands, after inducing the emigrants to surrender
and give up their arms, he had shot two women and
brained a third with the butt-end of his musket, and had
cut the throat of a wounded man whom he had dragged
from one of the wagons; that he had gathered the
property of the emigrants and disposed of it for his own
benefit. It was further proved that Lee shot two or
three of the wounded, and that when two girls, who had
been hiding in the brush, were brought into his presence
by an Indian after the massacre, the latter asked what
was to be done with them, to which Lee replied, "They 
are too old to be spared." "They are too pretty to be
killed," answered the chief. "Such are my orders," said
Lee, whereupon the Indian shot one, and Lee, dragging
the other to the ground, cut her throat.

Lee was convicted of murder in the first degree, and,
having been allowed to select his own method of 
execution, was sentenced to be shot. The case was appealed
to the supreme court of the territory, but the judgment
was sustained, and it was ordered that the sentence be
carried into effect on the 23d of March, 1877. The
others who had been tried were discharged from custody.

A short time before his execution Lee made a
confession in which he attempted to palliate his guilt by
throwing the burden of the crime on his accomplices,
especially on Haight and Higbee, and to show that the
massacre was committed by order of Brigham Young and
the High Council, all of which was absolutely false.

On the 13th of March he wrote: "I feel as composed
and as calm as a summer morning. I hope to meet my
fate with manly courage. I declare my innocence. I 
have done nothing designedly wrong in that unfortunate
and lamentable affair with which I have been implicated.



I used my utmost endeavours to save them from their sad
fate. I freely would have given worlds, were they at my
command, to have averted that evil. Death to me has no
terror. It is but a struggle, and all is over. I know
that I have a reward in heaven, and my conscience does
not accuse me."

Ten days later he was led to execution at the
Mountain Meadows. Over that spot the curse of the Almighty
seemed to have fallen. The luxuriant herbage that had
clothed it twenty years before had disappeared; the
springs were dry and wasted, and now there was neither
grass nor any green thing, save here and there a copse of
sage-brush or scrub-oak, that served but to make its
desolation still more desolate. It is said that the 
phantoms of the murdered emigrants still flit around the cairn
that marks their grave, and nightly reënact in ghastly
pantomime the scene of this hideous tragedy.

About ten o'clock on the morning of the 23d a party of
armed men, alighting from their wagons, approached the
site of the massacre. Among them were the United
States marshal, William Nelson, the district attorney, a
military guard, and a score of private citizens. In their
midst was John Doyle Lee. Blankets were placed over
the wheels of one of the wagons, to serve as a screen for
the firing party. Some rough boards were then nailed
together in the shape of a coffin, which was placed near
the edge of the cairn, and upon it Lee took his seat until
the preparations were completed. The marshal now read
the order of the court, and, turning to the prisoner, said,
"Mr. Lee, if you have anything to say before the order of
the court is carried into effect you can do so now."

Rising from his coffin, he looked calmly around for a
moment, and then with unfaltering voice repeated the
statements already quoted from his confession. "I have
but little to say this morning," he added. "It seems I



have to be made a victim; a victim must be had, and I
am the victim. I studied to make Brigham Young's will
my pleasure for thirty years. See now what I have come
to this day! I have been sacrificed in a cowardly, 
dastardly manner. I cannot help it; it is my last word; it
is so. I do not fear death; I shall never go to a worse
place than I am now in. I ask the Lord my God, if my
labours are done, to receive my spirit."

A Methodist clergyman, who acted as his spiritual
adviser, then knelt by his side and offered a brief prayer,
to which he listened attentively. After shaking hands
with those around him, he removed a part of his 
clothing, handing his hat to the marshal, who bound a 
handkerchief over his eyes, his hands being free at his own
request. Seating himself with his face to the firing party,
and with hands clasped over his head, he exclaimed:
"Let them shoot the balls through my heart. Don't let
them mangle my body."

The word of command was given, the report of the
rifes rang forth on the still morning air, and without a
groan or quiver the body of the criminal fell back 
lifeless on his coffin.

God was more merciful to him than he had been to his
victims.1



1 See Bancroft's Pacific States.
2 Washington E. Hinman.
           



 </field>
   </doc>
</add>